<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>creative activism &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/creative-activism/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Migration Matters: A Free Video Lecture Series</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/02/29/migration-matters-a-free-video-lecture-series/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[collidoscopeks]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 14:16:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4377</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When we talk about migration on this website, among our friends and colleagues, and particularly across the vast expanse of the internet, we are confronted with many misconceptions about who the immigrants and refugees of the world really are, what brings them to our countries and communities, and whether or not the statements made by politicians on immigration are true, let alone helpful. We write about the movement and coming together of people, because we believe commentary and discussion to be a powerful antidote to this perpetuation of misinformation. But are words, indeed our own voices, ever enough? A New Project: Migration Matters In collaboration with two inspiring women in the field of migration reporting and migration studies, we are embarking on a new chapter of Collidoscope&#8217;s mission in launching a free online course, which will deliver concise, accurate information about migration in just five minutes a day. This course will focus on promoting understanding of the issues: how and why migration happens, how it is being addressed around the world, and how we can become more informed actors in the process. We let &#8220;the experts&#8221; speak: accomplished, peer-reviewed researchers and educators, practitioners in the field, and migrants themselves. In [...]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When we talk about migration on this website, among our friends and colleagues, and particularly across the vast expanse of the internet, we are confronted with many misconceptions about who the immigrants and refugees of the world really are, what brings them to our countries and communities, and whether or not the statements made by politicians on immigration are true, let alone helpful.</p>
<p>We write about the movement and coming together of people, because we believe commentary and discussion to be a powerful antidote to this perpetuation of misinformation. But are words, indeed our own voices, ever enough?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-4371 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/TrailerThumbnail.jpg" width="650" height="366" /></p>
<p><strong>A New Project: <a href="https://www.generosity.com/community-fundraising/migration-matters-a-free-video-lecture-series/x/13390941">Migration Matters</a></strong></p>
<p>In collaboration with two inspiring women in the field of migration reporting and migration studies, we are embarking on a new chapter of Collidoscope&#8217;s mission in launching <a href="https://www.generosity.com/community-fundraising/migration-matters-a-free-video-lecture-series/x/13390941">a free online course</a>, which will deliver concise, accurate information about migration in just five minutes a day.</p>
<p>This course will focus on promoting understanding of the issues: how and why migration happens, how it is being addressed around the world, and how we can become more informed actors in the process. We let &#8220;the experts&#8221; speak: accomplished, peer-reviewed researchers and educators, practitioners in the field, and migrants themselves.</p>
<p>In line with what we have worked to create with the Collidoscope project, this course will foster a space for open conversation, where no concern is ridiculed and no question dismissed.</p>
<p>To learn more, visit the Migration Matters page and <a href="http://www.migrationmatters.me/">pre-enroll for this great course</a>! You can also follow Migration Matters on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/migrmatters">@MigrMatters</a> and on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/MigrationMatters/?fref=ts">Facebook</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Funding</strong></p>
<p>We can&#8217;t do it without your help &#8211; our loyal supporters, readers, friends, colleagues, and friends.</p>
<p>Please help us realize our goal of beginning an open, evidence-based conversation about the issues that matter most to us, to immigrants, to refugees, by <a href="https://www.generosity.com/community-fundraising/migration-matters-a-free-video-lecture-series/x/13390941">contributing to our crowd-funding campaign</a>. You can also help by spreading the word about this project in your community. The greater our reach, the more effective its message.</p>
<p>If you have any questions about Migration Matters or would like to be involved, please contact the team at migrmatters@gmail.com. Currently we are looking for individuals with experience in visual design, interactive online experiences, and data visualizations.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em><strong>Kelly and Sophia</strong></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: the Klezmer Gentiles</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2014 09:55:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Holocaust]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jewish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[memory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Poland]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2468</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[International artists in Berlin occupy a semi-privileged position, able to ask critical questions of society without being publicly rebuked. An example of such an artist is Soliman Lawrence. Soli has been photographing the memorialization of Jewish culture in Poland for years, following the tracks of a new form of engagement with the past, as enacted by a more recent generation of Poles. In contrast to Poland, Germany now has its fair share of Jews. What might this mean for memory and its rituals?...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>An interview is never one-sided &#8211; in fact, it is a constructive conversation. I am as much a part of this piece as the artist who answered my questions. Without the contributions of the other, individual statements would hold little significance. So thanks, Soli, for letting me share our conversation. </em></p>
<p>International artists in Berlin are one category of newcomers who, although shaping the cultural politics and economic fabric of Berlin perhaps more than other groups of foreign residents (those without German citizenship), are often left out of the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/11/integration-in-berlin-research-for-a-desolate-landscape/">critical integration debate</a>. Whether or not they learn German or German constitutional law seems to matter little to the politicians and journalists fueling the heavily institutionalized, assimilating discourse. I have yet to meet an artist who has been pressured by the authorities to &#8216;integrate&#8217; him or herself, as is the case with members of different social and economic groups.</p>
<p>This semi-privileged position has its benefits: Berlin&#8217;s creatives are often able to ask critical questions of society without being publicly rebuked, far enough from local history to recognize nuance and apply cultural critique in a non-threatening fashion.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2684 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>An example of such an artist is an old friend <a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/">Soliman Lawrence</a>. Soli has been photographing the memorialization of Jewish culture in Poland for years, following the tracks of a new form of engagement with the past, as enacted by a more recent generation of Poles. His collection of work is titled &#8220;<a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/unquietplacesphoto.html">For those whose faith has been broken</a>&#8220;. They do so, as Soliman&#8217;s stories and their pictures explain, through ritual, one example of which is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Klezmer">Klezmer</a> music. The fascinating part of this story: there are few Jews to speak of in Poland.</p>
<p>Beyond a revived Klezmer tradition, Soliman photographs reconstructed synagogues, Jewish-themed festivals, hand-made figurines, the maintenance of Jewish cemeteries &#8211; all weaving a tale of things past, now re-born as an ode to matzo ball soup or rabbinical characters.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2681 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland" width="640" height="423" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11-300x198.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11-650x429.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>Soliman is not Jewish, though his choice of topic likely gets many thinking that personal biography must inform the interest. I met with Soliman at a little cafe in Neukölln to talk art, history, and memory. Parallels between German memorialization of Jewish culture in Berlin and that which is happening in Poland were not at the tip of his tongue; these parallels were on the tip of mine, however.</p>
<p>Soliman is American by passport, has been a Berlin resident for more than 8 years, making the nationality question a bit tricky. He studied philosophy in the United States, stems originally from the Northern part of Florida, and has a contemplative way about him &#8211; he seems to move slowly, take things in and digest them before forming an opinion.</p>
<p>His artistic career began with a camera, has now evolved into a sort of philosophical exploration of what it means to remember. <em>Memory is at the center of my work</em>, he tells me, <em>how people remember after something has passed, how they remember together</em>. He is interested in the idea of <em><a href="http://www.postmemory.net/">post-memory</a>, the ways in which memory stays alive without the original witnesses</em>. Photography serves a crucial purpose, documentation allowing for connection.</p>
<p>Soliman first started making trips to Poland in 2006, visiting the growing Klezmer festivals in places like Krakaw. <em>Here is the biggest and best festival in Poland</em>, he tells me. I imagine VW buses jammed full with young, alternative Poles, spending warm nights outdoors, not for the beat of electronic sounds but for renditions of clarinet and fiddle. Actually, <em>it is quite mixed</em>, he tells me: young/old, hip/not.</p>
<p><em>When I first showed up in Krakaw, I was taking pictures of everything. I assumed a lot of the stuff I was photographing had something to do with Antisemitism &#8211; graffiti on the walls somehow looked antisemitic to me, these little tiles in the main square with five-pointed stars</em>, <em>for example</em>, he says with a laugh. <em>Then I realized that these stars were actually six-pointed, so </em>not <em>necessarily</em> <em>antisemitic</em>. <em>Very often, one finds what one searches for</em>, I add. This is even more true for a photographer, able to capture and catalog what may be happenstance occurrence, curating images into some sort of narrative about a people or place.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2682 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>That doesn&#8217;t mean that Antisemitism isn&#8217;t present in Polish society, however: <em>it&#8217;s complicated</em>, he says. An interview with Soliman on Jewish memorial culture in Poland appeared in 2012 in <em>die</em> <i>Zeit Online </i>with the headline: &#8220;<em>Wie Nicht-Juden die jüdische Kultur Polens wiederbeleben/</em> &#8220;<a href="http://www.zeit.de/video/2012-12/2032360755001/holocaust-wie-nicht-juden-die-juedische-kultur-polens-wiederbeleben">How Non-Jews Are Resurrecting Poland&#8217;s Jewish Culture</a>&#8220;. I recall watching the interview then, having heard of the beginnings of his Polish adventures back in 2010, when Soli and I first met, and being struck by the oddity of it all, the sense of a manufactured experience to take the place of an entire culture now lost. And yet, it was impossible not to find parallels with the city we both share, I felt: the way in which memory of Jewish culture in Berlin is fractured between recreations of the diaspora experience, a come-back Jewish culture in Germany, and a newer wave of young Israelis.</p>
<p>Soli has given quite a number of interviews in Germany since his project first began to receive attention. A <a href="http://juedische-woche-dresden.de/veranstaltung-2013/items/108.html">recent exhibition of his work in Dresden</a> put him into more contact with the German media. <em>So, did any of these journalists ask about your thoughts on Jewish memorialization in Germany, in Berlin, or on any similarities between Poland and Germany?</em>, I ask. At first, he doesn&#8217;t understand my question, seems a bit perplexed. Then, <em>No</em>,<em> in fact, no one even got close to formulating that question. Interesting that you bring that up. </em></p>
<p>Jewish culture in Berlin is diffuse, hard to put a finger on, as &#8211; with Jews everywhere &#8211; there is no one way to be Jewish and certainly no one way to be Jewish in Berlin. A memorial culture is also difficult to construct, when Jews are in fact present. To boot, there is no <em>one</em> way to memorialize the Holocaust and the thriving Jewish culture in Germany that preceded it. At least no one way that would satisfy the diverse groups who were affected by the genocide. In Poland, very little has happened at an institutional, top-down level. And so revivals of classic Ashkenazi traditions like Klezmer have been a means of memorializing a lost sector of Polish life, many years after its musicians were made to disappear.</p>
<p><em>At my first Klezmer festival, I didn&#8217;t really know what to do with myself. People were dancing, it was celebratory, there was this feeling of community</em>, he says. He was a bit stand-offish, not understanding why active participation was required. <em>This is the ritual</em>, he explains, <em>it is through such a collective ritual that some form of memory is reconstructed and created for the next generation.</em> <em>Many of these young people probably have no real connection to contemporary Jewish people</em>, he adds,<em> but this type of memory doesn&#8217;t require personal connection, rather an attachment to space and a desire to make a place &#8211; a memorial &#8211; out of it.</em></p>
<p>In Berlin, there is a strong attention to memorial sites or objects &#8211; the <a href="http://www.stolpersteine-berlin.de/en/stolpersteine"><em>Stolpersteine</em></a>, <a href="http://www.holocaust-mahnmal.de/en"><em>Memorial to the Murdered Jews of Europe</em></a>, <a href="http://www.slowtravelberlin.com/touching-berlins-ghosts/"><em>Bayerisches Viertel</em></a>, to name a few. These are spaces that are visited and even organized by many but are perhaps not as interactive or collective as a Klezmer ritual. One might simply pass by its insignia, whereas Klezmer is somehow a more active process, Soli explains.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2685 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9-300x199.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9-650x432.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p><em>But are these Klezmer festivals in Poland really about remembering and mourning the Holocaust? </em>I ask. <em>Yes, it is about that but not only about that.</em> <em>It is about thinking about the Jews that were once here, by people who were too young to have had the chance</em>.</p>
<p>There is a tendency<em> </em>in memorializing activities to focus on objects and their stories; materiality is desired, physical connection reconstructed. The Holocaust documentation and education center where I used to work curated a collection called &#8220;<a href="http://www.wsherc.org/museum/everyday-objects">Everyday Objects</a>&#8220;, the National Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM) releases <a href="http://www.ushmm.org/information/exhibitions/curators-corner">weekly stories online from its archival vault of objects</a>, and even the recent <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/sportingscene/2014/04/memory-objects-commemorating-the-boston-marathon-bombings.html?utm_source=dlvr.it&amp;utm_medium=twitter">Boston Marathon bombings are being actively commemorated through the collection of ordinary things</a>.</p>
<p><em>When talking with journalists, they just don&#8217;t really understand why Klezmer music is so popular in Poland, </em>Soli comments, as if to emphasize the stark differences between the German memory process and that of the Poland he knows:<em> Memory is expressed differently across space.</em> <em>My work is about these different memory ways, memory forms. </em></p>
<p>Surprising to many, Berlin is home to a fair number of Jews, and not just returned German Jews or those that fled from the former Soviet Union, but Israeli Jews, secular Israelis, secular Diaspora Jews from Argentina etc. &#8211; colliding in one city, not necessarily finding community among one another, because why should they? To make the argument, however, that perhaps things aren&#8217;t as different as they seem, I add that one does see a sort of stereotypical Jewish culture in Berlin, from the <a href="http://www.exberliner.com/locations/luigi-zuckermann-deli/">classic deli</a><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> </span>serving pastrami sandwiches to the local bagel shop. Both places in mind are not run by anyone of Jewish heritage, catering to a historic Jewish culture, perhaps even to New York Jewry rather than Berlin. This is not to say that there are no Jewish delis or bagel shops in Berlin that are owned by Jews. <em>But might the more theatrical recreations be a form of memorial culture, similar to Klezmer festivals?</em> I ask. <em>Maybe</em>, he says, <em>but I know a  few Israelis, and they don&#8217;t necessarily eat bagels. They go to this one shop on </em>Sonnenallee<em> where they can get hummus served warm, like back home in Israel</em>.</p>
<p>The varied layers of Jewish culture, identity, and memory in the Berlin landscape prevent one from making any static comparison to the situation in Poland, it seems &#8211; a place with very few Jews to speak of and a history wrought with a non-institutionalized form of memory, at least until recently. The Israeli and general Jewish presence in Berlin further complicates a comparison between the memory culture of Poland and that of Berlin in a very real sense. To be the authors of a tradition that re-appropriates Jewish tradition means being responsible for potential misappropriation. In Poland, I doubt there are too many active members of the Jewish community who would heavily criticize the rebirth of Klezmer in this form. <em>There aren&#8217;t</em>, Soli says.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2683 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>If he feels strange about researching this issue as an American artist without Jewish descent &#8211; <em>No</em>. The Holocaust is a large part of how Americans understand Germany, I add, in order validate his work from a place of personal opinion. The past was certainly a key factor in my own interest in contemporary German politics and society, as my <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/">article on Sachsenhausen</a> demonstrates.</p>
<p>The question is, if such a connection between a bleak past and curious future can be made, productively, and with much room for nuance and reflection. Soliman Lawrence&#8217;s work allows for just that. Like other artists, he is able to describe memory ways as they are occurring, not overtly criticizing but allowing others to draw their own conclusions or parallels.</p>
<p>We all remember differently. The most important thing is simply to remember.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>Jewish identity in Berlin, Jews in Germany, Israelis in Berlin: there is no shortage of debate, public presence, or diversity. Here a recent <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/culture/2014/05/so-long-israel-hello-berlin.html">article from <em>The New Yorker</em></a> on this topic and a few articles from us, written from the most varied of positions:</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/">Why Remembering the Holocaust is Good for Immigrants</a> &#8211; integration policy and a visit to Sachsenhausen concentration camp</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/07/rant-or-rave-jew-in-a-box/">Rant or Rave? Jew in a Box</a> &#8211; a controversial exhibit at the Berlin Jewish Museum</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">Interview: TV, the Treasury Minister, and Third Culture Kids</a> &#8211; Israeli in Berlin</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/07/interview-three-dimensions-of-integration/">Interview: Three Dimensions of Integration</a> &#8211; Jewish-American artist in Berlin</p>
<p>Last but not least, a few links for finding that Jewish deli or that Israeli hummus: <a href="http://www.berlinfo.com/Lifetime/Shopping/food/jewish/, http://forward.com/articles/165718/berlins-jewish-comeback/?p=al">Berlins Jewish Comeback</a>, <a href="//www.hagalil.com/deutschland/berlin/gemeinde/kosher.htm">Hagalil</a>, <a href="http://www.jewish-berlin.com/kosher.php">Jewish-Berlin</a>, <a href="http://www.berlinjewish.com/tips-for-your-berlin-vacation">Jewish in Berlin</a>, <a href="http://www.exberliner.com/food/land-of-the-lox-can-you-get-deli-food-in-berlin/">ExBerliner deli food list</a>.</p>
<p><em>All images were graciously provided by Soliman Lawrence as part of the series &#8220;<a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/unquietplacesphoto.html">For those whose faith has been broken</a>&#8220;. To see some of Soliman&#8217;s newer projects, check out his homepage. </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Seeing Berlin Through The Homeless</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2014 12:22:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bureaucracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GDR-DDR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitte]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Schöneberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2398</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[They wait for the subway doors to close before they address the car with a rehearsed speech. "Excuse the interruption, I am one of Berlin's annoying homeless people"... it usually begins, as they peddle newspapers and scan the crowd for an outstretched hand holding change or food. The majority of us keep our hands tucked away or firmly gripping our phones. Some of us fall into convenient bouts of exhaustion, promptly leaning back and closing our eyes. In this moment, we are restricted to a shared space...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_2604" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2604" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2604 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-650x433.jpg" alt="hermannplatz" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2604" class="wp-caption-text">Photo by Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>In Berlin they are especially visible on the <em>Bahn</em>. They wait for the subway doors to close before they address the car with a rehearsed speech. <em>Excuse the interruption, I am one of Berlin&#8217;s annoying homeless people&#8230;</em> it usually begins, as they peddle newspapers and scan<em> </em>the crowd for an outstretched hand holding change or food. The majority of us keep our hands tucked away or firmly gripping our phones. Some of us fall into convenient bouts of exhaustion, promptly leaning back and closing our eyes. In this moment, we are restricted to a moving car, a shared space. We can&#8217;t dodge a corner or cross the street, but we still find ways to make them invisible. We don&#8217;t look up because we feel uncomfortable. We become frustrated at them for making us feel this way. We may even become angry &#8211; at them, at society, at ourselves.</p>
<p>How the simple presence of one person can incite so much emotion, judgement, and shame.</p>
<p>How it must feel, to be simultaneously so visible and invisible.</p>
<div id="attachment_2605" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2605" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2605 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-650x459.jpg" alt="eye" width="650" height="459" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-650x459.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-300x212.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2605" class="wp-caption-text">Photo by Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><em>It&#8217;s one of the worst things for homeless people, being treated as invisible. Answer them when they speak to you, make eye contact, acknowledge them!</em> our guide Carsten Voss urges us by the end of our walk. We are wrapping up a tour called &#8220;Obdachslose zeigen ihr Berlin&#8221; (The homeless present their Berlin), run by non-profit organization <em>Querstadtein. </em>The group offers tours in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Mitte that show the reality of homelessness in the city.</p>
<p>Our guide speaks from personal experience. Decked out in designer glasses and a well-fitting sweater, it&#8217;s challenging to picture this man as the subject of the powerful story he delivers in front of stately <span class="st">Viktoria-Luise-Platz</span>. Carsten worked 80+ hours a week as a manager of an international tradeshow before burning-out and falling into depression. First came the loss of his job, then his apartment. He refused help from loved ones, other than taking refuge in a friend&#8217;s shed for a few months. It would be a year before he clawed his way back out. He cites one defining moment: <em>I happened to glance into someone&#8217;s window from the street. The woman was cooking and the man was watching </em>Tagesschau<em> on TV&#8230; I realized that if I didn&#8217;t make a change then, I would never have that again.</em></p>
<p>That year Carsten counted among Berlin&#8217;s estimated 4,000 <em>Obdachslose</em> (literally translates to &#8220;without shelter&#8221;). Not to be confused with <em>Wohnungslose</em> (&#8220;house-less&#8221;), which refers to those without homes but still in the system, <em>Obdachslose</em> are no longer in the system and may or may not have a place to sleep. Berlin has Germany&#8217;s highest concentration of <em>Obdachslose, </em>both from within and outside of the country.</p>
<p><em>There are three main categories of </em>Obdachslose <em>in Berlin</em>, Carsten explains early on in the tour. <em>Former refugees from East Germany, those groups of young people who usually have dogs with them, and immigrants.<br />
</em></p>
<p><a href="http://ec.europa.eu/social/main.jsp?catId=1061&amp;langId=en">Migrant homelessness throughout the EU</a> has risen in recent years, exacerbated by the economic crisis. This may come as no great surprise, though it&#8217;s a blow to hear that many in Berlin<em> end up staying because they find the conditions of being homeless here better than their lives back home. </em>Carsten describes this group in three geographic waves: the first from Poland, second from the Baltics, and third from Bulgaria and Romania<em>. Of course they came here planning to find jobs, start families, create a life. Some make it, but many don&#8217;t. </em></p>
<div id="attachment_2586" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-23-14-33-35.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2586" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2586 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-23-14-33-35.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-23 14.33.35" width="640" height="480" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2586" class="wp-caption-text">Cold Weather Assistance for Berlin&#8217;s Homeless by District, Winter 2013/14</p></div>
<p>Berlin has a long tradition of homelessness. It&#8217;s a poor city &#8211; Germany&#8217;s poorest &#8211; but also equipped with robust social services. Berlin has a history of attracting those who are &#8220;different&#8221;, including many immigrants, due to its diversity and tolerant atmosphere. During the days of the Berlin Wall, it was also a haven for males escaping military conscription (which ended altogether in 2011). Carsten moved to Berlin for this reason, and says he and many others like him entered fields like social work and education. This, he claims, has contributed to the city&#8217;s liberal nature and strong social net.</p>
<p>Berlin&#8217;s homeless tend to cluster in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Charlottenburg, two districts in West Berlin now more associated with high rents and artisanal cafes than alternative lifestyles. Carsten guides us to Nollendorfplatz, Berlin&#8217;s LGBT hub and site of the annual pride parade, Christopher Street Day. We stand across from the colorful <em>Regenbogen-Stele, </em>a r<span class="userContent">ainbow column erected in 2000 to celebrate the area&#8217;s high concentration of homosexual residents and open-minded atmosp<span class="text_exposed_show">here. The statue itself carries two symbols: the rainbow flag for gay pride and the <em>Rosa Winkel</em>, a pink badge first used by Nazis to distinguish homosexuals in concentration camps, and what later became an international symbol for gay rights.<br />
</span></span></p>
<div id="attachment_2507" style="width: 538px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/2014-03-23-14-21-00-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2507" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2507" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/2014-03-23-14-21-00-1.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-23 14.21.00-1" width="528" height="528" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2507" class="wp-caption-text">Nollendorf Platz&#8217;s &#8220;Regenbogen-Stele&#8221; or rainbow column celebrating gay rights</p></div>
<p>As we inspect the square, Carsten points out what our untrained eyes fail to see: a 24-hour grocery store well-equipped with bottle deposit machines, a van selling the street newspaper, a well-lit intersection. <em>Homeless people are part of this neighborhood, they have a community here</em>, he says.</p>
<p>But another faction of the city&#8217;s homeless blend in so well that we don&#8217;t see them at all. <em>Most people have an image in mind of the bag lady (or guy), unkempt and dirty, pushing around a cart filled to the brim with random items, muttering crazy things to themselves.</em>.<em>. most homeless people don&#8217;t look or act like that. </em> Carsten estimates that 60% fall into this category, homeless people who look &#8220;normal&#8221; so they can use spaces and services within the city without being noticed. They schedule their day in such a way that they always have a place to be, something to eat, even a bed to sleep in. They know when the citizens&#8217; office opens and when they can grab a shower, when they can rest in the library or supermarket, who is offering a free lunch or haircut in the city. <em>It&#8217;s an exhausting life, they have to be very organized, and they are constantly in public</em>, Carsten emphasizes: <em>the only time they have to themselves is in the shower.</em></p>
<div id="attachment_2621" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-24-08-25-20.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2621" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2621 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-24-08-25-20.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-24 08.25.20" width="640" height="480" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2621" class="wp-caption-text">Assistance notice for homeless youth in Charlottenburg</p></div>
<p>Carsten&#8217;s happy ending is a welcome take-away from an otherwise harrowing topic, but he warns against the assumption that all homeless people are unhappy or need to be saved. While many do suffer from mental illness and drug and alcohol abuse, others have deliberately chosen this lifestyle. <em>Some people want to live this way, and we have to respect that. We have to recognize them as part of society.</em></p>
<p><span class="userContent"><span class="text_exposed_show">It&#8217;s easy to dodge corners and cross streets, to switch subway cars to avoid someone&#8217;s stench or words, to grip our phones and look down. </span></span></p>
<p>It&#8217;s not as easy to look up.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>The Querstadtein homeless tours (in German) take place in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Mitte, usually on Sundays and for approximately 2 hours. Tickets cost <span class="st">€</span>9,40, and <span class="st">€</span>5,40 for students, seniors, and individuals on welfare. More information can be found at <em>http://querstadtein.org/de/stadtfuehrungen/.<br />
</em></p>
<p>For more on the Querstadtein tours in English, click <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/zeitgeist/berlin-tour-gives-a-glimpse-of-berlin-as-seen-by-homeless-people-a-913758.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>For more on the increasing restrictions on public space for homeless people across Europe, <a href="http://www.surveillance-and-society.org/articles5%283%29/homelessness.pdf">click here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reviewing the Rave: &#8220;We are the We&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/13/reviewing-the-rave-we-are-the-we/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 21:04:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1269</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We're so used to talking all the time that words tend to lose their effect. Especially when the talking is predominantly happening in one direction, as it so often does in immigration discourse. The <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/02/rave-i-am-not-a-terrorist/">Migrantas</a> organization is unleashing an alternate voice within immigrant women in Germany that is arguably just as powerful: their artistic creativity...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/1085152_547637008637523_1494864328_o.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-1277 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/1085152_547637008637523_1494864328_o.jpg?w=640" alt="1085152_547637008637523_1494864328_o" width="640" height="426" /></a></p>
<p>We&#8217;re so used to talking all the time that words tend to lose their effect. Especially when the talking is predominantly happening in one direction, as it so often does in immigration discourse. The <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/02/rave-i-am-not-a-terrorist/">Migrantas</a> organization is unleashing an alternate voice within immigrant women in Germany that is arguably just as powerful: their artistic creativity. Simple pencil and paper sketches are transformed into pictograms by the Migrantas artists, then shared with the city on billboards, postcards, and public transit. The finished products don&#8217;t utter a sound but are easily worth more than a thousand words.</p>
<p>This past April, Kelly and I participated in one of a series of <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/02/rave-i-am-not-a-terrorist/">Migrantas workshops</a> in Berlin. Though the two of us pretty much <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/about/">live and breathe immigration</a>, we were surprised how much there was left to reflect upon, namely our own migration experiences. For over two hours, we scribbled alongside five other participants in the very fitting <em>Haus der Kulturen der Welt</em> (House of World Cultures), producing a total of 28 sketches for the artists to work with. Our workshop group was younger than average and also more mobile and privileged: we were all well-educated and, except for Kelly, in possession of the highly-coveted EU passport. But the dynamics of integration go far beyond the legal and political. Economically, linguistically, professionally, socially, personally, even romantically&#8230; in one way or another we were all struggling to feel like insiders.  At the same time, we recognized and celebrated the excitement, enrichment, and fulfillment that accompanies the process.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/img_3348.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/img_3348.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_3348" width="640" height="368" /></a><strong>&#8220;Migration = Enrichment&#8221;/&#8221;&#8216;<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">Migrants&#8217; anyway</a>&#8221; <strong>(despite having a German passport)</strong><br />
</strong></p>
<p>This past Friday came the big reveal: we gathered with members of other workshops and the interested public at Berlin&#8217;s <em>Rotes Rathaus</em> for the opening of the exhibit showcasing our work. The exhibit was simple and straightforward, just like the Migrantas concept. A singular stretch of sketches grouped into common themes around accompanying pictograms. No curators, no conjectures, no conclusions. Only an opportunity to see the world through someone else&#8217;s lens and pencil strokes.</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-09-47-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3423" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-09-47-1-650x650.jpg" alt="2013-08-09-20-09-47-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-09-47-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-09-47-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></strong></p>
<p>The biggest take-away for Kelly and me came in how much in common we seemed to have with children of Turkish guest workers, students from Brazil, and grandmothers from Kurdistan. While our migration contexts, freedom of mobility, and future plans certainly vary drastically, our feelings about the integration process were at times strikingly similar. One group of images showed X&#8217;s over a mouth, a knot in a tongue, a speech bubble filled with jibber-jabber, and the phrase &#8220;I&#8217;m not stupid, I&#8217;m just starting to learn German!&#8221;. Where words may have only shown difference, our sketches revealed connection and commonality, finding themselves side-by-side on the board.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-25-01-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3424" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-25-01-1-650x650.jpg" alt="2013-08-09-20-25-01-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-25-01-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-25-01-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><strong>&#8220;Authorities&#8221;. Sketches underneath and to the right of the main pictogram by Kelly.</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/img_3390.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/img_3390.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_3390" width="518" height="518" /></a><strong>&#8220;Job, Effort, Luck, Rejection, Trainee, Intern, Degree, Training&#8221;. Sketch on upper right by Sophia.</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-28-36.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-28-36.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-08-09 20.28.36" width="640" height="480" /></a><strong>&#8220;Language, Communication, Friendship, Feelings, Smile&#8221;</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-24-00-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3426" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-24-00-1-650x650.jpg" alt="2013-08-09-20-24-00-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-24-00-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-24-00-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><strong>&#8220;Heimweh&#8221;/&#8221;Homesickness&#8221;</strong></p>
<p>The points of commonality extended beyond those with migration backgrounds, perhaps one of the most valuable but under-appreciated aspects of the work Migrantas does. As one German presenter shared during her welcome speech, images of twisted tongues and closed mouths transported her back to her first experience abroad in Spain with her family and the frustration and fear she felt about not being able to communicate. &#8220;My mother taught me the term <em>no hablo español</em>, and I noticed that the pronoun was missing. I thought she did it on purpose so that it&#8217;d be really clear I couldn&#8217;t speak the language.&#8221; Immigrants or not, these images deliver the compelling message that we are all individuals, we all have multi-faceted identities, and we have all at some point or another felt different. <em>Wir sind das Wir</em>. We are the we.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3427" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27-650x487.jpg" alt="2013-08-09-20-14-27" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2migrantas_piktogramm_wir_sind_das_wir_300dpi.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1337" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2migrantas_piktogramm_wir_sind_das_wir_300dpi.jpg?w=640" alt="migrantas_piktogram_wir_sind_das_wir_300dpi" width="589" height="589" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton </strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>Don&#8217;t forget to check out the Migrantas exhibit for yourself at Berlin&#8217;s </em>Rotes Rathaus at <em>Alexanderplatz. Free to the public and open until August 27th. Keep an eye out for upcoming Migrantas workshops and exhibitions around Germany by liking them on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/migrantas/144071052327456">Facebook</a>. Registration is free and open to all with a migration story to the city where they now reside.<br />
</em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">First and last photos by Ruben Gonzalez Escudero/Migrantas; all other photos by Sophia Burton</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rave: Neukölln&#8217;s Intercultural Day-to-Day</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2013 14:37:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gentrification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=891</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A Berlin restaurant with an American name run by a Tunisian who prepares Italian fare in Halal style? Anywhere else this collision of cultures on a plate would be considered poor marketing.  In Neukölln it's more or less the norm...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/2013-06-15-15-09-14.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-892 aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/2013-06-15-15-09-14.jpg" alt="2013-06-15 15.09.14" width="640" height="480" /></a>A Berlin restaurant with an American name run by a Tunisian who prepares Italian fare in Halal style? Anywhere else this collision of cultures on a plate would be considered poor marketing.  In Neukölln it&#8217;s more or less the norm.</p>
<p>&#8220;L.A. New York Restaurant&#8221; was the second stop along <em>Erkundung im Paradies, </em>one of numerous tours offered by <a href="http://route44-neukoelln.de/touren/paradies_tour1.html">Route 44</a> that explore Neukölln&#8217;s migration history and interculturalism. The tours are entirely female-run and designed by a group of diverse women who are proud to call Neukölln their &#8220;(second) home&#8221;.</p>
<p>Neukölln is Berlin&#8217;s 8th district and home to 320,000 residents, approximately 40% of which are not ethnically German. Almost 150 nationalities are represented (primarily Turkey, the Arab world, and former Yugoslavia) and the district is at the heart of Berlin&#8217;s gentrification debate, making Neukölln hard to ignore. Nonetheless, it was off my radar for years and continues to be for tourists who either don&#8217;t know it exists or have been warned it&#8217;s too dangerous to visit. My 250 page Berlin guide book from 2003 doesn&#8217;t say one word about Neukölln. Ten years later and it&#8217;s still not mentioned on <a href="http://www.timeout.com/berlin/features/10/berlin-area-guide">this list</a> or <a href="http://www.fodors.com/news/understanding-berlins-neighborhoods-5831.html">this list</a> or <a href="http://www.cityscouter.com/travelguides/berlin/Berlin-Districts.html">this list</a>. It is on <a href="http://berlin.cityseekr.com/cityguide/district-guide-1">this one</a>: &#8220;More down-to-earth are the working-class districts of Wedding in the north and Neukölln in the south, which is sometimes referred to as the Berlin Bronx. Although they both have a reputation of being ghettos for the poor, unemployed and other down-and-outs, they are not as bad as they are made out to be.&#8221; What a ringing endorsement.<em><br />
</em></p>
<p>The Route 44 girls describe Neukölln as a region of &#8220;irritating problems but fascinating potential&#8221;. Unfortunately Neukölln&#8217;s problems go beyond irritating to downright serious: they have one of the city&#8217;s highest unemployment rates (<a href="http://www.berlin.de/ba-neukoelln/derbezirk/arbeitslose.html">17%</a>), high child poverty rates, and a crime rate that is about 40% higher than Berlin&#8217;s average. But it is also home to immense diversity, creativity, and rich cultural history. Reducing Neukölln (or any struggling region) to the &#8220;poor, unemployed and other down-and-outs&#8221; is not only unfair, it&#8217;s unproductive.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/2013-06-15-15-44-50.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/2013-06-15-15-44-50.jpg" alt="2013-06-15 15.44.50" width="640" height="480" /></a><em>Erkundung im Paradies</em> or &#8220;Exploring Paradise&#8221; showcases this &#8220;fascinating potential&#8221; through an exploration of a neighborhood and its various houses of worship, educational institutions, trendy bars, and international restaurants. Yet perhaps the most interesting facet of the tour was not the stops itself, but the open dialogue it generated. The tour participants were largely locals and the intermittent chatter and questions culminated in a discussion on religion and the role of the headscarf. Hiba and Maria, our guides, responded openly and respectfully to questions from the group that ranged from  &#8220;Aren&#8217;t women forced to wear them?&#8221; to &#8220;Why don&#8217;t you wear one?&#8221; Hiba (Lebanese-German) and Maria (Pakistani-German) don&#8217;t wear headscarves and explained that while it&#8217;s a commitment they&#8217;re not ready to make now, they don&#8217;t rule it out for the future. Either way, it&#8217;s their choice alone.</p>
<p>When asked by a  journalist why they do the tours, they responded quite simply: &#8220;Neukölln has a bad reputation, and we want to change that.&#8221;</p>
<p>I&#8217;d say the guidebooks should take note, but I&#8217;m not sure we need them. These women are creating their own and it&#8217;s a lot more interesting.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>For more information on Route 44 tours, click <a href="http://route44-neukoelln.de/touren.html">here</a>. Tours are offered every first and third Saturday of the month and registration is not necessary. Bring something to cover your shoulders during visits to houses of worship. Tours are given in German but the guides offer a variety of other languages that include English, Urdu, Arabic, and Turkish.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>Funkhaus Europa recorded the above-mentioned tour and you can access the article and audio <a href="http://www.radiobremen.de/funkhauseuropa/aktuell/aktuell590.html">here. </a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Happy Weekend: A Roma (Re)Image</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/01/happy-weekend-a-roma-reimage/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/01/happy-weekend-a-roma-reimage/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2013 10:16:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=687</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Your perception of the Roma is inaccurate. I apologize for the bluntness, but you and I both know it's true. And <em>I</em> know you and I both know it's true because it's true for me, and I've studied this stuff. Not only have I studied this stuff (e.g. migration, integration, intercultural relations), but I consider myself a beacon of political correctness, yet I've <em>still</em> dressed up as a gypsy for Halloween more times than I care to admit. Why? ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I can think of several reasons why you should attend this Roma photography exhibit this weekend, and not just because your outdoor plans are shot thanks to this <em>über</em>-frustrating weather.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/roma-image-ausstellung-572x382.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/roma-image-ausstellung-572x382.jpg" alt="Roma-Image-Ausstellung-572x382" width="515" height="344" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Reason #1: Your perception of the Roma is inaccurate<br />
</strong></p>
<p>I apologize for the bluntness, but you and I both know it&#8217;s true. And <em>I</em> know you and I both know it&#8217;s true because it&#8217;s true for me, and I&#8217;ve studied this stuff. Not only have I studied this stuff (e.g. migration, integration, intercultural relations), but I consider myself a beacon of political correctness, yet I&#8217;ve <em>still</em> dressed up as a gypsy for Halloween more times than I care to admit. Why?</p>
<p><strong>Because the Roma are one of Europe&#8217;s most misunderstood, over-stereotyped, and under-represented groups. </strong></p>
<p>The Roma are known for residing in the outskirts of town &#8211; both physically and mentally &#8211; in &#8220;parallel societies&#8221;. Many believe that the Roma are either incapable or just plain unwilling to integrate. Yet, as is the case with many minority groups, there are much more powerful structural forces at work behind this phenomenon. Periods of political unrest and transition, targeted discrimination, cuts in welfare spending, and school and housing segregation have all contributed to (or caused, depending on how you want to see it)  the struggles and alienation of the European Roma. As a reaction to systematic discrimination, groups often tread even further away from mainstream society than they&#8217;ve already been pushed, which in turn fuels damaging stereotypes. And &#8217;round and &#8217;round we go.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/2w650c0-bild.jpeg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/2w650c0-bild.jpeg" alt="2,w=650,c=0.bild" width="576" height="324" /></a><a href="http://www.bild.de/news/inland/einbuergerung/die-wahrheit-ueber-armuts-einwanderung-in-deutschland-29361086.bild.html">Source</a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Reason #2: A Romani identity may be a misnomer, but it&#8217;s worth exploring</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">&#8220;Roma&#8221; is a blanket term for a group of people who originally migrated to Europe from India almost 1,000 years ago. They&#8217;re most commonly known as &#8220;Gypsies,&#8221; a name that actually comes from &#8220;Egyptian,&#8221; which they were initially mistaken for by Europeans due to their darker skin and colorful attire. Today, European Roma mostly come from the Balkans and their environs, the majority living in Bulgaria and Romania. Characterized by their nomadic lifestyle, the <strong>Roma can be found all throughout Europe and are the continent&#8217;s largest minority group</strong>.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">The Roma are therefore a diverse diaspora &#8211; much more so than they are often portrayed &#8211; which is why some call the search for a shared Romani identity and culture a vain endeavor. It may also play a role in why Germany didn&#8217;t recognize the killing of Roma during the Holocaust as ethnic genocide  until 1982 &#8211; although an estimated <a href="http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/en/article.php?ModuleId=10005219">25% of European Roma</a> were annihilated. By the time many Roma victims finally &#8220;qualified&#8221; for restitution, many of them had passed away.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Today, there is a fear and misconception of massive immigration of Roma to richer Western European countries since the admittance of Bulgaria and Romania to the EU in 2007. France went so far as to <a href="http://www.migrationinformation.org/Feature/display.cfm?ID=803">deport</a> more than 1,000 Roma back to their home countries in 2010. In Germany, the reality is that 80% of immigrants from these countries posses regular work and the net-migration rate (how many are arriving minus how many have left again) has since balanced out.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/eu-umgang-roma.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-703 aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/eu-umgang-roma.jpg" alt="eu-umgang-roma" width="640" height="463" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/eu-umgang-roma.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/eu-umgang-roma-300x217.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/eu-umgang-roma-650x470.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><a href="http://www.google.de/imgres?um=1&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sa=N&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;hl=de&amp;biw=1662&amp;bih=844&amp;tbm=isch&amp;tbnid=9C-iGQ-Mg6jbEM:&amp;imgrefurl=http://www.sueddeutsche.de/politik/roma-in-europa-eine-politische-bombe-1.1003626&amp;docid=zMsY0p6oyv6BTM&amp;imgurl=http://polpix.sueddeutsche.com/bild/1.1003627.1355793366/860x860/eu-umgang-roma.jpg&amp;w=860&amp;h=623&amp;ei=yGKnUZC7JImctQbNy4DIAg&amp;zoom=1&amp;iact=rc&amp;dur=430&amp;page=2&amp;tbnh=139&amp;tbnw=195&amp;start=35&amp;ndsp=43&amp;ved=1t:429,r:76,s:0,i:318&amp;tx=61&amp;ty=80">Source</a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Reason #3: The Roma deserve a space within Berlin&#8217;s (and Europe&#8217;s) cultural scene</strong></p>
<p>The Roma suffer from abject poverty, inadequate access to education and health care, and illiteracy (only <a href="http://www.bild.de/politik/inland/migration/die-6-wahrheiten-ueber-roma-29384608.bild.html">42% </a>of European Roma finish elementary school). They are also the targets of deep-rooted prejudice and stereotypes, a popular one being that they are all beggars and criminals.</p>
<p>Part of this exhibit&#8217;s goal is to explore and showcase the complexity of Roma identity by allocating a space for Romani artists. Rather than portraying images solely <em>of</em> Roma, this exhibit provides a space for the <em>work of</em> Roma, giving the group a space for cultural expression, recognition, and validation.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/roma_dpa.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/roma_dpa.jpg" alt="Roma Camp near Paris" width="640" height="320" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.taz.de/!113346/">Source</a></p>
<p><strong>Reason #4: It&#8217;s your last chance</strong></p>
<p>This weekend marks the last few days of  the Roma Image Studio exhibit, which concludes on June 2. You can find it in Neukölln&#8217;s <em>Galerie im Saalbau</em> on Karl-Marx-Straße 141. Admittance (and stereotype-debunking) free.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>Sources and more reading:</p>
<p>Exhibit description and photo <a href="http://www.neukoellner.net/kunst-kitsch/weg-vom-roma-klischee/">source</a> (German)</p>
<p>http://www.migrationinformation.org/Feature/display.cfm?ID=803 (English)</p>
<p>http://www.bbc.co.uk/insideout/southeast/series6/gypsy_travels.shtml (English)</p>
<p>http://www.dw.de/roma-more-integration-through-education/a-16662455 (English)</p>
<p>http://www.bild.de/politik/inland/migration/die-6-wahrheiten-ueber-roma-29384608.bild.html (German)</p>
<p>http://www.amaroforo.de/ (German)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/01/happy-weekend-a-roma-reimage/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rave: &#8220;I am not a Terrorist&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/02/rave-i-am-not-a-terrorist/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2013 12:00:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[design]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.wordpress.com/?p=69</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In Berlin, the dimensions of migration and diversity may sometimes be over-simplified, but groups like Migrantas are changing that, and doing so creatively. The best part: the voice and agency of the "immigrants", so often talked-about and so seldom talking-back, take center stage...
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>Migrantas &#8211; Visual Language of Migration</h3>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://www.grassrootsfeminism.net/cms/sites/default/files/logotype_migrantas.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="200" /></p>
<p><em>Occasionally, we will share either a little rant (something we dare to criticize) or a little rave (something we love)&#8230;maybe even both depending on the kind of juices we have flowing in response to this magnificent concrete jungle of ours. I wrote this particular Rave before having contacted the artistic heroes of <a href="http://www.migrantas.org/">Migrantas</a>, before having taken part in the process of telling my migration story and finding myself nearly in tears, not quite knowing what it was I had to share. Storytelling is like that, full of surprises and revelations. Sophia and I were two of the seven participants in the Berlin Migrantas workshop this past week. We are proud to announce that impressions and sketches will be exhibited in the </em>Rotes Rathaus<em> this coming August, three graphic designs resulting from the workshop to be seen on street corners around Berlin, as well. Until then, enjoy this little pat-on-the-back for some locally-based activists&#8230;</em></p>
<p>Recognizing difference in daily life is good for everyone &#8211; different conceptions of beauty, different beliefs in the cosmos, different  ideas of home and the familiar, even different interpretations of the classic sandwich. The more we realize that the uniqueness of our own culture(s) is only part and parcel to the city&#8217;s greater beat, the richer our lives, even if <i>Käsebrot</i> (a cheese and butter sandwich) will never know the joys of aioli and thinly-sliced tomato.</p>
<p>Today&#8217;s applause for doing the good work of &#8220;telling&#8221; such difference goes to the <a href="http://www.migrantas.blogspot.de/">Migrantas</a> project, whose particular bent on migration-focused creative activism came into my life by happenstance: passing an exhibition of their work in the halls of one of my university&#8217;s hideously functionalist buildings.</p>
<p>In Berlin, the dimensions of migration and diversity may sometimes be over-simplified, but groups like Migrantas are changing that, and doing so creatively. The best part: the voice and agency of the &#8220;immigrants&#8221;, so often talked-about and so seldom talking-back, take center stage.</p>
<p>The child of visual arts, graphic design, and social sciences, the workshop teams of Migrantas transform questions of movement, displacement, adjustment, and integration into opportunities for intercultural visual dialogue. At workshops organized between artists and (im)migrants, participants are asked to draw their multicultural, multi-layered experiences quickly with pencils. Little guidance is provided &#8211; call it a stream-of-consciousness meets ink blot approach to finding voice and using it. And then the sharing begins; a narrative catharsis, of sorts, ensues.</p>
<p>In the months following, the graphic designers work to transform these pieces of &#8220;voice&#8221; into simple but effective designs for the city, essentially designs meant to fit flexibly within the many nooks and crannies of public understanding. Posted like advertisements at bus stops or on prominent corners, public space is transformed. The city itself becomes a  &#8220;platform aimed to make visible the thoughts and feelings of those who have left their own country and now live in a new one&#8221; (Migrantas.org).</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://www.atissuejournal.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/Imigration_05.jpg" alt="" width="615" height="301" /></p>
<p>In 2006, Berlin played host to Migrantas exhibitions, seen from the anonymous seats of the U-Bahn to postcard-sized images found in smoky corners of the bar scene. Expect much more to come from this little army of activists in August 2013.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Keep an eye out for upcoming Migrantas workshops and exhibitions, by liking them on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/migrantas/144071052327456">facebook </a>. Registration is free and open to all with a migration story to the city where they now reside. ***And be </em><em>sure to send us suggestions for rants or raves in the future! We can&#8217;t always be so passionately opinionated <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.0.1/72x72/1f642.png" alt="🙂" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /> ***</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
