<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Religion &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/category/religion/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Why Feminism and Hijab Go Together</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/12/04/feminism-hijab-go-together/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2016 09:30:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[feminism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hijab]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4704</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As Muslim refugees who choose to wear hijab become a lasting part of the societies of those European states that have taken them in, their right to be different must be defended. Most importantly, we must defend the right of women to choose. It is this choice that makes women free. This is why feminism and hijab go together.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Donald Trump will soon take over the most (seemingly) powerful office in the United States. In just one month,&nbsp;<em>Vogue</em> will launch&nbsp;its <a href="http://en.vogue.fr/fashion/fashion-news/articles/conde-nast-international-launches-vogue-arabia/43938">first ever Arabia edition</a>. These two events are related &#8211; by hijab.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Only hours after Trump was proclaimed victor by electoral vote, a certain fear took hold in minority populations in the United States. Fear of deportation, of political oppression, of social persecution. This fear has proven itself well-founded. The Southern Poverty Law Center recently reported </span><a href="http://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/hate-on-the-rise-after-trumps-election">a dramatic increase in hate crimes and xenophobic harassment</a>, since Trump’s victory.</p>
<div id="attachment_4711" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4711" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4711 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341-650x433.jpg" alt="reise_usa-2015-bearbeitet-341" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4711" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Given the President-elect’s verbal attacks on Islam and Muslims in (or coming to) America, this fear of emboldened hostility in the general populace is felt <a href="http://people.com/bodies/muslim-women-scared-wear-hijab-trump-win/">ever so acutely</a> by America’s diverse Muslim community. Muslim women, in particular, have expressed a new hesitation to wear hijab in public &#8211; the traditional headscarf &#8211; following the election. As </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">New York Magazine</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> reports, many young Muslima <a href="http://nymag.com/thecut/2016/11/after-trumps-win-muslim-women-are-afraid-to-wear-the-hijab.html">took this fear to twitter</a>. One young woman tweeted her devout mother’s words of caution, &#8220;Please don’t wear your hijab today,&#8221; only to be attacked by right-wing trolls, twitter’s escalating problem in this age of free speech and anti-democratic vitriol. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Whether or not a Trump presidency and its fallout will actually lead to physical harm of Muslim women is not something we can know, right now. But we can juxtapose this fear&nbsp;with hijab as an object of both identity and ridicule&nbsp;&#8211; an object that conservative movements and some European governments have taken outright offense to.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Editor-in-chief of Vogue<em> Arabia</em> is a Saudi princess, a self-professed queen of elegant women in any silhouette. She, </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Deena Aljuhani Abdulaziz, </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">is also a champion of the down-to-earth cat-walk. And she does not (perhaps no surprise here) actually live in the Kingdom</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Although D. Aljuhani Abdulaziz&nbsp;does not herself wear hijab, she supports women who do. According to her interview with </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The New York Times</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, the consumer preferences of Muslim women are <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/11/03/fashion/islamic-fashion-vogue-arabia.html">at the core of this <em>Vogue</em></a>. The magazine’s mission for women in the Muslim world, she explained, is to highlight dress in its femininity, its creativity, and its usage by everyday women across the Arab world, hijab or no hijab. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is not only Arab women living in Doha or Beirut who ascribe to the beauty norms of hijab-wearing models and hijab-based marketing, thus <em>Vogue Arabia</em>’s readership will surely not stay confined to the Arab world. It is published online in both English and Arabic and maintains an international aesthetic (both in branding and in the women who gloss its pages). The princess and Conde Nast seem cognizant of the status of women in hijab: they represent an established style and lifestyle, on a global scale. </span></p>
<div id="attachment_4712" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4712" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4712 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2-650x433.jpg" alt="reise_london-2014-bearbeitet-2" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4712" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This recognition is not limited to Big Money in the Arab world. Women in hijab have begun to take their place among trendsetting brands in countries in which they are decidedly the minority. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Even in Trump’s America, CoverGirl recently <a href="http://firsttoknow.com/meet-the-new-face-of-covergirl-hijab-wearing-beauty-blogger-nura-afia/?utm_source=contentad_backfill&amp;utm_campaign=meet-the-new-face-of-cov-211246&amp;pp=1&amp;utm_medium=180533">added a Muslima in hijab</a> to its blogosphere and promotional sites, a hijab-friendly designer <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-37381770">stole the show at this year’s New York Fashion Week</a>, a U.S. beauty pageant contestant&nbsp;did <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/goatsandsoda/2016/11/29/503729951/the-beauty-pageant-contestant-wore-a-burkini">the whole thing in burkini and hijab</a>, and (if you haven’t heard) Marvel released <a href="http://marvel.wikia.com/wiki/Kamala_Khan_(Earth-616)">its first Muslima superhero</a>. Yes, even superheroes can wear scarves, and <a href="https://mic.com/articles/125199/badass-muslim-superheroes-comics-tv">it doesn&#8217;t stop at Marvel</a>.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><em>Vogue</em> and these other agents of popular culture bring the hijab into a different type of mainstream &#8211; of fashion and femininity. In asserting that &#8220;Yes, this too is a woman,&#8221; a woman’s choice of what to wear is expanded. Bikinis were first <a href="http://content.time.com/time/photogallery/0,29307,1908353_1905442,00.html">popularized and freed from social taboo</a> by aggressive marketing campaigns and photo-shoots. So, why not hijab? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Perhaps the most important point, however, is not whether or not hijab can be normalized; it is whether or not such mainstreaming actually leads to more freedom. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the case of Muslima in increasingly hostile environments, such as the United States or any European state as of late, this freedom is being put to the test. Hijab or body-covering of any sort is increasingly becoming a marker of difference. With the rise of the populist Right, our societies are becoming more and more opposed to such difference. And the power of the masses has, historically, had something to say about women’s dress, women’s bodies, and, ultimately, women’s rights. For better or for worse.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Women’s heads have been the subject of political struggle for centuries. In this century, the forcible removal of hijab has corresponded with two trends, in particular: with Western influence in majority-Muslim countries or, as this summer’s burkini controversy demonstrated, with Western societies asserting nationalistic values and (patriarchal) identity. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;Freedom from&#8221; or &#8220;freedom to&#8221; are phrases associated with women’s behaviors, from dress to sexual activity to reproductive health, from France to Saudi Arabia. And we are often told to take a side: &#8220;Do you want women to be free from patriarchal oppression?&#8221; or &#8220;Do you want women to be free to wear whatever they choose?&#8221; </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But how does one think about the fight to wear hijab and the fight to be freed from hijab in one, unified thought? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Iran is a near perfect testament to such a thought. The country&#8217;s transition from Reza Shah Pahlavi to Ayatollah Khomeini provides an example of an apparent (and near perfect) paradox in practice.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the late 1920s in a still monarchical Iran, the Shah instituted what he called &#8220;a gradual process of hijab removal&#8221; from public institutions. The Shah’s friend and mentor, Turkey’s Mustafa Kemal Attatürk, espoused the view that head-covering reflected not only non-Western dress but non-Western thought. &#8220;Backwards women&#8221; stood for an undesirable social system, which extended into the confines of the home. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hijab was thus a stand-in or a symbol for the greater societal transformation each autocratic leader desired for the value system of his society. If Turkey and Iran were to join the rational, &#8220;enlightened&#8221; throngs of European history, in body and in mind, women had to remove their scarves.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Iran, in the period between these so-called modernization reforms and the Revolution, looked much like any other European country, with tanned youth in swimsuits smoking cigarettes on the beach, and Beatles records flying off the shelves. But in the late 1970s, frustration with the corrupt dictatorship of the Shah and the monarchy as a system of undemocratic government brought thousands of Iranian men and women out onto the streets. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the early days of 1979, secular and religious women alike protested for the right to ascribe to the value system of their choice. Whether Western or not, it was up to women to decide, not the Shah. </span></p>
<div id="attachment_4714" style="width: 510px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4714" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4714 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Iranian_Revolution_1979_marching_young_people.jpeg" alt="iranian_revolution_1979_marching_young_people" width="500" height="339" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Iranian_Revolution_1979_marching_young_people.jpeg 500w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Iranian_Revolution_1979_marching_young_people-300x203.jpeg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4714" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Wikimedia Commons</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As the revolution took a strident Islamic turn, women who did not wear hijab began to see the institution of the new state as a threat to their freedom of choice. Indeed, the &#8220;Islamic&#8221; in &#8220;Islamic Republic&#8221; now meant hijab, for all women. Iranian women were thus divided along ideological lines, and the new Islamic state was thus effective in reducing the voice and power of its most educated and mobile constituency: women.</span></p>
<p><iframe title="March 8, 1979 Iranian Women March Against Hijab and Islamic Laws" width="650" height="488" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/pxGYLk92edY?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With religious rule by Ayatollah Khomeini came moral rule in the homes and upon the bodies of women. Laws protecting women against the men of their family were eliminated. But as long as women were covered, they were able to obtain political office, attend university, and build a career. The hijab acted as a pass into the greater halls of society. It continues to act as the safeguard of a theocratic order, which exercises control while permitting necessary freedoms.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Iranian case is not so different from the European burkini fiasco last summer. The burkini &#8211; a full-body covering made of swimwear material, with an attached head covering like a swim cap &#8211; was banned in many French towns and cities for its subversion of secularist values. Women were to uphold the state’s belief in its own ideological abstention from religious practice in public life. Even while swimming. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The ban has since been <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-37198479">overturned at a federal level</a>, though some French municipalities claim that they will continue to enforce it. The mayor in the town where the ban made headlines, with police officers requiring a woman to remove her <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/08/28/world/europe/france-burkini-bikini-ban.html?_r=0">burkini on the beach</a>, called the ban an attempt to require &#8220;<a href="http://edition.cnn.com/2016/08/30/europe/french-mayor-cogolin-burkini-ban/">them to adopt our way of life.&#8221;</a> The &#8220;them&#8221; in this sentiment could be none other than Muslims, Europe&#8217;s favorite Other.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Liberal democracies, which respect the rights of minorities, demand pluralism &#8211; in lifestyle, in religious practice, in appearance, in ideology. Why does this pluralism extend only partially to women?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In France, the beach was briefly a battlefield. Muslim women were caught at the cross hairs of a power play between establishment norms and the liberty of choice that defines many arguments of cultural expression in other countries. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But the battlefield is an ideological one, surpassing the boundaries of nation and norms. It all comes down to the right to choose.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This is something women have been fighting for for centuries, from the ability to choose political leadership to the ability to choose a marital partner. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We can debate the merits behind the practice of the headscarf, its history in the Islamic world or even in the life of the prophet Muhammad, but what we should not debate is the ability of a woman to choose a practice, if it does no harm to her. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">France, in particular, makes the argument that the mere act of covering the body does harm to &#8220;the dignity and liberty&#8221; of said body. The issue of hijab is thus framed as one of protection, i.e. paternalism. A closer look at France’s relationship to identity politics and its systematic attempts to eliminate differences for the sake of the secular, homogeneous French state suggests that the protection enacted here is a fairly one-way street: There is &#8220;freedom from&#8221; but rarely &#8220;freedom to.&#8221;<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In Germany, a similar ban on head coverings for women exists. This ban is <a href="http://www.dw.com/en/can-muslim-women-wear-a-headscarf-at-work-in-germany/a-17953746">often a private and religious matter</a>, with church-based organizations or certain institutions able to decide when and if they will tolerate hijab. The attempts by school districts to ban headscarves in their teaching staff have been only partially successful, as German courts usually have the last word, overturning discriminatory practices, unless a specific legal conflict can be identified.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">German politicians have <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/08/19/germanys-potential-burqa-ban-has-a-problem-where-are-the-burqas/?utm_term=.947e281fb60a">also proposed a burqa ban</a>. The only problem is: hardly any women in Germany wear a burqa. Here, a moral stance is taken in preventing supposed harm before this harm could be said to occur. Ideology much? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Of course, the burqa is far from the burkini or the hijab. But it is no coincidence that the burqa ban discussion resurfaced and gained political momentum around the time of the burkini fiasco in France. Some European leaders may oppose France&#8217;s handling of the burkini on its beaches, but many have verbally and practically expressed their approval of policing Muslim women&#8217;s dress.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If one were to apply this&nbsp;logic of&nbsp;infringement of personal liberty to other arenas affecting the female body, one would end up with a long list of potential offenders, from beauty salons to botox offices to lingerie stores, where certain body parts are literally strapped down and constrained for the sake of smooth curvature. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;But these things make us feel good, make us feel pretty,&#8221; a French woman would likely respond. &#8220;And this is my right!&#8221;</span></p>
<div id="attachment_4715" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4715" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4715 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420-650x433.jpg" alt="berlin-bearbeitet-2014-420" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4715" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Type &#8220;hijab&#8221; into Pinterest and a fashion show will appear &#8211; women who use hijab as a way to present themselves in their way to the world. Stroll down the Turkish market at Berlin&#8217;s Maybachufer and you will encounter smiling groups of Muslima holding silk scarves up to their faces, matching patterns with dresses and jackets in mind, practicing new and different folds, depending on the material.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are wedding hijabs, hijabs for supermarket trips, and hijabs for dates, just as there are shoes for weddings, for nights out, or for lazy Saturdays.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hijab, like shoes, can make women feel good, because they make women feel pretty in a way that is also comfortable. It is both a lifestyle with religious and cultural roots and an identity mixed up with the many different conceptions humans have of beauty. Beauty: with all its socio-cultural baggage, the construct of forces beyond our individual minds and mirrors, forces that will always be a little bit oppressive but also a little bit fun, because they are familiar and somehow the product of our daily life within them. And this is their, our right.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As Trump ascends his throne to rule over the many who do not approve of or give license to his authoritarianism or assimilationist view of cultural differences, the hijab becomes one of those things that needs protection.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As Muslim refugees who choose to wear hijab become a lasting part of the societies of those European states that have taken them in, their right to be different must be defended. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Most importantly, we must defend the right of women to choose.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is this choice that makes women free. This is why feminism and hijab go together.</span></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>For more on the history of women in Iran, from hairstyles to political movements, see these sources: U.S. Institute of Peace&#8217;s <a href="http://iranprimer.usip.org/resource/womens-movement">Iran Primer: the Women&#8217;s Movement;</a> these pieces from a </em>New York Times<em>&nbsp;series &#8220;<a href="http://nytlive.nytimes.com/womenintheworld/2015/06/02/6-pervasive-misconceptions-about-iranian-women/">6 Pervasive Misconceptions about Iranian Women</a>&#8221; and &#8220;<a href="http://nytlive.nytimes.com/womenintheworld/2015/09/15/the-day-100000-iranian-women-protested-the-head-scarf/">The Day 100,000 Women Protested the Headscarf</a>&#8220;; this acclaimed book on the complexity of the Revolution: </em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Islamic-Utopian-Political-Biography-2000-06-03/dp/B019NRY9QG/ref=sr_1_3?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1480842551&amp;sr=1-3&amp;keywords=an+islamic+utopian+ali+shari%27ati">An Islamic Utopian: A Political Biography of Ali Shari&#8217;ati;</a><em> and the memoir, </em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/1400064708/?tag=thneyo0f-20">Iran Awakening</a><em>, by the Nobel-prize-winning activist Shirin Ebadi.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>And if you&#8217;re curious about women in hijab on the internet and in the fashion world, here are some people to watch: <a href="https://www.hautehijab.com/blogs/hijab-fashion">Haute Hijab</a> (U.S. fashion blogger with an entry titled &#8220;Embracing Our Identity in a Post 2016 Election World&#8221;), <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC_KQKeg7kNrlvrIXPnpwgEA">Dina Tokio</a> (U.K. vlogger and fashion designer), <a href="http://ww38.hipsterhijabis.com/about.html">Hipster Hijabis</a> (just what it sounds like), <a href="http://hanatajima.com/">Hana Tajima</a> (up-and-coming U.K. fashion designer), and <a href="http://hijablicious.com/">Hijablicious</a> (a site for &#8220;hijab with soul&#8221;).</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Women Only: The Frauenraum</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 15:42:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gender]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4385</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I'm at Rathaus Wilmersdorf, a former city hall building turned refugee home in Berlin, where I teach a literacy class once a week. The home initially opened its doors to 178 refugees in September 2015, following Merkel's famous "Wir schaffen das" ("We can do it") declaration that sidestepped the Dublin Regulation and opened up Germany's borders to thousands of asylum seekers.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4394 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-01-27 12.51.04" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>It&#8217;s Thursday at 10:55, and I&#8217;m running late. I rush up to the security guards and hand over my ID. <em>Helfer?</em> (&#8220;volunteer?&#8221;) they ask. <em>Ja</em>, I answer, and wait for them to scribble down my name and give me a number so I can sign out later. I thank them and head inside to the office to sign for the room keys and get my name tag. Then it&#8217;s through the foyer and up three floors to room 3092. When breakfast is running late, the right half of the stairwell is still filled by a neat line of people waiting for their turn in the cafeteria. I squeeze by, ruffling the hair of the kids I recognize.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m at Rathaus Wilmersdorf, a former city hall building turned refugee home in Berlin, where I teach a literacy class once a week. The home initially opened its doors to <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/berlin/bezirke/kudamm/notunterkunft-fuer-fluechtlinge-in-berlin-im-rathaus-wilmersdorf-fehlen-duschen-und-dolmetscher/12199798.html">178 refugees</a> in September 2015, following Merkel&#8217;s famous &#8220;Wir schaffen das&#8221; (&#8220;We can do it&#8221;) declaration that <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/germany/11821822/Germany-drops-EU-rules-to-allow-in-Syrian-refugees.html">sidestepped the Dublin Regulation</a> and opened up Germany&#8217;s borders to thousands of asylum seekers.</p>
<p>Today, over 1400 refugees live in the Rathaus &#8211; mostly from Syria, Afghanistan, and Iraq &#8211; and there is talk of opening up an adjacent building to house an additional 900. As is the case all over the city, this home simply wouldn&#8217;t function without the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/">on-going assistance of volunteers</a> who help out with everything from interpretation and teaching to administrative and kitchen support.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4456 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-01-08 10.34.54" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Over the past eight months, Rathaus Wilmersdorf has become somewhat of a success story as far as refugee accommodations in Berlin go. It&#8217;s been visited by President Joachim Gauck and American actor Ben Stiller, as well as received significant media praise for its leadership and facilities. <a href="http://www.morgenpost.de/berlin/article207089933/Vachroi-verabschiedet-sich-als-Heimleiter-in-Wilmersdorf.html">One article</a> listed off the home&#8217;s impressive amenities, which include medical and midwife services, a laundry room, a hair salon, an internet <span class="st">café</span>, and yes, even our literacy class.</p>
<p>The literacy class, or &#8220;AB class&#8221; as we call it, does go beyond what many other refugee homes in Berlin offer. But what the article&#8217;s authors fail to mention (and are likely unaware of), is that the course comes with a complicated backstory that is indicative of a larger debate surrounding refugees in Germany today.</p>
<p>It all started early this year, after one volunteer noticed that a group of women were not showing up for the German class offered on the home&#8217;s fourth floor. These women were mostly Afghan and the majority also illiterate. However, a bit of digging (and a heavy dose of interpretation) revealed that they weren&#8217;t avoiding the class because the level was too difficult, as originally suspected. They weren&#8217;t going because, in the fourth floor class, there were men present. Or depending on who tells the story, “Because their husbands wouldn’t let them”.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4600 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-05-19 12.43.22" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>The decision was therefore made to start a new class on the third floor, taught and attended exclusively by women. The class was to be an extension of the adjacent <em>Frauenraum</em> or &#8220;women&#8217;s room&#8221;. At Rathaus Wilmersdorf, the <em>Frauenraum</em> is a standing room open almost daily, so long as there are volunteers present. At the refugee home in former Tempelhof airport, the <em>Frauenraum</em> operates on a weekly project basis, led by a volunteer platform called <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">Give Something Back to Berlin</a>.</p>
<p>Regardless of the format, the concept remains the same: The <em>Frauenraum</em> is a safe place where women can be amongst themselves. In Rathaus Wilmersdorf, they sew, practice German, or just hang out and have a cup of tea. Small children are allowed, but men are forbidden from entering. We&#8217;ve even had to throw out a male journalist on occasion. The home&#8217;s former director described it as a place where &#8220;<a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/berlin/warum-thomas-de-vachroi-der-perfekte-aufbauhelfer-fuer-fluechtlingsheime-ist-23775578">female residents are enjoying their freedom and unveiling themselves.</a>&#8221; I can only assume he meant this both literally and figuratively, as not all the women wear headscarves, but some who do do indeed take them off when in the <em>Frauenraum</em> or during class.</p>
<p>I fell into the role of literacy teacher by way of the <em>Frauenraum</em>, where I started volunteering in January. The class was already up and running but they wanted to offer it on more days and were having trouble finding willing teachers. Other <em>Frauenraum</em> volunteers, I was told, had flatly refused to teach out of principle, scoffing at the idea that a separate class be created when there was a perfectly good one already on offer. This is Germany, after all, a country where men and women are presumably equal and interact on all levels of society. If the husbands had a problem with that, tough. Isn&#8217;t it in the best interest of these women that we integrate them into our way of life as quickly as possible?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4460 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-05-12 11.42.50" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>These days, it is difficult to have a discussion in Germany about refugees that doesn&#8217;t include a question about gender. <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/02/08/not-our-women-from-cologne-to-berlin/">Post-Cologne</a>, it is near impossible. Despite the fact that the attacks on New Year&#8217;s Eve were carried out by a more diverse group than originally portrayed in the media, that night&#8217;s unfortunate events have marked a turning point in attitudes towards refugees.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.focus.de/politik/deutschland/zdf-umfrage-offenbart-so-haben-die-silvester-uebergriffe-beeinflusst-was-deutsche-ueber-fluechtlinge-denken_id_5213962.html">One poll</a> showed that, between December 2015 and January 2016 alone, the number of Germans who felt the country couldn&#8217;t handle the influx of refugees rose from 46% to 60%. Thirty-three percent stated that Cologne had &#8220;fundamentally changed&#8221; their opinions about refugees. And the ring-wing <span class="st"><em>Alternative für Deutschland</em></span> (AfD) party, which initially emerged in opposition to the euro, has placed anti-refugee sentiment at the core of their increasingly popular platform. Their leader has controversially <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/alternative-for-germany-shows-its-true-right-wing-colors-a-1076259.html">called for the use of firearms against incoming refugees</a>.</p>
<p>This is the same country that was at the forefront of Europe&#8217;s refugee response only nine months ago. The same country that led the continent&#8217;s discourse on establishing a common European solution. The same country that initiated what became globally lauded as <em>Wilkommenskultur</em> (welcome culture).</p>
<p>So, what&#8217;s changed?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4401 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-650x650.jpg" alt="2016-02-10 11.59.46" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-300x300.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>When the “refugee crisis” hit Germany last summer, hundreds of residents felt compelled to slather butter on rolls and pass them out to refugees arriving at train stations. This was by all accounts heart-warming and admirable, but it was also the easy part. The conversation we are having now is a more complicated one, one that even the seemingly simple question of whether to offer a female-only literacy class echoes:</p>
<p>What happens next and how might our society change as a result?</p>
<p>One could blame Cologne, but the foundation for this confrontation was laid long before. A staggering <a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article147280667/Fuer-die-meisten-gehoert-der-Islam-nicht-zu-Deutschland.html">60% of the country</a> is of the opinion that Islam does not belong in Germany. (It is also worth noting that Germans consistently overestimate the number of Muslims living in the country. The real figure, while one of the highest in the EU, <a href="http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2015/11/17/5-facts-about-the-muslim-population-in-europe/">is still only 5.8%</a>.)</p>
<p>There is an underlying preconception in Germany, as in many Western countries, that Islam is synonymous with misogyny and a lack of female rights. That “<a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article149756193/Wie-Sumtes-Wutbuerger-lernten-Fluechtlinge-zu-lieben.html">according to their religion, women are nothing</a>” or even more extreme, that &#8220;<a href="http://www.vice.com/de/read/fluechtlinge-vergewaltigen-deutsche-kinder-wie-rassisten-versuchen-stimmung-gegen-alle-nicht-deutschen-zu-machen-775">these young men will come and rape our daughters</a>&#8220;. This preconception likely stems from a variety of factors: images we see in the media, politicians portraying Muslims as backward or extremist, or current conflicts within the Middle East. An argument heard less often is made by <a href="http://ideas.time.com/2013/11/01/do-muslim-women-need-saving/">Columbia University Professor Lila Abu-Lughod</a>, who explores the conflation of religion and socioeconomic status. Gender inequality within Muslim majority societies stems mainly from economic inequality, and migrants in Germany have traditionally been low-skilled. Therefore what we may label as clashes due to religion may have stronger roots in poverty and lack of opportunity.</p>
<p>Earlier this year in Berlin, <a href="http://www.rbb-online.de/politik/beitrag/2016/04/berlin-kopftuch-streit-vor-arbeitsgericht-keine-guetliche-einigung.html">a young teacher went to court</a> because she was denied a teaching post due to her headscarf (the case was thrown out on grounds of the state&#8217;s Neutrality Act). More recently in Switzerland, a <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-36382596">regional authority ruled</a> that two teenage brothers must shake the hands of their female teachers despite it being against their religious beliefs to touch women they are not related to. Traditionally receiving societies such as Germany are perpetually learning how to manage integration in the face of growing diversity. Unfortunately, we seem insistent on concentrating on how &#8220;their values&#8221; may threaten &#8220;ours&#8221;, rather than on what type of society we want to live in together.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4406 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-02-17 12.07.15" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>To be fair, my own engagement at the Rathaus has not come without challenges. On my first day teaching, I swallowed a lot of frustration as another volunteer and I watched the women turn to their husbands for approval before following us to class. <em>Nur Frauen</em> (&#8220;only women&#8221;), we tried to communicate to the more skeptical looking of the men with a smile, while I stifled the urge to roll my eyes.</p>
<p>We&#8217;ve also heard a host of disturbing stories by way of the interpreters. Rape, abuse, threats of divorce. Some stories are from Afghanistan while others allegedly took place here in Berlin. At times, I am ashamed to find myself relieved that I can&#8217;t talk to the women directly about what I&#8217;ve heard, for fear it might affect the way I interact with them. For now, our exchanges are limited to topics like telling time and types of fruit &#8211; they&#8217;re big fans of banana and pineapple &#8211; as well as the apparently always shocking and never boring topic of me being a 30 year old woman without a husband or children (some of my students have 6, 7, even 9 children).</p>
<p>But until we&#8217;re able to have those more in-depth conversations, I remain convinced that offering a class under imperfect circumstances is better than offering no women&#8217;s class at all. For what, I&#8217;ve asked myself, will give these women more independence than the ability to navigate the city on their own? And what will give them a better chance of being able to navigate the city on their own than the ability to read and write?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4405 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-04-20 10.14.53" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Nothing exhibited this more clearly to me than a few weeks ago, when we held an arts project week for our women. The week consisted of two trips to separate parks so they could learn about various plant types and practice drawing them. The excitement of the women was palpable. They got to have a Middle Eastern picnic, a real treat after months of bland cafeteria fare. They got to pick flowers in the woods to take back to the home. There was laughing, there was dancing, and there were so many selfies.</p>
<p>We later found out through interpreters that, for several of the women, it was their first time in a park without a husband or male relative.</p>
<p>At the end of the week, a local artist took the womens&#8217; drawings and stenciled them onto power boxes near the Rathaus. On the Friday, we took a stroll around the neighborhood together to see them for the first time. The Farsi-speaking volunteer asked the women to point out their drawings and explain why they chose to draw them specifically. &#8220;Who drew this?&#8221; she asked when we got to the second box, pointing to a beautiful palm tree. &#8220;Me,&#8221; answered one of our students, &#8220;I drew it because it reminds me of home. And if you cut off the head, the whole plant dies.&#8221;</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The Frauenraum at Rathaus Wilmersdorf is looking for volunteers. To get involved, sign up at https://volunteer-planner.org/.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>For another take on the headscarf, I recommend watching <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/video/2015/jun/24/hijab-not-oppression-feminist-statement-video">this Guardian video</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>All photos my own.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: &#8220;I&#8217;m not Turkish, but my husband is&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[love]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tunisia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1251</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In a capital city marked by transformation and transience, where people are perpetually coming and going, it can feel like a true rarity to meet someone actually from that city. “H” was my first Berlin friend from Berlin. We met through a language website, after she sent me a request to practice French in exchange for German. H was working on her degree to become a French teacher. I was still new to the city and could count my local friends on one hand...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_3811" style="width: 733px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://jurigottschau.com/"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3811" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3811 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz.jpg" alt="grillplatz" width="723" height="482" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz.jpg 723w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 723px) 100vw, 723px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3811" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p style="text-align: left;">In a capital city marked by transformation and transience, where people are perpetually coming and going, it can feel like a true rarity to meet someone actually <em>from</em> that city.</p>
<p>&#8220;H&#8221; was my first Berlin friend from Berlin. We met through a language website, after she sent me a request to practice French in exchange for German. H was working on her degree to become a French teacher. I was still new to the city and could count my local friends on one hand. The first time we hung out was in February 2012 at a cafe under the <em>Savignyplatz S-Bahn</em> arches. H ended up helping me with my research on teacher quality in Germany, and I gave her tips for her upcoming study abroad program in France. Soon enough our linguistic meet-ups evolved into a friendship that waved off grammar practice in favor of relaxed Sunday afternoon coffee dates.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Our relationship also became a kind of exchange of culinary cultures. I started joining her annually to break the fast during Ramadan. As the resident atheist I wouldn&#8217;t fast before these meals. Yet I&#8217;d still be the one gnawing away at my fingers until sundown, while H and her sisters waited patiently for their first sips of rose flavored water and soup drizzled with fresh lemon juice. In return, H  joined my international crew of friends for her first Thanksgiving dinner, initiated into the world of cranberry sauce, candied sweet potatoes, and general American gluttony. Her contribution &#8211; mounds of Turkish <em>Lahmacun</em> (spiced lamb pizza) &#8211; was eagerly divvied up like party favors at the end of the night.</p>
<div id="attachment_3611" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3611" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3611 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340-650x650.jpg" alt="IMG_3340" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3611" class="wp-caption-text">Ramadan dinner with H</p></div>
<p style="text-align: left;">It didn&#8217;t take long for us to discover our mutual fascination with questions of citizenship and identity. We attended several events together on the topic and often spent our cafe time discussing our hybrid families and understanding of <em>Deutschsein</em> or &#8220;Germanness&#8221;. See, while H is a true <em>Berlinerin</em> &#8211; she was born and grew up here &#8211; her parents are from Tunisia. We shared the feeling of having more than one home; while I straddled the Atlantic, H had a foot on either side of the Mediterranean. But unlike me, H had grown up with the challenge of having to persistently defend her Germanness, to the wider community and to her own parents.</p>
<p>In countries like Germany that are still embracing their multicultural identities &#8211; Germany first recognized itself as a country of immigration in 2005 &#8211; too many still have a binary understanding of native vs. foreigner that acknowledges bloodlines over birthplace and physical appearance over personal identity. There remains a habit of probing those who look &#8220;different&#8221; about their roots, otherwise known as the dreaded &#8220;But where are you <em>really</em> from?&#8221; <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/">question</a>. Those on the receiving end of this question are often referred to as the &#8220;perpetual foreigner&#8221;, ethnic minorities who will always be seen as the “other” because of how they look.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">In H&#8217;s case, it didn&#8217;t take long to notice that the vast majority of those she came across assumed she was Turkish, including other Turkish-Germans. &#8220;Oh right, the Turkish one,&#8221; a girl on her basketball team responded, when I introduced myself as H&#8217;s friend. H once told me she gets asked if she&#8217;s Turkish more than her best friend, an actual Turkish-German who happens to be blond and fair-skinned.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3697 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-650x487.jpg" alt="2014-01-19 17.26.48" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>The confusion isn&#8217;t all too surprising, considering H&#8217;s darker features, for one, and the demographics of the city, for two. Turkish-Germans are the city&#8217;s largest ethnic minority and the largest community of Turks outside of Turkey. Estimates of the number of Turks in Berlin range from 200,000-500,000 (a combination of those with Turkish passports, partial Turkish ancestry, and ethnic minorities from Turkey). A far cry from the approximately <a href="http://www.berlin.de/lb/intmig/statistik/demografie/einwohner_staatsangehoerigkeit.html">1,500 Tunisian nationals</a> in Berlin.</p>
<p>The story of H&#8217;s parents also mirrors that of many Turkish-Germans. They immigrated to the city separately as part of a guest-worker program in the 1970s and met on the job at corporate giant, Siemens. Originally, they planned to return to Tunisia together. The couple worked 2-3 jobs, sending remittances to family in Tunisia to save up to build a house there. They sent their 3 eldest daughters back for 9 years to live with relatives and go to school. But when Germany tightened family reunification laws in the 80&#8217;s, excluding those older than 16 without German citizenship, they brought the 3 girls back to Berlin to keep the family together, by then consisting of 5 daughters.</p>
<p>H is daughter number 4 and has only visited Tunisia on vacation. She admits that a distinction exists between the older and younger sisters, due to this geographic divide in upbringing, especially apparent in attitudes toward the headscarf and family planning. Her oldest sister &#8220;lives by the Qu&#8217;ran&#8221; and hopes to move back to Tunisia permanently one day. H, on the other hand, identifies as a &#8220;<em>Berlinerin</em> with Tunisian roots&#8221;; she has no intention of leaving Germany anytime soon.</p>
<div id="attachment_3791" style="width: 657px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3791" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3791 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg" alt="htunisia" width="647" height="484" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg 647w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia-300x224.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 647px) 100vw, 647px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3791" class="wp-caption-text">H on vacation in Tunisia</p></div>
<p>When it comes to questions and comments about her being Turkish, I&#8217;ve only ever seen H respond with patience and grace. It&#8217;s the difficulties with her own parents, and especially mother, that affect her most. If you ask her about her upbringing, H will tell you that her parents were &#8220;pretty modern for immigrant standards&#8221;, letting her play sports and stay out with friends until 10pm. Sleepovers and clubs weren&#8217;t allowed, but H found ways around her parents&#8217; rules, such as working at social events like the <em>Volksfest </em>and later heading west to Dortmund for university.</p>
<p>Boyfriends, on the other hand, were out of the question. Particularly those outside of the Tunisian-German community. H dated a little in secret, but didn&#8217;t get serious with anyone until she met &#8220;A&#8221; at 19. At 28, A was almost a decade older and managing a series of internet cafes. The flirtation started small with jokes at the shop, building up slowly to weekend jogs together. Finally, A asked H out on a date.</p>
<p>H managed to keep the relationship hidden from her parents for 6 years. &#8220;I was sure they&#8217;d disapprove because he&#8217;s Turkish,&#8221; she explains. Even though both Tunisians and Turks in Germany are predominantly Muslim, H says it&#8217;s not uncommon for the older immigrant generations to be prejudiced against one another. &#8220;The Tunisians here think that all Turkish boys are in gangs, are loud and have no respect, and don&#8217;t achieve anything,&#8221; H claims; &#8220;Tunisians in Tunisia think more positively about Turks than Tunisians in Germany do.&#8221;</p>
<p>When she told her parents about the relationship in 2013, her mother threatened that H was &#8220;ruining her life&#8221; and that if she continued, they would disown her. &#8220;I haven&#8217;t even told them yet that A is Shiite,&#8221; H joked (her family is Sunni).</p>
<div id="attachment_3792" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3792" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3792 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-650x202.jpg" alt="A&amp;H" width="650" height="202" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-650x202.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-300x93.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3792" class="wp-caption-text">A &amp; H</p></div>
<p>According to H, the problem is her mother&#8217;s stubbornness more than anything else. But listening to the stories one can&#8217;t help but notice an underlying theme of fear, logical or not. A fear of losing one&#8217;s child. A fear of not relating to one&#8217;s grandchildren. A fear of the dilution of one&#8217;s cultural lineage over generations. &#8220;Many in the Tunisian-German community are scared that their kids will marry Turks and end up in Turkey,&#8221; H agrees, &#8220;my mother is also afraid her grandchildren will never learn Arabic.&#8221; H and her sisters speak strictly Tunisian Arabic with their parents. When just amongst each other, a mix of Arabic and German.</p>
<p>Language is just one question of many that H and A will face as parents. They have already decided that A will primarily speak Turkish and H mostly German, which she is more comfortable with than Arabic. They have even talked about where they will <em>really</em> end up one day. H tells me that the Tunisian consulate pays for the bodies of Tunisian nationals in Germany to be sent back for burials. A, who came to Berlin at 18 as a student, gave up his Turkish passport to become German.  As an entrepreneur he&#8217;s eager to launch projects in Turkey and maybe even retire there one day, but is limited without citizenship.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">After months of not seeing each other, H and I finally find time last November for one of our Sunday coffee dates. H arrives to the Italian cafe in an uncharacteristically bulky sweater that makes me raise my eyebrows. Shortly after ordering our lattes and chocolate cake, she spills the beans: she and A have gotten married, and she&#8217;s newly pregnant. The religious ceremony was held at their apartment with an Imam presiding and a handful of their closest friends and siblings present. H&#8217;s parents chose not to return early from their vacation in Tunisia to attend. As for their upcoming grandchild, wherever he or she decides to be &#8220;<em>really</em> from&#8221;, they are still in the dark.</p>
<p><em> &#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong> </em></p>
<p><em>&#8220;A&#8221; requested that this article remain anonymous, in order to not further weaken his cause, should H&#8217;s parents somehow come across it.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Circumcision at the Jewish Museum Berlin</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/12/05/review-circumcision-jewish-museum-berlin/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2014 13:14:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Judaism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3532</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Circumcision has a history of being used to make distinctions between 'us' and 'them', particularly in Germany. In the United States the debate on foreskin or no-foreskin looks much different, citing hygiene rather than religious freedom. This begs the question if arguments against a religious practice, such as the one raised in the German context, can ever be purely about legal arguments - for the rights of children, as German courts have decreed - when strong divisions between those of Christian heritage and those of Muslim and/or Jewish heritage remain. This question was the inspiration for the newest exhibition at the Jewish Museum Berlin, a timely one, at that...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Circumcision has a long history of enabling Othering processes, i.e. society defining itself on the basis of what it is not. According the Duke anthropologist <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/william-m-obarr/celebrating-circumcision_1_b_1902275.html">William O’Barr</a>, the absence of circumcision in Michelangelo’s famous <em>David</em> exemplifies this bit: Despite David’s well-known Jewish roots, let alone his place as a key protagonist in the Jewish scriptural tradition, his foreskin remains seemingly intact; this David seems more Florentine, more like the dominant Europeans at the time, than Jewish.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/books/2011/jul/29/david-mary-hoffman-review"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3537" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/David-Michelangelo-007.jpg" alt="David Michelangelo" width="487" height="293" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/David-Michelangelo-007.jpg 459w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/David-Michelangelo-007-300x180.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 487px) 100vw, 487px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Michelangelo likely had little experience with circumcision, given that this practice was historically reserved for the Jewish minority. The lack of foreskin thus served as a point from which the fringe of majority culture could be measured. Most Europeans at the time were simply <em>not </em>circumcised.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">In Germany, circumcision is still a practice attributed to members of the Jewish and Islamic traditions. Given Germany&#8217;s immigration history, the practice also serves largely to distinguish more recent immigrants from your German with either Catholic or Protestant roots. In kind, the debate as to the legality and humanity of the removal of a child&#8217;s foreskin has taken on an us vs. them quality. The discussion has also tended to position &#8216;reason and modernity&#8217; against &#8216;antiquated tradition&#8217;, as this<a href="http://www.taz.de/!98008/"> interview</a> with a German Green Party member indicates (a party, which gave strong support to legislation banning the practice among infants and young children). Just two years ago, a Cologne court ruled against the circumcision of youngsters. The decision was presented as an act in favor of the human rights of children &#8211; this logic continues to dominate.</p>
<p>In the United States, approx. 79% of men are circumcised, <a href="http://www.cdc.gov/hiv/pdf/prevention_research_malecircumcision.pdf">according to the Center for Disease Control</a>. Many of these men do not belong to religious traditions that prescribe the practice; I doubt many parents would cite compliance with God&#8217;s covenant as the reason for their son’s procedure. Since its introduction during WWII as a matter of (presumed) <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2788411/">hygiene</a>, it never had time to become a pronounced public marker of difference.</p>
<div id="attachment_3565" style="width: 541px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://www.guggenheim.org/new-york/collections/collection-online/artwork/3478"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3565" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3565 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/circumcision-january1.jpg" alt="circumcision-january pollock" width="531" height="450" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/circumcision-january1.jpg 531w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/circumcision-january1-300x254.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 531px) 100vw, 531px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3565" class="wp-caption-text">Jackson Pollock 1946, &#8220;Circumcision&#8221;</p></div>
<p>But even in the United States, the practice has more recently come under a critical knife, though more medical than cultural, as a recent <em>Atlantic </em><a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2014/12/foreskin-keep-or-cut/383362/">article</a> on the subject illustrates. The more contemporary critique in the United States seems to be little more than an attempt to re-evaluate the merits of bodily modification, without going so far as to refer to this practice as &#8216;mutilation&#8217; on the part of fundamentalist religions.</p>
<p>Given this background, the importance of context is undeniable in evaluating the discourse on circumcision from one place to another. In other words, the &#8216;who&#8217;s who&#8217; in <em>beschnitten</em> vs. <em>unbeschnitten</em> may say much more about the state of society (and its latent tensions) than medical-ethical arguments against the practice immediately reveal. This begs the question if arguments against a religious practice, such as this one, can ever be purely about the rights of children, as German courts have decreed and German politicians argued. This question and the delicate history from which it emerges were the inspiration for the newest exhibition at the <a href="http://www.jmberlin.de/main/EN/homepage-EN.php">Jewish Museum Berlin</a> – an institution known for <a href="http://www.jmberlin.de/main/EN/03b-Academy/04-Academy-Programs/00-academy-programs.php">programming</a> on inclusion/diversity topics that extends beyond the docket of Jewish history and culture.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Haut-Ab.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-3569 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Haut-Ab.jpg" alt="Haut Ab" width="330" height="374" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Haut-Ab.jpg 330w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Haut-Ab-264x300.jpg 264w" sizes="(max-width: 330px) 100vw, 330px" /></a></p>
<p>The exhibit, &#8220;<a href="http://www.jmberlin.de/main/DE/01-Ausstellungen/02-Sonderaustellungen/2014/brit-mila.php">Haut ab!</a>&#8221; or &#8220;<a href="http://www.jmberlin.de/main/EN/01-Exhibitions/02-Special-Exhibitions/2014/brit-milah.php">Snip it!</a>&#8220;, opened a little more than one month ago. Days before the exhibit’s scheduled reveal, I had the opportunity to take part in a preview for bloggers and tweeters. Our tour guide was the exhibition’s co-curator, an expert in Judaica. In addition to the objects&#8217; historical significance, her comments revealed a recognition of the tightly-stretched contemporary fabric upon which the exhibit rests. The careful placement of artifacts, soundbites, and images transmits a similar message of a need to explain and take stock of a (perhaps unnecessarily) tension-filled topic, in light and because of history.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3539 size-large aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004-650x365.jpg" alt="WP_20141022_004" width="650" height="365" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004-650x365.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Entering through the exhibit&#8217;s initial darkened spaces &#8211; final preparations being made, lighting not quite right &#8211; a historical narrative of a religion&#8217;s genesis and later adaptations in diaspora forms a quilt of impressions. The next rooms give way to the ritual&#8217;s place in Islam and the stark move from Christianity&#8217;s embrace of old Jewish tradition &#8211; as being sacredly tied to the life and times of Jesus &#8211; to artists&#8217; depictions of Othered violence, even savagery, against children. Juxtaposed with a historical development are artifacts from the Islamic ceremony in which a young boy is inducted into a long Muslim lineage. For all Berliners, the following image is a familiar one: costumes for a &#8216;little prince&#8217;, complete with scepter and golden cap. But how many recognize this as part of a fundamental <em>rite de passage, </em>the commanded removal of foreskin? Images of the sons of German guest workers in the 1970s, little princes in-waiting, place the practice further back in German heritage than the media tends to convey. As Germany&#8217;s immigration history indicates, circumcision is nothing new. But this photograph of an eager little boy could have been taken last week, swimming in a hat much too big among a happy mass of friends and family.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3558 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016-650x365.jpg" alt="WP_20141022_016" width="650" height="365" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016-650x365.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>The final room of the exhibit greets visitors with an interactive arrangement of outside discourses on circumcision, clips taken primarily from American television. Images and audio insert diverse perspectives into what our guide calls &#8216;the polemical German frame&#8217;. Familiar cartoons and sitcoms cast blue light onto the carpeted floor. Scenes from South Park, Judge Judy. As we exit, a final work, the oeuvre of commentary, salutes its visitors: three figures, bodies identical, if not for the flags draped over three sets of genitalia.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-3557 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021-365x650.jpg" alt="WP_20141022_021" width="350" height="623" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021-365x650.jpg 365w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021-168x300.jpg 168w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021.jpg 366w" sizes="(max-width: 350px) 100vw, 350px" /></a></p>
<p>One could make the case that circumcision in Germany is more a stand-in for society&#8217;s difficult grappling with religious difference and demographic change. Perhaps more background is needed to do so, however. So to be more specific, as a <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/politik/deutschland/studie-belegt-grosse-vorbehalte-gegenueber-muslimen-a-1006332.html">recent study</a> by the <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/en/welcome/">Berlin Institute for Empirical Migration and Integration Research</a> indicates, a majority of Germans polled continue to see Islam as un-German &#8211; this despite the approx. 5+ million Muslims who have made Germany their home. To complicate things, Germany is one of the most secular countries in Europe, with most of its residents of so-called Christian heritage bearing little association to either church or faith in their daily lives. There is also a history of a certain institutional religiosity despite public secularism: for example, the prominence of the CDU Party (Christian Democratic Union) and the obligatory church-tax to Protestant or Catholic churches, even synagogues, while blatantly excluding Muslim houses of prayer.</p>
<p>As this new exhibit at the Jewish Museum Berlin demonstrates, circumcision in Germany is complicated, deeply embedded in <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/28/world-cup-fever-how-malleable-is-german-identity/">the question of German identity</a> and the norms that demarcate such a thing. I wonder, though, if the constant discussion serves only to create scandal out of culture. For where is Othered difference, when there is no longer spectacle?</p>
<p>&#8220;Snip it&#8221;/&#8221;Haut ab&#8221; at the Jewish Museum Berlin runs until March 1. It&#8217;s worth a visit.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>All images are linked to original source or were otherwise taken by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: Three Dimensions of Integration</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/07/interview-three-dimensions-of-integration/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/07/interview-three-dimensions-of-integration/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2014 07:14:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ex-pat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kreuzberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theater]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2212</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It's easy (and admittedly amusing) to reduce expats to stereotypes, as if we all neatly fall into one or the other category based on which country we hail from, what we do for a living, or where we party and eat brunch. Reality is always more nuanced and multi-dimensional. Dare we even say, interesting?...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Immigrant integration and identity can be very personal subjects and not everyone wishes for their views and experiences to be made public. Though all the stories in this interview are true, names and some cities have been changed to protect the artist&#8217;s identity, per his request.</em></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_0609.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_0609.jpg?w=640" alt="Admiralbruecke in Kreuzberg" width="604" height="604" /></a></p>
<p>It&#8217;s easy (<a href="http://www.uberlin.co.uk/stereotypes-different-expats-youll-meet-berlin/">and admittedly amusing</a>) to reduce expats to stereotypes, as if we all neatly fall into one or the other category based on which country we hail from, what we do for a living, or where we party and eat brunch. Reality is always more nuanced and multi-dimensional. Dare we even say, interesting?</p>
<p>Take Alex, American-born artist and documentary filmmaker living in Berlin. On first sight, the dual American-Polish citizen may appear to fit into a few niches: creative type with a studio in <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/20/lens-an-ode-to-the-maybachufer/">trendy Kreuzberg</a>, one of a rapidly growing number of young <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/07/rant-or-rave-jew-in-a-box/">Jews in Berlin</a>, jetsetter popping between speaking engagements in Europe and gigs in Los Angeles and Seattle. But Alex&#8217;s life in Berlin was more happy accident than predestined by career or background. The idea came from a professor who happened to hear him &#8220;complaining in the hallway about wanting to leave [his homestate] Illinois” and suggested a semester program in Offenbach near Frankfurt, Germany.</p>
<p>In 2003, Alex left the U.S. for Germany, and in the past decade, has spent time in Frankfurt, Stuttgart, and Karlsruhe. For the past six years he has been Berlin-based.</p>
<p><a href="http://friedrichshainblog.de/santa-maria-gutes-mexikanisches-restaurant-in-berlin-kreuzberg/"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2225" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/santa-maria-mexikaner-kreuzberg.jpg" alt="santa maria in kreuzberg" width="600" height="450" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/santa-maria-mexikaner-kreuzberg.jpg 600w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/santa-maria-mexikaner-kreuzberg-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/santa-maria-mexikaner-kreuzberg-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></a></p>
<p>I meet Alex in his studio on Adalbertstraße, where he shows me some clips of his documentary films and tells me start-ups are starting to take-over former artist space in the building. &#8220;Do you feel integrated?&#8221; I ask later over habanero-spiked food and aguas frescas at Oranienstraße&#8217;s Santa Maria Restaurant. &#8220;You&#8217;re really making me think here,&#8221; Alex ponders, slicing into his pumpkin burrito, &#8220;it&#8217;s a top-heavy question though, isn&#8217;t it? Depends on what you mean by &#8216;integrated&#8217;.&#8221;</p>
<p>Alex isn&#8217;t a fan of dichotomies, the idea that every question always has a right or wrong answer. He prefers to see the world in three dimensions, which he describes as &#8220;the pause in-between inhaling and exhaling&#8221;. Fittingly, by the end of our conversation, he&#8217;s given us three dimensions through which to consider integration.</p>
<p><strong>The Dance Performance</strong></p>
<p>Alex recently attended a dance performance by Wang Ramirez, a pair that works between Berlin, Paris, and London and are &#8220;<a href="http://wangramirez.com/">as diverse as the cultures that clashed and harmonized when its founders met</a>.&#8221;</p>
<p>“She is ethnically Korean but grew up in Germany, and he grew up in France but has Spanish roots,” Alex explains. &#8220;At one part during the evening&#8217;s program, a woman comes on stage and asks them one of those typical questions about language and identity. How their backgrounds influence their performance and such. Wang and Ramirez respond in a mix of languages and movements, getting progressively more incoherent, to show how essentially absurd and futile that question can be.&#8221;</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://vimeo.com/79000095"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter  wp-image-2223" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/wangramirez.jpg" alt="wangramirez" width="601" height="335" /></a><br />
<strong>The Jewish Guilt</strong></p>
<p>While attending a conference in Weimar to hear a professor friend of his speak, Alex was approached by a young German student looking for participants in a Jewish identity project.&#8221;He had just found out that he had some Jewish ancestry,&#8221; Alex recounts. &#8220;He wanted to do a photography project on young Jews in Germany to acknowledge this, and asked us if we would participate. Later, when my friend and I were alone and could discuss openly, we realized this project, like so many others, was focused on the past. My friend said, &#8216;why doesn&#8217;t he focus on Germany&#8217;s future instead, as a multicultural country? Perhaps learning Turkish would be a more meaningful contribution.’&#8221;</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>The Subway Encounter</strong></p>
<p>One late night on the U-Bahn, Alex found himself among a group of young Turkish-Germans. &#8220;People can&#8217;t usually tell where I&#8217;m from right off the bat. These guys in the U-Bahn asked me. My grandfather was a Sephardic Jew from Beirut, so I just told them I had a Lebanese grandfather and left out the rest. Once they thought I was Arab they started on how they love everyone and all religions&#8230; <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/">Muslims</a>, Christians, Jews, etc. Later I wondered how the conversation would have been different if I had said I was Jewish.&#8221;</p>
<p><a href="http://www.aviatorsandacamera.com/travel/nye-art-technology-in-berlin-part-2/"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter  wp-image-2224" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/ubahn.jpg" alt="berlin u-bahn" width="533" height="397" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/ubahn.jpg 259w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/ubahn-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 533px) 100vw, 533px" /></a></p>
<p>&#8212;&#8211;</p>
<p>&#8220;Berlin is a great place to come and figure out who you are and what you want to do. It&#8217;s just not the best place to make that happen, funding and opportunity wise,&#8221; Alex explains. &#8220;I always say Berlin is a city full of possibility, but not necessarily potential.&#8221; Alex, like many expats, is not sure what the future holds, other than it being a transnational one. No matter how much opportunity exists on the West Coast, it seems he will always be tied to Germany and, more specifically, Berlin. &#8220;Berlin is a city that breaks my heart,&#8221; he reminisces, &#8220;it broke my heart even before I lived here. Just the thought that a place like this even exists.”</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>First image by Sophia Burton, all others linked to sources.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/07/interview-three-dimensions-of-integration/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Happy Weekend Review: An Old-New Christmas Market</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/12/20/happy-weekend-review-an-old-new-christmas-market/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2013 14:39:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[consumerism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[food]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[holidays]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1906</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Let's just come right out with it: It's hard to beat Christmas in Germany. Glühwein, cookies, classic lights, decorations strewn across homes and street corners, a calendar that expects, nay, requires you eat a chocolate per day... it's simply wonderful. Though I grew up in the US, my family celebrated Christmas the Teutonic way. I have more than fond memories of hiding the Buttergebäck and Lebkuchen in the laundry room from our Opa so he wouldn't devour them in one sitting, ripping open a human-size Adventskalendar in the course of one night made by our Oma...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/rixdorfer1200.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter  wp-image-1907" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/rixdorfer1200.jpg" alt="Rixdorfer1200" width="627" height="351" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/rixdorfer1200-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/rixdorfer1200-310x174.jpg 310w" sizes="(max-width: 627px) 100vw, 627px" /></a></p>
<p>Let&#8217;s just come right out with it: It&#8217;s hard to beat Christmas in Germany. <a href="http://www.gluhweinmix.com/whatisgluhwein.htm"><em>Glühwein</em></a>, cookies, classic lights, decorations strewn across homes and street corners, a <a href="http://german.about.com/library/definitions/bldef_cmas0301.htm">calendar</a>that expects, nay, <em>requires </em>you eat a chocolate per day&#8230; it&#8217;s simply wonderful. Though I grew up in the US, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/26/lens-coming-home/">my family</a> celebrated Christmas the Teutonic way. I have more than fond memories of hiding the <em>Buttergebäck</em> and <em>Lebkuchen</em> in the laundry room from our <em>Opa </em>so he wouldn&#8217;t devour them in one sitting, ripping open a human-size <em>Adventskalendar</em> in the course of one night made by our <em>Oma</em>, and relishing the torture of opening presents one-by-one on Christmas Eve under the illuminated <em>Tannenbaum</em>.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/baum.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter  wp-image-1909" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/baum.jpg?w=640" alt="baum" width="604" height="604" /></a></p>
<p>The only thing that was missing on our side of the Atlantic &#8211; and perhaps the pinnacle of Germany&#8217;s Christmas genius &#8211; was the <em>Weihnachtsmarkt.</em> The magical, cheerful Christmas market that makes it socially acceptable to go for a <em>Glühwein</em> at lunch with colleagues and eat your weight in candied almonds and those heart-shaped cinnamon cookie necklaces with cheesy phrases on them (ok, no one <em>actually</em> eats the cookie necklaces). The Christmas market that is part amusement park, part shopping center, part bar, part concert, part house of worship. The Christmas market that makes standing outside for hours in winter a desirable activity.</p>
<p>But Christmas markets aren&#8217;t all about empty calories, booze, and decorations. They&#8217;re also not just there for music, gift shopping, and family/friend time. And &#8211; hear me out &#8211; they&#8217;re not just about religion on either end of the purely-Christian-to-overly-PC-spectrum. In its truest sense, a market is a space for community gathering, exchange, and learning. Which is why when I travel, the market is the first place I turn to for an inside look at a different culture and way of life. A Christmas market can be a place for opportunity as much as it is a place for celebration, regardless of religion, background, gender, age, or anything else. And like Kelly wrote this past summer, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/">it&#8217;s about showing up</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/santa.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1912" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/santa.jpg?w=640" alt="santa" width="640" height="640" /></a></p>
<p>Of course Christmas markets come in all shapes and sizes and with varying levels of kitsch and educational potential. In Berlin, there are the <em>über</em>-commercial markets at all major tourists points throughout the city that focus on food and fun: Alexanderplatz, Zoo, Potsdamer Platz. For those who want to class it up a bit, there&#8217;s Gendarmenmarkt and Schloss Charlottenburg. For a smaller-town feel, and if you&#8217;re willing to make the trek outside the <em>Ring</em>, there&#8217;s Spandau. There are even themed markets, like the <a href="http://www.kadre.de/">Designmarket</a> and <a href="http://weihnachten.tagesspiegel.de/schwedischer-weihnachtsbasar.html">Swedish Christmas Market</a>. There is certainly <em>something for everyone</em>, but I&#8217;ve only been to one Christmas market in Berlin that feels truly modern in its <em>inclusion of everyone</em>, and that&#8217;s the Alt-Rixdorfer Market in <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/">Neukölln</a>.<em><br />
</em></p>
<p>Funnily enough, the Alt-Rixdorfer market is more about the past than the future. <em>Alt</em> means &#8220;old&#8221; and is a nod to the neighborhood&#8217;s history which is played out with petroleum lighting, young men acting as the &#8220;town crier&#8221; with old-fashioned megaphones, and pony rides. <a href="http://www.slowtravelberlin.com/in-search-of-rixdorf/">Rixdorf</a> has a long and proud history as a Protestant bohemian refugee settlement from the 1700s and retains its old-fashioned and quaint feel to this day. Its identity is more that of small village than city neighborhood, especially when juxtaposed with the hustle and bustle of <em>Karl-Marx Strasse </em>around the corner.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/rixdorfdouble.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1918" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/rixdorfdouble.jpg" alt="rixdorfdouble" width="470" height="597" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/rixdorfdouble.jpg 470w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/rixdorfdouble-236x300.jpg 236w" sizes="(max-width: 470px) 100vw, 470px" /></a></p>
<p>But besides these touches of years ago, besides the ubiquitous pork products, candied apples, and singing, the Alt-Rixdorfer market offers something different. The stands are primarily run by local clubs, organizations, and charity groups who display and sell homemade wares, whip up international culinary delights, and advocate for their respective causes. And while the market is still predominantly Christian in framework, it&#8217;s not necessarily Christian in purpose. From where I was standing &#8211; bundled up and elbow-to-elbow with young families, Turkish and Arab youth, homosexual couples, a trail of wheelchairs, and my international friends &#8211; the purpose was inclusion, diversity, and participation. Crawling amongst the hoards from stand to stand, I learned about district issues, was served by special needs residents, bought a handmade card with a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamsa"><em>Hamsa</em></a> on it, munched on Korean fried veggies, and watched kids run around proudly to keep the petroleum lights ablaze. What a more meaningful experience than the usual attempt at diversifying such an event: a Dreidel in one corner and Döner stand in the other with everything else green, red, and factory produced inbetween.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/koreanstand.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1917" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/koreanstand.jpg" alt="koreanstand" width="640" height="640" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/koreanstand.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/koreanstand-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>&#8220;Inclusion&#8221; is a hot topic these days in Berlin, Germany, and beyond. Yet when it comes to who needs inclusion and where, people and politics tend to focus on &#8220;special needs students&#8221; and &#8220;the school&#8221;. What about the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/">open Iftar dinner</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/">woman led neighborhood tour</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/">public gallery</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/21/lens-warm-nights-are-for-cricket/">baseball field</a>, and Christmas market? These are also shared community spaces that can promote inclusion of all residents through interaction, learning, and participation. The Alt-Rixdorfer Market shows us that a small effort to include the entire neighborhood can not only make cold feel warm and old feel new, but make Christmas about community.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>First photo <a href="http://www.weihnachteninberlin.de/binaries/asset/image_assets/1322607/ratio_16_9/1380794288/570x321/">source;</a> Rixdorf photo <a href="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%C3%B6hmisch-Rixdorf">source</a>; Karl-Marx Strasse <a href="http://www.stadtentwicklung.berlin.de/staedtebau/foerderprogramme/aktive_zentren/pix/start/2011-karl-marx-str-003.jpg">source</a>; all other photos by Sophia Burton</p>
<p><em>The Alt-Rixdorfer Christmas market takes place in Neukölln&#8217;s Richardplatz  annually on the 2. Advent (usually the first or second weekend of December).</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: TV, the Treasury Minister, and Third Culture Kids</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2013 13:08:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ex-pat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jewish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Third Culture Kids]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1543</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It's not everyday you're on TV, let alone get alluded to as a traitor by a host of public figures, including the Minister of the Treasury, all for being an expat. But both of these things happened to my friend and colleague Moran Yaheli when she was recently profiled in a report about Israelis living abroad...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/img_2302.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/img_2302.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_2302" width="640" height="425" /></a>It&#8217;s not everyday you&#8217;re on TV, let alone get alluded to as a traitor by a host of public figures, including the Minister of the Treasury, all for being an expat. But both of these things happened to my friend and colleague Moran Yaheli when she was recently profiled in a TV report about Israelis living abroad.</p>
<p><em>We were on 4 episodes, there were 5 in total, and I&#8217;ve been on the morning talk show and the radio, </em>Moran recounts&#8230; <em>and I was told that a satire show used our part from the morning show. This Sunday I&#8217;m going to be on another morning show panel. I&#8217;m a Z-list celebrity!</em></p>
<p>But we&#8217;ll get back to that.</p>
<p>Moran moved to Berlin from Tel Aviv in 2011 after meeting her now fiancé, Bastiaan (Bas). Their story alone is a lesson in 21st century romances: they met on the online Couchsurfing platform, and Moran spent a few nights on Bas&#8217; couch in Amsterdam while traveling around Europe. After surviving a few months of long-distance Skype calls and the occasional visit, the two decided to make a home for themselves in Europe. They both found jobs in Berlin and now live together in the <em>Schöneberg</em> district. Last year they welcomed their first baby, a beautiful boy named Tommy.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/israel-part-ii-081-kl-auto.jpeg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1627" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/israel-part-ii-081-kl-auto.jpeg?w=640" alt="Israel part II 081 kl auto" width="640" height="425" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/israel-part-ii-081-kl-auto.jpeg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/israel-part-ii-081-kl-auto-300x199.jpeg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/israel-part-ii-081-kl-auto-650x431.jpeg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>Tommy is primed to grow up as what has been coined the Third Culture Kid (TCK): &#8220;a person who has spent a significant part of his or her developmental years outside their parents’ culture&#8221; (David Pollock). With an Israeli mother, Dutch father, childhood (or at least babyhood) in Germany, and frequent trips to both mother- and fatherlands, Tommy will grow up navigating at least three cultural codes, languages, and geographies. It may seem like an unusual life, but it&#8217;s more and more a norm in our increasingly globalized and interconnected world. Even Buzzfeed published an <a href="http://www.buzzfeed.com/regajha/31-signs-youre-a-third-culture-kid">article</a> on &#8220;signs you&#8217;re a TCK&#8221; that included swearing in multiple languages, time zone expertise, and a transient understanding of &#8220;home&#8221;.</p>
<p><em>Tommy is a child of combined cultures, </em>Moran reflects<em>&#8230; he has both an Israeli and Dutch passport&#8230; but even though he was born in Berlin he can&#8217;t be a German citizen (without giving up the Israeli one). It&#8217;s the same for me, I feel I have more than one &#8220;home&#8221;, and I guess he will have that, too.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/285679521_640.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1580" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/285679521_640.jpg" alt="285679521_640" width="640" height="360" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/285679521_640.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/285679521_640-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/285679521_640-310x174.jpg 310w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://vimeo.com/41264088">Source</a></p>
<p>With only 8 months behind him so far in this world, Tommy has already taken two lengthy trips to Tel Aviv and one to the Netherlands. He is a dual citizen and hears an average 2-4 languages per day: Hebrew from his mom, Dutch from his dad, German from his environment, and English, the language in which his parents communicate.</p>
<p><em>We want to do the OPOL method, &#8216;One Parent One Language&#8217;, have you heard of it? </em>Moran asks me.<em> That way he gets just Hebrew from me, just Dutch from Bas. Tommy&#8217;s baby noises are kind of both Hebrew and Dutch, he does a lot of the &#8220;Chhh&#8221; noise&#8230; </em>she giggles.<em> When the neighbor babysits he only speaks German with him. I want him to go to a bilingual Hebrew-German Kita </em>(child care center).</p>
<p>Tommy is not just (im)migrant, not just citizen, but somewhere in between. He was born and lives in Berlin but isn&#8217;t a German citizen. If he moves to either Israel or the Netherlands, he will be moving there as a citizen but won&#8217;t necessarily have grown up there. His diverse lineage, cross-cultural upbringing, and even his darker features may mean he carries the mark of <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/"><em>Migrationshintergrund</em></a> most of his life, whether in Germany, Israel, the Netherlands, or somewhere else. Tommy will &#8220;build relationships to all these cultures but perhaps never have full ownership of any&#8221;. TCKs often feel a stronger sense of belonging and connection to others who have a similar background rather than a particular one. When Tommy grows up, he may fall in love and marry another TCK, someone who grew up in Rome with Singaporean and British parents, or perhaps someone from Sydney with French and Brazilian parents. Studies say his chances of doing so are <a href="http://www.denizenmag.com/2011/09/infographic-the-modern-third-culture-kid/">1 in 4</a>. His future inclination to raise his children as TCKs? <a href="http://www.denizenmag.com/2011/09/infographic-the-modern-third-culture-kid/">Even higher</a>. His sense of home will be an abstract one, one that he feels more in relation to people, memories, and experiences than citizenship, borders, and geography.</p>
<p><em>I can&#8217;t vote in Israel because Israeli doesn&#8217;t allow absentee ballots&#8230; even my cousin </em>(in Israel)<em> doesn&#8217;t think I should be able to vote in their elections because I don&#8217;t live there, </em>Moran rolls her eyes.<em> But even though I don&#8217;t live in Israel, I still feel it&#8217;s my home&#8230; my friends and family are there. As for Tommy, he will have 3 homes for now and as he grows maybe just two- Israel which he will visit a lot, and Holland where he will likely live at some point. If we&#8217;re in Holland or Germany, I&#8217;m going to be seen as a foreigner. I don&#8217;t want Tommy to be made fun of or be ashamed of me. So it&#8217;s important for me that Tommy meets and grows up in an international environment, with kids who also have diverse backgrounds. With other kids like him.<br />
</em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/2013-10-08-16-38-33.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/2013-10-08-16-38-33.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-10-08 16.38.33" width="512" height="682" /></a></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Confusions and complications aside, studies on Third Culture Kids show that they reap a whole host of benefits from their intercultural upbringings and lifestyles: TCKs live in four countries during their lives on average, 85% speak two or more languages (47% speak three or more), and 90% earn a Bachelor&#8217;s Degree with 40% going on to further study. Statistically they&#8217;re a well-educated, well-rounded, and well-suited group for the demands of the 21st century, both professionally and personally. They just may have difficulty articulating to you <a href="http://vimeo.com/41264088">where home is</a>.</p>
<p><em>I don&#8217;t know where Tommy will end up, </em>considers Moran.<em> Right now the current situation in Israel is complicated and I can&#8217;t see us going back. Economically, politically, demographically, religiously, etc. But I am not giving up hope&#8230; Israel is a beautiful place, the best place, it&#8217;s just unfortunately in crisis. If things get better I would be on the first plane home. And, if the situation improves, I would love for Tommy to choose Israel, too.  </em></p>
<p>As to the economic situation&#8230;</p>
<p><em>The rising number of Orthodox Jews is scary and it is so expensive to live in Tel Aviv. I paid the same rent for a shoebox in Tel Aviv as I do now with Bas in our big, new flat in Berlin. Groceries are over twice as expensive in Israel than Germany!</em></p>
<p>126% more expensive in fact, which brings us back to the TV report. Grocery and rent costs were one topic Moran and a series of other Israeli expats were asked about when interviewed about living abroad. The economic situation in Israel is pretty dire and gave rise to the ongoing social justice protests that began in 2011, the largest in the country&#8217;s history with over 1 million people gathering in Tel Aviv&#8217;s Rabin Square. While mostly focused on the cost of living differences, Moran also got token questions about what it feels like to be a Jew in Germany. On the show, the journalist shuttles her over to the Holocaust Memorial to the Jews in <em>Mitte</em>. He&#8217;s curious how she feels when she sees it.</p>
<p><em>The Jewish Memorial doesn&#8217;t speak to me,</em> Moran explained first to the journalist and later to me. <em>It&#8217;s more the everyday. Like seeing trains covered in snow&#8230; we don&#8217;t have snow covered trains in Israel and it reminds me of images we saw in school of the deportation of the Jews. Or hearing the voice on the train say &#8216;</em>Ausstieg&#8217;<em> which always makes me think of &#8216;Auschwitz&#8217;. Seeing old people on the street and wondering what role they played in World War II.</em></p>
<p>And the Minister of the Treasury? When asked to respond to the TV report, he was in Budapest, giving a speech on antisemitism.</p>
<p><em>A word to all those who have &#8220;had it&#8221; and left for Europe&#8230; </em>Moran translates his response for me&#8230;<em> I&#8217;m here to deliver a speech in the Budapest Parliament about antisemitism, to remind them of how they tried to kill my father here only because Jewish people didn&#8217;t have their own land, how they did kill my grandfather in a camp, how they starved my uncles, how my grandmother was rescued at the last second from a &#8220;death march&#8221;. So excuse me if I&#8217;m a bit impatient with people who are willing to throw away the only homeland the Jewish people have ever had, just because Berlin is &#8220;more convenient&#8221;.</em></p>
<p>Other politicians and one of the country&#8217;s most famous lawyers went so far as to call the Israeli expats in Berlin &#8220;traitors&#8221; and &#8220;slime that crawls in the sewer of Jewish society&#8221;, respectively. On the whole, however, Moran reports positive responses and understanding from those back in Israel, something she claims is a shift from the Zionist past.</p>
<p><em>It&#8217;s the older generation that has a problem with people leaving Israel&#8230; the ones who escaped antisemitism, built the country and died in wars to protect it, </em>Moran explains. <em>They see our leaving as abandoning the ship, the cause, the ideal&#8230; for money. My parents were born in Israel but my grandparents were from Europe, so I have two passports, too, </em><em>Israeli and Romanian. </em><em>I want Tommy to grow up with both tradition and choice&#8230; for his religion and for where he makes his home. </em></p>
<p>And choices he will have&#8230;</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>For those with Hebrew skills or simply interested in watching and pretending to understand (like me), you can check out the video that includes Moran, Bas, and Tommy <a href="http://news.nana10.co.il/Article/?ArticleID=1007634">here</a>. Also, I recommend this great little video about TCKs made by a Georgetown University student <em><a href="http://vimeo.com/41264088">here</a></em>. There&#8217;s also a Facebook group dedicated to TCKs around the world, check it out <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Third-Culture-Kids-TCKs/274710935889196">here</a>! </em></p>
<p><em>For the German perspective on the German-Israeli friendship and the question of expats, click <a href="http://www.sueddeutsche.de/politik/israel-berlin-wir-fahren-nach-berlin-1.1793580">here</a> (for German speakers). </em></p>
<p>All images not with a linked source are my own or Moran&#8217;s.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Ramadan with Neighbors: It&#8217;s About Showing Up</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2013 14:17:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kreuzberg]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1203</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For those non-Muslims among us, Ramadan is an almost hidden spectacle with mysterious allure: the hot tea, the music, and the platters of food only come out when the sun has turned in for the day or before it has even appeared. We hear the clatter of dishes from our neighbors’ windows late into the night or watch children unpack colorful sweets on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eid_ul-Fitr"><i>Eid al-Fitr</i></a>, all without necessarily being able to place these traditions in our own line of experience. In honor of the last night of Ramadan, here is a reflection on an event Sophia and I attended last Friday as part of Berlin's festival <a href="http://www.piranhakultur.de/event/events_2013/naechte_des_ramadan"><i>die </i></a><i><a href="http://www.piranhakultur.de/event/events_2013/naechte_des_ramadan">Nächte des Ramadan</a>, </i>the Nights of Ramadan...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Many of the world&#8217;s cities teem with fasting bodies during the c. 30 days of the Muslim holiday of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramadan_(calendar_month)">Ramadan</a>. About <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/berlin/berlinerstatistik/1670484.html">300,000 Muslims</a> live in Berlin: that makes for a lot of hungry individuals during the holy month. Of course, not every Muslim fasts, not every faster is Muslim, and not all Muslims celebrate Ramadan the same (or even at all). But for those non-Muslims among us, Ramadan is an almost hidden spectacle with mysterious allure: the hot tea, the music, and the platters of food that only come out when the sun has turned in for the day or before it has even appeared. We hear the clatter of dishes from our neighbors’ windows late into the night or watch children unpack colorful sweets on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eid_ul-Fitr"><i>Eid al-Fitr</i></a>, all without necessarily being able to place these traditions in our own line of experience. So, what is it actually like to break the fast at the end of the day among friends and family? Among neighbors?</p>
<p>Today is the last day of Ramadan, so it is high time for some reflection on an event Sophia and I attended last Friday as part of Berlin&#8217;s festival <a href="http://www.piranhakultur.de/event/events_2013/naechte_des_ramadan"><i>die </i></a><i><a href="http://www.piranhakultur.de/event/events_2013/naechte_des_ramadan">Nächte des Ramadan</a>, </i>the Nights of Ramadan. Organized by the <a href="http://kreuzbergmuseum.de/index.php?id=1">Kreuzberg Museum</a>, the whole community was invited to an <a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/berlin/muslime-in-berlin-reim-den-ramadan,10809148,23930332.html"><i>Iftar </i></a>celebration, the nightly breaking of the fast, in the museum&#8217;s garden right near <i>Kottbusser Tor</i>. Of course the breaking of bread in the privacy of one’s home is different from the organization of an intentional <em><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/10/whose-multikulti-is-it-the-elusive-definition-of-multiculturalism/">Multikulti</a></em> program. This event was not just about eating and drinking in public after another day doing without: it was about bringing fasting bodies together with the curious non-Muslims or non-fasters among us.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/photo.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1208" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/photo.jpg?w=640" alt="photo" width="640" height="640" /></a></p>
<p><i>The gates to the Kreuzberg Museum open to long tables and benches decked with white cloth and table settings. Plates of bloated dates run down the center, stuffed with walnuts, dark chocolate, and coconut.  </i>&#8220;They just put everything in them our bodies might want”,<i> says the small-framed woman across from me with a laugh &#8211; an instructor of </i><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">Integrationskurse</a><i>* in Berlin, she tells me. Having fasted and even worked all day, she doesn&#8217;t seem one bit tired, rather concentrated and composed. I am boiling in the midst of what I consider extreme humidity; not a bead of sweat is to be seen on her face which sits surrounded by heavy, sage-green cloth. </i>“You just get used to it, to not eating”,<i> she responds, when I ask if it is difficult, my flashbacks of Lent-related chocolate withdrawal ever-present. </i>“And I can lay down once and a while at work to rest”,<i> she adds. She has been fasting for years, even before she was a practicing Muslim. </i>“I used to fast with my brother, though my parents never participated”.<i> She is originally from Azerbaijan, six years in Germany and still not sure if it’s home. “</i>They are German”,<i> she says pointing to her three friends, “</i>I just live here”<i>. A laugh erupts into the sticky night. She rests her palm on her cheek. </i></p>
<p><i>I find the buffet prepared by (the speaker’s words not mine) </i>die Arabische Frauen<i> (Arab women) and try to take a picture of the overwhelming spread. Ladies in bright colors scurry to assemble more heaps of greasy drumsticks, mounds of semolina and rice with toasted almonds, deep-fried spinach and clumps of rose-colored meat in a breaded dress. </i></p>
<p><i>A small man brings the microphone to his lips  &#8211; not on the stage, but beneath it &#8211; and the prayer begins. It is exactly 9:02pm, and the sun has sunken beneath the city lights. No one dares to nibble on the dates, which is the signal that the fast has been broken. It is silent except for the melodic call to prayer. The teacher from Azerbaijan mouths the words without making a sound, her cheekbones concealed now by the edges of her headscarf</i>. <i>Her head turns downward to fall into her hands forming an invisible Koran in her lap, her palms and their scriptures seeming to capture all sound.</i></p>
<p><i>The three friends of our new teacher-friend return to the table with piles of food, offering us as much as we like, since we will not be getting in line until after those who have fasted. When we protest, the teacher remarks in between slow and measured bites off the chicken bone in her hand,</i> “Your stomach shrinks throughout the day, so your eyes are much bigger than your capacity”. <i>She smiles and points to the mound of food in the middle of our table. Köfte is rolled onto our plates as we politely probe with questions. The three friends are just beginning their 20s, studying at university, active in the </i>organization <a href="http://www.muslimische-jugend.de/">Muslimische Jugend in Deutschland e.V</a><i>. Their involvement in this organization brought them and the teacher together, who seems to smile adoringly but wisely at her younger companions as they speak. None of the three wear </i>hijab; <i>one is engaged to her high school sweetheart and studying to earn her PhD in forensic science. </i></p>
<p style="text-align: center;" align="center"> <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/photo-2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter  wp-image-1207" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/photo-2.jpg?w=640" alt="photo (2)" width="448" height="448" /></a></p>
<p><i>The director of the Kreuzberg Museum addresses the public – families finished eating though chattering loudly as ever, interested passers-by with backpacks watching the stage, the Kreuzberg Fire Dept. laughing with friends and looking dapper in suits. A small German man in a somber white button-down and black pant, he thanks the neighbors for their patience in tolerating the noise and those neighbors who came to take part, then introduces the musical performance of the night. The Iraqi-German musician <a href="http://www.saif-karomi.com/music.htm">Saif Karomi</a> enters the stage with a beautiful Oud gripped in his right hand. His music, with the accompaniment of a slender wooden flute and a steady Djembe, seeps out into the night. Most of the windows from Kotti’s high-rise apartments are glowing, many left open to let the sounds and the light stream in. </i></p>
<p style="text-align: center;" align="center"><a href="http://www.piranhakultur.de/gallery/ramadan_2013/saif_karomi_02_08"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1231" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/music.jpg" alt="Music" width="400" height="333" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/music.jpg 400w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/music-300x249.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a></p>
<p><i>Trays of dessert circulate the courtyard: pistachio cream with rose water in a honey-soaked pancake </i>(Qatayef);<i> walnuts bathed in honey, chopped, and folded delicately into sweet bread; pistachio and nougat doused in dark chocolate and coconut. Hot tea is served in elegant glasses fit to the palm. Clapping begins in rhythmic compliment to the weeping lull of the Oud. At 11pm the lanterns are extinguished. We head out the gates of the Kreuzberg museum, passing a line of young people smoking on the steps near the sheet of Kebap shops and neon-lit bars. We move on and outward into the other neighborhoods we know well, my body in anything but a state of want.</i></p>
<p align="center"> <a href="http://www.recettes-cuisine-afrique.info/IMG/jpg/Qatayef.jpg"><img loading="lazy" src="http://www.recettes-cuisine-afrique.info/IMG/jpg/Qatayef.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="300" /></a></p>
<p>At this event, I kept asking myself what the words &#8220;integration&#8221; and &#8220;diversity&#8221; really mean to the politicians who speak them. To me, it is not about &#8220;to each his or her own&#8221; or just about learning the majority language, rather it is about taking part in a two-way process. It is about getting to know one another and forging new spaces of neighborhood between these ways of knowing. It is often just about showing up to our neighbor’s barbecue, about inviting the friendly guy from the <i>Späti</i> to a party, about delivering mail to the lady upstairs (even if she never looks friendly) and staying in a slightly damp hallway to chit-chat (and not because you want to). I have learned from these experiences that it really is just about going to places, interacting with others, and maybe asking questions. Taking an interest in the life and interests of one’s neighbor is an integral part of what it means to live in a metropolis. Any other way forward and things might just fall apart.</p>
<p>Ramadan is one way of holding everything together, keeping us honest in whether or not we really value difference – just like I really value pistachio cream and the Oud, maybe just as much as I value mayo on my fries or the American Diner. Such meet-your-neighbor events also give us reason to congregate and converse about all the things we do not know but might just assume about one another. Not everyone at this event wore <em>hijab</em> or prayed with beads, not everyone fasted, not everyone was Muslim or even the same type of Muslim, for that matter.</p>
<p>It should be of interest to all of us that nearly 7% of Berlin&#8217;s population may be abstaining from food and water in 90 degree heat and 50% humidity, still going to work, driving cars, pushing strollers, running errands, participating in daily life during the holiest days in the Muslim religion. This phenomenon is happening all over the world, times ten, in many different shapes and flavors.</p>
<p>The Kreuzberg Museum holds this event every year. We hope events like it will show up in places less expected than Kreuzberg, maybe even more situated in the everyday. We just have to show up and be a part of it.</p>
<p><i>&#8211; By <b>Kelly Miller</b></i></p>
<p>*<i>Integrationskurse</i> are federally mandated integration courses for immigrants and refugees within their first three years of residence in Germany. However, these courses have only been in existence since 2005, allowing many earlier waves of immigrants the chance to participate in a combination of language-learning and cultural orientation after the three year period has passed.</p>
<p>Photos by Sophia Burton or otherwise sourced with link to image.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rave: Neukölln&#8217;s Intercultural Day-to-Day</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2013 14:37:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gentrification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=891</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A Berlin restaurant with an American name run by a Tunisian who prepares Italian fare in Halal style? Anywhere else this collision of cultures on a plate would be considered poor marketing.  In Neukölln it's more or less the norm...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/2013-06-15-15-09-14.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-892 aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/2013-06-15-15-09-14.jpg" alt="2013-06-15 15.09.14" width="640" height="480" /></a>A Berlin restaurant with an American name run by a Tunisian who prepares Italian fare in Halal style? Anywhere else this collision of cultures on a plate would be considered poor marketing.  In Neukölln it&#8217;s more or less the norm.</p>
<p>&#8220;L.A. New York Restaurant&#8221; was the second stop along <em>Erkundung im Paradies, </em>one of numerous tours offered by <a href="http://route44-neukoelln.de/touren/paradies_tour1.html">Route 44</a> that explore Neukölln&#8217;s migration history and interculturalism. The tours are entirely female-run and designed by a group of diverse women who are proud to call Neukölln their &#8220;(second) home&#8221;.</p>
<p>Neukölln is Berlin&#8217;s 8th district and home to 320,000 residents, approximately 40% of which are not ethnically German. Almost 150 nationalities are represented (primarily Turkey, the Arab world, and former Yugoslavia) and the district is at the heart of Berlin&#8217;s gentrification debate, making Neukölln hard to ignore. Nonetheless, it was off my radar for years and continues to be for tourists who either don&#8217;t know it exists or have been warned it&#8217;s too dangerous to visit. My 250 page Berlin guide book from 2003 doesn&#8217;t say one word about Neukölln. Ten years later and it&#8217;s still not mentioned on <a href="http://www.timeout.com/berlin/features/10/berlin-area-guide">this list</a> or <a href="http://www.fodors.com/news/understanding-berlins-neighborhoods-5831.html">this list</a> or <a href="http://www.cityscouter.com/travelguides/berlin/Berlin-Districts.html">this list</a>. It is on <a href="http://berlin.cityseekr.com/cityguide/district-guide-1">this one</a>: &#8220;More down-to-earth are the working-class districts of Wedding in the north and Neukölln in the south, which is sometimes referred to as the Berlin Bronx. Although they both have a reputation of being ghettos for the poor, unemployed and other down-and-outs, they are not as bad as they are made out to be.&#8221; What a ringing endorsement.<em><br />
</em></p>
<p>The Route 44 girls describe Neukölln as a region of &#8220;irritating problems but fascinating potential&#8221;. Unfortunately Neukölln&#8217;s problems go beyond irritating to downright serious: they have one of the city&#8217;s highest unemployment rates (<a href="http://www.berlin.de/ba-neukoelln/derbezirk/arbeitslose.html">17%</a>), high child poverty rates, and a crime rate that is about 40% higher than Berlin&#8217;s average. But it is also home to immense diversity, creativity, and rich cultural history. Reducing Neukölln (or any struggling region) to the &#8220;poor, unemployed and other down-and-outs&#8221; is not only unfair, it&#8217;s unproductive.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/2013-06-15-15-44-50.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/2013-06-15-15-44-50.jpg" alt="2013-06-15 15.44.50" width="640" height="480" /></a><em>Erkundung im Paradies</em> or &#8220;Exploring Paradise&#8221; showcases this &#8220;fascinating potential&#8221; through an exploration of a neighborhood and its various houses of worship, educational institutions, trendy bars, and international restaurants. Yet perhaps the most interesting facet of the tour was not the stops itself, but the open dialogue it generated. The tour participants were largely locals and the intermittent chatter and questions culminated in a discussion on religion and the role of the headscarf. Hiba and Maria, our guides, responded openly and respectfully to questions from the group that ranged from  &#8220;Aren&#8217;t women forced to wear them?&#8221; to &#8220;Why don&#8217;t you wear one?&#8221; Hiba (Lebanese-German) and Maria (Pakistani-German) don&#8217;t wear headscarves and explained that while it&#8217;s a commitment they&#8217;re not ready to make now, they don&#8217;t rule it out for the future. Either way, it&#8217;s their choice alone.</p>
<p>When asked by a  journalist why they do the tours, they responded quite simply: &#8220;Neukölln has a bad reputation, and we want to change that.&#8221;</p>
<p>I&#8217;d say the guidebooks should take note, but I&#8217;m not sure we need them. These women are creating their own and it&#8217;s a lot more interesting.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>For more information on Route 44 tours, click <a href="http://route44-neukoelln.de/touren.html">here</a>. Tours are offered every first and third Saturday of the month and registration is not necessary. Bring something to cover your shoulders during visits to houses of worship. Tours are given in German but the guides offer a variety of other languages that include English, Urdu, Arabic, and Turkish.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>Funkhaus Europa recorded the above-mentioned tour and you can access the article and audio <a href="http://www.radiobremen.de/funkhauseuropa/aktuell/aktuell590.html">here. </a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rant or Rave? Jew in a Box</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/07/rant-or-rave-jew-in-a-box/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/07/rant-or-rave-jew-in-a-box/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2013 08:51:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jewish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[museums]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.wordpress.com/?p=178</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p style="text-align:left;">What did you first think of when you read the post title? Saturday Night Live? World War II? Either way, I'm pleased to have gotten your attention. Let's talk about Jew in a Box...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/jewishmuseum.png"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-189" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/jewishmuseum.png" alt="jewishmuseum" width="599" height="397" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/jewishmuseum.png 599w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/jewishmuseum-300x198.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 599px) 100vw, 599px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">What did you first think of when you read the post title? Saturday Night Live? World War II? Either way, I&#8217;m pleased to have gotten your attention. Let&#8217;s talk about Jew in a Box.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Jew in a Box is a nickname for what the Jewish Museum in Berlin is calling <em>Die ganze Wahrheit</em>, or The Whole Truth: a special exhibit that teaches Germans about real-life Jews, to put it bluntly. For two hours a day, a Jewish volunteer sits in a box and answers questions from museum-goers about all things Jewish. Any topic is free game, from God to Netanyahu to pork to circumcision.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">A half-Jew myself, I really want to like this exhibit. And I do in many ways. I believe that direct exposure to &#8220;others&#8221; can help break down barriers and generate understanding between groups. <strong>It often just takes meeting one person to humanize an entire group and start to break down harmful stereotypes.</strong> And a forum for being open and where there are no stupid questions, well let&#8217;s just say I often wish life were like that.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">I also appreciate the focus on the<em> current</em> experience of Jews in Germany. Germany does a whole lot to acknowledge the past, but the fact remains that <strong>most Germans today don&#8217;t have regular contact with Jews and know little about their religion and culture.</strong> Or maybe they do, and just don&#8217;t know it. Many would likely be surprised to learn that Berlin has a thriving &#8211; and growing &#8211; population of young Israelis and Jews. <a href="http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/features/2013/02/201322711114892470.html">Experts put estimates at up to 30,000</a>, maybe even higher since many Israelis have European passports and <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">aren&#8217;t considered immigrants</a>. Of course that doesn&#8217;t come close to the half a million Jews who lived in pre-war Germany, but it&#8217;s still considerable.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Negative reactions to the exhibit span from calling it &#8220;distasteful&#8221; to &#8220;degradation of the Jew.&#8221; I wouldn&#8217;t go as far to say the latter, but can understand a bit of the former. I see how the &#8220;box&#8221; analogy would make one uneasy. There&#8217;s also a fine line between being open and disrespectful, and with no filters and provocative signs surrounding the exhibit with statements like &#8220;The Jews are guilty of everything,&#8221; there&#8217;s potential for things to get offensive. But probably the biggest problem with this exhibit is that it&#8217;s somewhat reductionist. The Jews are more than a religious group- they are a diaspora, and a diverse one at that. An Orthodox Jew living in Brooklyn and a Jew from Ethiopia living as a Christian to escape persecution have less in common than I do with Oprah.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Can any one Jew really give &#8220;the whole truth&#8221;? This half-Jew isn&#8217;t sure.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>The Whole Truth runs from March 22- September 1, 2013. The Jewish Museum is located at Lindenstraße 9-14  10969 Berlin.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Photo Source: <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/04/05/world/europe/berlin-exhibition-on-judaism-hits-a-nerve.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=0">New York Times</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/07/rant-or-rave-jew-in-a-box/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
