<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>education &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/education/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Migration Matters: A Free Video Lecture Series</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/02/29/migration-matters-a-free-video-lecture-series/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[collidoscopeks]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 14:16:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4377</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When we talk about migration on this website, among our friends and colleagues, and particularly across the vast expanse of the internet, we are confronted with many misconceptions about who the immigrants and refugees of the world really are, what brings them to our countries and communities, and whether or not the statements made by politicians on immigration are true, let alone helpful. We write about the movement and coming together of people, because we believe commentary and discussion to be a powerful antidote to this perpetuation of misinformation. But are words, indeed our own voices, ever enough? A New Project: Migration Matters In collaboration with two inspiring women in the field of migration reporting and migration studies, we are embarking on a new chapter of Collidoscope&#8217;s mission in launching a free online course, which will deliver concise, accurate information about migration in just five minutes a day. This course will focus on promoting understanding of the issues: how and why migration happens, how it is being addressed around the world, and how we can become more informed actors in the process. We let &#8220;the experts&#8221; speak: accomplished, peer-reviewed researchers and educators, practitioners in the field, and migrants themselves. In [...]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When we talk about migration on this website, among our friends and colleagues, and particularly across the vast expanse of the internet, we are confronted with many misconceptions about who the immigrants and refugees of the world really are, what brings them to our countries and communities, and whether or not the statements made by politicians on immigration are true, let alone helpful.</p>
<p>We write about the movement and coming together of people, because we believe commentary and discussion to be a powerful antidote to this perpetuation of misinformation. But are words, indeed our own voices, ever enough?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-4371 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/TrailerThumbnail.jpg" width="650" height="366" /></p>
<p><strong>A New Project: <a href="https://www.generosity.com/community-fundraising/migration-matters-a-free-video-lecture-series/x/13390941">Migration Matters</a></strong></p>
<p>In collaboration with two inspiring women in the field of migration reporting and migration studies, we are embarking on a new chapter of Collidoscope&#8217;s mission in launching <a href="https://www.generosity.com/community-fundraising/migration-matters-a-free-video-lecture-series/x/13390941">a free online course</a>, which will deliver concise, accurate information about migration in just five minutes a day.</p>
<p>This course will focus on promoting understanding of the issues: how and why migration happens, how it is being addressed around the world, and how we can become more informed actors in the process. We let &#8220;the experts&#8221; speak: accomplished, peer-reviewed researchers and educators, practitioners in the field, and migrants themselves.</p>
<p>In line with what we have worked to create with the Collidoscope project, this course will foster a space for open conversation, where no concern is ridiculed and no question dismissed.</p>
<p>To learn more, visit the Migration Matters page and <a href="http://www.migrationmatters.me/">pre-enroll for this great course</a>! You can also follow Migration Matters on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/migrmatters">@MigrMatters</a> and on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/MigrationMatters/?fref=ts">Facebook</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Funding</strong></p>
<p>We can&#8217;t do it without your help &#8211; our loyal supporters, readers, friends, colleagues, and friends.</p>
<p>Please help us realize our goal of beginning an open, evidence-based conversation about the issues that matter most to us, to immigrants, to refugees, by <a href="https://www.generosity.com/community-fundraising/migration-matters-a-free-video-lecture-series/x/13390941">contributing to our crowd-funding campaign</a>. You can also help by spreading the word about this project in your community. The greater our reach, the more effective its message.</p>
<p>If you have any questions about Migration Matters or would like to be involved, please contact the team at migrmatters@gmail.com. Currently we are looking for individuals with experience in visual design, interactive online experiences, and data visualizations.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em><strong>Kelly and Sophia</strong></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Berlin needs you (but why?)</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/04/review-berlin-needs-you-but-why/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/04/review-berlin-needs-you-but-why/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2014 08:20:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2702</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Why is immigration important? The debate takes many angles. There's the demographic argument, that developed countries with low birth rates and aging populations need bodies to maintain the replacement rate. There's the globalization take, that the movement of people in all forms is increasingly inevitable and contributes to global competitiveness and 21st century skills. The moral or even religious spin, emphasizing human dignity, charity, an obligation for prosperous nations to help those more needy. But few arguments are as pervasive as the economic one...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_2738" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdad.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2738" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2738 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad.jpg?w=640" alt="" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad-300x199.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2738" class="wp-caption-text">©Barbara Dietl</p></div>
<p>Why is immigration important? The debate takes many angles. There&#8217;s the <a href="http://www.thelocal.de/20131126/germany-needs-more-immigration">demographic argument</a>, that developed countries with low birth rates and aging populations need bodies to maintain the replacement rate. There&#8217;s the globalization take, that the movement of people in all forms is increasingly inevitable and contributes to global competitiveness and 21st century skills. The moral or even religious spin, emphasizing human dignity, charity, and an obligation for prosperous nations to help those more needy. Yet few arguments are as pervasive as the economic one: that immigrants fill labor shortages, tend to be more innovative, start businesses and create jobs, pay taxes, and contribute to the social welfare net (yes, often more than they &#8220;take away&#8221;).</p>
<p>It is this economic argument that is often relied upon as a point of mutual agreement that immigrants are needed. Maybe not <a href="http://www.dw.de/opinion-foreigners-welcome-sort-of/a-17651819">“wanted”</a>, but at least needed.</p>
<p>This argument extends beyond newcomers to the 2nd and 3rd generations. In countries like Germany where the history of immigration has been primarily low skilled, children of migrants still face numerous linguistic, cultural, and socioeconomic challenges. These are exacerbated by a stratified education system that is associated with lower educational attainment, limited access to higher education, and fewer chances for economic mobility. Germany fares particularly poorly in this arena: it has the <a href="http://www.oecd.org/general/oecdeducationsystemsleavemanyimmigrantchildrenflounderingreportshows.htm">OECD&#8217;s largest performance disparity</a> between native and immigrant students and is one of the only countries where 2nd generation students perform worse on international assessments than the 1st generation.</p>
<p>Enter <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> (Berlin needs you!), a program that works to improve the educational and economic outcomes of students with migrant backgrounds. Launched by the state of Berlin as part of its overall integration plan in 2006, it aims to increase the number of these students entering the public sector by 25% by bridging schools with the professional world. It is coordinated by BQN, <em>das Berufliche Qualifizierungsnetzwerk für Migrantinnen und Migranten in Berlin</em> (the Vocational Qualification Network for Immigrants in Berlin) and is funded by the state of Berlin.</p>
<p><iframe title="Berlin braucht dich! - Diverse Wege in die Arbeitswelt" width="650" height="366" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fwBxQu93g3o?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>The program works in cycles: a day-long introduction to a business or organization for 7th graders, a week-long internship for 8th graders, 3-week internships for 9th graders, and training and application days for 10th graders. Participating schools help their students find training spots with an online matching tool. Spots are currently offered in Berlin&#8217;s public sector, public companies, and the metal and electrical industries, though BQN is working toward expanding the program to include small businesses. The program has also evolved from a focus on the vocational training system (<em>Duales System</em> &#8211; working and learning in a company) to more dual study opportunities <em>(Duales Studium</em> &#8211; studying and working simultaneously).</p>
<p>Mitri Sirin, a German TV reporter of Turkish-Syrian background, moderates the 5th <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> consortium meeting in June. He highlights the culture of low expectations and need for more varied training opportunities for migrant students during a panel on diversity politics.<em> The idea that any kid in the 7th grade would know what they wanted to be when they grow up is a fairy tale,</em> he scoffs. <em>Of course I was funneled into a vocational internship with other kids like me. I was still able to make something or other of myself</em>, he adds to chuckles from the audience,<em> but not all are so lucky.</em></p>
<div id="attachment_2790" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdconsortium.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2790" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2790 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium.jpg?w=640" alt="Berlin braucht dich! Consortium Meeting June 2014" width="640" height="480" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2790" class="wp-caption-text"><em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> Consortium Meeting June 2014 ©BQN Berlin</p></div>
<p>When the panel concludes, a group of giggling students race out from behind the stage to plaster black paper on the windows and switch off the lights. It&#8217;s a bit eerie to be cloaked in darkness with pop music blaring before 11am, but soon enough the black-light theater performance has the audience tapping their feet and grinning widely. While entirely up for interpretation, the images of a ball being passed around between two sets of hands and a student struggling in a white sheet before becoming a colorful butterfly suggests a story-line of transnationalism and diversity.</p>
<p><em>The theater program is</em> <em>a kind of &#8220;empowerment action&#8221;</em>, explains Robert Westermann, PR Manager of Berlin braucht dich! <em>The group comes from one of the 32 schools we cooperate with&#8230; students from this school also take part in our internships. </em></p>
<p>Later that morning, we make sure to join the small workshop where the same students share their experiences. <em>I&#8217;ve been in Germany for 2 years and can&#8217;t speak German that well,</em> <em>but black-light theater is like another language that I can speak to everyone, without having to actually say anything, </em>shares one Iranian girl.  <em>In theater you have to learn to control yourself, but you can also be free</em>, says another. <em>Theater has taught me how to be loud</em>, exclaims a third.</p>
<div id="attachment_2737" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2737" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2737 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht.jpg?w=640" alt="Schule am Schloss students post-performance. Source: Berlin braucht dich!" width="640" height="480" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2737" class="wp-caption-text"><em>Schule am Schloss</em> students take a bow post-performance ©BQN Berlin</p></div>
<p><em>In my view, the most innovative aspect of </em>Berlin braucht dich!<em> is that schools and companies are working together on a constant and sustainable level</em>, describes Robert.<em> This stable network makes it possible to operationalize key ideas around &#8220;intercultural openness&#8221;, by changing structures, processes, and mentalities. </em></p>
<p><em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> has experienced marked success in its 8 years of operation. Since 2006, the ratio of trainees in the public sector with a migration background has been steadily on the rise and by 2009 had doubled to 16.9%. By 2013, every 5th trainee (20.5%) in the public sector and public companies had a migration background.</p>
<p>Yet it is the emphasis on mutually understood and implemented &#8220;intercultural openness&#8221; that implies <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> is about more than Euro signs. In addition to securing a more intercultural workforce through sheer numbers, BQN offers free <a href="http://www.berlin-braucht-dich.de/aktivitaeten/diversity-trainings/">diversity trainings</a> for partner schools and businesses. Migration is acknowledged not only as a reality, but as a key factor that contributes both &#8220;to our quality of life now and the sustainability of our future.&#8221; While the demand for such trainings has been low on the school side, BQN has implemented many with employees from their partner companies.</p>
<div id="attachment_2800" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdstudents.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2800" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2800 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents.jpg?w=640" alt="bbdstudents" width="640" height="480" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2800" class="wp-caption-text">Moderator and TV reporter Mitri Sirin (middle) with theater group students ©BQN Berlin</p></div>
<p>The path to a truly intercultural workforce is still laden with hurdles. Recent studies on Germany show that <a href="http://www.migazin.de/2014/06/02/vorurteil-widerlegt-junge-migranten-nicht-haeufiger-kriminell-als-deutsche-jugendliche/">prejudice</a> and <a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/karriere/studie--mit-tuerkischem-namen-sinken-chancen-auf-ausbildungsmarkt,10808620,26663588.html">hiring discrimination</a> against students with migrant backgrounds is alive and well. Access to higher education and many employment opportunities is entirely off the table, as a disproportionate number &#8211; <a href="http://www.boeckler.de/35923_41774.htm">about half</a> &#8211; of these students are funneled into the lowest vocational school track. As one of the business representatives at the meeting explained to the theater group, <em>If any of you came into an interview at our offices, you would do great. But to get to the interview stage, you would still have to pass the entrance test first, which focuses on German, math, and logic. </em></p>
<p>Challenges such as these require integrated policy approaches. Approaches that distinguish the actors involved and hold them accountable for their roles in changing the structures, norms, and mentalities that fuel these challenges. Approaches that extend beyond just the economic argument and are brave enough to acknowledge everyone&#8217;s role in fostering an intercultural and inclusive society that values the potential of each individual. In short, Berlin doesn&#8217;t just need you. It needs all of us.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>Thank you to Robert Westermann, PR Manager of <em>Berlin braucht dich!, </em>for inviting us to the consortium meeting and providing information for this article.</p>
<p>For more information on <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em>, check out their German website <a href="http://www.berlin-braucht-dich.de/">here</a>. Info in English can be found <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/ewsi/en/practice/details.cfm?ID_ITEMS=13081">here. </a></p>
<p>For another article from us on Berlin based programs for students with migrant backgrounds, click <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/18/rave-education-per-square-kilometer/%20">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/04/review-berlin-needs-you-but-why/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Seeing Berlin Through The Homeless</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2014 12:22:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bureaucracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GDR-DDR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitte]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Schöneberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2398</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[They wait for the subway doors to close before they address the car with a rehearsed speech. "Excuse the interruption, I am one of Berlin's annoying homeless people"... it usually begins, as they peddle newspapers and scan the crowd for an outstretched hand holding change or food. The majority of us keep our hands tucked away or firmly gripping our phones. Some of us fall into convenient bouts of exhaustion, promptly leaning back and closing our eyes. In this moment, we are restricted to a shared space...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_2604" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2604" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2604 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-650x433.jpg" alt="hermannplatz" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2604" class="wp-caption-text">Photo by Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>In Berlin they are especially visible on the <em>Bahn</em>. They wait for the subway doors to close before they address the car with a rehearsed speech. <em>Excuse the interruption, I am one of Berlin&#8217;s annoying homeless people&#8230;</em> it usually begins, as they peddle newspapers and scan<em> </em>the crowd for an outstretched hand holding change or food. The majority of us keep our hands tucked away or firmly gripping our phones. Some of us fall into convenient bouts of exhaustion, promptly leaning back and closing our eyes. In this moment, we are restricted to a moving car, a shared space. We can&#8217;t dodge a corner or cross the street, but we still find ways to make them invisible. We don&#8217;t look up because we feel uncomfortable. We become frustrated at them for making us feel this way. We may even become angry &#8211; at them, at society, at ourselves.</p>
<p>How the simple presence of one person can incite so much emotion, judgement, and shame.</p>
<p>How it must feel, to be simultaneously so visible and invisible.</p>
<div id="attachment_2605" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2605" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2605 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-650x459.jpg" alt="eye" width="650" height="459" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-650x459.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-300x212.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2605" class="wp-caption-text">Photo by Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><em>It&#8217;s one of the worst things for homeless people, being treated as invisible. Answer them when they speak to you, make eye contact, acknowledge them!</em> our guide Carsten Voss urges us by the end of our walk. We are wrapping up a tour called &#8220;Obdachslose zeigen ihr Berlin&#8221; (The homeless present their Berlin), run by non-profit organization <em>Querstadtein. </em>The group offers tours in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Mitte that show the reality of homelessness in the city.</p>
<p>Our guide speaks from personal experience. Decked out in designer glasses and a well-fitting sweater, it&#8217;s challenging to picture this man as the subject of the powerful story he delivers in front of stately <span class="st">Viktoria-Luise-Platz</span>. Carsten worked 80+ hours a week as a manager of an international tradeshow before burning-out and falling into depression. First came the loss of his job, then his apartment. He refused help from loved ones, other than taking refuge in a friend&#8217;s shed for a few months. It would be a year before he clawed his way back out. He cites one defining moment: <em>I happened to glance into someone&#8217;s window from the street. The woman was cooking and the man was watching </em>Tagesschau<em> on TV&#8230; I realized that if I didn&#8217;t make a change then, I would never have that again.</em></p>
<p>That year Carsten counted among Berlin&#8217;s estimated 4,000 <em>Obdachslose</em> (literally translates to &#8220;without shelter&#8221;). Not to be confused with <em>Wohnungslose</em> (&#8220;house-less&#8221;), which refers to those without homes but still in the system, <em>Obdachslose</em> are no longer in the system and may or may not have a place to sleep. Berlin has Germany&#8217;s highest concentration of <em>Obdachslose, </em>both from within and outside of the country.</p>
<p><em>There are three main categories of </em>Obdachslose <em>in Berlin</em>, Carsten explains early on in the tour. <em>Former refugees from East Germany, those groups of young people who usually have dogs with them, and immigrants.<br />
</em></p>
<p><a href="http://ec.europa.eu/social/main.jsp?catId=1061&amp;langId=en">Migrant homelessness throughout the EU</a> has risen in recent years, exacerbated by the economic crisis. This may come as no great surprise, though it&#8217;s a blow to hear that many in Berlin<em> end up staying because they find the conditions of being homeless here better than their lives back home. </em>Carsten describes this group in three geographic waves: the first from Poland, second from the Baltics, and third from Bulgaria and Romania<em>. Of course they came here planning to find jobs, start families, create a life. Some make it, but many don&#8217;t. </em></p>
<div id="attachment_2586" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-23-14-33-35.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2586" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2586 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-23-14-33-35.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-23 14.33.35" width="640" height="480" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2586" class="wp-caption-text">Cold Weather Assistance for Berlin&#8217;s Homeless by District, Winter 2013/14</p></div>
<p>Berlin has a long tradition of homelessness. It&#8217;s a poor city &#8211; Germany&#8217;s poorest &#8211; but also equipped with robust social services. Berlin has a history of attracting those who are &#8220;different&#8221;, including many immigrants, due to its diversity and tolerant atmosphere. During the days of the Berlin Wall, it was also a haven for males escaping military conscription (which ended altogether in 2011). Carsten moved to Berlin for this reason, and says he and many others like him entered fields like social work and education. This, he claims, has contributed to the city&#8217;s liberal nature and strong social net.</p>
<p>Berlin&#8217;s homeless tend to cluster in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Charlottenburg, two districts in West Berlin now more associated with high rents and artisanal cafes than alternative lifestyles. Carsten guides us to Nollendorfplatz, Berlin&#8217;s LGBT hub and site of the annual pride parade, Christopher Street Day. We stand across from the colorful <em>Regenbogen-Stele, </em>a r<span class="userContent">ainbow column erected in 2000 to celebrate the area&#8217;s high concentration of homosexual residents and open-minded atmosp<span class="text_exposed_show">here. The statue itself carries two symbols: the rainbow flag for gay pride and the <em>Rosa Winkel</em>, a pink badge first used by Nazis to distinguish homosexuals in concentration camps, and what later became an international symbol for gay rights.<br />
</span></span></p>
<div id="attachment_2507" style="width: 538px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/2014-03-23-14-21-00-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2507" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2507" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/2014-03-23-14-21-00-1.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-23 14.21.00-1" width="528" height="528" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2507" class="wp-caption-text">Nollendorf Platz&#8217;s &#8220;Regenbogen-Stele&#8221; or rainbow column celebrating gay rights</p></div>
<p>As we inspect the square, Carsten points out what our untrained eyes fail to see: a 24-hour grocery store well-equipped with bottle deposit machines, a van selling the street newspaper, a well-lit intersection. <em>Homeless people are part of this neighborhood, they have a community here</em>, he says.</p>
<p>But another faction of the city&#8217;s homeless blend in so well that we don&#8217;t see them at all. <em>Most people have an image in mind of the bag lady (or guy), unkempt and dirty, pushing around a cart filled to the brim with random items, muttering crazy things to themselves.</em>.<em>. most homeless people don&#8217;t look or act like that. </em> Carsten estimates that 60% fall into this category, homeless people who look &#8220;normal&#8221; so they can use spaces and services within the city without being noticed. They schedule their day in such a way that they always have a place to be, something to eat, even a bed to sleep in. They know when the citizens&#8217; office opens and when they can grab a shower, when they can rest in the library or supermarket, who is offering a free lunch or haircut in the city. <em>It&#8217;s an exhausting life, they have to be very organized, and they are constantly in public</em>, Carsten emphasizes: <em>the only time they have to themselves is in the shower.</em></p>
<div id="attachment_2621" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-24-08-25-20.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2621" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2621 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-24-08-25-20.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-24 08.25.20" width="640" height="480" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2621" class="wp-caption-text">Assistance notice for homeless youth in Charlottenburg</p></div>
<p>Carsten&#8217;s happy ending is a welcome take-away from an otherwise harrowing topic, but he warns against the assumption that all homeless people are unhappy or need to be saved. While many do suffer from mental illness and drug and alcohol abuse, others have deliberately chosen this lifestyle. <em>Some people want to live this way, and we have to respect that. We have to recognize them as part of society.</em></p>
<p><span class="userContent"><span class="text_exposed_show">It&#8217;s easy to dodge corners and cross streets, to switch subway cars to avoid someone&#8217;s stench or words, to grip our phones and look down. </span></span></p>
<p>It&#8217;s not as easy to look up.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>The Querstadtein homeless tours (in German) take place in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Mitte, usually on Sundays and for approximately 2 hours. Tickets cost <span class="st">€</span>9,40, and <span class="st">€</span>5,40 for students, seniors, and individuals on welfare. More information can be found at <em>http://querstadtein.org/de/stadtfuehrungen/.<br />
</em></p>
<p>For more on the Querstadtein tours in English, click <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/zeitgeist/berlin-tour-gives-a-glimpse-of-berlin-as-seen-by-homeless-people-a-913758.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>For more on the increasing restrictions on public space for homeless people across Europe, <a href="http://www.surveillance-and-society.org/articles5%283%29/homelessness.pdf">click here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Multiculturalism, Diversity, and the Big City</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2013 18:48:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kreuzberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1358</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[With my back to them at the street-side café I felt like a judge on "<a href="http://www.nbc.com/the-voice/">The Voice</a>", straining my neck for any hint of where they were from or what they looked like, resisting the urge to swirl around and start dancing on my chair. Truth be told my ears had perked up as soon as the trio plopped down at the table behind me, switching between topics like gentrification in Kreuzberg and the cultural difference between <em>Kaffee</em> and "coffee" as quickly as they were switching between German and English...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/photo-1-2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/photo-1-2.jpg" alt="photo-1 (2)" width="640" height="640" /></a></p>
<p>With my back to them at the street-side café I felt like a judge on &#8220;<a href="http://www.nbc.com/the-voice/">The Voice</a>&#8220;, straining my neck for any hint of where they were from or what they looked like, resisting the urge to swirl around and start dancing on my chair. Truth be told my ears had perked up as soon as the trio plopped down at the table behind me, switching between topics like gentrification in Kreuzberg and the cultural difference between <em>Kaffee</em> and &#8220;coffee&#8221; as quickly as they were switching between German and English.</p>
<p>Voice #1: &#8220;I speak differently when I speak to you, or to Brits, or to other Americans. I’m speaking much slower right now and I explain things differently.&#8221; <em> Aha! A fellow American. Is she a teacher? Is this a language class? </em><em>&#8220;</em>Wait, were you just speaking in English or German?&#8221; <em>Hmm, maybe not a teacher. Did she also grow up with both languages? Is that a slight accent I detect? </em></p>
<p>Voice #2: &#8220;My name, Uyen&#8230; well for us the middle name is actually the main name, the name before that is just to make the name more beautiful. And my last name is unique, a combination of my mother&#8217;s and father&#8217;s names. Even my sisters don&#8217;t have it because the province where I was born doesn&#8217;t have the same rules like they do here.&#8221; &#8216;<em>Uyen&#8217;&#8230; is that Vietnamese? Germany has <a href="http://www.germany.info/Vertretung/usa/en/05__Legal/02__Directory__Services/04__Family__Matters/__Name.html">laws</a> about children&#8217;s names.. maybe she was born in Vietnam and then her family moved to Germany and her sisters were born here?</em></p>
<p>Voice #3: &#8220;In another language it&#8217;s always different, the, the&#8230; how do you say <em>Betonung auf Englisch</em>?&#8221; <em>The others are struggling to find the translation, should I interject&#8230;? No that&#8217;d be rude, though maybe they&#8217;d appreciate the&#8230;</em></p>
<p>SLAM! Down went my button and I whirled around.</p>
<p>&#8220;Emphasis!&#8221; I yelped, nearly toppling over on the cobblestones. &#8220;Sorry&#8230; for, uh, listening in on your conversation,&#8221; I continued a bit sheepishly, trying to redeem myself, &#8220;It was just really interesting!&#8221;</p>
<p>Lucky for me they were not only open to the vocabulary assistance but also for a chat with the lady who&#8217;d been shamelessly eavesdropping on them (and typing up parts of their conversation, they&#8217;d later learn).  Ten minutes later it was clear that while my sleuthing wasn&#8217;t entirely off the mark, it wasn&#8217;t the whole picture either. Voice #1 belonged to Lea: originally born in Serbia but living in the US for most of her life, currently pursuing a Master&#8217;s degree in Social Work in Boston, but had spent a few years of her upbringing in Germany. Her German, just like mine, was fluent and <em>almost</em> accent free but peppered by the occasional grammar mistake or forgotten vocabulary word. Voice #2 was Uyen: Vietnamese-German (or <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">German-Vietnamese</a>) as I suspected. Born in Vietnam, grew up in Berlin, also currently studying. And Voice #3 was Nicole&#8217;s: A German also working toward her degree in Social Work. The three were in a class together but it wasn&#8217;t a language one. Instead they were enrolled in an international summer course called &#8220;Diversity in the Big City&#8221;. A course focused on diversity in urban environments for those working in social professions and partly financed by the Federal Foreign Office in cooperation with the DAAD, Germany&#8217;s Academic Exchange Service. The course examines diversity through four lenses: social participation, social structure and urban development, migration and integration, and education.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-22-16-28-54.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-22-16-28-54.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-08-22 16.28.54" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>This is one of those moments I wish Chancellor Angela Merkel had been around to see. Not that I think about Merkel all that often or necessarily consider her a fun café partner, but it would&#8217;ve been satisfying to show the politician who proclaimed that &#8220;<a href="http://www.thenewamerican.com/world-news/europe/item/8685-sarkozy-joins-cameron-merkel-condemns-multiculturalism">multiculturalism has utterly failed</a>&#8221; this positive example of multiculturalism in the everyday.</p>
<p>And there we go again with one of our favorite words, &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221;. If we were so inclined, we could spend this whole damn blog analyzing that term. We wouldn&#8217;t mind so much actually &#8211; Kelly can&#8217;t even use the term &#8220;culture&#8221; without first defining it and I could happily talk your ears off about the relationship between cultural capital and educational achievement. Thankfully we&#8217;re savvy enough to realize it wouldn&#8217;t make things very fun for all of you. <em>Or would it?</em> No, of course it wouldn&#8217;t. Moving on. But write us if it might.</p>
<p>To be fair, it&#8217;s pretty near impossible to create a definitive understanding of &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221;.  The word&#8217;s become increasingly loaded as countries face burgeoning levels of immigration and struggle to incorporate diverse populations within their borders. In turn it&#8217;s dissected by academics, used strategically to shape policy, and tossed around in the everyday. It&#8217;s elusive and as some like to call it, a &#8220;moving target&#8221;. Kelly hit the nail on the head in one of <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/10/whose-multikulti-is-it-the-elusive-definition-of-multiculturalism/">her posts</a> and then bolded that nail so you&#8217;d pay attention: &#8220;The various meanings of <em>Multikulti</em> are just as ‘multi’ as the differences the word aims to describe&#8221;<strong>.</strong></p>
<p>I think we can start by agreeing that there is a stark difference between <em>saying</em> you&#8217;re something and actually <em>doing</em> something. Sociology Professor and Harvard PhD Irene Bloemraad has packaged this difference into a neat little theory called &#8220;symbolic&#8221; vs. &#8220;material&#8221; multiculturalism. In other words, talking the talk vs. walking the walk.</p>
<p>The United States, for example, is all about <em>symbolic multiculturalism</em>. Whichever food related metaphor you prefer &#8211; &#8220;melting pot&#8221;, &#8220;salad bowl&#8221;, or &#8220;ethnic stew&#8221; (yup, people say that) &#8211; the country&#8217;s national identity is forever tied to immigration and diversity. Yet as Bloemraad rightly points out, the US&#8217;s support of multiculturalism is more social than political: the country <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2NpHwYrIXWY">embraces multiculturalism</a> and individual expression but is not big on providing institutionalized resources toward integration and the political participation of immigrants.</p>
<p><em>Material multiculturalism</em> on the other hand is the government stepping in and addressing immigrant integration in an institutionalized way. Merkel&#8217;s certainly right that Germany is far from being a beacon of multiculturalism, but let&#8217;s not ignore the positive &#8220;material&#8221; work the country has recently embarked on: <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">integration courses</a>, new citizenship laws, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/18/rave-education-per-square-kilometer/">educational initiatives</a>, etc. Lea, Uyen, and Nicole&#8217;s &#8220;Diversity in the Big City&#8221; course is another example of how a small effort can promote multiculturalism both symbolically and materially: creating a space for international students to study diversity is a symbolic acknowledgement that those working in social spheres should gain this perspective. Funding these courses through the government is a material backing of this acknowledgement.</p>
<p>Much work still needs to be done, and I&#8217;m the first to acknowledge that four highly educated women chatting diversity over cappuccinos is a far cry from the challenges many other groups face in regards to integration. But whatever &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221; is, may, or should be, it hasn&#8217;t failed. It&#8217;s a symbolic and material work in progress. <em>Our</em> work in progress.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The adorable café pictured above is called</em> <a href="http://www.schoenescafe.de/">schönes café</a> <em>and is located in Kreuzberg&#8217;s Graefekiez. For more information on the &#8220;Diversity in the Big City&#8221; course and others run by DAAD, click <a href="https://www.daad.de/deutschland/studienangebote/sommerkurse/en/?ipp=50&amp;seite=1&amp;sk_akademie=0&amp;skchapter=0&amp;skduration=0&amp;skenter=&amp;skid=841&amp;sksubject=12&amp;skterm=&amp;sktown=&amp;stipendiate=0">here</a>. </em></p>
<p>Non-professional photos by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rave: Education Per Square (Kilo)Meter</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/18/rave-education-per-square-kilometer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2013 08:26:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moabit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=787</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[After all this talk about <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/">Nazis</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/">N-Words</a>, and <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/29/prejudice-with-condiments-understanding-schwabenhass/">negative stereotypes</a>, I think it's time we had some good news around here, don't you? <p style="text-align:left;">Enter <em>Ein Quadratkilometer Bildung</em>, or "Square Kilometer Education".</p>
<p style="text-align:left;"><em>Quadratkilometer Bildung</em> (QKB) is an educational development and learning platform that addresses education on a regional basis, with a focus on disadvantaged populations. They call it "closing gaps". I call it common sense...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/galerie1_1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-788" style="margin: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/galerie1_1.jpg" alt="Galerie1_1" width="642" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/galerie1_1.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/galerie1_1-300x199.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/galerie1_1-650x432.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 642px) 100vw, 642px" /></a></p>
<p>After all this talk about <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/">Nazis</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/">N-Words</a>, and <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/29/prejudice-with-condiments-understanding-schwabenhass/">negative stereotypes</a>, I think it&#8217;s time we had some good news around here, don&#8217;t you?</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Enter <em>Ein Quadratkilometer Bildung</em>, or &#8220;Square Kilometer Education&#8221;.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.eu/"><em>Quadratkilometer Bildung</em></a> (QKB) is an educational development and learning platform that addresses education on a regional basis, with a focus on disadvantaged populations. QKB programs bridge schools with other regional institutions relevant to the lives of youth: we&#8217;re talking everything from youth service and day care centers to local authorities and city government. Programs also focus on <a href="http://oecdeducationtoday.blogspot.de/2013/05/evolving-attitudes-towards-early.html">early childhood education</a> and getting parents and community members involved early on. Education is thus attacked from multiple angles and a wider lens, becoming more collaborative, holistic, and effective. They call it &#8220;closing gaps&#8221;. I call it common sense.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/galerie5_1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/galerie5_1.jpg?w=300" alt="Galerie5_1" width="652" height="434" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Like most countries, Germany&#8217;s education system has its strengths and its weaknesses. The strongly adhered to tracking system employed by most German states means that students graduate with recognized qualifications and are better prepared for jobs, but are also separated early (usually in 4th grade) and only interact with students of their &#8220;level&#8221;. The recent focus on <a href="http://www.unesco.de/5588.html?L=1">inclusive education</a> has increased interest in <em>Gesamt</em>&#8211; or <em>Gemeinschaftsschulen</em> (comprehensive schools for all students), yet Germany&#8217;s federal system gives states control over their respective education systems. Read: it&#8217;s up to the individual states and may never happen. As long as tracking persists, and socioeconomic status remains <a href="http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00148-006-0102-y#page-1">the major determinant</a> for which track a child is funneled into, students with <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">migration backgrounds</a> will remain at a disadvantage.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Not surprisingly, QKB is run in two areas of Berlin plagued by low socioeconomic status and high numbers of residents with migration backgrounds: <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/">Neukölln</a> and Moabit. The Neukölln QKB program focuses on experiential learning workshops, early math skills, and talent development. In Moabit, programs emphasize <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/01/happy-weekend-a-roma-reimage/">Roma</a> school mentors and learning therapy for students with disabilities. Both programs pinpoint the need for early childhood language acquisition and increased parental involvement.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/tools11-e1374079477814.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/tools11-e1374079477814.jpg?w=300" alt="Tools1" width="637" height="471" /></a><strong>Unsere Traum Schule/Our Dream School (my favorite response: &#8220;a small petting zoo with small animals because the big ones&#8230;&#8221;)</strong></p>
<p>A few weeks ago, Kelly and I attended QKB&#8217;s second annual Film Night where the organization shared mini-clips of their programs and opened the floor for discussion. Together with the rest of the audience, we giggled through scenes of preschoolers scrunching their faces while trying to balance a scale, cringed at kids fitting themselves into drawers and shoving one another under cupboards, and came close to tears at emotional testimonials from mentors and parents.</p>
<p>The German term for education<em>, Bildung</em>, is more complex and comprehensive than its English counterpart. <em>Sich bilden</em> means &#8220;to form&#8221; or &#8220;to give rise to&#8221;. We&#8217;ve already agreed it takes a village to raise a child. How long before we realize that means the whole village?</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By</em><strong><em> Sophia Burton</em> </strong></p>
<p><em>In September 2013, QKB is opening a <a href="http://campusbildungimquadrat.eu/temporaeregalerie/">temporary gallery</a> at Berlin&#8217;s infamous </em><a href="http://tonymacaroni.wordpress.com/2012/08/24/campus-rutli-cr%C2%B2/">Campus Rütli – CR²</a> <em>school. The exhibit will serve as a communications platform connecting educational institutions with artists and the community. More information about the success of QKB programs by region (in German) can be found <a href="http://www.google.de/imgres?um=1&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sa=N&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;hl=de&amp;biw=1564&amp;bih=872&amp;tbm=isch&amp;tbnid=uqxsaX3evs8U1M:&amp;imgrefurl=http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.org/impressum/&amp;docid=4p0JNgWBJqHJiM&amp;imgurl=http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.org/wp-content/themes/km2/background/hintergrund3.jpg&amp;w=1024&amp;h=768&amp;ei=MormUafvG6nx4QSE9oHoBQ&amp;zoom=1&amp;iact=hc&amp;vpx=497&amp;vpy=219&amp;dur=1489&amp;hovh=194&amp;hovw=259&amp;tx=148&amp;ty=93&amp;page=1&amp;tbnh=141&amp;tbnw=188&amp;start=0&amp;ndsp=40&amp;ved=1t:429,r:3,s:0,i:91">here</a>. Information on QKB in English can be found <a href="http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.eu/">here</a> (click &#8220;km2 Education in English&#8221;).<br />
</em></p>
<p>First and second photo <a href="http://www.google.de/imgres?um=1&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sa=N&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;hl=de&amp;biw=1521&amp;bih=899&amp;tbm=isch&amp;tbnid=T1N-winrd21uFM:&amp;imgrefurl=http://www.land-der-ideen.de/presse/meldungen/ein-quadratkilometer-bildung&amp;docid=uokQqHVMjOJSjM&amp;imgurl=http://www.land-der-ideen.de/sites/default/files/styles/galleryformatter_slide/public/gallery/Galerie1_1.jpg&amp;w=800&amp;h=532&amp;ei=OM7mUcvDNIq1tAaR44CACw&amp;zoom=1&amp;iact=rc&amp;dur=360&amp;page=1&amp;tbnh=137&amp;tbnw=185&amp;start=0&amp;ndsp=39&amp;ved=1t:429,r:25,s:0,i:163&amp;tx=171&amp;ty=51">source</a>; Third photo <a href="http://www.google.de/imgres?um=1&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sa=N&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;hl=de&amp;biw=1521&amp;bih=899&amp;tbm=isch&amp;tbnid=bmcFUeai-R91iM:&amp;imgrefurl=http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.org/tools/&amp;docid=zkAFP8FKT9dE4M&amp;imgurl=http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/06/Tools1.jpg&amp;w=1500&amp;h=1125&amp;ei=VNHmUYjEFNDEtAaY1oDgDg&amp;zoom=1&amp;iact=rc&amp;dur=285&amp;page=1&amp;tbnh=158&amp;tbnw=209&amp;start=0&amp;ndsp=39&amp;ved=1t:429,r:31,s:0,i:181&amp;tx=116&amp;ty=109">source</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Become a German (in just under 650 hours)</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2013 08:48:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=823</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[You must clean up after your dog. You must ride your bike in the right direction of the bike lane, </em>recites a Russian student. <strong>The audience chuckles.</strong> <em>First work, then... </em>chants the teacher. <strong>The audience groans.</strong> <em>Do you know any examples of German humor?</em> asks the teacher. <em>Uhhh, </em>fumbles the Japanese student. 10 seconds go by. <em>I'm still thinking, </em>he mutters and scratches his head. <strong>The audience roars...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/12_jorge_prados_beratungstermin_04.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/12_jorge_prados_beratungstermin_04.jpg" alt=" BERATUNGSTERMIN (BEI DER INDUSTRIE-UND HANDELSKAMMER)" width="640" height="360" /></a>No, not you, unless you&#8217;re interested. If so, then it&#8217;s time to sharpen your pencils, place them neatly in one of Germany&#8217;s ubiquitous pencil cases, and get ready to go back to school.</p>
<p>Let&#8217;s rewind a bit: <strong>For a long time, Germany refused to acknowledge itself as a &#8220;land of immigration&#8221;.</strong> The bulk of recent immigration came from post-World War II guest worker programs which were initially meant to be temporary, but many migrants stuck around. Their children and children&#8217;s children &#8211; the second and third generations &#8211; were born in Germany but continued to face challenges in regards to integration. They struggled socioeconomically and educationally, lacked German language proficiency, and often lived in parallel societies. In addition, Germany&#8217;s population was aging and fertility rates were declining.</p>
<p>So at the turn of the 21st century, Germany also made a sharp turn where immigration policy was concerned. Integrating &#8220;non-ethnic&#8221; immigrants and their children (and recruiting highly-skilled immigrants) became a priority. A <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">birthplace citizenship provision</a> was introduced, a national integration plan created, and a &#8220;Federal Commissioner for Migration, Refugees, and Integration&#8221; established. Language became the focal point of integration efforts:<strong> the majority of third country nationals (those from outside of the EU ) are now required to take over 600 hours of state-funded integration courses.</strong></p>
<p>Which brings us back to &#8220;Become a German&#8221; or <em>Werden Sie Deutscher</em>, a new documentary that follows an integration course in Berlin over the course of 10 months. We watch as the class &#8211; whose &#8220;stars&#8221; come from countries like Uruguay, Bangladesh, Bulgaria, and Turkey &#8211; wades its way through simulated spats with neighbors and gay marriage debates in the classroom to real-life job search trials and mundane subway rides.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/start1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-833 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/start1.jpg" alt="start1" width="682" height="381" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/start1-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/start1-310x174.jpg 310w" sizes="(max-width: 682px) 100vw, 682px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Cultural Orientation &#8211; Rules and Behaviors. &#8220;Time is money&#8221;&#8230;&#8221;First work, then play&#8221;.</strong></p>
<p>As with any documentary, scenes are cut and pasted together to elicit the most laughs and cringe-worthy moments. Since this is Germany, at least half of the movie zooms in on bureaucracy and rules. <em>You must never</em> <em>throw out an important piece of paper</em>. <em>You must clean up after your dog. You must ride your bike in the right direction of the bike lane, </em>recites a Russian student. <strong>The audience chuckles.</strong> <em>First work, then&#8230; </em>chants the teacher. <strong>The audience groans.</strong> <em>Do you know any examples of German humor?</em> asks the teacher. <em>Uhhh, </em>fumbles the Japanese student. 10 seconds go by. <em>I&#8217;m still thinking, </em>he mutters and scratches his head. <strong>The audience roars.</strong> <em>Please wait outside,</em> instructs a bureaucrat to a family standing outside Berlin&#8217;s <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/24/lens-becoming-foreign-at-the-auslanderbehorde/">foreign resident center</a> in the middle of winter. <strong>The audience gasps. </strong></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/image-475099-galleryv9-svlk.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-835 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/image-475099-galleryv9-svlk.jpg" alt="Film / Werden sie Deutscher" width="640" height="359" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/image-475099-galleryv9-svlk.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/image-475099-galleryv9-svlk-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/image-475099-galleryv9-svlk-650x364.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/image-475099-galleryv9-svlk-310x174.jpg 310w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>The bureaucracy focus is exaggerated, considering that only 45 of the 645 required course hours are delegated to &#8220;orientation&#8221;. Yet, despite how <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/22/lens-becoming-berlinerin-at-the-burgeramt/">ridiculous </a>or boring German bureaucracy may seem, it&#8217;s a necessary system to understand and be able to navigate when living here. Just like regular school, these courses are not all about grades and memorization. They&#8217;re about life skills.</p>
<p>Though far from perfect, these courses are also a commendable effort in giving the newly arrived a fighting chance. The United States proudly waves its &#8220;multiculturalism loving melting pot of immigration&#8221; banner far and wide, but where is its federal office of immigrant integration and state-funded language courses? The adult immigrants I volunteered with in the US came to English class every day after work of entirely their own volition and out of their own pockets.</p>
<p>This film poses a host of larger questions about integration governance: What responsibility do countries have in welcoming newcomers and preparing them for their new society? What should (or shouldn&#8217;t) integration courses be teaching besides language? What does it really mean to be &#8220;integrated&#8221;? It also ignores some important questions: How do courses handle students with varying levels of education and literacy in their native tongues?  <strong>How are regular schools and the media addressing migration to promote intercultural understanding on the side of &#8220;natives&#8221;?</strong> How must German society continue to evolve to truly meet their new-found claim as a &#8220;land of immigration&#8221;?</p>
<p>Integration is, after all, a two-way street. Let&#8217;s just hope we&#8217;re all riding in the right direction.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By</em><strong><em> Sophia Burton</em></strong></p>
<p>&#8220;Werden Sie Deutscher&#8221; is currently <a href="http://www.werdensiedeutscher.de/kinotermine/">playing</a> in select cities around Germany.</p>
<p>Photo sources:<a href="http://www.spiegel.de/kultur/kino/kinodokus-werden-sie-deutscher-und-beerland-starten-a-886037.html"> Spiegel </a>and <a href="http://www.werdensiedeutscher.de/">Werden Sie Deutscher</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
