<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Multikulti &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/multikulti/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Interview: Hamid, Stardom, and the Difference Threshold</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/30/interview-hamid-stardom-and-the-difference-threshold/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/30/interview-hamid-stardom-and-the-difference-threshold/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2013 20:02:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Charlottenburg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Iran]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1346</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It's November of last year and Kelly and I are visiting relatives of mine in Soest, a small town of under 50,000 in Northwestern Germany. We're hanging out in the kitchen, chatting over a cup of coffee, when one of my cousin's friends walks in. He pauses with one arm holding open the door, staring at us like a deer in headlights. Before we have the chance to say <em>Hallo</em> he's turned and raced up the stairs to my cousin's room. <em>Teenage boys</em>, we initially chuckled...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/hamdchristmas.jpg"><img loading="lazy" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/hamdchristmas.jpg?w=640" alt="hamdchristmas" width="640" height="480" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Christmas Greetings from Hamid!</p></div>
<p>It&#8217;s November of last year and Kelly and I are visiting relatives of mine in Soest, a small town of under 50,000 in Northwestern Germany. We&#8217;re hanging out in the kitchen, chatting over a cup of coffee, when one of my cousin&#8217;s friends walks in. He pauses with one arm holding open the door, staring at us like a deer in headlights. Before we have the chance to say <em>Hallo</em> he&#8217;s turned and raced up the stairs to my cousin&#8217;s room. <em>Teenage boys</em>, we initially chuckled, thinking perhaps he had been surprised to find two random ladies in his friend&#8217;s kitchen. A couple hours later Kelly comes to the more probable conclusion: he was surprised to find two random <em>foreigners speaking English</em> in his friend&#8217;s kitchen.</p>
<p>Of course this kid had encountered English before, but most likely in the classroom, in books, on TV, and maybe even on a trip abroad. In the space of his friend&#8217;s home, we were completely out-of-context and foreign. It wasn&#8217;t the shock of his life, but it was a little more &#8220;difference&#8221; than he was used to.</p>
<div id="attachment_1824" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/soest2.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1824" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-1824 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/soest2.jpg?w=640" alt="soest2" width="640" height="640" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/soest2.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/soest2-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1824" class="wp-caption-text">The English Speaking Foreigners in Soest, November 2012</p></div>
<p>For those of us who live in diverse and international metropolises like Berlin, our &#8220;difference&#8221; thresholds tend to be higher.  We encounter &#8220;different&#8221; and &#8220;foreign&#8221; most days and in many forms: people, foods, music, smells, attire, houses of worship, celebrations, even neighborhoods. A few words in a foreign language doesn&#8217;t usually startle us, but that doesn&#8217;t mean we don&#8217;t have difference thresholds of our own.</p>
<p>My &#8220;foreign language in the kitchen&#8221; equivalent was a hair salon in Charlottenburg.</p>
<p>For months I drove by Salon Hamid Nosrati on the bus or my bike en route to the office, straining my neck to observe a man prance around to blaring music as he chopped and trimmed, or sprawled out on a lounge chair outside the shop, praying to the sun gods (this is Burton family speak and means tanning, not actual praying), all while wearing bejeweled short shorts and crop tops. Hamid was eccentric, theatrical, and deliciously fun to watch. But his &#8220;difference&#8221; factor was a tick or two higher than I was used to &#8211; plus my hair was at stake &#8211; so I resigned myself to a spectator role and continued making appointments at my run-of-the-mill, cappuccino-serving, music-free salon instead.</p>
<p>It took about half a year, a few internal pep talks, and some online review reading before I finally summoned up the courage to make my first appointment. As soon as I walked in, Hamid greeted me with a broad smile, cheek kisses, and the familiar <em>du.</em> I was waved over to the ornate red couch to wait my turn and quickly gave up on the magazines to take in the sensory overload that would leave my head spinning and my foot tapping: Persian music blaring from the speakers, Brandy music videos from my middle school days playing on silent, gaudy statues of cherubs, seductive posters of Hamid, and of course the real deal right in front of me: adeptly shaving a teenage boy&#8217;s head while vigorously shaking his hips to the beat.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3415 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/2013-08-09-16-13-091-650x650.jpg" alt="2013-08-09-16-13-09" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/2013-08-09-16-13-091.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/2013-08-09-16-13-091-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p><em>My passion is dance,</em> Hamid shares the obvious with me later while confidently snipping away at my bangs. <em>And hair styling of course, too,</em> he adds, chuckling, <em>dancing and hair styling,</em> <em>just like my mother. </em>He does a little spin and grabs the hairspray. I ask him if he grew up in Germany. He tells me his family immigrated to Berlin from Iran many years ago, he spent four years in Palma de Mallorca at some point, went to cosmetology school in Berlin, but doesn&#8217;t want to discuss exact dates. He also makes it very clear he won&#8217;t discuss politics.</p>
<p>&#8220;How do you identify yourself? As Persian, German, both?&#8221; I ask, trying to focus on his story.</p>
<p><em>When people ask I say Iran is my home&#8230; I&#8217;m from there, I am Persian. But Berlin is my home, too.</em> <em>I love Germany, it&#8217;s a nice, rich country. And I love Berlin, it&#8217;s a pulsating, vibrant city&#8230; very </em>Multikulti<em>. I&#8217;ve seen it change a lot over the years&#8230; I was here before and after the Wall. I used to get a visa to go to the east on the weekends.  </em></p>
<p>&#8220;What does <em><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/10/whose-multikulti-is-it-the-elusive-definition-of-multiculturalism/">Multikulti</a></em> mean for you?&#8221;</p>
<p><em>Different people from different countries and cultures, living together</em>, he replies simply, looking outside, swooping his arms, potentially demonstrating the space in which they do that.</p>
<p>&#8220;Does your salon tend to be <em>Multikulti</em>? In terms of your clients and employees?&#8221; I ask, thinking about his assistant who asked me if I was Turkish while he blow-dried my hair, then leaned in and giggled, adding <em>because Germans don&#8217;t have this much hair.</em></p>
<p><em>Yes, many of my clients and employees have a </em><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">Migrationshintergrund</a><em>, but everyone is welcome here</em>, Hamid emphasizes. His sister works part-time in the salon and his main assistant, Ali, is Turkish-Yugoslavian. Another Persian woman who didn&#8217;t speak any German was a newer employee.  <em>All the Persians in Berlin know me, </em>Hamid acknowledges.<em> But my clientele is very mixed. </em></p>
<div style="width: 399px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/hamidandkader.jpg"><img loading="lazy" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/hamidandkader.jpg" alt="hamidandkader" width="389" height="583" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Hamid with Kader Loth</p></div>
<p>Hamid brands himself as a &#8220;Star Friseur&#8221; (Star Hairstylist), in a sense bridging his dancing and hair styling passions. His clients range from kids from the neighborhood to Kader Loth, a famous Turkish-German photography model. Taped to his front window is a photo of him with Berlin&#8217;s mayor, Klaus Wowereit. Yet when asked what &#8220;Star Friseur&#8221; means to him, Hamid was more concentrated on the process than the person: <em>We&#8217;re all stars. It&#8217;s about wanting to feel like one more than actually being one. </em>Again he emphasizes: <em>Everyone is equal to us here</em>.</p>
<p>Hamid’s philosophy on integration is strikingly similar to his philosophy on hair: <em>Integration is personal, it comes from the individual and from inside. You have to make yourself welcome, not just expect others to do it for you.<br />
</em></p>
<p>&#8220;But how does one do that?&#8221;</p>
<p><em>You have to be yourself and be proud of who you are. I am who I am: I have my passions and live my life the way I want. I love everyone else even if they don’t love me back. </em>(I think of all the strange looks I&#8217;ve seen Hamid elicit from old ladies on the bus)<em>. Some people hate the Germans, but I just tell them the best way to overcome that is to just love them back anyway. They get confused by that,</em> he laughs.</p>
<p>By the end of our chat Hamid has taken my number and invited me to go dancing with him sometime. Keeping up with him won&#8217;t be easy, but it shouldn&#8217;t matter much. After all, we&#8217;re all stars to Hamid.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>Salon Hamid Nosrati is on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/SalonHamidNosrati">Facebook</a> and located at <a href="http://bing.com/maps/default.aspx?v=2&amp;pc=FACEBK&amp;mid=8100&amp;where1=Kantstra%C3%9Fe+69%2C+10627++Berlin%2C+Germany&amp;FORM=FBKPL0&amp;name=Salon+Hamid+Nosrati&amp;mkt=en-US" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">Kantstraße 69, 10627 Berlin, Germany.</a></p>
<p>All photos not sourced are either mine or from Salon Hamid&#8217;s Facebook page.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/30/interview-hamid-stardom-and-the-difference-threshold/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: the Istanbul Connection</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/29/beyond-berlin-the-istanbul-connection/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2013 18:14:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastarbeiter-guestworker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Istanbul]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1643</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Istanbul gives Berlin its baseline. In kind, Berlin is richly integrated into the complexity of Istanbul. For no relationship is ever purely one-sided. And so a Berlin : Istanbul connection, which moves beyond <i>Gastarbeiter</i> music and Fatih Akin films, is what one can find after six days immersed in the shapes and silhouettes of this city of 13 million...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Istanbul gives Berlin its baseline. In kind, Berlin is richly integrated into the complexity of Istanbul. For no relationship is ever purely one-sided. And so a Berlin : Istanbul connection, which moves beyond <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/oct/25/music-germany-migrant-workers-compilation"><em>Gastarbeiter </em>music</a> and <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0015359/">Fatih Akin films</a>, is what one can find after six days immersed in the shapes and silhouettes of this city of 13 million.</p>
<div id="attachment_1654" style="width: 630px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/photogram-20131024120809.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1654" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1654" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/photogram-20131024120809.jpg" alt="Photogram-20131024120809" width="620" height="620" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/photogram-20131024120809.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/photogram-20131024120809-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1654" class="wp-caption-text">Europe meets Asia</p></div>
<p>The <a href="http://www.dw.de/turkish-guest-workers-transformed-german-society/a-15489210">guest-worker program between Turkey and Germany</a> is often cited as the beginning of a long-standing socio-cultural and economic relationship, though such ties <a href="http://www.slowtravelberlin.com/a-short-history-of-turkish-berlin/">got their start long before</a> the post-war boom period of the 1960s. The &#8216;Turkish factor&#8217;, regardless of how it came to be, makes Berlin, and Germany for that matter, the place we know. Without it, students would miss their late night meaty snack in the likes of Döner, the skyline would miss many of its stunning minarets, and the census would be sorely missing the strength of difference (just to name a few).</p>
<p>But being Turkish, German-Turkish, or Turkish-German in Berlin are states of being <a title="Over and Over" href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">without a formula</a>. In other words, there is <a href="http://www.slowtravelberlin.com/a-short-history-of-turkish-berlin/">more to the Turkish factor than just culinary contributions</a> and street-side renditions of &#8220;<em>walla</em>&#8221; taking place on German soil. There is, in fact, also a &#8216;German factor&#8217; abroad.</p>
<p>Traveling to Istanbul opens up the possibility for a more two-sided conversation, where the German traveler can encounter home and the foreign at the same time, in a place familiar but distant in its urban position. And that is just what we (me and my German companion, Juri) did just a few weeks ago.</p>
<p><strong>Day 1 in Istanbul: Stammtisch</strong></p>
<p>Upon our arrival into Istanbul&#8217;s (proudly named) Ataturk airport, we were led like lost sheep into the belly of a beast, i.e. Turkey&#8217;s passport control. All around us the air buzzed in German, repeating the ritual of my everyday commute on the metro, this time with the confusion and frustration of a forced queue in a city far away from German-land. A mustached man holding a sign for <em>Studenten der Humboldt Universität</em> (students of Berlin&#8217;s Humboldt University) stood on the other side of the human barrier, shifting his weight methodically. Entering behind us would certainly be this year&#8217;s study trip from <a href="http://www.sowi.hu-berlin.de/studiengaenge/masowi/getma">Humboldt University&#8217;s Turkish German Master&#8217;s program</a> in the social sciences, which sends Berliners to Ankara and Istanbul every year.</p>
<p>As we wandered into one bookshop after another on our first evening, it seemed that not only visiting German students would be speaking the language of <em>Sauerbraten</em> and Goethe<i>.</i> Residents of Istanbul are learning <em>Almanca </em>(German), maybe now more than ever.</p>
<div style="width: 506px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_almanca.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class=" " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_almanca.jpg" alt="Istanbul_Almanca" width="496" height="496" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">advertisements for German language learning in a bookshop</p></div>
<p><strong>Day 2 in Istanbul: Book Swap</strong></p>
<p>Juri and I stumbled upon a German bookstore on an afternoon of gray and drizzle, just off the pedestrian-friendly thoroughfare of <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2013/06/14/world/europe/taksim-scenes.html?_r=0">Taksim</a>. Within seconds of walking through quaint double doors, we could hear &#8211; once again &#8211; the language of my daily commute. A young German woman chatted enthusiastically with her father, a yellow Reclam paperback of some German classic in her hand. Her father peered over his narrow reading glasses, raising his eyes just to hit the inventory at the back of the store &#8211; stacks of imported magazines and newspapers, including the kitschy tabloids older women with orange hair read at the bus stops in Berlin.</p>
<p>I wandered to the western edge of the dimly lit shop, discovering 20 ft. high shelves of children&#8217;s books in German. Perhaps kids in Istanbul will also grow up reading <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pippi_Longstocking"><em>Pippi Langstrumpf.</em></a></p>
<div id="attachment_1644" style="width: 506px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_books.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1644" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-1644" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_books.jpg" alt="Istanbul_books" width="496" height="496" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_books.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_books-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 496px) 100vw, 496px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1644" class="wp-caption-text">German children&#8217;s literature</p></div>
<p><strong>Day 3 in Istanbul: Sharing the Lunch Box</strong></p>
<p>The Germans take their bread seriously, carefully kneading in all kinds of goodies the average American baker might omit out of concern for dental integrity. The so-called Turkish bread one can purchase in Berlin, from <em>Dönerbrot</em> to <em>Milchbrot</em>, has no fit-for-a-squirrel seeds to offer. Enter <em>Vollkornbrot &#8211; </em>your triple whole grain bread &#8211; to be found in your average Istanbul super market. For all the yoga-bending heath nuts in Berlin: this bread is manufactured in Turkey, though ingredients on the package are also translated into German.</p>
<p>And the bread fun doesn&#8217;t stop here. Even the Döner in Istanbul is served in a bun much robuster than Berlin&#8217;s &#8216;Turkish&#8217; prototype.</p>
<div id="attachment_1648" style="width: 506px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_bread.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1648" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-1648" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_bread.jpg" alt="Istanbul_bread" width="496" height="496" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_bread.jpg 620w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_bread-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 496px) 100vw, 496px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1648" class="wp-caption-text">just your everyday super market</p></div>
<p><strong>Day 4 in Istanbul: The Döner Stories</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">The picture of this Döner? No, it wasn&#8217;t taken in Berlin. This dripping lance of assorted protein can be found on the lively streets of Istanbul, where Döner kiosks are visited with as much enthusiasm as in Berlin (so it appeared). There are slight differences in the composition of the sandwich, or shall we say differences in Döner before it became <em>Döner Kebap</em> in Berlin. As the rumor goes, <em>Döner Kebap</em> was invented by a <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/foodanddrink/4295701/The-man-who-invented-the-doner-kebab-has-died.html">Turkish-German named Mahmut</a>, who happened to serve the traditional vertical meat in a triangular cut of flat bread, instead of in more pita-like Istanbul fashion. The reason, as stated in this same rumor: more bread, so that drunken Berliners might stumble home with saucy meats intact.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Thirty some years later in Istanbul, meat on a spit can now be received with french fries and fried veggies in that bread package. Berliner style.</p>
<div style="width: 568px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_dc3b6ner.jpg"><img loading="lazy" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_dc3b6ner.jpg" alt="Istanbul_Döner" width="558" height="558" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">is it lamb? chicken? beef? everything? it&#8217;s Döner.</p></div>
<p><strong>Day 5 in Istanbul: Gimme Some Cake with that Coffee</strong></p>
<p>The German concept of <em>Kaffee und Kuchen</em> (coffee and cake), which inspires the strip of torte-laden cafes in my neighborhood, has made its way to Istanbul in a rich way. Istanbul has its fair share of home-grown sweets, the most delicious ones in fact, involving large amounts of crude honey and nut-laced syrups. Yet, cake with layers of unsweetened cream and a buttery crust, a small apple tart without cinnamon, or a cream-puff styled torte reminds me of my Sunday afternoons devouring Berlin&#8217;s <em>Kuchen</em> culture with friends. And this in the city of the best Baklava I have ever put in my mouth.</p>
<p>In Istanbul&#8217;s trendy harbor-side district, <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/travel/2013/mar/22/istanbul-karakoy-top-10-cafes-shops-galleries">Karaköy</a>, we doused ourselves in familiar sugars at a cafe called <a href="http://www.karabatak.com/">Karabatak</a>. A locale where locals in tweed jackets and horn-rimmed glasses slowly sip syrup-sweetened black coffee from delicate (read tiny) French presses. The influence of the Viennese coffee genius and founder Julius Meinl saturates the deco. Dressed up like a Freudian coffee salon, tiles lining the walls, jazzy serenades rolling into &#8216;intellectual&#8217; conversations, one could also be in Berlin&#8217;s Prenzlauer Berg. The extensive magazine selection: <em>Der Spiegel</em>, <em>Marie Claire Deutschland</em>, <em>Vogue Deutschland</em>, dispersed among the newest copy of T<em>he New Yorker</em> and Turkish design magazines. A cosmopolitan coffee date full of Berlin swag and Turkish youngsters.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_cafe.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_cafe.jpg?w=640" alt="Istanbul_cafe" width="512" height="682" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Day 6 in Istanbul:</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Repeat cosmopolitan coffee date with Berlin swag and Turkish youngsters. For hours and with many forks.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Day 7 in Istanbul: What I Know</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">We boarded our plane in the dark and found ourselves again in German-land, surrounded by the lucid colors of night and the strangely familiar. The smells that had once been part of a Berlin immigrant cityscape were, after the return, now an experience tied to a place, constitutive of a tangible and pungent cross-continental connection. Two worlds connect. In fact, they were never separated.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">We had only heard one side of the conversation.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">&#8211; <em>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em><a href="http://www.dw.de/turkish-guest-workers-transformed-german-society/a-15489210">Approximately 3 million residents or citizens of Germany have Turkish background</a>, meaning either they or their parents were born in Turkey, according to the German system of demographic classification. The Turkish population in Germany intensified with the guest-worker agreement between Turkey and Germany, which allowed for the reunification of families four years following the initial agreement, thereby turning the &#8216;guest-worker&#8217; into an immigrant with, in many cases, children. Today, <a href="http://www.dw.de/turkeys-economic-boom-lures-german-workers/a-16873373">more and more Germans (with or without background) are considering a move to Turkey</a>, learning about Turkey, or learning Turkish, reflecting the true nature of a two-sided relationship. </em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">All photos were taken by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Whose Multikulti is it? The elusive definition of Multiculturalism</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/10/whose-multikulti-is-it-the-elusive-definition-of-multiculturalism/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2013 21:24:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=985</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The various meanings of the German word <em>Multikulti </em>are just as 'multi' as the differences the word aims to describe. Take the <em>Multikulti </em>breakfast, for example. Apparently, a "<em>Multikulti</em> breakfast" is eating Vegemite with maple syrup. Or is it? ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: justify;">If you put the German word <em>Multikulti* (</em>translated as &#8216;multicultural&#8217;, though it means much more) into Google Images, the many different representations, interpretations, and applications of the word appear in the humorous montage only the inter-webs can produce. Children with varying skin tones and hair textures playing together, ethnically diverse adults holding hands on a lawn, differently colored chess pieces dotting a globe, or &#8211; my favorite &#8211; a cartoon depiction of <em>Multikulti</em> individuals against a backdrop of the percentages of <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/"><em>Menschen mit</em> <em>Migrationshintergrund,</em></a> individuals with migration background, in large cities in Germany. A rosy-cheeked Muslim, a brown boy with a German flag, and&#8230;a strange child with a large gold necklace? <strong>The various meanings of <em>Multikulti </em>are just as &#8216;multi&#8217; as the differences the word aims to describe.</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://www.duesseldorf-blog.de/"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://www.duesseldorf-blog.de/wp-content/uploads/2009/01/integration.jpg" alt="" width="397" height="320" /></a></p>
<p><strong>the Public</strong></p>
<p>On the streets of Berlin, in the local paper, in the city&#8217;s stuffy Metro cars the picture isn&#8217;t any clearer. A sign reading &#8220;Multikulti party catering&#8221;  swings from a Senegalese food cart at the Bergmannstraßenfest. Heaps of thickly-sliced fried plantains with Cocktail sauce. &#8220;Multikulti in Schöneberg&#8221; headlines a newspaper article on real estate development. Dark-haired children frolicking on a sidewalk with no blonde-haired children in sight. &#8220;Multikulti shop&#8221; describes a place where one can find &#8216;party hats&#8217; and exotic party favors, as told from an elderly woman on the U-7. &#8220;Multikulti has absolutely failed&#8221; smeared across the room in the Chancellorin&#8217;s <a href="http://www.sueddeutsche.de/politik/integration-seehofer-sieben-punkte-plan-gegen-zuwanderung-1.1012736">speech</a>. Words planted within an integration discourse just learning to deal with real, long-lasting immigration, rather than the comings and goings of guest-workers.</p>
<p>In the airwaves of Berlin the word <em>Multikulti</em> is used as one might use &#8220;diversity&#8221;, even as one might simply say &#8220;different&#8221; or &#8220;differences&#8221;. <strong>It is sometimes used without comment or value-judgment. It is sometimes used to draw  lines in the sand between <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">integration</a> &#8211; read assimilation &#8211; and segregation &#8211; read parallel societies &#8211; as if any process were ever so clear and immediate.</strong> But when is such a word political and when does it <em>just</em> mean &#8216;different&#8217;?</p>
<p>Take the <em>Multikulti </em>breakfast, for example. A &#8220;<em>Multikulti</em> breakfast&#8221; is eating Vegemite with maple syrup, apparently. Simply put: something a little different from somewhere a little further than Cologne, Munich, or even Rostock, could be <em>Multikulti.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.morgengold.de/live/"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://www.morgengold.de/live/digitalAssets/125/125059_illu_multikulti_l.gif" alt="" width="536" height="225" /></a></p>
<p><strong>the Personal</strong></p>
<p>I spoke to a friend with whom I study sociocultural anthropology here in Berlin about what the word <em>Multikulti</em> means to him. He is young, German, gay, well-educated, well-traveled, and &#8216;anthropologically curious&#8217; (i.e. we love to deconstruct words like &#8216;culture&#8217;, making this whole piece quite a challenge in and of itself). He lives in the African Viertel in Wedding (my old stomping grounds) and spends quite a bit of time in <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/">Neukölln</a> &#8211; the district branded with <em>Multikulti </em>as both claim-to-fame and <a href="http://www.stern.de/tv/sterntv/heinz-buschkowsky-multikulti-ist-gescheitert-1906880.html">scandal</a>.</p>
<p><em>Close your eyes and think of </em>Multikulti. <em>Now open them. What do you see</em>? I was hoping that such an exercise would work a little bit like Google Images, assembling a lovely decoupage of different ideas and popular motifs with the speed of a mouse-click. <em>I just think of Multivitaminsaft</em><em>, </em>multivitamin juice<em>.</em> <em>It just sounds like putting together a bunch of different pieces</em>, then branding the whole jar with a catch-all phrase for society&#8217;s use. <em>Do you see </em>Multikulti<em> in Wedding? </em>I ask. Wedding has a high and growing number of non-German residents, in terms of both citizenship and place of birth. <em>No, because it just exists. So, I wouldn&#8217;t call it Multikulti per say. <strong>It isn&#8217;t hyped up yet, like it is in Neukölln.</strong> <strong>Since everyone is moving to Neukölln, it&#8217;s become </strong></em><strong>Multikulti<em>. </em><em>I also just think of <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/18/happy-weekend-karneval-der-kulturen-carnival-of-cultures/">Karneval der Kulturen</a>. </em></strong><em>Packaged things&#8230;</em>Packaged diversity, rather than the real stuff, which doesn&#8217;t need external PR.</p>
<p><em>Multikulti</em>: the catch-all black-box term for dealing with difference. Its meaning depends on whose mouth delivers it, which  spaces enclose it (or don&#8217;t), and in which situation such a word is flung into the public or personal realm. And that is just the tip of the Vegemite-syrup-breakfast sandwich.</p>
<p>Understanding <em>Multikulti </em>is situational, buried in context and everyday life. <strong>It is a filler word, one to be picked up and laid down in places where our language fails at getting at complexities of urban encounters and differences, at challenging and playful <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/welcome-to-collidoscope/">collisions</a>.</strong> Before any more political discussions continue as to whether Berlin as a city will &#8220;fail&#8221; because of its <em>Multikulti</em> character, perhaps we should confirm just exactly what this <em>Multikulti is</em> to us, to voters, to residents, to admirers, to little children appearing in articles for or against a concept they may have never even heard of. This is a concept, <em>Multikulti</em> and multiculturalism, which, as our societies embrace difference as more the norm than the exception, might become irrelevant.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.eltern.de/kleinkind/erziehung/multikulti.html"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://s1.eltern.de/thumbnails/0001/00000000001/02/01/400pxx300px/0201a2c51441606763fa18b32f8ddd0auniqueidkindergarten_multikulti.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="300" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>*</em>Multikulti<em> is a term in the German language to be found not only in Germany, but in Austria and Switzerland, as well. This piece does not attempt to glorify the practice of &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221; politically or socially, nor does it seek to provide an operational definition for all uses of the term. Multiculturalism, including the more socially-flexible and popular term of </em>Multikulti<em> particularly in Berlin, will never mean one thing to all people. Multiculturalism is, however, often a matter of policy, making it concrete and important for the lives of many &#8211; which begs the question as to the efficacy of shaping society on the basis or in opposition to an elusively undefinable phenomenon. As the above picture illustrates, only through communication between these various poles of whatever </em>Multikulti<em> may be, can policies which are good for everyone be implemented and public discourses celebrating difference passed on.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>For a comprehensive review of the policy side of Multiculturalism in both the Americas and the European Union, see the Migration Policy Institute&#8217;s informative <a href="http://www.duesseldorf-blog.de/">report.</a></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Photo sources: images linked to web source</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rave: Neukölln&#8217;s Intercultural Day-to-Day</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2013 14:37:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gentrification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=891</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A Berlin restaurant with an American name run by a Tunisian who prepares Italian fare in Halal style? Anywhere else this collision of cultures on a plate would be considered poor marketing.  In Neukölln it's more or less the norm...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/2013-06-15-15-09-14.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-892 aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/2013-06-15-15-09-14.jpg" alt="2013-06-15 15.09.14" width="640" height="480" /></a>A Berlin restaurant with an American name run by a Tunisian who prepares Italian fare in Halal style? Anywhere else this collision of cultures on a plate would be considered poor marketing.  In Neukölln it&#8217;s more or less the norm.</p>
<p>&#8220;L.A. New York Restaurant&#8221; was the second stop along <em>Erkundung im Paradies, </em>one of numerous tours offered by <a href="http://route44-neukoelln.de/touren/paradies_tour1.html">Route 44</a> that explore Neukölln&#8217;s migration history and interculturalism. The tours are entirely female-run and designed by a group of diverse women who are proud to call Neukölln their &#8220;(second) home&#8221;.</p>
<p>Neukölln is Berlin&#8217;s 8th district and home to 320,000 residents, approximately 40% of which are not ethnically German. Almost 150 nationalities are represented (primarily Turkey, the Arab world, and former Yugoslavia) and the district is at the heart of Berlin&#8217;s gentrification debate, making Neukölln hard to ignore. Nonetheless, it was off my radar for years and continues to be for tourists who either don&#8217;t know it exists or have been warned it&#8217;s too dangerous to visit. My 250 page Berlin guide book from 2003 doesn&#8217;t say one word about Neukölln. Ten years later and it&#8217;s still not mentioned on <a href="http://www.timeout.com/berlin/features/10/berlin-area-guide">this list</a> or <a href="http://www.fodors.com/news/understanding-berlins-neighborhoods-5831.html">this list</a> or <a href="http://www.cityscouter.com/travelguides/berlin/Berlin-Districts.html">this list</a>. It is on <a href="http://berlin.cityseekr.com/cityguide/district-guide-1">this one</a>: &#8220;More down-to-earth are the working-class districts of Wedding in the north and Neukölln in the south, which is sometimes referred to as the Berlin Bronx. Although they both have a reputation of being ghettos for the poor, unemployed and other down-and-outs, they are not as bad as they are made out to be.&#8221; What a ringing endorsement.<em><br />
</em></p>
<p>The Route 44 girls describe Neukölln as a region of &#8220;irritating problems but fascinating potential&#8221;. Unfortunately Neukölln&#8217;s problems go beyond irritating to downright serious: they have one of the city&#8217;s highest unemployment rates (<a href="http://www.berlin.de/ba-neukoelln/derbezirk/arbeitslose.html">17%</a>), high child poverty rates, and a crime rate that is about 40% higher than Berlin&#8217;s average. But it is also home to immense diversity, creativity, and rich cultural history. Reducing Neukölln (or any struggling region) to the &#8220;poor, unemployed and other down-and-outs&#8221; is not only unfair, it&#8217;s unproductive.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/2013-06-15-15-44-50.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/2013-06-15-15-44-50.jpg" alt="2013-06-15 15.44.50" width="640" height="480" /></a><em>Erkundung im Paradies</em> or &#8220;Exploring Paradise&#8221; showcases this &#8220;fascinating potential&#8221; through an exploration of a neighborhood and its various houses of worship, educational institutions, trendy bars, and international restaurants. Yet perhaps the most interesting facet of the tour was not the stops itself, but the open dialogue it generated. The tour participants were largely locals and the intermittent chatter and questions culminated in a discussion on religion and the role of the headscarf. Hiba and Maria, our guides, responded openly and respectfully to questions from the group that ranged from  &#8220;Aren&#8217;t women forced to wear them?&#8221; to &#8220;Why don&#8217;t you wear one?&#8221; Hiba (Lebanese-German) and Maria (Pakistani-German) don&#8217;t wear headscarves and explained that while it&#8217;s a commitment they&#8217;re not ready to make now, they don&#8217;t rule it out for the future. Either way, it&#8217;s their choice alone.</p>
<p>When asked by a  journalist why they do the tours, they responded quite simply: &#8220;Neukölln has a bad reputation, and we want to change that.&#8221;</p>
<p>I&#8217;d say the guidebooks should take note, but I&#8217;m not sure we need them. These women are creating their own and it&#8217;s a lot more interesting.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>For more information on Route 44 tours, click <a href="http://route44-neukoelln.de/touren.html">here</a>. Tours are offered every first and third Saturday of the month and registration is not necessary. Bring something to cover your shoulders during visits to houses of worship. Tours are given in German but the guides offer a variety of other languages that include English, Urdu, Arabic, and Turkish.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>Funkhaus Europa recorded the above-mentioned tour and you can access the article and audio <a href="http://www.radiobremen.de/funkhauseuropa/aktuell/aktuell590.html">here. </a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Happy Weekend: Breakfast with Korea, Supper with Afghanistan</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/14/happy-weekend-breakfast-with-korea-supper-with-afghanistan/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/14/happy-weekend-breakfast-with-korea-supper-with-afghanistan/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2013 14:01:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=800</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Tomorrow is the <a href="http://www.allnationsfestival.de/">All Nations Festival</a>: an open house to many of the city's embassies, consulates, and cultural centers. Get ready for free food, dance performances, calligraphy workshops, language lessons, and interesting tales to this year's theme of "superstition" from the following participating countries: Afghanistan, Ethiopia, Bolivia, China, Guinea-Bissau, Indonesia, Iraq, Yemen, Korea, Malawi, Malaysia, Malta, Nepal, Palestine, South Sudan, Chad, Venezuela (and the Konrad-Adenauer Stiftung). It is no coincidence that many of the countries registered have faced bad press or sweeping generalizations as of late, no coincidence that they are opening their doors and hoping to share something with their neighbors...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>48 Stunden Neukölln may be taking over most calendars this weekend but another event &#8211; one equally worthy of applause  for its focus on cultural engagement with urban space and difference &#8211; is the <a href="http://www.allnationsfestival.de/">All Nations Festival</a>: an open house to many of the city&#8217;s embassies, consulates, and cultural centers.</p>
<p>The theme for this year is &#8220;superstition&#8221;, i.e. the differences between perceptions of what is good or mystical in one culture and bad, scary, even ugly, in another. Think of the practice of shaking hands in one setting, or bowing and refusing a hand in another. Myth and norms surround both exercises of the typical greeting ritual, though we often are not aware of the reasons why such habits exist in the first place, which stories or beliefs surround them. This is one day to find out in action!</p>
<p>An intercultural journey through a <strong>program of free food (eating with hands or seated on the floor is to be expected), dance, martial arts, calligraphy workshops, language sessions, and surprise performances</strong> awaits those ready to hop from site to site with the <a href="http://www.allnationsfestival.de/main/tickets.html">festival&#8217;s passport </a>in hand. These <strong>free passes are available at tourist offices or at participating centers on the day of the event.</strong> For those over-achievers among us, the opening ceremony will be at the <strong>Korean Cultural Center at 11 am</strong>, likely featuring a delicious breakfast as has been the tradition for past festivals (something a bit snazzier than your typical <em>Brötchen</em> smorgasbord, I presume).</p>
<div style="width: 630px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img loading="lazy" src="http://dsfov63mrkqa8.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/05/ANF_2009_Botschaft_von_Sri_Lanka.jpg" alt="ANF_2009_Botschaft_von_Sri_Lanka" width="620" height="465" /><p class="wp-caption-text">Sri Lankan Embassy, 2011</p></div>
<p>A downloadable map of all participating locations can be found <a href="http://www.allnationsfestival.de/down/ANF_2013_karte.pdf">here</a>. This year&#8217;s participating countries are as follows: <strong>Afghanistan, Ethiopia, Bolivia, China, Guinea-Bissau, Indonesia, Iraq, Yemen, Korea, Malawi, Malaysia, Malta, Nepal, Palestine, South Sudan, Chad, Venezuela (and the Konrad-Adenauer Stiftung). </strong>It is no coincidence that many of the countries registered have faced bad press as of late, popular generalizations, or just plain old international misunderstanding. They want to open their doors and share a different lens, open up about what they find scary or good in the world, and do it with their neighbors and co-residents of the city.<strong> </strong></p>
<p>My only question is, where you at United States?! Let it not be forgotten that cultural diplomacy is more powerful than wiretapping one&#8217;s neighbors. At a time when America might just be boiled down to twinkies, Budlight, and the CIA in the media, showing up for an event that supports interculturalism and multiculturalism &#8211; something America is supposed to be &#8220;good&#8221; at &#8211; might not be such a bad idea. But then again, most of the other G-20 countries are no where to be found, so perhaps the message is louder if the room is, well, smaller <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.0.1/72x72/1f642.png" alt="🙂" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></p>
<p><em>-By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>Photo Source: <a href="http://himbeer-magazin.de/veranstaltungen/all-nations-festival/">Himbeer Magazin</a><a href="http://himbeer-magazin.de/veranstaltungen/all-nations-festival/"><br />
</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/14/happy-weekend-breakfast-with-korea-supper-with-afghanistan/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The N-Word</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2013 12:20:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nazi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=658</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When I posted the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/">Who's/Whose Normal?</a> article a few weeks ago, I expected the "N-word" of interest to be<em> Neger</em>, a term that falls somewhere between "negro" and "nigger" on the translation and offensiveness spectrum. Instead, the strongest reactions came in response to another N-Word: Nazi...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;">When I posted the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/">Who&#8217;s/Whose Normal?</a> article a few weeks ago, I expected the &#8220;N-word&#8221; of interest to be<em> Neger</em>, a term that falls somewhere between &#8220;negro&#8221; and &#8220;nigger&#8221; on the translation and offensiveness spectrum. Instead, the strongest reactions came in response to another N-Word: Nazi.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/thenword.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-756" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/thenword.png" alt="thenword" width="546" height="366" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">For those who haven&#8217;t read the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/">original post</a>, the controversy stemmed from a comparison I made between a Berlin storefront poster campaign and Nazi propaganda (on an aesthetic &#8211; not political &#8211; basis). On second thought, I shouldn&#8217;t put that last bit in parentheses, because it&#8217;s the essence of my point. Despite Berlin being <strong>Germany&#8217;s most ethnically and culturally diverse city</strong>, these particular <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/2013-04-11-09-35-05.jpg">storefront posters</a> feature <em>only</em> heterosexual Caucasian families. On an aesthetic basis (skin tone, facial features, body build), they don&#8217;t differ much from the fair blond couples on Nazi posters. A couple brunettes are included here or there, but I don&#8217;t consider that diversity. The bad man himself was a brunette, no? That&#8217;s probably not going to make me any friends either.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">While I am in no way comparing the people from this store to Nazis (I repeat: in no way!), I was disappointed by these posters and the message they send. On multiple posters and within an <a href="http://www.leiser.de/frontend/startseite.htm">entire website</a>, I find it disconcerting to see only one type of ethnicity, sexuality, and idea of beauty. And both creative process scenarios &#8211; whether <em>Leiser</em> consciously made this decision or didn&#8217;t realize that this is what they were doing &#8211; are also disconcerting.</p>
<p>Although many agreed with me that the images were problematic, my Nazi comparison was not as well-received. In the spirit of promoting discourse and &#8220;seeing things from every lens&#8221;, I thought it critical to share a selection of these reactions. Disclaimer: All German comments have been loosely translated by yours truly.</p>
<p><strong>German Commenter 1:</strong> In the U.S., you use the term &#8220;Nazi&#8221; as a joke, e.g. &#8220;You&#8217;re a cleaning Nazi&#8221;, just like we say the term <em>Negerküss</em> [Nigger-kiss]. Neither group considers the history and context of the other. In Germany, we only call really evil and abominable people Nazis, people who seem to be OK with what the Nazis did. It is the worst insult you can give someone. That&#8217;s why it&#8217;s such a hard pill for me to swallow when &#8220;normal&#8221; people (even if they are racist or discriminatory) are compared with Nazis, just like it is hard for Americans when they hear us use the term <em>Neger</em>.</p>
<p><strong>German Commenter 2:</strong> Sophia, you have to be really careful with the use of the term &#8220;Nazi&#8221;. Your comparison [of the storefront posters] to Nazi propaganda goes too far. Germans have a total complex when it comes to our history and you can&#8217;t just make that sort of comparison. As an American, you can&#8217;t understand how hard it is growing up with this history&#8230; You&#8217;re not exactly going to make friends with this sort of comparison.</p>
<p><strong>German/American Commenter in response to above:</strong> Is being critical un-German? Isn&#8217;t that how the Germans got into the Nazi/Holocaust mess to begin with?</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>American Commenter in response to above:</strong> Oh my god! Do these people seriously believe that anti-black racism is the same as calling someone &#8220;a cleaning Nazi&#8221;?? And that you can&#8217;t possibly understand that because you didn&#8217;t grow up there? WTF! I&#8217;m not jumping in because I don&#8217;t want to hijack a thread and you&#8217;re being much more diplomatic than I would be, but dude! What the hell!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-767 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes.jpg" alt="yikes" width="592" height="437" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes-300x221.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 592px) 100vw, 592px" /></a><strong>Me after reading the comments</strong></p>
<p>What these comments have made clear is that context is paramount in the interpretation of language. Perhaps more importantly, however, it has made clear that one shouldn&#8217;t limit themselves to only their immediate context. We can&#8217;t always dissect every word to see if it may offend someone, but we should be more mindful of the political, cultural, and historical contexts of other groups when using potentially hurtful language.</p>
<p>I&#8217;ve often heard that Americans are more PC (politically-correct) than Europeans. Yet, this discussion has shown me that that is not necessarily the case. All nations have sore spots in their histories &#8211; some more recent than others, some that should be sorer than they seem to be &#8211; where we need to tread lightly. We also handle these sensitive topics differently. There&#8217;s still no slavery memorial in Washington, DC, but the German capital is laden with memorials and museums acknowledging their &#8220;black mark on history&#8221;. Americans are known for being the kings (&amp; queens!) of PC language, but the Germans actually came up with a dictionary of Nazi terms to promote awareness of their use.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/350_b22810-2_u1d.gif"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/350_b22810-2_u1d.gif" alt="350_B22810-2_U1D" width="350" height="469" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>&#8220;A &#8216;Coming To Terms With The Past&#8217; Dictionary: The use of Nazi language in public speech&#8221; (</strong><a href="http://www.google.de/imgres?um=1&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sa=N&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;hl=de&amp;biw=1540&amp;bih=844&amp;tbm=isch&amp;tbnid=Ynymf1mQ2JxEDM:&amp;imgrefurl=http://www.wbg-wissenverbindet.de/WBGShop/php/Proxy.php%3Fpurl%3D/wbg/products/show,29637.html&amp;docid=VJO4nm_T0fhTJM&amp;itg=1&amp;imgurl=http://www.wbg-wissenverbindet.de/WBGShop/resources/cover/350_B22810-2_U1D.gif&amp;w=350&amp;h=469&amp;ei=WDWvUYqbB4bTtAapy4C4BA&amp;zoom=1&amp;iact=rc&amp;dur=292&amp;page=1&amp;tbnh=133&amp;tbnw=99&amp;start=0&amp;ndsp=60&amp;ved=1t:429,r:5,s:0,i:99&amp;tx=83&amp;ty=83">Source</a><strong>)</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Yes, the Germans have a word for &#8220;coming to terms with the past&#8221;: <em>Vergangenheitsbewältigung.</em> <em>Vergangenheit</em> simply means &#8220;the past&#8221;, but <em>bewältigen </em>can translate to several verbs, including &#8220;to overcome&#8221;<em>. </em><strong>What does it mean &#8211; as nations and people -to overcome difficult periods in our history?</strong> Does it mean erecting public memorials and monuments? Does it mean holding companies responsible for the images that they portray and promote? Does it mean never using the &#8220;N-word&#8221; or, alternately, being able to use it as a joke? I&#8217;m all ears and mindful speech.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Happy Weekend: Karneval der Kultur(en), Carnival of Culture(s)?</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/18/happy-weekend-karneval-der-kulturen-carnival-of-cultures/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/18/happy-weekend-karneval-der-kulturen-carnival-of-cultures/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2013 12:29:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=617</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What if the local government wanted to take stock of its cultures, parade its diversity through the city streets – what would you wear to participate? This weekend Berlin’s parade of culture, <a href="http://www.karneval-berlin.de/de/"><em>Karneval der Kulturen</em></a>, takes over my Kreuzberg <em>Kiez</em> (neighborhood) once again, promising to leave trails of glitter and plastic cocktail remnants in its wake, as well as much food for thought in answering this question of cultural self-representation...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What if the local government wanted to take stock of its cultures, parade its diversity through the city streets – what would you wear to participate? This weekend Berlin’s parade of culture, <a href="http://www.karneval-berlin.de/de/"><em>Karneval der Kulturen</em></a>, takes over my Kreuzberg <em>Kiez</em> (neighborhood) once again, promising to leave trails of glitter and plastic cocktail remnants in its wake, as well as much food for thought in answering this question of cultural self-representation.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/karnevalderkulturen_woman.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-624 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/karnevalderkulturen_woman.jpg" alt="KarnevalderKulturen_woman" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/karnevalderkulturen_woman.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/karnevalderkulturen_woman-300x199.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/karnevalderkulturen_woman-650x432.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>With residents from nearly 160 different nations or nation-states, Berlin has many cultures to cover. There are more than 4,500 participants in the parade and fair, leaving many of these cultures untouched, I&#8217;m afraid.</p>
<p>At Hallesches Tor, food, drink, and musical merriment will give quite an entertaining glimpse of Berlin&#8217;s official multiculturalism, even if it is just a beginning. Shots of Arak on ice or fried plantains with peanut sauce, ‘authentic’ cuisine from the familiar Polish pierogi to the distant Equadorian empanada, soft serve ice cream and funnel cake served in dishes with the American flag &#8211; there is no shortage of interesting eats.</p>
<p>A collection of stages expose visitors to everything from ‘Mestizo rock’ to Balkan brass with plenty of room to dance (and there will be dancing, if my previous experience has taught my worn-out feet anything); wares from Africa &#8211; region often unspecified &#8211; blend with specialty teas from the Middle East, often advertised as &#8216;tastes from the Orient&#8217;; drum circles abound, as do slack-lining youth and spontaneous picnics. The combinations and divisions from one supposed culture &#8211; one <em>Kulturkreis &#8211;</em> to the next are sometimes interesting, sometimes decidedly humorous.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/karnevalderkulturen_women.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-628 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/karnevalderkulturen_women.jpg" alt="KarnevalderKulturen_women" width="512" height="338" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/karnevalderkulturen_women.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/karnevalderkulturen_women-300x198.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/karnevalderkulturen_women-650x429.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" /></a></p>
<p>The parade is the true highlight, beginning tomorrow at 12:30 at Hermannplatz and continuing on to Yorckstraße. 79 groups, representing a ‘culture’ or ethnic identification within Berlin, are registered to participate. The registration process is important in gaining recognition as a cultural unit within the German system. As a <a href="http://www.taz.de/!66525/">Berlin-based anthropologist</a> described it, wearing a mask at Karneval der Kulturen is a form of willing integration. Implicit in this statement is the critique of the official dressing-up of cultures, the categorization of different ways of life, and the parading of such in vibrant and exoticized forms.</p>
<p>It is no coincidence that Karneval der Kulturen was an initiative of the office for migration and integration in 1993, and no coincidence that some groups are always represented in extravagance, while others remain nearly hidden from view. Putting a city&#8217;s multiculturalism out on display can be an opportunity for inclusion and appreciation of diversity; it can also be an opportunity for classification and typification of <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">identities</a>, ignoring the splendid diversity occurring <i>between categories and across them</i>.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/karnivalderkulturen_parade.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-625 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/karnivalderkulturen_parade.jpg" alt="karnivalderkulturen_parade" width="460" height="307" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/karnivalderkulturen_parade.jpg 460w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/karnivalderkulturen_parade-300x200.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 460px) 100vw, 460px" /></a></p>
<p>At last year’s Karneval der Kulturen, I found myself twirling in the warm air to the sounds of ‘gypsy music’ by a Hungarian band with a group of Germans, Americans, and Iranians. We devoured Hombow and Senegalese fries, giving culinary recommendations to a banker in a suit from Paris.</p>
<p>For all the official critiques of the event and the hope that it will grow with the city in its definitions and portrayals, there has got to be something said for the pleasant intercultural encounter the Karneval affords. Just be sure when photographing the half-naked women in golden headdress to recognize what we might not be seeing: which groups do not dare to participate in the official display, which cultures fear  walking the streets freely, or which have nothing &#8216;exotic&#8217; to represent. Most importantly, it might be interesting to truly ask how one captures a culture in a costume, in a plastic cup, or on a plate&#8230;the jury is still out on that one.</p>
<p>In the mean time, viva Karneval der Kulturen!</p>
<p><em>-By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>Photo source: <a href="http://www.karneval-berlin.de/de/">Karneval der Kulturen e.V.</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/18/happy-weekend-karneval-der-kulturen-carnival-of-cultures/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rant: Who&#8217;s/Whose Normal?</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2013 09:06:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Afrodeutsch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[consumerism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=514</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It's these little images, phrases, and jokes that become so deeply engrained within our mindsets and pervasive within our culture that they are considered "normal". But in a city as diverse as Berlin - where 1 in every 7 inhabitants is non-German, over 138 countries are represented, and the LGBT population is one of Europe's largest - what or who the hell is "normal" anyway? And whose definition are we even using?...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/2013-04-23-09-36-18.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/2013-04-23-09-36-18.jpg" alt="2013-04-23 09.36.18" width="459" height="344" /></a></p>
<p>It&#8217;s the little things that count, right? Unfortunately more than we give them credit for.</p>
<p>The fuel that perpetuates group divisions comes in all shapes and sizes. Prejudice and fear of the other is not innate in us, it is taught. And many of the &#8220;lessons&#8221; we receive are so subliminal and seemingly minor that they are dismissed as not warranting attention, let alone action. That or they go unnoticed altogether.</p>
<p>Like when my German relatives and colleagues jokingly use the term <em>Negerküsse</em> (N***** kisses) to describe marshmallow filled chocolates that went by this name in a former era. While younger Germans have been taught that the word <em>Neger*</em> is highly offensive, the term <em>Negerküsse</em> has persevered and is still considered by many to be cute and funny. What&#8217;s not so cute and funny but happening in the current era?<em> Afrodeutsche</em> children <a href="http://www.bildungswald-welper.de/seminar_negerkuesse.html">being called <em>Negerküsse</em></a> because they have darker skin and feeling ostracized for looking &#8220;different&#8221;.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/negerkuss_collage.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-523 aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/negerkuss_collage.jpg" alt="negerkuss_collage" width="411" height="287" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/negerkuss_collage.jpg 400w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/negerkuss_collage-300x210.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 411px) 100vw, 411px" /></a><strong>&#8220;Negerküsse&#8221; sind wir nicht/We&#8217;re not &#8220;N***** kisses&#8221; (A project for Afro-German youth and their parents)</strong></p>
<p>It&#8217;s these little images, phrases, and jokes that become so deeply engrained within our mindsets and pervasive within our culture that they are considered &#8220;normal&#8221;. But in a city as diverse as Berlin &#8211; where 1 in every 7 inhabitants is non-German, over 138 countries are represented, and the LGBT population is one of Europe&#8217;s largest &#8211; what or who the hell is &#8220;normal&#8221; anyway? And whose definition are we even using?</p>
<p>I&#8217;m not sure which definition the folks at the Leiser shoe store chain are using, but it seems pretty antiquated to me. Their new marketing campaign, <em>Traumpaare</em> (dream pairs), packages pairs of shoes alongside &#8220;dreamy&#8221; couples, all of which are heterosexual and Aryan with &#8211; surprise! &#8211; blond, blue-eyed children.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/2013-04-11-09-35-05.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/2013-04-11-09-35-05.jpg" alt="2013-04-11 09.35.05" width="535" height="402" /></a></p>
<p>For kicks, I gave their <a href="http://www.leiser.de">website</a> a quick look to see if I was missing anything, but only found more of the same. It seems Leiser&#8217;s idea of diversity is a brunette. As far as skin pigment, facial features, and sexual orientation go, these advertisements do not stray very far from Nazi propaganda:</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/aryan-family-neues-volk-1a8ezjw.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-521 aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/aryan-family-neues-volk-1a8ezjw.jpg" alt="aryan-family-neues-volk-1a8ezjw" width="297" height="414" /></a>Now, I&#8217;m not calling anyone at Leiser a Nazi any more than I&#8217;m saying that plastering a Turkish or Thai face on these posters will fix race relations. I&#8217;m sure Leiser wasn&#8217;t trying to be divisive with their poster campaign; in fact, I&#8217;m sure they didn&#8217;t think about it at all. And just like their creative process, the effect of these images will go largely unnoticed because they&#8217;re just storefront posters. They&#8217;re not a man screaming from a podium; they&#8217;re not even a racist comment muttered under someone&#8217;s breath on the subway. But they exist and they perpetuate a societal idea(l) of beauty and belonging that is outdated at best and exclusionary at worst.</p>
<p>In the Berlin I know, &#8220;normal&#8221; is my apartment building filled half with German seniors and half with young families from Spain, Greece, and Poland. It&#8217;s a park full of Vietnamese- and Thai-German families selling <em>pad thai</em> and drinking Beck&#8217;s. It&#8217;s a subway ride at 4am after a friend&#8217;s party, sitting next to a couple Turks and across from a pair of transvestites.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Rather than be discriminatory, let&#8217;s become more discerning and increase our awareness of hurtful language and misrepresentative images. We could all stand to pay more attention to these (not so) little things in life.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>*The term Neger is tricky to translate into English because of the socio-historical differences between Germany and the US that affect language around race. Officially, Neger translates to &#8220;nigger,&#8221; but the term has historically been used much more neutrally in Germany and is sometimes translated to &#8220;negro&#8221;. Today, the term Neger is widely regarded as offensive and campaigns exist to eradicate its use altogether. Accepted German terms for describing darker skinned individuals are &#8220;Afrodeutsch&#8221; (Afro-German) or &#8220;Schwarze(r)&#8221; (black). </em></p>
<p><!-- [if gte mso 9]&gt;--></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Happy Weekend: &#8220;It&#8217;s not about integration&#8221;, or isn&#8217;t it?</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/11/happy-weekend-its-not-about-integration-or-isnt-it/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/11/happy-weekend-its-not-about-integration-or-isnt-it/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2013 10:42:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theater]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=498</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Tonight at <a href="http://www.ballhausnaunynstrasse.de/index.php?id=21&#38;evt=810">Ballhaus Naunynstraße</a>, İmran Ayata und Neco Çelik will present the opening of their newest play, "<em>Liga der Verdammten</em>" (League of the Damned), tackling the dynamic configuration of players and fans in Kreuzberg's very own "<em>Multi-Kulti</em>" football league, <em><a href="http://www.tuerkiyemspor.info/">Türkisempor</a>. </em>Originally formed by Berlin's  marginalized 'guest workers' just 35 years ago, its reputation proceeds it, as do the stereotypes...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Because it is spring, the streets are a bit more bedazzled with color. Be it the bright scoops of Waldmeister ice cream or the gorgeously green chestnut trees that seem to have suddenly appeared, the city is a-blooming. Balls, bikes, and shorts are emerging in kind, which leads quite nicely to this Saturday&#8217;s tip. Surprise, it has nothing to do with good eats but with the stage and, well, the connection between immigration and football (or soccer for the Americans among us).</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/esra_rotthoffballhausnaunynstrasse.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-501 alignnone" style="margin: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/esra_rotthoffballhausnaunynstrasse.jpg" alt="Esra_RotthoffBallhausNaunynstrasse" width="460" height="231" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/esra_rotthoffballhausnaunynstrasse.jpg 460w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/esra_rotthoffballhausnaunynstrasse-300x150.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 460px) 100vw, 460px" /></a></p>
<p>Tonight at <a href="http://www.ballhausnaunynstrasse.de/index.php?id=21&amp;evt=810">Ballhaus Naunynstraße</a>, İmran Ayata und Neco Çelik will present the opening of their newest play, &#8220;<em>Liga der Verdammten</em>&#8221; (League of the Damned), tackling the dynamic configuration of players and fans in Kreuzberg&#8217;s very own &#8220;<em>Multi-Kulti</em>&#8221; football league, <em><a href="http://www.tuerkiyemspor.info/">Türkisempor</a>. </em>Originally formed by Berlin&#8217;s  marginalized &#8216;guest workers&#8217; just 35 years ago, its reputation proceeds it, as do the stereotypes. But &#8220;[it] is not about integration&#8221;, Neco Çelik told <em>die Taz,</em> a daily newspaper,<em> </em>on Thursday. This is the beauty of the play: it is a story about a lifestyle, a community, a sport-culture of roughness and realness in response to societal pressure without intending to play into the trap of &#8216;ethnic&#8217; theater. One could even say that this piece is about the game of making a life after immigration&#8230;or one could say that it is, in fact, JUST about football.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignright" style="margin: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/d567a-566px-257e1.png" alt="" width="204" height="204" />The play premieres tonight, but it runs until 24.05. Each showing begins at 8pm, leaving a few hours between the end of the work day and the stage to kick around a ball, maybe get some green grass on the knees. In springtime, there might be nothing better.</p>
<p>Happy playing or spectating, and of course, happy weekend!</p>
<p><em>-By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em><em><a href="http://www.tuerkiyemspor.info/">Türkisempor</a></em> might be forced to close its doors, cancelling its season and youth programs due to lack of funds. &#8220;Berlin without Türkisempor is like </em>Wurst<em>without curry&#8221; says it&#8217;s campaign; this might be one statement not worth testing for validity. For more information on how to get involved in saving one of Kreuzberg&#8217;s and Berlin&#8217;s great intercultural institutions, visit the campaign <a href="http://www.tuerkiyemspor.info/magazin/artikel.php?artikel=1679&amp;type=2&amp;menuid=128&amp;topmenu=45">site</a> to donate or find out more about the league, its programs in the community, and its plans for the future. </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/11/happy-weekend-its-not-about-integration-or-isnt-it/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
