<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Why Feminism and Hijab Go Together</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/12/04/feminism-hijab-go-together/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2016 09:30:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[feminism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hijab]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4704</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As Muslim refugees who choose to wear hijab become a lasting part of the societies of those European states that have taken them in, their right to be different must be defended. Most importantly, we must defend the right of women to choose. It is this choice that makes women free. This is why feminism and hijab go together.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Donald Trump will soon take over the most (seemingly) powerful office in the United States. In just one month,&nbsp;<em>Vogue</em> will launch&nbsp;its <a href="http://en.vogue.fr/fashion/fashion-news/articles/conde-nast-international-launches-vogue-arabia/43938">first ever Arabia edition</a>. These two events are related &#8211; by hijab.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Only hours after Trump was proclaimed victor by electoral vote, a certain fear took hold in minority populations in the United States. Fear of deportation, of political oppression, of social persecution. This fear has proven itself well-founded. The Southern Poverty Law Center recently reported </span><a href="http://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/hate-on-the-rise-after-trumps-election">a dramatic increase in hate crimes and xenophobic harassment</a>, since Trump’s victory.</p>
<div id="attachment_4711" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4711" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4711 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341-650x433.jpg" alt="reise_usa-2015-bearbeitet-341" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4711" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Given the President-elect’s verbal attacks on Islam and Muslims in (or coming to) America, this fear of emboldened hostility in the general populace is felt <a href="http://people.com/bodies/muslim-women-scared-wear-hijab-trump-win/">ever so acutely</a> by America’s diverse Muslim community. Muslim women, in particular, have expressed a new hesitation to wear hijab in public &#8211; the traditional headscarf &#8211; following the election. As </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">New York Magazine</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> reports, many young Muslima <a href="http://nymag.com/thecut/2016/11/after-trumps-win-muslim-women-are-afraid-to-wear-the-hijab.html">took this fear to twitter</a>. One young woman tweeted her devout mother’s words of caution, &#8220;Please don’t wear your hijab today,&#8221; only to be attacked by right-wing trolls, twitter’s escalating problem in this age of free speech and anti-democratic vitriol. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Whether or not a Trump presidency and its fallout will actually lead to physical harm of Muslim women is not something we can know, right now. But we can juxtapose this fear&nbsp;with hijab as an object of both identity and ridicule&nbsp;&#8211; an object that conservative movements and some European governments have taken outright offense to.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Editor-in-chief of Vogue<em> Arabia</em> is a Saudi princess, a self-professed queen of elegant women in any silhouette. She, </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Deena Aljuhani Abdulaziz, </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">is also a champion of the down-to-earth cat-walk. And she does not (perhaps no surprise here) actually live in the Kingdom</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Although D. Aljuhani Abdulaziz&nbsp;does not herself wear hijab, she supports women who do. According to her interview with </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The New York Times</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, the consumer preferences of Muslim women are <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/11/03/fashion/islamic-fashion-vogue-arabia.html">at the core of this <em>Vogue</em></a>. The magazine’s mission for women in the Muslim world, she explained, is to highlight dress in its femininity, its creativity, and its usage by everyday women across the Arab world, hijab or no hijab. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is not only Arab women living in Doha or Beirut who ascribe to the beauty norms of hijab-wearing models and hijab-based marketing, thus <em>Vogue Arabia</em>’s readership will surely not stay confined to the Arab world. It is published online in both English and Arabic and maintains an international aesthetic (both in branding and in the women who gloss its pages). The princess and Conde Nast seem cognizant of the status of women in hijab: they represent an established style and lifestyle, on a global scale. </span></p>
<div id="attachment_4712" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4712" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4712 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2-650x433.jpg" alt="reise_london-2014-bearbeitet-2" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4712" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This recognition is not limited to Big Money in the Arab world. Women in hijab have begun to take their place among trendsetting brands in countries in which they are decidedly the minority. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Even in Trump’s America, CoverGirl recently <a href="http://firsttoknow.com/meet-the-new-face-of-covergirl-hijab-wearing-beauty-blogger-nura-afia/?utm_source=contentad_backfill&amp;utm_campaign=meet-the-new-face-of-cov-211246&amp;pp=1&amp;utm_medium=180533">added a Muslima in hijab</a> to its blogosphere and promotional sites, a hijab-friendly designer <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-37381770">stole the show at this year’s New York Fashion Week</a>, a U.S. beauty pageant contestant&nbsp;did <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/goatsandsoda/2016/11/29/503729951/the-beauty-pageant-contestant-wore-a-burkini">the whole thing in burkini and hijab</a>, and (if you haven’t heard) Marvel released <a href="http://marvel.wikia.com/wiki/Kamala_Khan_(Earth-616)">its first Muslima superhero</a>. Yes, even superheroes can wear scarves, and <a href="https://mic.com/articles/125199/badass-muslim-superheroes-comics-tv">it doesn&#8217;t stop at Marvel</a>.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><em>Vogue</em> and these other agents of popular culture bring the hijab into a different type of mainstream &#8211; of fashion and femininity. In asserting that &#8220;Yes, this too is a woman,&#8221; a woman’s choice of what to wear is expanded. Bikinis were first <a href="http://content.time.com/time/photogallery/0,29307,1908353_1905442,00.html">popularized and freed from social taboo</a> by aggressive marketing campaigns and photo-shoots. So, why not hijab? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Perhaps the most important point, however, is not whether or not hijab can be normalized; it is whether or not such mainstreaming actually leads to more freedom. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the case of Muslima in increasingly hostile environments, such as the United States or any European state as of late, this freedom is being put to the test. Hijab or body-covering of any sort is increasingly becoming a marker of difference. With the rise of the populist Right, our societies are becoming more and more opposed to such difference. And the power of the masses has, historically, had something to say about women’s dress, women’s bodies, and, ultimately, women’s rights. For better or for worse.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Women’s heads have been the subject of political struggle for centuries. In this century, the forcible removal of hijab has corresponded with two trends, in particular: with Western influence in majority-Muslim countries or, as this summer’s burkini controversy demonstrated, with Western societies asserting nationalistic values and (patriarchal) identity. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;Freedom from&#8221; or &#8220;freedom to&#8221; are phrases associated with women’s behaviors, from dress to sexual activity to reproductive health, from France to Saudi Arabia. And we are often told to take a side: &#8220;Do you want women to be free from patriarchal oppression?&#8221; or &#8220;Do you want women to be free to wear whatever they choose?&#8221; </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But how does one think about the fight to wear hijab and the fight to be freed from hijab in one, unified thought? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Iran is a near perfect testament to such a thought. The country&#8217;s transition from Reza Shah Pahlavi to Ayatollah Khomeini provides an example of an apparent (and near perfect) paradox in practice.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the late 1920s in a still monarchical Iran, the Shah instituted what he called &#8220;a gradual process of hijab removal&#8221; from public institutions. The Shah’s friend and mentor, Turkey’s Mustafa Kemal Attatürk, espoused the view that head-covering reflected not only non-Western dress but non-Western thought. &#8220;Backwards women&#8221; stood for an undesirable social system, which extended into the confines of the home. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hijab was thus a stand-in or a symbol for the greater societal transformation each autocratic leader desired for the value system of his society. If Turkey and Iran were to join the rational, &#8220;enlightened&#8221; throngs of European history, in body and in mind, women had to remove their scarves.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Iran, in the period between these so-called modernization reforms and the Revolution, looked much like any other European country, with tanned youth in swimsuits smoking cigarettes on the beach, and Beatles records flying off the shelves. But in the late 1970s, frustration with the corrupt dictatorship of the Shah and the monarchy as a system of undemocratic government brought thousands of Iranian men and women out onto the streets. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the early days of 1979, secular and religious women alike protested for the right to ascribe to the value system of their choice. Whether Western or not, it was up to women to decide, not the Shah. </span></p>
<div id="attachment_4714" style="width: 510px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4714" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4714 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Iranian_Revolution_1979_marching_young_people.jpeg" alt="iranian_revolution_1979_marching_young_people" width="500" height="339" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Iranian_Revolution_1979_marching_young_people.jpeg 500w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Iranian_Revolution_1979_marching_young_people-300x203.jpeg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4714" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Wikimedia Commons</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As the revolution took a strident Islamic turn, women who did not wear hijab began to see the institution of the new state as a threat to their freedom of choice. Indeed, the &#8220;Islamic&#8221; in &#8220;Islamic Republic&#8221; now meant hijab, for all women. Iranian women were thus divided along ideological lines, and the new Islamic state was thus effective in reducing the voice and power of its most educated and mobile constituency: women.</span></p>
<p><iframe title="March 8, 1979 Iranian Women March Against Hijab and Islamic Laws" width="650" height="488" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/pxGYLk92edY?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With religious rule by Ayatollah Khomeini came moral rule in the homes and upon the bodies of women. Laws protecting women against the men of their family were eliminated. But as long as women were covered, they were able to obtain political office, attend university, and build a career. The hijab acted as a pass into the greater halls of society. It continues to act as the safeguard of a theocratic order, which exercises control while permitting necessary freedoms.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Iranian case is not so different from the European burkini fiasco last summer. The burkini &#8211; a full-body covering made of swimwear material, with an attached head covering like a swim cap &#8211; was banned in many French towns and cities for its subversion of secularist values. Women were to uphold the state’s belief in its own ideological abstention from religious practice in public life. Even while swimming. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The ban has since been <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-37198479">overturned at a federal level</a>, though some French municipalities claim that they will continue to enforce it. The mayor in the town where the ban made headlines, with police officers requiring a woman to remove her <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/08/28/world/europe/france-burkini-bikini-ban.html?_r=0">burkini on the beach</a>, called the ban an attempt to require &#8220;<a href="http://edition.cnn.com/2016/08/30/europe/french-mayor-cogolin-burkini-ban/">them to adopt our way of life.&#8221;</a> The &#8220;them&#8221; in this sentiment could be none other than Muslims, Europe&#8217;s favorite Other.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Liberal democracies, which respect the rights of minorities, demand pluralism &#8211; in lifestyle, in religious practice, in appearance, in ideology. Why does this pluralism extend only partially to women?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In France, the beach was briefly a battlefield. Muslim women were caught at the cross hairs of a power play between establishment norms and the liberty of choice that defines many arguments of cultural expression in other countries. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But the battlefield is an ideological one, surpassing the boundaries of nation and norms. It all comes down to the right to choose.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This is something women have been fighting for for centuries, from the ability to choose political leadership to the ability to choose a marital partner. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We can debate the merits behind the practice of the headscarf, its history in the Islamic world or even in the life of the prophet Muhammad, but what we should not debate is the ability of a woman to choose a practice, if it does no harm to her. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">France, in particular, makes the argument that the mere act of covering the body does harm to &#8220;the dignity and liberty&#8221; of said body. The issue of hijab is thus framed as one of protection, i.e. paternalism. A closer look at France’s relationship to identity politics and its systematic attempts to eliminate differences for the sake of the secular, homogeneous French state suggests that the protection enacted here is a fairly one-way street: There is &#8220;freedom from&#8221; but rarely &#8220;freedom to.&#8221;<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In Germany, a similar ban on head coverings for women exists. This ban is <a href="http://www.dw.com/en/can-muslim-women-wear-a-headscarf-at-work-in-germany/a-17953746">often a private and religious matter</a>, with church-based organizations or certain institutions able to decide when and if they will tolerate hijab. The attempts by school districts to ban headscarves in their teaching staff have been only partially successful, as German courts usually have the last word, overturning discriminatory practices, unless a specific legal conflict can be identified.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">German politicians have <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/08/19/germanys-potential-burqa-ban-has-a-problem-where-are-the-burqas/?utm_term=.947e281fb60a">also proposed a burqa ban</a>. The only problem is: hardly any women in Germany wear a burqa. Here, a moral stance is taken in preventing supposed harm before this harm could be said to occur. Ideology much? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Of course, the burqa is far from the burkini or the hijab. But it is no coincidence that the burqa ban discussion resurfaced and gained political momentum around the time of the burkini fiasco in France. Some European leaders may oppose France&#8217;s handling of the burkini on its beaches, but many have verbally and practically expressed their approval of policing Muslim women&#8217;s dress.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If one were to apply this&nbsp;logic of&nbsp;infringement of personal liberty to other arenas affecting the female body, one would end up with a long list of potential offenders, from beauty salons to botox offices to lingerie stores, where certain body parts are literally strapped down and constrained for the sake of smooth curvature. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;But these things make us feel good, make us feel pretty,&#8221; a French woman would likely respond. &#8220;And this is my right!&#8221;</span></p>
<div id="attachment_4715" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4715" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4715 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420-650x433.jpg" alt="berlin-bearbeitet-2014-420" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4715" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Type &#8220;hijab&#8221; into Pinterest and a fashion show will appear &#8211; women who use hijab as a way to present themselves in their way to the world. Stroll down the Turkish market at Berlin&#8217;s Maybachufer and you will encounter smiling groups of Muslima holding silk scarves up to their faces, matching patterns with dresses and jackets in mind, practicing new and different folds, depending on the material.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are wedding hijabs, hijabs for supermarket trips, and hijabs for dates, just as there are shoes for weddings, for nights out, or for lazy Saturdays.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hijab, like shoes, can make women feel good, because they make women feel pretty in a way that is also comfortable. It is both a lifestyle with religious and cultural roots and an identity mixed up with the many different conceptions humans have of beauty. Beauty: with all its socio-cultural baggage, the construct of forces beyond our individual minds and mirrors, forces that will always be a little bit oppressive but also a little bit fun, because they are familiar and somehow the product of our daily life within them. And this is their, our right.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As Trump ascends his throne to rule over the many who do not approve of or give license to his authoritarianism or assimilationist view of cultural differences, the hijab becomes one of those things that needs protection.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As Muslim refugees who choose to wear hijab become a lasting part of the societies of those European states that have taken them in, their right to be different must be defended. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Most importantly, we must defend the right of women to choose.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is this choice that makes women free. This is why feminism and hijab go together.</span></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>For more on the history of women in Iran, from hairstyles to political movements, see these sources: U.S. Institute of Peace&#8217;s <a href="http://iranprimer.usip.org/resource/womens-movement">Iran Primer: the Women&#8217;s Movement;</a> these pieces from a </em>New York Times<em>&nbsp;series &#8220;<a href="http://nytlive.nytimes.com/womenintheworld/2015/06/02/6-pervasive-misconceptions-about-iranian-women/">6 Pervasive Misconceptions about Iranian Women</a>&#8221; and &#8220;<a href="http://nytlive.nytimes.com/womenintheworld/2015/09/15/the-day-100000-iranian-women-protested-the-head-scarf/">The Day 100,000 Women Protested the Headscarf</a>&#8220;; this acclaimed book on the complexity of the Revolution: </em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Islamic-Utopian-Political-Biography-2000-06-03/dp/B019NRY9QG/ref=sr_1_3?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1480842551&amp;sr=1-3&amp;keywords=an+islamic+utopian+ali+shari%27ati">An Islamic Utopian: A Political Biography of Ali Shari&#8217;ati;</a><em> and the memoir, </em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/1400064708/?tag=thneyo0f-20">Iran Awakening</a><em>, by the Nobel-prize-winning activist Shirin Ebadi.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>And if you&#8217;re curious about women in hijab on the internet and in the fashion world, here are some people to watch: <a href="https://www.hautehijab.com/blogs/hijab-fashion">Haute Hijab</a> (U.S. fashion blogger with an entry titled &#8220;Embracing Our Identity in a Post 2016 Election World&#8221;), <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC_KQKeg7kNrlvrIXPnpwgEA">Dina Tokio</a> (U.K. vlogger and fashion designer), <a href="http://ww38.hipsterhijabis.com/about.html">Hipster Hijabis</a> (just what it sounds like), <a href="http://hanatajima.com/">Hana Tajima</a> (up-and-coming U.K. fashion designer), and <a href="http://hijablicious.com/">Hijablicious</a> (a site for &#8220;hijab with soul&#8221;).</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Value of Foreign Life: when the law demands &#8220;integration&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/08/25/the-value-of-foreign-life/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2016 11:23:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bundestag]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[language-learning]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4676</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Until now, immigration policy in Germany has followed a pathway defined by residency, employment, and citizenship restrictions. Put another way, policy has been concerned with 3 primary questions: Who is allowed to stay, who is allowed to work, and who is, ultimately, allowed to participate fully in the political process of the Federal Republic. But something changed this past July, when German Parliament passed its first ever law mandating a particular type of immigrant and refugee integration. Source: DPA The new Integrationsgesetz mandates fulfillment of a German principle of social and economic assimilation. This principle has little precedent, in terms of a comprehensive law. There have been expectations and additions to existing legislation in the past, but never has there been governmental action specifically devoted to the question of whether or not newcomers have found ways to fit in. And never has this governmental action been tied to sanctions, if benchmarks and timelines aren&#8217;t met. The new law measures the ability of newcomers to fare well on the basis of language and employment, with respect to natives: They are to learn German, well, within 5 years and become economically self-sufficient as soon as possible. Welfare and other subsidies are tethered to employment programs. Specific to [...]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Until now, immigration policy in Germany has followed a pathway defined by residency, employment, and citizenship restrictions. Put another way, policy has been concerned with 3 primary questions: Who is allowed to stay, who is allowed to work, and who is, ultimately, allowed to participate fully in the political process of the Federal Republic.</p>
<p>But something changed this past July, when <a href="http://www.bmi.bund.de/SharedDocs/Pressemitteilungen/DE/2016/07/integrationsgesetz-vom-bundestag-verabschiedet.html">German Parliament passed its first ever law mandating a particular type of immigrant and refugee integration</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4686" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4686" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4686 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte-650x365.jpeg" alt="fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte" width="650" height="365" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte-650x365.jpeg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte-300x169.jpeg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte.jpeg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte-310x174.jpeg 310w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4686" class="wp-caption-text">Source: <a href="http://www.bmi.bund.de/SharedDocs/Pressemitteilungen/DE/2016/07/integrationsgesetz-vom-bundestag-verabschiedet.html"> DPA</a></p></div>
<p>The new <em>Integrationsgesetz </em>mandates fulfillment of a German principle of social and economic assimilation. This principle has little precedent, in terms of a comprehensive law. There have been expectations and additions to existing legislation in the past, but never has there been governmental action specifically devoted to the question of whether or not newcomers have found ways to fit in. And never has this governmental action been tied to sanctions, if benchmarks and timelines aren&#8217;t met.</p>
<p>The new law measures the ability of newcomers to fare well on the basis of language and employment, with respect to natives: They are to learn German, well, within 5 years and become economically self-sufficient as soon as possible. Welfare and other subsidies are tethered to employment programs. Specific to refugees, asylum applicants awaiting refugee status will be recruited for low-paying (1 euro/hour) jobs as soon as they are registered with the authorities, no matter the qualifications they bring with them from their home countries.</p>
<p>This approach is known as the welfare-to-work model, popularized by the Clinton administration in the U.S. and implemented in Germany since 2002 in the form of the <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/thema/arbeitslosengeld_ii/">Hartz-IV</a> reforms. <a href="http://99percentinvisible.org/episode/magic-bureaucrat-riverside-miracle/">Research has shown</a> that welfare-to-work programs, rather than re-training newcomers or supporting them while they seek jobs for which they are actually qualified, have serious long-term consequences. Stagnation and even regression is the word.</p>
<p>The integration law presupposes and, indeed, requires a &#8220;help yourself&#8221; attitude. This was precisely the message of the German austerity program of Hartz-IV, forever unpopular among the Left. This correlation between the new integration program and austerity language has led some members of German Parliament to send up flares.</p>
<p>The economist and Green Party representative Brigitte Pothmar <a href="https://www.tagesschau.de/inland/integrationsgesetz-127.html">criticized the intent and scope</a> of the law specifically on the point of low-wage jobs: &#8220;According to its supporters&#8217; own language, the legislature plans to spend 3 million euros on ridding refugees of boredom. But refugees don&#8217;t need occupational therapy. They want to learn and they want to actually get to work!&#8221;</p>
<p>A <a href="https://www.tagesschau.de/inland/integrationsgesetz-127.html">similar critique was wielded </a>by the Left Party representative Sabine Zimmerman, calling the law exclusionary at best. In terms of the economy, in particular, &#8220;This type of work [1 euro jobs] does not provide any opportunity to earn qualifications or to truly learn the language. In effect, it makes it even harder for real opportunities to come about.&#8221;</p>
<p>But it is not only the language of self-help and the threat of stagnation that these parliamentary representatives are worried about. If newcomers are unable to reach German proficiency in 5 years&#8217; time or are unable to maintain employment, residency permits will not be renewed or will be outright denied. Other sanctions, such as restrictions on housing and overall mobility, also apply.</p>
<p>Likewise, those who prove to be &#8220;exceptionally well integrated,&#8221; according to the law&#8217;s system of measurement, will be granted the privilege of ungarnered residency within 5 years. There is a carrot at the end of the integration stick. And it looks a lot like survival.</p>
<p>The media&#8217;s response to the new integration law, as well as that of practitioners in the field, has been swift and strident, criticizing the way in which the word &#8220;integration&#8221; is tied to fundamentals like housing and residency permits. The well-respected German weekly <em>die Zeit </em><a href="http://www.zeit.de/politik/deutschland/2016-05/integrationsgesetz-fluechtlinge-wohnsitz-parlament-meseberg">reported the law&#8217;s final drafting</a> with the headline &#8220;Work better, fail quicker.&#8221; Another well-respected paper, the daily <em>Süddeutsche Zeitung</em>, printed the news with the headline &#8220;An integration law that doesn&#8217;t deserve its name.&#8221;</p>
<p>This new law does intend to simplify and expedite the processing of the many asylum applications Germany continues to receive. For many of the law&#8217;s opponents, this addition of asylum proceeding reform was reason enough to support the law. Yet it may be more restrictive than helpful to those applying for asylum. The <a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article156905294/Unter-einer-Bedingung-koennen-abgelehnte-Asylbewerber-bleiben.html">headline provided by the right-leaning daily</a> <em>die Welt </em>for the new law is telling: &#8220;Asylum-seekers can stay only under one condition.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>Value Judgement</strong></p>
<p>What does this have to do with the title of this article, the value of a foreign life?</p>
<p>Any subject of law, citizen or not, is assigned a particular value, as reflected in and by society. Law most often protects the value of the universal person in that it prevents harm and injustice within the scope of its jurisdiction, no matter the origin of said person. Natives cannot kill tourists or undocumented migrants, for example. This is still a crime.</p>
<p>But this goes both ways. Law is discerning, as are its makers. It can decide when and if certain protections or privileges are granted. In this act of exercising certain judgment, determining who is the recipient and who is not, a value judgement is passed. In the case of Germany&#8217;s new and unprecedented integration law, those who become German in the ways the law prescribes have value enough to stay. Those who fall short do not.</p>
<p>This value judgement is apparent in the language of the law itself, as well as in discussions surrounding it. One example is the usage of the word &#8220;<em>i</em><em>ntegrationsunwillig</em>&#8220;, meaning &#8220;unwilling to integrate.&#8221; Its counterpart, a noun, is <em>Integrationsverweigerung</em>, which takes a stronger tone: It means &#8220;refusal to integrate.&#8221; The subjects who exhibit these traits become subject to the sanctions mentioned above, likely to eventual deportation, thus forfeiture of assets, professional networks, and personal relationships in Germany.</p>
<p>This language makes clear assumptions about intent and character far more than it does about simply the state of things, of whether or not an individual has found him/_/herself to belong in their new home. &#8220;Unwilling&#8221; implies a flouting of both convention and the laws of the land. Cultural difference becomes cultural deviance within this frame, and those who do not fit in effectively become criminals.</p>
<p>The perceived understanding of integration behind this language of &#8220;unwilling&#8221; is most problematic in that it devalues the experience of the newcomer and abdicates the native of certain responsibilities by way of this process.</p>
<p>In other words, what of the many natives who will refuse to grant newcomers a job because of their last name, because of their fear of ISIS or simply of Islam?</p>
<p>What of the slow-moving bureaucracy that will prevent timely and efficient completion of an integration course, or of the notoriously unfriendly bureaucrats who will make registration for state-subsidized language courses or other training programs a painful and humiliating process?</p>
<p>Will the other side, at any point in this hypothetical pathway to official integration, be charged with an unwilling and outright difficult attitude?</p>
<p>The law, by default of its creation, values natives above foreigners. The answers to all the above questions will tend to err on the side of the native for this reason, and responsibility will continue to be a weight born by the weakest, the least valued. These are the immigrants, the asylum-seekers, and the refugees of today.</p>
<p>Germany has done so much good for the refugees of the world in this past year. This new law is an unfortunate development.</p>
<p>It is unfortunate that the integration law negates the complexity of human behavior and the ways in which human beings tend to respond to mechanisms of control. It is unfortunate that it transforms a once two-way street into a narrow, one-way turnpike, failing to recognize that tying belonging to an existential crisis is one sure way to create another type of crisis, one of protracted isolation and despair. <strong><br />
</strong></p>
<p><strong>The Way Out</strong></p>
<p>One does not become a part of a group by the force of policy, nor does one come to belong anywhere by resigning to segregation and the apathy of staying apart.</p>
<p>But I for one would rarely speak to my German neighbors if I didn&#8217;t feel that they would smile at me and wish to speak back. I am too sensitive of feeling unwanted and merely tolerated to make myself so vulnerable. In a similar way, if I were just learning German, I would rarely try to order in German on a busy bakery morning. I would rarely try to ask any questions of the service personnel at the mall. I would be too afraid of looking and feeling defeated for the stern face, the impatient twitch, and the impolite interruption that often peppers such interactions with shame.</p>
<p>And if I cannot imagine doing these things, as someone with no experience of war or traumatic displacement, I cannot imagine it for all newcomers from Syria and elsewhere &#8211; human beings who have suffered the extremes of suffering.</p>
<p><strong>Laws may not be made for empathetic social responses, but norms are. In response to this new law, a little normative empathy is in order. Perhaps it is time not for sanctions but for a new German way of being with each other.<br />
</strong></p>
<p>Small gestures like the prolific smile, like deferring to others in line at the grocery store, like trying (only trying!) to give directions in English, like waiting patiently for a German-learner to get out their form of a German sentence, will bring the empathy this law is so clearly lacking. If this happens, Syrians and Afghans and Eritreans and Kurds (etc) are made to feel that they are also people of value.</p>
<p>For anthropologists and sociologists, value is a social construct. It does not exist inherent to things, to substance. Rather it is made within a system of prioritizing this, disregarding that, supporting the success of this and punishing the success of that. Value is a trait or state to be expressed through norms, such as everyday behavior, as well as structures, such as divisions of labor or the segmentation of achievement within public schools*. It is a process, not a prescription.</p>
<p>We&#8217;ll see soon enough if the process can rise above this law.</p>
<p>&#8211;<em>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*For more on this critical view of how and why value is created in society, see the well-known work of anthropologist David Graeber on the topic, available as a PDF <a href="https://monoskop.org/File:Graeber_David_Toward_an_Anthropological_Theory_of_Value.pdf">here</a>. You will never see prices and social priorities the same!</p>
<p><iframe style="position: absolute; top: 0px; left: 0px; width: 1px; height: 1px; visibility: hidden; background: #ffffff none repeat scroll 0% 0%;" name="xdcom_frame" width="300" height="150"></iframe></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Women Only: The Frauenraum</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 15:42:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gender]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4385</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I'm at Rathaus Wilmersdorf, a former city hall building turned refugee home in Berlin, where I teach a literacy class once a week. The home initially opened its doors to 178 refugees in September 2015, following Merkel's famous "Wir schaffen das" ("We can do it") declaration that sidestepped the Dublin Regulation and opened up Germany's borders to thousands of asylum seekers.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4394 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-01-27 12.51.04" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>It&#8217;s Thursday at 10:55, and I&#8217;m running late. I rush up to the security guards and hand over my ID. <em>Helfer?</em> (&#8220;volunteer?&#8221;) they ask. <em>Ja</em>, I answer, and wait for them to scribble down my name and give me a number so I can sign out later. I thank them and head inside to the office to sign for the room keys and get my name tag. Then it&#8217;s through the foyer and up three floors to room 3092. When breakfast is running late, the right half of the stairwell is still filled by a neat line of people waiting for their turn in the cafeteria. I squeeze by, ruffling the hair of the kids I recognize.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m at Rathaus Wilmersdorf, a former city hall building turned refugee home in Berlin, where I teach a literacy class once a week. The home initially opened its doors to <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/berlin/bezirke/kudamm/notunterkunft-fuer-fluechtlinge-in-berlin-im-rathaus-wilmersdorf-fehlen-duschen-und-dolmetscher/12199798.html">178 refugees</a> in September 2015, following Merkel&#8217;s famous &#8220;Wir schaffen das&#8221; (&#8220;We can do it&#8221;) declaration that <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/germany/11821822/Germany-drops-EU-rules-to-allow-in-Syrian-refugees.html">sidestepped the Dublin Regulation</a> and opened up Germany&#8217;s borders to thousands of asylum seekers.</p>
<p>Today, over 1400 refugees live in the Rathaus &#8211; mostly from Syria, Afghanistan, and Iraq &#8211; and there is talk of opening up an adjacent building to house an additional 900. As is the case all over the city, this home simply wouldn&#8217;t function without the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/">on-going assistance of volunteers</a> who help out with everything from interpretation and teaching to administrative and kitchen support.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4456 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-01-08 10.34.54" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Over the past eight months, Rathaus Wilmersdorf has become somewhat of a success story as far as refugee accommodations in Berlin go. It&#8217;s been visited by President Joachim Gauck and American actor Ben Stiller, as well as received significant media praise for its leadership and facilities. <a href="http://www.morgenpost.de/berlin/article207089933/Vachroi-verabschiedet-sich-als-Heimleiter-in-Wilmersdorf.html">One article</a> listed off the home&#8217;s impressive amenities, which include medical and midwife services, a laundry room, a hair salon, an internet <span class="st">café</span>, and yes, even our literacy class.</p>
<p>The literacy class, or &#8220;AB class&#8221; as we call it, does go beyond what many other refugee homes in Berlin offer. But what the article&#8217;s authors fail to mention (and are likely unaware of), is that the course comes with a complicated backstory that is indicative of a larger debate surrounding refugees in Germany today.</p>
<p>It all started early this year, after one volunteer noticed that a group of women were not showing up for the German class offered on the home&#8217;s fourth floor. These women were mostly Afghan and the majority also illiterate. However, a bit of digging (and a heavy dose of interpretation) revealed that they weren&#8217;t avoiding the class because the level was too difficult, as originally suspected. They weren&#8217;t going because, in the fourth floor class, there were men present. Or depending on who tells the story, “Because their husbands wouldn’t let them”.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4600 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-05-19 12.43.22" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>The decision was therefore made to start a new class on the third floor, taught and attended exclusively by women. The class was to be an extension of the adjacent <em>Frauenraum</em> or &#8220;women&#8217;s room&#8221;. At Rathaus Wilmersdorf, the <em>Frauenraum</em> is a standing room open almost daily, so long as there are volunteers present. At the refugee home in former Tempelhof airport, the <em>Frauenraum</em> operates on a weekly project basis, led by a volunteer platform called <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">Give Something Back to Berlin</a>.</p>
<p>Regardless of the format, the concept remains the same: The <em>Frauenraum</em> is a safe place where women can be amongst themselves. In Rathaus Wilmersdorf, they sew, practice German, or just hang out and have a cup of tea. Small children are allowed, but men are forbidden from entering. We&#8217;ve even had to throw out a male journalist on occasion. The home&#8217;s former director described it as a place where &#8220;<a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/berlin/warum-thomas-de-vachroi-der-perfekte-aufbauhelfer-fuer-fluechtlingsheime-ist-23775578">female residents are enjoying their freedom and unveiling themselves.</a>&#8221; I can only assume he meant this both literally and figuratively, as not all the women wear headscarves, but some who do do indeed take them off when in the <em>Frauenraum</em> or during class.</p>
<p>I fell into the role of literacy teacher by way of the <em>Frauenraum</em>, where I started volunteering in January. The class was already up and running but they wanted to offer it on more days and were having trouble finding willing teachers. Other <em>Frauenraum</em> volunteers, I was told, had flatly refused to teach out of principle, scoffing at the idea that a separate class be created when there was a perfectly good one already on offer. This is Germany, after all, a country where men and women are presumably equal and interact on all levels of society. If the husbands had a problem with that, tough. Isn&#8217;t it in the best interest of these women that we integrate them into our way of life as quickly as possible?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4460 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-05-12 11.42.50" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>These days, it is difficult to have a discussion in Germany about refugees that doesn&#8217;t include a question about gender. <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/02/08/not-our-women-from-cologne-to-berlin/">Post-Cologne</a>, it is near impossible. Despite the fact that the attacks on New Year&#8217;s Eve were carried out by a more diverse group than originally portrayed in the media, that night&#8217;s unfortunate events have marked a turning point in attitudes towards refugees.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.focus.de/politik/deutschland/zdf-umfrage-offenbart-so-haben-die-silvester-uebergriffe-beeinflusst-was-deutsche-ueber-fluechtlinge-denken_id_5213962.html">One poll</a> showed that, between December 2015 and January 2016 alone, the number of Germans who felt the country couldn&#8217;t handle the influx of refugees rose from 46% to 60%. Thirty-three percent stated that Cologne had &#8220;fundamentally changed&#8221; their opinions about refugees. And the ring-wing <span class="st"><em>Alternative für Deutschland</em></span> (AfD) party, which initially emerged in opposition to the euro, has placed anti-refugee sentiment at the core of their increasingly popular platform. Their leader has controversially <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/alternative-for-germany-shows-its-true-right-wing-colors-a-1076259.html">called for the use of firearms against incoming refugees</a>.</p>
<p>This is the same country that was at the forefront of Europe&#8217;s refugee response only nine months ago. The same country that led the continent&#8217;s discourse on establishing a common European solution. The same country that initiated what became globally lauded as <em>Wilkommenskultur</em> (welcome culture).</p>
<p>So, what&#8217;s changed?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4401 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-650x650.jpg" alt="2016-02-10 11.59.46" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-300x300.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>When the “refugee crisis” hit Germany last summer, hundreds of residents felt compelled to slather butter on rolls and pass them out to refugees arriving at train stations. This was by all accounts heart-warming and admirable, but it was also the easy part. The conversation we are having now is a more complicated one, one that even the seemingly simple question of whether to offer a female-only literacy class echoes:</p>
<p>What happens next and how might our society change as a result?</p>
<p>One could blame Cologne, but the foundation for this confrontation was laid long before. A staggering <a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article147280667/Fuer-die-meisten-gehoert-der-Islam-nicht-zu-Deutschland.html">60% of the country</a> is of the opinion that Islam does not belong in Germany. (It is also worth noting that Germans consistently overestimate the number of Muslims living in the country. The real figure, while one of the highest in the EU, <a href="http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2015/11/17/5-facts-about-the-muslim-population-in-europe/">is still only 5.8%</a>.)</p>
<p>There is an underlying preconception in Germany, as in many Western countries, that Islam is synonymous with misogyny and a lack of female rights. That “<a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article149756193/Wie-Sumtes-Wutbuerger-lernten-Fluechtlinge-zu-lieben.html">according to their religion, women are nothing</a>” or even more extreme, that &#8220;<a href="http://www.vice.com/de/read/fluechtlinge-vergewaltigen-deutsche-kinder-wie-rassisten-versuchen-stimmung-gegen-alle-nicht-deutschen-zu-machen-775">these young men will come and rape our daughters</a>&#8220;. This preconception likely stems from a variety of factors: images we see in the media, politicians portraying Muslims as backward or extremist, or current conflicts within the Middle East. An argument heard less often is made by <a href="http://ideas.time.com/2013/11/01/do-muslim-women-need-saving/">Columbia University Professor Lila Abu-Lughod</a>, who explores the conflation of religion and socioeconomic status. Gender inequality within Muslim majority societies stems mainly from economic inequality, and migrants in Germany have traditionally been low-skilled. Therefore what we may label as clashes due to religion may have stronger roots in poverty and lack of opportunity.</p>
<p>Earlier this year in Berlin, <a href="http://www.rbb-online.de/politik/beitrag/2016/04/berlin-kopftuch-streit-vor-arbeitsgericht-keine-guetliche-einigung.html">a young teacher went to court</a> because she was denied a teaching post due to her headscarf (the case was thrown out on grounds of the state&#8217;s Neutrality Act). More recently in Switzerland, a <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-36382596">regional authority ruled</a> that two teenage brothers must shake the hands of their female teachers despite it being against their religious beliefs to touch women they are not related to. Traditionally receiving societies such as Germany are perpetually learning how to manage integration in the face of growing diversity. Unfortunately, we seem insistent on concentrating on how &#8220;their values&#8221; may threaten &#8220;ours&#8221;, rather than on what type of society we want to live in together.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4406 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-02-17 12.07.15" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>To be fair, my own engagement at the Rathaus has not come without challenges. On my first day teaching, I swallowed a lot of frustration as another volunteer and I watched the women turn to their husbands for approval before following us to class. <em>Nur Frauen</em> (&#8220;only women&#8221;), we tried to communicate to the more skeptical looking of the men with a smile, while I stifled the urge to roll my eyes.</p>
<p>We&#8217;ve also heard a host of disturbing stories by way of the interpreters. Rape, abuse, threats of divorce. Some stories are from Afghanistan while others allegedly took place here in Berlin. At times, I am ashamed to find myself relieved that I can&#8217;t talk to the women directly about what I&#8217;ve heard, for fear it might affect the way I interact with them. For now, our exchanges are limited to topics like telling time and types of fruit &#8211; they&#8217;re big fans of banana and pineapple &#8211; as well as the apparently always shocking and never boring topic of me being a 30 year old woman without a husband or children (some of my students have 6, 7, even 9 children).</p>
<p>But until we&#8217;re able to have those more in-depth conversations, I remain convinced that offering a class under imperfect circumstances is better than offering no women&#8217;s class at all. For what, I&#8217;ve asked myself, will give these women more independence than the ability to navigate the city on their own? And what will give them a better chance of being able to navigate the city on their own than the ability to read and write?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4405 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-04-20 10.14.53" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Nothing exhibited this more clearly to me than a few weeks ago, when we held an arts project week for our women. The week consisted of two trips to separate parks so they could learn about various plant types and practice drawing them. The excitement of the women was palpable. They got to have a Middle Eastern picnic, a real treat after months of bland cafeteria fare. They got to pick flowers in the woods to take back to the home. There was laughing, there was dancing, and there were so many selfies.</p>
<p>We later found out through interpreters that, for several of the women, it was their first time in a park without a husband or male relative.</p>
<p>At the end of the week, a local artist took the womens&#8217; drawings and stenciled them onto power boxes near the Rathaus. On the Friday, we took a stroll around the neighborhood together to see them for the first time. The Farsi-speaking volunteer asked the women to point out their drawings and explain why they chose to draw them specifically. &#8220;Who drew this?&#8221; she asked when we got to the second box, pointing to a beautiful palm tree. &#8220;Me,&#8221; answered one of our students, &#8220;I drew it because it reminds me of home. And if you cut off the head, the whole plant dies.&#8221;</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The Frauenraum at Rathaus Wilmersdorf is looking for volunteers. To get involved, sign up at https://volunteer-planner.org/.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>For another take on the headscarf, I recommend watching <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/video/2015/jun/24/hijab-not-oppression-feminist-statement-video">this Guardian video</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>All photos my own.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Migration Matters: A Free Video Lecture Series</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/02/29/migration-matters-a-free-video-lecture-series/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[collidoscopeks]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 14:16:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4377</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When we talk about migration on this website, among our friends and colleagues, and particularly across the vast expanse of the internet, we are confronted with many misconceptions about who the immigrants and refugees of the world really are, what brings them to our countries and communities, and whether or not the statements made by politicians on immigration are true, let alone helpful. We write about the movement and coming together of people, because we believe commentary and discussion to be a powerful antidote to this perpetuation of misinformation. But are words, indeed our own voices, ever enough? A New Project: Migration Matters In collaboration with two inspiring women in the field of migration reporting and migration studies, we are embarking on a new chapter of Collidoscope&#8217;s mission in launching a free online course, which will deliver concise, accurate information about migration in just five minutes a day. This course will focus on promoting understanding of the issues: how and why migration happens, how it is being addressed around the world, and how we can become more informed actors in the process. We let &#8220;the experts&#8221; speak: accomplished, peer-reviewed researchers and educators, practitioners in the field, and migrants themselves. In [...]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When we talk about migration on this website, among our friends and colleagues, and particularly across the vast expanse of the internet, we are confronted with many misconceptions about who the immigrants and refugees of the world really are, what brings them to our countries and communities, and whether or not the statements made by politicians on immigration are true, let alone helpful.</p>
<p>We write about the movement and coming together of people, because we believe commentary and discussion to be a powerful antidote to this perpetuation of misinformation. But are words, indeed our own voices, ever enough?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-4371 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/TrailerThumbnail.jpg" width="650" height="366" /></p>
<p><strong>A New Project: <a href="https://www.generosity.com/community-fundraising/migration-matters-a-free-video-lecture-series/x/13390941">Migration Matters</a></strong></p>
<p>In collaboration with two inspiring women in the field of migration reporting and migration studies, we are embarking on a new chapter of Collidoscope&#8217;s mission in launching <a href="https://www.generosity.com/community-fundraising/migration-matters-a-free-video-lecture-series/x/13390941">a free online course</a>, which will deliver concise, accurate information about migration in just five minutes a day.</p>
<p>This course will focus on promoting understanding of the issues: how and why migration happens, how it is being addressed around the world, and how we can become more informed actors in the process. We let &#8220;the experts&#8221; speak: accomplished, peer-reviewed researchers and educators, practitioners in the field, and migrants themselves.</p>
<p>In line with what we have worked to create with the Collidoscope project, this course will foster a space for open conversation, where no concern is ridiculed and no question dismissed.</p>
<p>To learn more, visit the Migration Matters page and <a href="http://www.migrationmatters.me/">pre-enroll for this great course</a>! You can also follow Migration Matters on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/migrmatters">@MigrMatters</a> and on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/MigrationMatters/?fref=ts">Facebook</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Funding</strong></p>
<p>We can&#8217;t do it without your help &#8211; our loyal supporters, readers, friends, colleagues, and friends.</p>
<p>Please help us realize our goal of beginning an open, evidence-based conversation about the issues that matter most to us, to immigrants, to refugees, by <a href="https://www.generosity.com/community-fundraising/migration-matters-a-free-video-lecture-series/x/13390941">contributing to our crowd-funding campaign</a>. You can also help by spreading the word about this project in your community. The greater our reach, the more effective its message.</p>
<p>If you have any questions about Migration Matters or would like to be involved, please contact the team at migrmatters@gmail.com. Currently we are looking for individuals with experience in visual design, interactive online experiences, and data visualizations.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em><strong>Kelly and Sophia</strong></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>&#8220;Not our Women&#8221; after Cologne</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/02/08/not-our-women-from-cologne-to-berlin/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2016 08:20:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[feminism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugeecrisis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sexism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4347</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Sounding like the crescendo long-awaited by right-wing populists, the attacks on New Year's Eve in Cologne occurred. "Will they treat our women well? Will they know how to speak to and appreciate our women?" a Cologne politician asked on national German public radio in the days following the attacks. It is no slip of the tongue that a possessive article precedes "women".  Belonging to a place can quickly devolve into sentiments of ownership, as well as xenophobia.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Middle class and low-income white men are<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/02/04/opinion/white-americas-broken-heart.html?_r=0"> suffering from &#8220;broken hearts&#8221;</a>, Bill Clinton told a crowd of Hillary Clinton supporters this month. They&#8217;re looking for ways to feel strong again, less power-less in the face of &#8220;great demographic change,&#8221; he continued. Increasing rates of a certain type of immigration compounded with a decline in the legitimacy of traditional masculinity, in which only dudes could consume mass-market beer (see <a href="http://adage.com/article/cmo-strategy/coors-light-campaign-women-drinkers-mind/302334/">Coors&#8217; inclusion of women in their advertising</a>) and be celebrated for their singular athleticism (see U.S. women&#8217;s World Cup victory), are having grave effect: The mortality rate for white men is increasing, not declining, as compared to other groups, Bill C. emphasized.</p>
<p>Sure, this data could be interpreted to mean that white men are in crisis. Yet it could also be interpreted as a re-distribution of territorial domains. White men, no longer allowed to consume and stock-pile exorbitantly more than their fair share, are thus bearing the brunt of what the rest of us face (to varying degrees): the strain of child-rearing and poor-paying jobs, social stigma and disrespect, and broken promises by our most trusted institutions.</p>
<p>Whether or not this latter interpretation is the correct one is worthy of debate; however, this is not the article with which to properly frame and carry out this debate. Rather, I would like to begin a discussion on the significance and impact for women and for immigrants of this declining white male power. Although Bill Clinton would surely prefer for me to focus on the United States, Germany will be the setting &#8211; a country witnessing the simultaneous effects of the white male crisis (from now on referred to as <strong>WMC</strong>) and the increase of immigrants from majority Muslim countries, where gendered power operates within very different historical parameters.</p>
<p>Germany&#8217;s position as key humanitarian actor in the refugee crisis and the role of its leader, a woman, in steering and driving EU and regional responses to the crisis, make it all the more compelling as far as WMC and demographic change are concerned. The very recent attacks on women in Cologne, in which more than 100 young women were violated physically, sexually, and personally (in any combination) by presumed immigrants and asylum applicants* provide a precise situation on which to base a discussion of WMC. The framework for this discussion begins in the fall of 2015, namely with Germany&#8217;s decision to shoulder much of the burden of the Syrian conflict.</p>
<div id="attachment_4350" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4350" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4350 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/do-not-touch-me-_New-Yorker-650x451.jpg" alt="women refugees Germany Cologne" width="650" height="451" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/do-not-touch-me-_New-Yorker-650x451.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/do-not-touch-me-_New-Yorker-300x208.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/do-not-touch-me-_New-Yorker.jpg 690w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4350" class="wp-caption-text">Source: The New Yorker</p></div>
<p>As it became clear this past August that the staggering flows of those fleeing to Europe would not ebb, the European Union began to see the task of absorption and processing no longer as a matter of will but of inevitability. In confronting the situation, quotas for the distribution of asylum applicants to <a href="http://themigrationist.net/2015/10/07/refugee-quota-the-end-of-the-eu-or-the-beginning-of-collective-humanitarianism/">each of the 28 member states were passed</a>; the numbers initially named were quickly surpassed by an increasingly grim reality; and certain states balked at EU Commission attempts to enforce said quotas. And people kept coming, washing up dead or alive.</p>
<p>Germany, as the largest economy and most populous country in the EU, then began to go it alone: Angela Merkel (and her coalition government) bypassed the gates of EU political convention, <a href="https://meta.tagesschau.de/id/102472/merkel-weist-verantwortung-fuer-fluechtlingsandrang-zurueck">effectively eliminating the so-called Dublin III protocol for those migrants and recognized refugees with a Syrian passport</a>. Instead of languishing in the overwhelmed border camps and courts of Greece, Malta, and Italy, hundreds of thousands were now free to head by train and foot and truck northward toward Germany, their nationality allowing them passage in a system otherwise characterized by strict enforcement of where-you-put-your-foot-down-first jurisdiction.</p>
<p>In this political moment, in this shift from common EU debate and problem-solving to geopolitical activism, Angela Merkel came to symbolize the potential for a woman&#8217;s leadership in crisis (for which the world has far too few examples, by nature of the big P [patriarchy]). For many refugees, in particular, she came to embody a sort of migration-maternalism: a woman opens her arms to millions of displaced human beings, largely Muslim; <em>her</em> country embraces them; and, although a tough reality of asylum proceedings** awaits, they may come and be cared for in the interim.</p>
<p><strong>Then, sounding like the crescendo long-awaited by right-wing populists, the attacks on New Year&#8217;s Eve in Cologne occurred. </strong></p>
<p>For those not yet familiar with the details of the Cologne attacks, here is a quick and fairly accurate summation, gleaned from multiple news sources that have worked to continually revise and update their assessments of the situation in real-time:</p>
<p>Late on the eve of the New Year, a band of men carried out a series of coordinated frisks, assaults, and robberies in and around Cologne&#8217;s large and iconic train station. The <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2016/01/10/462558773/night-of-shame-week-of-soul-searching-cologne-attacks-divide-germany">Associated Press reported</a> a total of 379 criminal complaints, with 40% including allegations of sexual assault (inappropriate touching, groping, and even rape). Police reports initially described the suspected men as &#8220;refugees&#8221; before details had been confirmed, <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/cologne-attacks-trigger-raw-debate-on-immigration-in-germany-a-1071175.html">Spiegel Online reported</a>. Victims interviewed described men of Middle Eastern and North African appearance. This information was then passed on to the press and reassembled into a series of articles and shock-mongering headlines.</p>
<p><a href="http://There were thirty-two suspects identified: nine Algerians, eight Moroccans, five Iranians, four Syrians, three Germans, one Iraqi, one Serb, and one American. Many more should be located as investigations commence. Yet we do know that 22 of the suspects are asylum applicants - trying to gain refugee status for themselves.">The New Yorker writes</a> that of the 32 suspects identified, 9 were Algerian, 8 were Moroccan, 5 were Iranian, 4 were Syrian, 3 were German, and 3 were Iraqi, Serb, and American, respectively. This makes for a group a bit more multicultural than the police and the press led the public to believe. The article goes on to write &#8220;we do know that 22 of the suspects are asylum applicants.&#8221; The <a href="https://www.bundesregierung.de/Content/DE/Mitschrift/Pressekonferenzen/2016/01/2016-01-08-regpk.html">German government has since confirmed</a> that more than merely a few of the suspects were in the midst of asylum proceedings.</p>
<p>Perhaps most important to the Cologne event is not what we know about these criminals but what we know about the effects of their behavior.</p>
<p>It took only a few hours for a certain voice to dominate the German airwaves, calling for the protection of &#8220;our women&#8221; against the in-compatibility of largely Muslim newcomers, or a narrative of an Oriental Other assaulting Germany&#8217;s young and female. It did not help that this discussion began on the sidelines; official accounts and both public and popular media arrived painfully late.</p>
<p>Right from the start, Cologne police failed to promptly inform the public, in part out of fear that Germany&#8217;s growing Nativist movement would run with not yet substantiated suspicions, leading to <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/german-refugee-hostel-attacks-on-the-rise-a-1027994.html">more attacks on asylum housing and processing facilities than the increasing incidence the country had already been forced to publicly confront (and condemn)</a>. The public TV network ZDF failed to report the attacks in a timely fashion, a whole four days late to be precise. Word initially broke from unofficial sources, namely from neighborhood activists and victims who took to social media. Yet initial caution by journalistic publications soon gave way to reductionist interpretations of the night in question, most notably in illustrated form at two prominent news sources.</p>
<p>The newspaper giant <em>Süddeutsche Zeitung</em> used its front page to depict the penetration of a white woman&#8217;s pubic region by a pitch black hand. The leading weekly magazine <em>Focus </em>featured a naked, blonde woman smeared with hand prints in black paint.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4352 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/sueddeutsche_zeitung_focus_titelseite-627x288.jpg" alt="sueddeutsche_zeitung_focus_titelseite-627x288" width="627" height="288" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/sueddeutsche_zeitung_focus_titelseite-627x288.jpg 627w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/sueddeutsche_zeitung_focus_titelseite-627x288-300x138.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 627px) 100vw, 627px" /></p>
<p>These publications were not right-wing brochures stoking existing flames. They were Germany&#8217;s moderate dailies and weeklies, stoking the fears of a majority trying to hold it all in and, ultimately, together. In other words, fearful and fear-mongering reactions blending women&#8217;s bodies with foreign elements came from the middle of society. Not from the fringe.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/cologne-attacks-trigger-raw-debate-on-immigration-in-germany-a-1071175.html">41% of Germans polled do not think the media is doing enough</a>, has been critical enough, in their reporting on and of the Cologne attacks. It is a frightening moment when citizens trust Facebook posts and tweets more than the national news providers. And when Facebook posts by everyday Germans include statements like &#8220;Where were the girls screaming &#8216;welcome&#8217; this time? Those whores would certainly have loved to have their crotches or tits grabbed by countless hands&#8221;, the trouble seems deeper, stickier, knee-deep in a mess of WMC and identity in flux.</p>
<p>&#8220;Will they treat our women well? Will they know how to speak to and appreciate our women?&#8221; a <a href="http://www.deutschlandfunk.de/straffaellig-gewordene-auslaender-grenze-fuer-ausweisung.868.de.html?dram:article_id=342031">Cologne politician asked on national German public radio</a> in the days following the attacks. It is no slip of the tongue that a possessive article precedes &#8220;women&#8221;.  Belonging to a place can quickly devolve into sentiments of ownership.</p>
<p>Interpreting and responding to the events of Cologne are largely white males in power, be it the incompetent police chief or the parliamentary members who have rushed to pass new asylum legislation. And so, this string of event and response begs the following question: Is the outrage directed toward Cologne&#8217;s perpetrators less about the violation of women and more about the violation of the status quo &#8211; a violation only offensive when committed by outsiders, by non-white, non-native males?</p>
<p><strong>The Body-Politic</strong></p>
<p>The confluence or, better yet, the conflation of female body, female person, and nation had arrived long before Cologne, before Mama Merkel. History provides countless examples of an event similar to the rhetoric now heard after Cologne, in which nationalism, xenophobia, and socioeconomic flux have coalesced around the female form, thereby rallying around all the ways we choose to represent and activate this gender. These times are also characterized by a similar strain of WMC, caused by WWI national humiliation and WWII national dismantlement, respectively.</p>
<p>In Nazi Germany, the female body became both a cherished garden and weapon of the state. The womb was a tool to be pointed directly at the enemy, outnumbering and eliminating their corrupt bloodlines. Women received medals of honor (<i><a href="http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/en/article.php?ModuleId=10005205">Mutterehrenkreuz</a></i>) for their reproductive service to the nation, and were extolled in propaganda for their virtuosity (though simultaneously sexualized in artistic depictions).</p>
<div id="attachment_4353" style="width: 441px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4353" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4353 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/74853-431x650.jpg" alt="74853" width="431" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/74853.jpg 431w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/74853-199x300.jpg 199w" sizes="(max-width: 431px) 100vw, 431px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4353" class="wp-caption-text">Source: USHMM</p></div>
<p>In the GDR, <a href="http://www.dw.com/en/the-victims-of-east-germanys-doping-program-are-still-suffering/a-18038630">young women and pre-pubescent girls were taken by the state and trained to be superior athletes</a> in dance and gymnastics. Their bodies were submitted to cruel fitness and hormonal regimes, not to mention sexual and physical abuse, for the sake of the state&#8217;s prestige. If their little bodies could be the strongest and most agile on the global stage, so would the state be seen as an emblem of strength under international socialism.</p>
<p>We are now at a similar juncture of the female body, the boundaries of nation and belonging, and the rise of a fear of outsiders &#8211; those beyond our high walls. The moral lines are clearer, with Germany acting as the haven-provider to a great number of human beings, and the gendered terrain more complicated, with confrontational waves of feminism and anti-feminism meeting at the issue of sexual violence.</p>
<p>Germany&#8217;s populist conservative party, known for its Nativist and nationalistic language, has seized the issue for the purpose of its own political ascent. This party, which calls itself &#8220;the Alternative for Germany&#8221;*** (in short form AfD), and its supporters have grabbed hold of statements by ordinary, not necessarily right-wing citizens to assert their points across the playing field of internet activism. One such comment appropriated for their messaging: &#8220;Is it for this that I donated half of the contents of my wardrobe? Is this the new Cologne? Is this the new Germany?&#8221;</p>
<p>Many frightened and frustrated Germans, men and women alike, now find themselves the target of further right-wing propagandizing and the machinery it seeks to build. Amidst the lack of confidence much of the country has expressed in its leader, Angela Merkel, there are increasingly fewer obstructions in this machinery&#8217;s path.</p>
<p>Particularly in Cologne, right-wing movements maintain a dreary precedence. Only a few years ago, a <a href="http://www.sueddeutsche.de/news/politik/landtag-nsu-morde-gegen-anschlagsopfer-in-koeln-wurde-nicht-ermittelt-dpa.urn-newsml-dpa-com-20090101-150906-99-06268">series of terrorist attacks by neo-Nazis</a><a href="http://www.sueddeutsche.de/news/politik/landtag-nsu-morde-gegen-anschlagsopfer-in-koeln-wurde-nicht-ermittelt-dpa.urn-newsml-dpa-com-20090101-150906-99-06268"> on an immigrant district and on immigrant-owned shops in the area</a> left much of Germany stunned. The persistent local neo-Nazi scene, combined with a strong football-hooligan landscape, has made Cologne the stage for many an uncomfortable attack on people who dare to be different.</p>
<p>Perhaps it is thus no surprise that the right-wing AfD is gaining momentum: For the first time ever, they&#8217;ve reached <a href="http://www.focus.de/politik/videos/waere-am-sonntag-bundestagswahl-neuer-hoechststand-afd-liegt-in-umfragen-bei-13-prozent-der-waehlerstimmen_id_5237952.html">double-digits with 13%</a>. This is no small jump in a parliamentary system, where the majority parties hold 25-30%.</p>
<p>The political battlefield has thus become more right-leaning in response to Cologne. Parties like AfD and the Pegida movement are the victors; the victims, i.e. women, have been shoved to the sidelines, it would seem.</p>
<div id="attachment_4359" style="width: 560px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4359" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4359 size-full" title="http://www.handelsblatt.com/politik/deutschland/swr-und-alternative-fuer-deutschland-afd-ist-ploetzlich-nicht-mehr-rechtspopulistisch/12670452.html" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/3-format2010.jpg" alt="http://www.handelsblatt.com/politik/deutschland/swr-und-alternative-fuer-deutschland-afd-ist-ploetzlich-nicht-mehr-rechtspopulistisch/12670452.html" width="550" height="309" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/3-format2010.jpg 550w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/3-format2010-300x169.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/3-format2010-310x174.jpg 310w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4359" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Handelsblatt</p></div>
<p>Many feminist activists have begun to call attention to the way in which certain men have used the Cologne attacks to, again, co-opt women&#8217;s experiences for their own ends. Not only AfD supporters have jumped at the chance to speak of &#8220;our women&#8221; in a tone that decries immigrants; ordinary citizens have found justification for their anti-immigrant feelings in the example of the assaulted woman. &#8216;As if these voices were not also sexist, not also part of a system in which violence against women persists?!&#8217; these activists write. Using the hashtag <a href="http://ausnahmslos.org/">#ausnahmslos</a>, activist women seek to reclaim the discussion from groups with fingers and tongues quick to spread a message of natives-or-else. &#8216;Women&#8217;s safety and respect or else, more like it!&#8217; they respond.</p>
<p>The old guard of women&#8217;s rights has since positioned itself in the quick-finger camp. Alice Schwarzer, one of Germany&#8217;s most iconic feminists, now in her 70s, <a href="http://www.aliceschwarzer.de/artikel/das-sind-die-folgen-der-falschen-toleranz-331143">rashly called for the mandatory re-socialization of young immigrant men</a> in order to prevent such attacks in the future. Her vocality in the women&#8217;s rights arena has more traditionally <a href="http://www.sueddeutsche.de/leben/alice-schwarzer-in-der-prostitutionsdebatte-kaeufliche-koerper-kaeufliche-seelen-1.1834875">been associated with the issue of prostitution</a> in Germany, which is legal and thus state-regulated. But on this question of bodies, it would appear that the fear of the foreigner has somehow superseded fear of the consequences of Patriarchy&#8230; or these fears have became one and the same.</p>
<p>As #ausnahmslos activists emphasize, sexual violence is not an element foreign to Germany. Barriers to the inclusion of women in the workplace; in the general economy of goods, people, and services; and the social realm, such as the basketball court or nightclub, continue to persist. Stopping the discussion at &#8220;cultural assimilation&#8221; and re-education of foreigners is just another example of an ineffective approach &#8211; ineffective at addressing the systemic perceptions and symbolism that perpetuate violence against women everywhere.</p>
<p>Sexual violence and, in particular, violence against women in any form will not stop with the closure of borders or with the re-education of millions of Muslims. To boot, millions of Muslims already respect and honor the rights and bodies of women. And millions of Muslims are already of the understanding that they will adopt the norms of their new society as far as safety and well-being of their neighbors is concerned. For this problem of gender subjugation, disrespect, and a negative power differential (favoring the Almighty Male) will transcend and outlive migration. Because power is power anywhere. And injustice is injustice anywhere and elsewhere, as well as right here at home.</p>
<p><strong>But Alice Schwarzer may still be right in her comments &#8211; right in its <em>affect</em>. For is it not right to be just a little scared, and to respond in kind?</strong></p>
<p>No matter how much one would like to see this event as complex and thus respect its complexity, fear of the Other and an increased frustration with Germany&#8217;s role in shouldering the refugee burden is fully justified. Even for those suffering from WMC.</p>
<p>This fear &#8211; that newcomers will disrupt the existing social order, will displace and threaten our bodies and livelihoods &#8211; is not without logical, emotional, and even physical (that is, viscerally experienced) reason. Violence, though particularly sexual violence, is offensive in all the ways the actions of human beings toward other human beings can offend, particularly as this offense relates to the national mythology of belonging, of mother-land or father-land. The female body is a battlefield or, better, a litmus test for just how much we can welcome outsiders, and for when we will lash out at them with prods of cultural reductionism, instead. Especially when this tendency to lash out and reduce can be therapeutic.</p>
<p>It is a great challenge of conscience and certainly of policy to admit that fear and mistrust is valid, as concerns the more than 1 million asylum applicants who Germany will have welcomed (albeit temporarily) by spring. But only by legitimizing and honoring this fear can we begin to confront the entanglement of sexism, violence, and cultural change. Preparing society for this shift must begin with a validation and recognition that all this will be difficult and wrought with growing pains. Otherwise, fears can fester.</p>
<p>As can be witnessed on the other side of the Atlantic, when the fears of a large class of individuals goes unrecognized, it can lead to reactionary populism. Donald Trump&#8217;s loyal followers <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/authoritarians-agree-trump-for-president/2016/01/19/407f58ec-bef0-11e5-bcda-62a36b394160_story.html">yearn for someone to tell them that they can, again, have durable value in the face of great rupture</a>, and in the face of the kind of poverty and disillusionment that break the soul. Pegida and the AfD loan German men the agency they feel they lack in the face of massive cultural change and EU politics, even if this means taking the country away from all the people who are different and honor difference. Added to existing WMC, Germany could be in for the type of election that introduced certain historical cowboys and charismatic soldiers to the ranks of leadership.</p>
<p>But coddling and stroking the threatened will not prevent the growth of right-wing extremism in the United States or Germany, nor do these fears warrant more than brief validation. Fear may be legitimate, but it is neither productive nor is it right. For the hearts of white men may be broken. But so are the bodies of too many women. And so are the lives of too many refugees.</p>
<p>&#8211; By <strong><em>Kelly Miller</em></strong></p>
<p>*I use the term &#8220;asylum applicants&#8221; throughout this text in reference to the different terms of status and legitimacy granted those fleeing conflict, persecution, and poverty, explained thoroughly, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/04/30/refugees-welcome-local-interventions-for-an-eu-dilemma/">here</a>, in my article on refugee status in Germany.</p>
<p>**Asylum applicants refer to precisely that: individuals who do not yet hold UNHCR (official) refugee status, but are seeking this status through the adjudication process of the country for which they are applying for asylum. Germany evaluates the &#8220;believability&#8221; or plausibility of each applicant&#8217;s claim to political and personal persecution endangering their life. This process once took years, has now been largely accelerated to operate a revolving door, moving those out who do not meet asylum requirements and moving those in who wish to submit an application.</p>
<p>The source for the social media quotes was initially this <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/cologne-attacks-trigger-raw-debate-on-immigration-in-germany-a-1071175.html">excellent article at Spiegel Online</a>, which was verified by a bit of my own digging. Continue to follow the discussion on twitter, by searching &#8220;#ausnahmslos&#8221; or &#8220;#koeln&#8221;. The field and its actors are sure to shift further in the coming months.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: Four Hours at Lageso</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2015 00:01:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bureaucracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moabit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4145</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is Lageso (Das Landesamt für Gesundheit und Soziales), the State Office for Health and Social Affairs. This is Berlin's primary registration center for the initial reception of asylum seekers. This is Germany's most infamous symbol of the refugee crisis. Two days prior I had signed up to volunteer on a website called Volunteer Planner. After a cursory registration process, a click of a button was all it took to commit to a shift at a registration center, refugee home, or other institution in the city where help is needed (read: basically everywhere).  ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4323 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-650x319.png" alt="boys_lageso" width="650" height="319" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-650x319.png 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-300x147.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>A curly-haired two year old hangs from my hip. His modest number of pounds start to wear on my side as I spin us back and forth in the narrow space. By some stroke of luck he has yet to start crying (this doesn&#8217;t last). He giggles, bouncing up and down, as if we are playing a game. &#8220;He seems to like you,&#8221; a volunteer next to me looks on and smiles, &#8220;almost like he wants to go home with you.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;He may have to,&#8221; I mutter in response. It has been a long ten minutes since I last saw his mother. I try desperately to remember her face &#8211; or at least the color of her headscarf. My voice starts to crack and I realize in horror a cold is coming on (&#8220;Am I infecting hundreds of refugees?&#8221;). A few minutes later we find her, a pair of black shoes in her hands. She holds them up proudly and points to herself. We are only supposed to be finding clothes for her son and she knows it, but I let her take the shoes and boy (now crying), and go.</p>
<p>Curly-haired boy and his mother are my latest charges from the never-ending mass of parents and children waiting to be accompanied down the hallway of donated clothing. This group is only a microcosm of the larger crowd waiting outside in the evening twilight where volunteers pass out hot tea and coffee. Kids get <em>Kinderschokolade </em>and granola bars. The building entrance is guarded to ensure not everyone infiltrates the chaos at once.</p>
<p>Back inside, a winter jacket and pair of warm shoes are the big prizes. Our chief responsibility is to make sure each child walks out with just one of each. I negotiate with parents: &#8220;She can have that coat, but you&#8217;ll need to give me the one she&#8217;s wearing now.&#8221; When language fails, I make a trading gesture with my hands or remove the jacket from the child&#8217;s back myself. How quickly the urge to be generous is superseded by pragmatism (&#8220;Even <em>I</em> could get by with only one coat&#8221;).</p>
<p>&#8220;You have to be careful,&#8221; a middle-aged female volunteer warns me as I re-fold a stack of jeans, &#8220;Roma families sneak in to take clothing and then sell it at the flea market.&#8221; I nod but am at a loss as to what to do with the information. Is she advocating that we start using racial profiling? Regardless of the Roma, some families may have already taken their turn down the hallway. Others could be successfully registered and in possession of their <a href="http://www.euronews.com/2015/09/16/which-european-countries-offer-the-most-social-benefits-to-migrants/">monthly stipend</a>. There&#8217;s really no way to tell.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4321 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_0599" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Our makeshift shopping strip consists of one narrow hallway and a back room for sorting and storage. On either side of the hallway are smaller rooms the size of coat checks, one holding clothing for adults and the other medicine and hygienic articles. It is very cramped. Fathers plea with volunteers for their family&#8217;s turn down the hallway. Once in, mothers rip clothing off hangers to hold up to their children and approximate size. Some kids are fussy about colors; others peer up with wide eyes and tightly pressed lips. Volunteers buzz by in a flurry of aspired productivity and surveillance, their name-tags as frayed as their nerves.</p>
<p>A cameraman waltzes in with his crew. The bright lens focuses on me as I kneel down to re-velcro a young boy&#8217;s shoes. We have yet to find boots that fit; these blue sandals are the ones in which he arrived to Germany, completely ill-suited for the looming winter. We both turn, squint, and smile anyway. This is the shot they want, and they are gone within the minute.</p>
<p>This is Lageso (<em>Das Landesamt </em><span class="st"><em>für Gesundheit und Soziales)</em>, the State Office for Health and Social Affairs</span>. This is <span class="st">Berlin&#8217;s primary registration center for the initial reception of asylum seekers. This is Germany&#8217;s most infamous symbol of the refugee crisis.</span></p>
<p>Two days prior I had signed up to volunteer on a website called <a href="https://volunteer-planner.org/">Volunteer Planner</a>. After a cursory registration process, a click of a button was all it took to commit to a shift at a registration center, refugee home, or other institution in the city where help is needed (read: basically everywhere).  An impressive resource to get people engaged quickly, though seemingly lacking any accountability for volunteers who fail to show up or for organizations advertising shifts that fall through or no longer exist (the day before I was turned away from a home in Schöneberg because the coordinator was not present).</p>
<p>In addition to locations, one can select specific tasks. This is an all-hands-on-deck scenario and there is something for everyone, from Arabic and Farsi interpretation (in high demand) to kitchen assistance and coffee distribution. At Lageso, I sign up to be a <em>Springer/in </em>or &#8220;Jumper&#8221;, who, according to the website, &#8220;helps wherever is most needed, is assigned to a team, and will be led by hand to their task.&#8221;</p>
<p>But upon arrival I am not assigned to a team nor led anywhere, let alone by hand. After finding a sticker on which to scribble my name, I walk around aimlessly until a smiley blond girl takes pity on me and leads me to the storage room. A few minutes later I am with a new girl who is in a room within this room, sorting through boxes of clothing donations in the dark. I glance at the heaps of dusty sweaters and immediately regret not having brought my allergy medicine.</p>
<p>We start unpacking boxes of blankets. &#8220;Is there somewhere specific we should put these?&#8221; I ask my sorting partner. She shrugs. &#8220;On those shelves, I think,&#8221; she says, pointing to the overstuffed racks behind us. Ten minutes later, another volunteer: &#8220;No, don&#8217;t unpack the blankets,&#8221; he instructs us in a mix of German and English. &#8220;Put them in a corner so we can take them to a refugee home later.&#8221;</p>
<p>I give up on the blankets and turn my attention to the clothes. Thankfully, some boxes are categorized, and I pick up one marked &#8220;children&#8221;. I plan to sort the contents and add them to the shelves, which are loosely organized by gender and size. In one pair of pants I notice a bulge in the pocket and pull out a knife. I pass it along to a guy with a clipboard who looks like he knows what he is doing. He turns and sets it on another shelf, near a box of children&#8217;s toys.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4322 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_0600" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>I&#8217;m finally getting into a groove when another volunteer comes up behind me, visibly frustrated. &#8220;I spent days putting this together and now everyone&#8217;s destroying it,&#8221; she complains to clipboard guy, motioning to the overflowing shelves. He glances up over his glasses. &#8220;We&#8217;ll discuss it at Monday&#8217;s meeting,&#8221; he promises. I don&#8217;t know what I&#8217;ve done wrong, but I am sure of two things: We are all working on top of one another and there is no one in charge.</p>
<p>When the refugee crisis became front page news this past summer, thousands of Germany&#8217;s residents jumped to provide clothing and supplies, offer short-term housing solutions, or pass out sandwiches to refugees as they poured into train stations around the country. Many continue to help, some using vacation days to do so. On a civilian level, the outpouring of support in Germany has been heart-warming, encouraging, even pride-inducing.</p>
<p>Charitable and non-profit initiatives also abound. Groups have launched fundraising efforts to help those in particularly dire situations, like this <a href="https://www.betterplace.org/de/projects/37503-hilfe-fur-familie-ahmed">Iraqi father who suffered a heart attack</a>. There are <a href="http://www.unhcr.org/5655d27f6.html">bike riding lessons</a> for women and <a href="http://www.abendblatt-berlin.de/2015/12/03/ein-zirkus-fuer-die-gute-sache/">circus activities</a> for kids. A local photographer has started a &#8220;<a href="https://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.400616063468410.1073741835.295071407356210&amp;type=3">Humans of Lageso&#8221; page</a> to shed light on individual refugee stories. Herbert Grönemeyer, a famous German singer, has <a href="http://www.stern.de/lifestyle/leute/lageso-in-berlin---herbert-groenemeyer-finanziert-waermebusse-fuer-fluechtlinge-6605406.html">financed heated buses</a> so those waiting to register at Lageso can take turns warming up.</p>
<p><span class="st">But civilian good-will and a display of <span class="st"><em>Willkommenskultur</em></span> (welcome culture) can only go so far in serving the approximately 800,000 asylum seekers that Germany will receive this year &#8211; a figure that is <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/sep/06/refugee-crisis-germany-response-heartwarming-will-pressures-show">more a projection than a guest list</a>. What some in Berlin may call growing pains in learning to accommodate unprecedented waves of refugees, others deem a failure of the system and local leadership. German towns such as Passau, a Bavarian town of 50,000, have cited <a href="http://nmd.bn02750.bethemd.wayport.net/index.adp?MacAddr=68%3aA8%3a6D%3a4B%3a7A%3a8C&amp;IpAddr=10.128.29.239&amp;Ip6Addr=&amp;vsgpId=&amp;vsgId=41975&amp;UserAgent=&amp;ProxyHost=&amp;TunnelIfId=95270&amp;VlanId=20">much more success in handling the inflow</a>.</span></p>
<p><span class="st">The press have reported on the turbulent conditions at Lageso ad nauseam, both locally and <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/11/27/world/europe/germany-berlin-migrants-refugees.html?_r=0">internationally</a>. Refugees wait for weeks if not months to be registered. They line up for hours each day, often beginning the night before. People sleep in the streets. Most don&#8217;t receive enough to eat and drink. Heated tents were only made available <a href="http://www.stilinberlin.de/2015/12/fugeela-refugees-in-berlin-6-html.html">a few days ago</a>. &#8220;Refugee crisis? More like bureaucratic crisis!&#8221; protesters chanted <a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/1678473329031122/">on November 29th</a>, calling the local government to action. Understaffed and overworked employees have anonymously <a href="http://www.rbb-online.de/politik/thema/fluechtlinge/berlin/2015/12/lageso-innenansichten-mitarbeiter.html">detailed the on-going chaos</a> to the press. On December 10th, the Head of Lageso, Franz Allert, was <a href="http://www.focus.de/politik/deutschland/migration-lageso-chef-tritt-zurueck_id_5143744.html">pushed into resignation</a>. </span></p>
<p>Curly-haired boy and his mom are back outside, but at least now with warmer feet and some chocolate in their bellies. I pull my phone out of my pocket: three and a half hours have passed. There isn&#8217;t an eight hour work day in recent memory I can remember having been more exhausting. Admiration for the other volunteers &#8211; many of whom do this regularly, including night shifts &#8211; rushes within me. As does panic. The support is incredible, but is it sustainable?</p>
<p>We need to get this right, and not just in the short-term.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By<strong> Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>For up to date information in English on the refugee situation in Berlin, we recommend reading the <a href="http://www.stilinberlin.de/?s=FuGeeLa">FuGeeLa updates</a> by Stil in Berlin. <a href="http://www.findingberlin.com/how-to-help-refugees-in-berlin-winter-2015/">Finding Berlin</a> also provides comprehensive resources for how to help. </em></p>
<p><em>To sign up for volunteer shifts in Berlin, try <a href="https://volunteer-planner.org/helpdesk/">Volunteer Planner</a> (in German) or look for opportunities through <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">Give Something Back to Berlin</a> (in English). <a href="http://moabit-hilft.com/">MoabitHilft</a> is very engaged at Lageso and many of the regular volunteers at the center are affiliated with this organization.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>If you are donating clothing to refugee homes, please do your best to package them by type (e.g. age and size) and consider buying socks which are often in short supply. Even better: check first with the home to see what is most needed!</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Moralpolitik and the Ressentiments of Change</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 15:35:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4120</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[According to headlines, the German government has pledged haven – albeit temporary in many cases – to up to 800,000 refugees or migrants applying for asylum in the country. The U.S., despite initial wavering, has signaled that it will work to raise its refugee quota yearly, with the goal of a 100,000 cap by 2017. Yet within and around this historical moment of humanitarian crisis and measured political response are the inflammatory words of Donald Trump. He recently roared to a crowd in Iowa that, if elected, he “will deport all of the 11 million illegal migrants in this country.”]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As German and U.S. refugee policies inevitably collide in light of current events, this writer finds herself in the United States. The other writer of this blog will soon be in Germany, taking stock of the so-called “refugee crisis” on the ground. On my side of the Atlantic, a crisis is not yet to be felt… at least not so acutely. This has as much to do with media semantics as it does with history.</p>
<p>According to headlines, the German government has pledged haven – albeit temporary in many cases – <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/aug/20/germany-raises-estimate-refugee-arrivals-800000">to up to 800,000 refugees or migrants applying for asylum in the country</a>. The U.S., despite initial wavering, <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/news/nation/2015/09/20/increase-admission-refugees-kerry-says/fnCweeIlCS8g47VF7VAkBP/story.html">has signaled that it will work to raise its refugee quota</a> yearly, with the goal of a 100,000 cap by 2017. The Pope, as leader of the spiritual state of Catholicism, <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">has planned to make migrants and refugees one of the few central issues of his travels around the Western Hemisphere this week</a>.</p>
<p>All at once, it seems that moral duty, a college ethics course, and politics have fused into one mandate to assist.</p>
<p>Yet within and around this historical moment of humanitarian crisis and measured political response are the inflammatory words of Donald Trump. He recently roared to a crowd in Iowa that, if elected, he “<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">will deport all of the 11 million illegal migrants in this country.</a>” When asked by Univision’s anchor Jorge Ramos how he would accomplish such a feat, he coolly responded, “I’m a great manager.”</p>
<div id="attachment_4127" style="width: 630px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4127" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-4127" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg" alt="Donald Trump immigration" width="620" height="372" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg 620w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP-300x180.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4127" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Charlie Neibergall/AP via <em><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">The Guardian</a></em></p></div>
<p>One can easily get caught up in the absurdity that is the American campaign season, enjoying its theatrics as a harmless part of the celebrity process. But Trump’s words should hold weight, and they should be cause for alarm.</p>
<p>Trump’s message is not as obtuse, as unnecessarily harsh as it might seem; it reflects not only present sentiment but historical precedent… for both the United States and Germany. With the current refugee and migrant crisis, old tensions are slowly and loudly being unearthed. And the mobility of many of the world&#8217;s displaced, traumatized, and poor is not likely to change any time soon.</p>
<p>National Public Radio’s <em>Fresh Air</em> <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/10/439114563/americas-forgotten-history-of-mexican-american-repatriation">recently interviewed</a> one of the scholars behind the book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Decade-Betrayal-Mexican-Repatriation-1930s/dp/0826339735">Decade of Betrayal: Mexican Repatriation in the 1930s</a>”. The volume documents a massive and relentless deportation program at a time when xenophobia and economic distress were rampant. Historians Raymond Rodriguez and Francisco Balderrama document what is nothing short of a terrifying episode in American history – frightening for what right-wing reactionaries in a new age of migration might be capable of.</p>
<p>As Rodriguez shared with <em>Fresh Air</em>’s host, Terry Gross, the 1930s treated Mexican Americans with great malice and abuse. For reason only of their heritage, they were targeted by government programs and private citizens alike. This abuse culminated in the federal government&#8217;s campaign to strip millions of Americans of their citizenship. Not all those rounded up in deportation raids were naturalized citizens, though <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">estimates suggest than ½ of those expelled were</a>. Most were visa-holders of some sort, their only crime having been born a member of a demonized ethnic group.</p>
<p>Governmental programs to round up and expel society’s undesirables often begin in cities, according to history (see the American strategy of Japanese internment or Nazi Germany&#8217;s institution of the urban ghetto). And so Los Angeles was the primary target of the government’s Mexican American deportation program. Largely as a response to the despair the Great Depression had unleashed across the country, officials systematically sent entire families from the L.A. area back to Mexico, with no infrastructure in place to receive them. <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">From 1929 to 1944, 1/3 of L.A.’s Mexican American population was deported</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4128" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4128" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4128" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-650x487.jpg" alt="Los Angeles Mexican Americans 1932" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4128" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Los Angeles Public Library/Herald Examiner Collection via <em><a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">National Public Radio</a></em></p></div>
<p><em>Ressentiments</em> – projection of resentment or fear onto often vulnerable groups in society – were widespread both in the U.S. and in Germany throughout the Great Depression. Xenophobia in the face of severe economic collapse paved the way for Germany’s organized extermination machinery. The U.S.’s internment of Japanese and German citizens, its continued subordination of Black Americans, and its systematic deportation of Mexican Americans demonstrate that this country was in no way spared such a nasty past.</p>
<p>Slowly but surely, such <em>ressentiments</em> have now begun to return. This time, Germany may be more in the right, even despite a few documented attacks on refugee facilities, while America edges closer toward the precipice of wrong.</p>
<p>…</p>
<p>On my side of the ocean, I have arrived into a complicated sector of the nexus of natural diversity and these increasing <em>ressentiments. </em>Vancouver, Washington, where both my parents now live, <a href="http://www.thenation.com/article/browning-america/">is becoming increasingly &#8220;Brown&#8221;</a>. Separated only by a short bridge across the Columbia River, Southwest Washington has become Portland&#8217;s semi-urban/semi-rural extension. Because the northern bank of the river offers families more space for cheaper, better funded schools for fewer private tax dollars, and income tax exemption, immigrants who may have otherwise moved to the Portland, Oregon metro area are now planting themselves on the side of its less expensive neighbor. Portland, as a result, <a href="http://www.oregonlive.com/news/index.ssf/2009/01/in_a_changing_world_portland_r.html">has become increasingly White</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4129" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4129" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4129" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-650x366.jpg" alt="Interstate bridge over the Columbia River, connecting Portland, Oregon and Vancouver, Washington" width="650" height="366" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-650x366.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-300x169.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4129" class="wp-caption-text">Interstate bridge over the Columbia River, connecting Portland, Oregon and Vancouver, Washington</p></div>
<p>According to most recent U.S. census data, Vancouver is now 11% Hispanic, inching closer to the national average. We can expect this number to be much higher in reality, as immigrants will often opt out of participation in the census. There are other ethnic groups represented in Vancouver’s demographic development: For example, 18% of families speak a language other than English at home, and the traditional taco truck has recently seen competition in North African, Japanese, and Thai flavors.</p>
<p>None of this would seem all that significant, if I were not writing about a traditionally conservative county, with once sprawling farm land and a historical military base; a county that has now been converted into a rare blend of suburban developments, strip malls, urbane boutiques, and miles and miles of regional road. The nickname of &#8220;Van-tucky&#8221;* &#8211; something I have only heard used on the other side of the water, mind you &#8211; might tell you all you need to know.</p>
<p>The rate of poverty in Vancouver is also higher than the national average. Vancouver&#8217;s mayor recently <a href="http://www.cityofvancouver.us/ced/page/affordable-housing-task-force">launched a task force</a> to investigate the cause of growing homelessness, rising rents, and increased demand for housing in the city’s most accessible and commercially viable areas. Serving as Portland’s &#8220;bedroom community&#8221; brings with it numerous tax and transportation disadvantages, as well, such as costly inter-city transit for a significant commuter population and bridges nationally notorious for being structurally unsound.</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p>In a brand-new cocktail bar in downtown Vancouver, which serves only locally-distilled (read artisanal) spirits, I sip my smoky-cucumber-tequila mixture and listen in on the interaction between the unlikely combination of guests who have just joined me on the patio. Three White bikers &#8211; two older women with smokers&#8217; cough and one machismo with a mustache &#8211; scoff at the price of their beer. Across from them at a nearby table, two women in their mid-20s, both with long black hair, one who speaks English with an accent.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-4130" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-650x366.jpg" alt="cocktail Vancouver, Washington" width="650" height="366" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-650x366.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-300x169.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Older veterans and cowboy-like characters are scattered across Vancouver’s downtown like curated remains of what was once here. They drink Rainier out of cans &#8211; Washington State’s Pabst Blue Ribbon with more local charm &#8211; and chain smoke in the park. They inhabit the dive bars with names like &#8220;Lounge&#8221; and antique neon advertisements. It seems that establishments like this new artisanal cocktail bar threaten to upset a tender balance between familiarity, comfort, and growth.</p>
<p>“$4! Bullshit”, one of the women hollers. The two younger ladies nudge their shoulders closer together, in order to continue a conversation disrupted by the boom of our three new patio companions.</p>
<p>The machismo turns toward the young women’s table, putting his hand on one of their legs. “Where you from, honey?&#8221;, he begins his monologue, &#8220;I’m a native, been here for more than 20 years, Detroit before that. You know how much this place has changed?”</p>
<p>Neither responds; however, the one whose leg is playing host to the man’s hand begins to shift uncomfortably.</p>
<p>&#8220;Where you from honey? You aren&#8217;t from around here, I can tell you that!&#8221;, one of the older women yells between sips from her can. “When did Rainier get this damn expensive? It’s bullshit, $4! I’ll tell you something…”</p>
<p>One of the young, dark-haired women flashes machismo a smile. &#8220;I&#8217;m from Panama!&#8221;, she says, and extends her hand for a shake. He takes it and squeezes it, returning both their hands to the table.</p>
<p>“I’m American, from here&#8221;, the other woman says, her leg now turned as far away from his body as the chair allows.</p>
<p>&#8220;But where are your parents from then?&#8221;, machismo asks with a chuckle. &#8220;That&#8217;s what I&#8217;m asking, ain&#8217;t it?&#8221;</p>
<p>She concedes, but stands to use the restroom (or simply disappear into the building) as she does: &#8220;Well, I&#8217;m Filipino.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p><em>Ressentiments</em> toward the Other can begin and fester in spaces of socioeconomic change. With President Obama’s pledge to take in 100,000 refugees, the question becomes “How will this country prepare its citizens to engage respectfully and kindly with members of a majority Muslim country?” The first step in this process is realizing that we have a lot of work to do, and we need politicians who will help us get there.</p>
<p>Germany has seen a fair share of reporting on the readiness of its population to open its arms to newcomers. It is easy to draw parallels to the past, particularly to Germany’s track record in <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/20/441732811/in-germany-migrants-find-footing-but-also-some-resistance">failing to integrate its guest-worker population and in promoting ethnic-based citizenship until it was almost too late</a>. However, it is Germany the rest of the world now looks to in awe &#8211; for choosing a kind of <em>moralpolitik</em> over patterns of the past.</p>
<p>Being so far away from a society I sometimes feel I know more about than my own (society of origin), I can’t help but beam with pride in watching small towns across Germany distribute clean clothes, socks, new toys, children’s books, and warm meals to the thousands of human beings in need who have crossed their borders. Nevertheless, Germany has since issued temporary border controls. Order still wins out over populist charity.</p>
<p>But aiming for a collective solution to the continuous stream of migrants and refugees into Europe, German leaders have worked to reach agreement upon a refugee quota for EU member states. Just this Tuesday this quota became a provisional reality.</p>
<p>Time will tell if all members comply, and if a sense of moral duty is really as strong as images of kind citizens touting bags of donations suggest. Yet I do have the sense that with each step toward welcoming the Other, <em>ressentiments</em> have fewer chances of surviving. When demonstrations of kindness are just so strong, so publicly undeniable, that Trump-esque hate can find no oxygen for its fire.</p>
<p>That is what I hope for America.</p>
<p>At the moment, the U.S. remains crippled and complicated by its multi-layered fears of all the regions of the world it has wronged. As UN Ambassador <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/23/442761552/10-000-syrian-refugees-just-the-floor-of-u-s-effort-says-ambassador-power">Samantha Power made clear in an NPR interview recently</a>, the country is not ready to simply do the right thing; it has to be a calculated response, taking security into account.</p>
<p>Overcoming fear is America&#8217;s consistent and stubborn challenge. I just hope the mistakes of the 1930s can mean something.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*Van-tucky is a reference to the southern state of Kentucky, the unofficial home of fried-chicken and horse races.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: &#8220;I&#8217;m a Human Being&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 11:21:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Austria]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[family]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Taiwan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vienna]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4019</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Vienna. Seat of the former Austro-Hungarian Empire. Widely considered the gateway to Eastern Europe. Home to a United Nations headquarters and numerous international companies and universities. The Austrian capital has long been a city of immigration – even when politics have told a different story – and a staggering 50% of the population has what’s referred to as a “migration background”. So it’s not as if I expected Vienna to not be multicultural...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_4028" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4028" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4028 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-650x581.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender" width="650" height="581" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-650x581.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-300x268.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender.jpg 728w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4028" class="wp-caption-text">Sophia, Christina, and Suzi at the 2015 Vienna Pride Parade</p></div>
<p>Vienna. Seat of the former Austro-Hungarian Empire. Widely considered the gateway to Eastern Europe. Home to a United Nations headquarters and numerous international companies and universities. The Austrian capital has long been a city of immigration – even when politics have told a different story – and a staggering <a href="https://www.wien.gv.at/english/social/integration/basic-work/facts-figures.html">50% of the population</a> has what’s referred to as a “migration background”.</p>
<p>So it’s not as if I expected Vienna to <em>not</em> be multicultural.</p>
<p>What I didn’t expect when <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/03/23/lens-on-leaving-homes/">moving to Vienna from Berlin</a> was to encounter some of the most fascinating “mixes” of my life: A half-Indian, half-Italian who grew up in the US and lives in Vienna with her half-Austrian, half-French boyfriend? A Chinese-American who fell in love with her German boyfriend in Hong Kong? A half-Austrian, half-Sicilian who met her Indian husband in London? The combinations are unexpected, beautiful, and dare I say, collidoscopic? (And their potential future children even more so).</p>
<div id="attachment_4031" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4031" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4031 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-650x475.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(3)" width="650" height="475" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-650x475.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-300x219.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4031" class="wp-caption-text">Christina poses with a cow in Austria on a family roadtrip</p></div>
<p>Christina, the first close friend I made in Vienna, is no different. Born in Taiwan to a Taiwanese mother and Austrian father, at age three her family moved to San Jose, California, where her younger brother was born. Kindergarten was spent in Vienna, where she lived with her father and grandparents while mom and brother stayed in the US. At age six the entire family moved to Taiwan for four years. Then it was back west to Seattle from ages 10-16 where Christina spent the longest stretch of her childhood, what she calls her &#8220;most formative years&#8221;. Her last two years of high school were completed in Taipei, where she graduated with the globally recognized International Baccalaureate Diploma.</p>
<p>“I was missing roots as a kid, our family was always bouncing around,&#8221; she tells me.</p>
<p>This triangular ping ponging between nations resulted in three different passport combinations within a family of four: Christina’s brother, born in the US, is a dual Austrian-American citizen but “avoids Austria now because of the mandatory military service.” Mom is dual Taiwanese-Austrian, “but never felt completely comfortable in Austria”. And Christina and her father are purely Austrian, on paper anyway.</p>
<p>&#8220;A long time ago my dad had the chance to become an American citizen but decided against it,&#8221; she says smirking, &#8220;He&#8217;s a proud Austrian.”</p>
<div id="attachment_4057" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4057" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4057 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_9365" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4057" class="wp-caption-text">Christina with her parents in Taiwan</p></div>
<p>It is to her father and his “pride” that Christina attributes her last 16 years in Vienna. &#8220;My dream was to go to Georgetown [University],&#8221; Christina tells me one warm evening in the <em>Museumsquartier</em>, her fingers tapping the stem of her <em>Hugospritz</em>. &#8220;I applied and got in… my mom supported it, but my dad kept saying I had to go to university in Austria. It was always really important to him that, as the oldest child, I embrace my Austrian roots.&#8221;</p>
<p>Christina ended up moving to Vienna against her will: “I didn&#8217;t have any connection to Austria at that time other than having spent the occasional summer there with my grandparents.” The first year, she expressed her anger by skipping class in favor of exploring the city and having fun.</p>
<p>“And then I got pregnant,” she says laughing, “the biggest rebellion of all!”</p>
<div id="attachment_4059" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4059" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4059 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371-650x650.jpg" alt="IMG_9371" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4059" class="wp-caption-text">Mother-daughter surfing trip in Morocco</p></div>
<p>Christina’s daughter Illeana (Illy) was born when she was 20. She raised Illy as a single mother while completing her degrees in Economics and Sinology, with “lots of help” from friends with similar bi-cultural backgrounds. She counts half-Austrian friends from South Africa and Bolivia among her closest, along with a half-Kosovan, half-Czech hair salon owner named Suzi. “None of us knew what we were doing… it was experimental parenting. I think if I raised a child now I’d be much more nervous!”</p>
<p>After making it over the hump of her first year, Vienna started to feel like home. “I began to realize how much I love it here,” Christina reflects. Now one could say Christina is as Austrian as they come. Her German is flawless and chock full of colloquialisms, she sings along to Austrian <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schlager_music">Schlager</a></em>, and her drink of choice is the ubiquitous <em><a href="http://austrianwineusa.com/2013/12/20/12-days-of-austrian-wine-enjoy-a-gspritzer/">Weisser Spritzer</a></em>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4064" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4064" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4064 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-650x602.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(7)" width="650" height="602" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-650x602.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-300x278.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7.jpg 701w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4064" class="wp-caption-text">Christina skiing in Kaprun, Austria</p></div>
<p>None of that, however, stops her from craving Taiwanese ‘Three-Cups Chicken’ or her favorite American cereal, ‘Lucky Charms’. “I’m biracial and tri-cultural,” she states without hesitation. And while rewarding on personal and professional levels (she’s also fluent in Mandarin), Christina’s background has not gone unchallenged in a city that still struggles to see itself as a place of migration and diversity.</p>
<p>Christina has encountered countless variations of the “<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/">But where are you <em>really</em> from?</a>” question over the years. “When I first got to Vienna, there were fewer minorities and diversity didn&#8217;t work very well,” she remarks, “I remember meeting one guy who could not comprehend why I looked the way I did but had a very common German last name,&#8221; she rolls her eyes at the memory. &#8220;I literally had to spell it out for him by saying, &#8216;If you, an Austrian, had a baby with a Taiwanese woman, the result would be me!’”</p>
<div id="attachment_4034" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4034" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4034 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-650x488.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(6)" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4034" class="wp-caption-text">Christina&#8217;s 3rd Birthday in Los Angeles, California</p></div>
<p>This phenomenon isn’t limited to Vienna. In Japan, a newly crowned biracial beauty queen has been fielding questions on a regular basis about what parts of her are “Japanese”. <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/30/world/asia/biracial-beauty-queen-strives-for-change-in-mono-ethnic-japan.html">“But I am a Japanese,”</a> is her response. On the other side of the world, in the US, Rachel Dolezal was recently exposed for her elaborate deception as a Black woman – a &#8220;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/18/opinion/charles-blow-the-delusions-of-dolezal.html?smid=fb-share">one-directional privilege</a>&#8221; that could never have been successful the other way around, due to socially constructed perceptions of race. The recurring theme? If you are one drop of minority, we will question your Belonging to the majority.</p>
<p>Christina acknowledges that even she is not immune to societal attitudes about migrants in Austria. &#8220;I&#8217;ve learned that, in Austria, migrants get classified into &#8216;good&#8217; and &#8216;bad&#8217;,&#8221; she explains.</p>
<p>&#8220;Asians are considered ‘good’ because they’re quiet, stay out of trouble, and work hard. Turkish people are unpopular because a lot of them refuse to adapt to the Austrian way of life and bring hordes of family members over, all the while claiming benefits from the Austrian government. Blacks have it the worst, though, probably because they stand out the most and are still viewed by many locals as low-lifes and drug dealers.&#8221;</p>
<div id="attachment_4029" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4029" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4029 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-650x472.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(1)" width="650" height="472" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-650x472.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-300x218.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4029" class="wp-caption-text">Christina riding a (fake) bull at Glacier National Park, Montana</p></div>
<p>While Christina is well aware that the US has its own challenges regarding diversity, she does view it as more progressive: “In the US, people at least get it when you tell them that you&#8217;re biracial.”</p>
<p>It was 1999 when Christina was last in the US, before Illy&#8217;s birth and before the 9/11 attacks. While she’s now seriously considering a move back, it&#8217;s unclear when she will be able to. Christina is not a US citizen and needs a green card. Her most recent attempt at the <a href="http://travel.state.gov/content/visas/english/immigrate/diversity-visa/instructions.html">Diversity Visa Lottery</a> was unsuccessful. “My dad told me he is reconsidering becoming an American citizen just so that he can help get us over there,” Christina recently shared. <a href="http://www.migrationpolicy.org/article/family-reunification">Family reunification</a> is one of the four major pathways for foreigners to become legal residents of the US.</p>
<p>Legal challenges are also not Christina’s only concern. “Sometimes I worry that people in the US will annoy me with their ignorance,” she says laughing. At the same time, she is drawn to the lifestyle. She observes her American friends move to houses with pools, which, compared to Viennese city apartments, seem like mansions. Illy, a recovering Justin Bieber addict who recently graduated to a One Direction obsession, is thrilled with the prospect. “A typical Austrian teenager,” Christina chuckles.</p>
<p>You could call Christina many things: A transnational, an immigrant, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">a third-culture kid</a>, a foreigner, a native, an expat. But none of these categories really fit given the fluidity of her upbringing and identity. We use labels to establish connections and try to make sense of things, but they can also dilute the intricacy and beauty of reality.</p>
<p>&#8220;I&#8217;m not 100% of anything,&#8221; is how Christina describes it. &#8220;Sometimes when people ask what I am, I just answer that I&#8217;m a human being.&#8221;</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Photos provided by Christina and Sophia.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Refugees Welcome: Local Interventions for an EU Dilemma</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/04/30/refugees-welcome-local-interventions-for-an-eu-dilemma/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/04/30/refugees-welcome-local-interventions-for-an-eu-dilemma/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 13:04:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[European Union]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3965</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This article is intended to inform, as well as to encourage advocacy and action. As any seasoned volunteer or activist knows, engagement relies heavily on context, identifying not only how to get involved but why and in which capacity, based on the complex landscape of need one encounters.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Saturday, the 18th of April, a small fishing vessel capsized off the coast of Libya on its way to one of the European Union’s coastal states. On its way, it passed through waters patrolled by the European Union&#8217;s security agency, Frontex. Its demise was quick, only 28 passengers were rescued; an estimated 900 are said to have perished. Of the dead, roughly 200 had had little chance of escape, locked securely in the ship&#8217;s hull by the smugglers commissioned with their passage. A similar event had made headlines just the Sunday before: 400 dead in the water. Yet even more sobering is the UN&#8217;s projected number of migrant deaths by the end of 2015: <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/italy/11548995/Mediterranean-migrant-crisis-hits-Italy-as-EU-ministers-meet-live.html">approximately 30,000</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_3993" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3993" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3993 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-650x488.jpg" alt="Essen_ProAsyl" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3993" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Pro Asyl</p></div>
<p>Although this tally of the dead got its start long ago, both the number and its surrounding political situation seem to be escalating at an alarming rate. It is possible that this escalation is, in part, due to the quick reporting the digital-age affords a global readership. But, given the current death toll and its greater context of inter-regional instability, one thing seems fairly certain: If safer pathways for migration to the European Union continue to remain restricted or inaccessible to many, the intersecting lines of risk and desperation will continue to make safety subordinate to a chance at what is (presented as) a better life.</p>
<p>Yet the most immediate and real consequence of these reports of danger leading to disaster may not be deterrence but desensitization: The drowned and discarded may begin to shock a little less with each headline, and, worse yet, public support for the displaced &#8211; in our communities, off our shores, and even in those far-off lands to which our governments sell arms in exchange for cheap manufactured goods (an oversimplification of the global balance of trade, of course, but the point remains a valid one) &#8211; may wane.</p>
<p>But this doesn&#8217;t have to be the case. This article is intended to inform, as well as to encourage advocacy and action. As any seasoned volunteer or activist knows, engagement relies heavily on context, identifying not only how to get involved but why and in which capacity, based on the complex landscape of need one encounters. And so, I will first offer a summary of information I find important in creating this context, beginning with an understanding of Germany&#8217;s position in the asylum system of the European Union and followed by an unpacking of certain terms and categories. The latter is not meant to distinguish between and thus arrange various grades of human value based on one&#8217;s reasons for migration; rather, examining these categories is an attempt to identify and elucidate the different contours and sites of vulnerability to be found in refugee and immigrant advocacy, with navigating such categories being crucial to successful support. The most important bit follows these term-laden sections &#8211; namely, a list of ways to get involved in Berlin housing facilities and neighborhood support centers for asylum-applicants. Some options for digital activism and direct actions around Germany will also be included for our readers further afield.</p>
<p>In the end, my hope is to transform this article into a helpful resource page for the <em>Collidoscope</em> webpage. Thus feedback on ways to improve its information and add to or amend its list of opportunities for involvement is greatly appreciated!</p>
<p><strong>Asylum in the EU and refugee status in Germany: an overview</strong></p>
<p>It is helpful to continue with numbers as a means of illustrating the magnitude of the situation (despite my preference for qualitative vs. purely quantitative data &#8211; for which this blog tends to be a perfect example). In 2014, Germany housed approximately 173,000 applicants for asylum, an increase of 192% from the previous year. By the end of 2015, upwards of 300,000 applicants for asylum are projected to enter and remain temporarily in the country [source: <a href="http://www.bamf.de/DE/Infothek/Statistiken/Asylzahlen/asylzahlen-node.html">BAMF</a>]. Despite its shock-value, this remains a small number in the grand scheme of immigration flows. Relative to the asylum policies of the other G-20 countries, however, this is a significant number. The United States, for example, processed 121,000 asylum claims in 2014, a country with four times the population of Germany [source: <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/europe/new-migration-crisis-overwhelms-european-refugee-system/2015/04/21/3ab83470-e45c-11e4-ae0f-f8c46aa8c3a4_story.html">Washington Post</a>].</p>
<p>This does not mean that all claims and their applicants are granted residency in Germany. In fact, most are rejected, resulting in deportation either once a decision has been reached or in a temporary stay of inevitable deportation. Only 24% were granted refugee status in 2014, which excludes a guarantee of permanent status, i.e. returning &#8220;status-refugees&#8221; to their countries of origin once conflicts can be said to be resolved. Last year, only 1.8% received the coveted gift of permanent asylum [source: <a href="http://www.bamf.de/SharedDocs/Anlagen/DE/Publikationen/Broschueren/broschuere-bundesamt-in-zahlen-2014-asyl.pdf?__blob=publicationFile">BAMF</a>].</p>
<p>Nevertheless, 2014&#8217;s final tally of approximately 34,000 accepted refugees indicates a lag in the participation of other EU member states, such as the Netherlands, Poland, or Ireland, not to mention the strange and ineffective logic behind the so-called Dublin III convention*. As the commissioner for the German federal agency for migration and refugees, Aydan Özoguz, commented just last week: “The European asylum system doesn’t work. Some countries are doing very little. We are one of the richest countries and we want to help, but it’s not okay that Germany, Sweden and France are taking 50 percent of the refugees, while other countries do nothing” [source: <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/europe/new-migration-crisis-overwhelms-european-refugee-system/2015/04/21/3ab83470-e45c-11e4-ae0f-f8c46aa8c3a4_story.html">Washington Post</a>].</p>
<p>EU leaders met just last week in an emergency summit to discuss changes to this increasingly dysfunctional system. Given Germany&#8217;s position as home to the greatest number of asylum-applicants, decisions made here set both the moral and practical tone for the other states in the European Union&#8217;s common asylum system &#8211; an infrastructure guided less by comprehensive agreements and more by a few select rules. At the summit&#8217;s conclusion, leaders agreed to invest more money in rescue efforts: more boats and life-vests for the Mediterranean. But what of more legal, safe pathways into the European Union?</p>
<p>Over the last few days, arguments have been made for a reform to the immigration policies that prevent potential workers from entering the country by legal means, unrelated to the conditions for asylum but also free from the ardor of submitting a claim and waiting years for a decision. <a href="http://www.iwkoeln.de/presse/interviews/beitrag/michael-huether-in-der-welt-iw-fordert-mehr-fluechtlinge-fuer-deutschen-arbeitsmarkt-223062">According to the Institut für deutsche Wirtschaft</a> (IW), one in five asylum-applicants has a college degree and one in three are skilled in some trade or another. With German industry&#8217;s sustained calls for increased immigration (to compensate for an aging or less technically-skilled population), providing a more accelerated pathway to a safe life in Germany for those migrants who qualify, while meeting the utilitarian imperative of the political establishment, seems like a win-win. Traditional asylum and provisions for refugees would not be eliminated, by any means, but the number of migrants from poor or conflict-ridden countries would be allowed to increase, saving many the eventual rejection most asylum-applicants face once they arrive in Europe, if they are lucky enough to survive the journey (see the <a href="http://heindehaas.blogspot.de/2015/04/let-their-people-drown-how-eu.html">recent appeal from social scientist Hein de Haas</a> for more on this argument).</p>
<p>However, as is often the case in coordinated responses to humanitarian need, calculations of domestic burden vs. benefit will dominate. And an end to these calculations is nowhere in sight. That is to say, if we wait for political change, we may be waiting at a high opportunity cost &#8211; that of everyday advocacy for and support of the displaced. But first, categories&#8230;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Refugee&#8221; or &#8220;asylum-seeker&#8221;?</strong></p>
<p>The distinction between those with refugee status and those who have submitted an application for asylum (referred to as &#8220;asylum-applicant&#8221; thus far) is an important one, as it helps to explain the origins and role of the <em>Flüchtlingsheim</em> (state-sponsored but privately-run housing facility for asylum-applicants) in the everyday landscape of German towns and cities, including Berlin. Of course, the implementation of national asylum law can vary state by state, given Germany&#8217;s federal balance of power; Saxony, Bavaria, and Berlin may differ in the scope and quantity of services provided to asylum-applicants residing in each state&#8217;s respected <em>Flüchtlingsheime,</em> for example,<em> </em>as this <a href="http://www.proasyl.de/de/news/detail/news/pro_asyl_studie_zur_unterbringung_von_fluechtlingen_in_deutschland/">study</a> demonstrates. But, in all cases, the foundation of German asylum law is built on a differentation between those whose claims have been adjudicated (decided by a judge in German administrative court) and those who have filed claims but are awaiting a decision, assigning different rights and restrictions to these different groups, accordingly. The most important rights and restrictions are those affecting the freedom of movement and activity for those migrants to fall in the &#8220;asylum-applicant&#8221; category. They are as follows:</p>
<p>&#8211; Asylum-applicants are generally not allowed to work until they receive formal status: either as a &#8220;refugee&#8221; (a temporary status, in most cases), as an &#8220;asylee&#8221; (long-term or permanent status), or as a &#8220;tolerated person&#8221; (<em>Geduldete</em>). There are, of course, some exceptions to this rule; for example, asylum-applicants in Berlin and Brandenburg are allowed to pursue employment one year after their application has been submitted, though this work allowance remains heavily restricted and qualified. This means that, in general, asylum-applicants are not able to provide for themselves, thereby becoming fully dependent on the services financed by the federal government, the respective state, and third-parties responsible for service provision. The housing facility system of the <em>Flüchtlingsheim</em> was established both to meet the need for accommodation and to enforce this ban on employment.</p>
<p>&#8211; Up until January of this year, all asylum-applicants were to remain in the state and district either in which they had applied for asylum or to which they had been assigned. They were not able to determine this geographical location or the particular facility in which they would live, even in the case of friends or relatives already in the country. These rules for residency and domicile make up the German system of <em>Residenzpflicht.</em> According to the organization Pro Asyl, <a href="http://www.proasyl.de/de/themen/basics/basiswissen/rechte-der-fluechtlinge/bewegungsfreiheit/residenzpflicht/">these restrictions have been partially lifted</a>. It is unclear, however, to what extent the residency requirement will be relaxed. And as with any policy reform, there will certainly be a lag in public officials and bureaucrats implementing changes. In other words, asylum-applicants may still be prohibited (by staff and local enforcement personnel) from leaving their assigned district, and limits to mobility may still be decided on a state-by-state and case-by-case basis.</p>
<p>&#8211; Residents of <em>Flüchtlingsheime</em> are frequently re-distributed to prevent over-crowding and to maintain an equitable distribution of the financial burden, relative to each state&#8217;s population and economic situation. The freedom of movement, which the abolition of <em>Residenzpflicht </em>may have provided, is overruled and/or overshadowed by this re-distribution mandate.</p>
<p>&#8211; Once asylum-applicants have received a decision from the judge &#8211; the time between the initial filing of the application, the hearing, and the eventual decision often proving to be a year-long ordeal -, those without status granted are either returned to their country of origin (often within a few months of the decision) or are given a <i>Duldung</i>, becoming a &#8220;tolerated person&#8221; for as long as the state deems their return difficult (e.g. in the case of illness, psychological distress, age, family relations, financial situation in the country of origin). <em>Geduldete</em> are free to seek employment and live among the general population, securing their own housing, albeit within the town/city of their asylum-application. But, in most cases, they are not entitled to the same social services as those with refugee status and can be deported at any time, particularly in the case of a minor infraction.</p>
<p>These terms serve to complicate the issue of refugees and the work of refugee advocacy, as various levels of status and treatment before the law are at play. In my opinion, when the media and public discourse fail to make these distinctions, the complexity of the issue and its effect on the experience of real human beings is side-lined to a language that prefers the simplicity of pure humanitarianism &#8211; a moral outlook recognized neither by German law-makers nor by the structures of the European Union. In simple terms, those crossing the Mediterranean and those living in close quarters in Berlin&#8217;s many <em>Flüchtlingsheime </em>are not all &#8220;refugees&#8221;. If they were, they would receive the humane treatment popular opinion affords them.</p>
<div id="attachment_3994" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3994" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3994 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind-650x650.jpg" alt="Deichkind" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3994" class="wp-caption-text">German pop group Deichkind; Source: <a href="https://instagram.com/p/0tB_FivQxn/">Instagram</a></p></div>
<p>Yet, when we acknowledge that it is precisely because of the precarity of their status that they need our help, the situation looks much different. And local interventions in the experience of this precarity become most important, beyond #refugeeswelcome.</p>
<p><strong>How to help</strong></p>
<p>A few weeks ago I visited a new housing facility for asylum-applicants in Reinickendorf, one of the northernmost districts of Berlin. In an idyllic setting, surrounded by pine and quiet residential streets, a former High School has been converted into a 300 bed hostel for migrants awaiting status. The space is rudimentary but well-organized, staff making do with donated toys and German courses, among other diverse activities, as a means to entertain the many children &#8211; many of whom have been waiting for more than two months to enroll in the local school. The staff &#8211; about 10 in number &#8211; communicate with residents in what seems to be a mix of German, English, French, and enthusiastic signage. There is an artist working on the aesthetic revitalization of the place &#8211; literally making the dark halls of a High School a place that feels like home for its residents. There are social workers and psychologists who visit on occasion. Basic meals are catered three times a day on a set schedule. &#8220;House Rules&#8221; are posted in various languages in the foyer. And security guards patrol the grounds, which are clearly the remains of a once vibrant schoolyard, complete with a basketball court (nets partially intact) and a covered concrete playground for jumping rope and hopscotch. We chat about setting up in-house cooking activities, to bring residents and staff closer together, and about using the open space to start a garden, giving the families an opportunity to build and realize a strenuous but rewarding project, even harvest its fruits. The plans are piece-meal and heavily reliant on donations and organizational finesse. In many ways, it is simply about showing up (a familiar mantra), trying to be of help, and deferring to the staff who are there throughout the week trying to make the facility a better place for all who live there.</p>
<p>There are more than 40 facilities just like this one across Berlin, housing upwards of 11,000 asylum-applicants. <a href="http://www.morgenpost.de/berlin/article139453814/Senat-baut-36-neue-Fluechtlingsheime-in-Berlin.html">36 more facilities just like them are planned</a> for the end of 2015. The need is great, but so is this city. Here is a list of established groups across Berlin who work directly with <em>Flüchtlingsheime </em>like the one mentioned above; all of these organizations are certainly eager for new volunteers:</p>
<p>Flüchtlingsinitiative Klausener Platz [evagoemuesay(at)gmail.com]</p>
<p><a href="https://hellersdorfhilft.wordpress.com/">Hellersdorf hilft e.V.</a></p>
<p>Initiative Grenzen weg Hellersdorf [grenzenweg(at)gmx.de]</p>
<p><a href="http://www.wir-netzwerk.de/">Willkommen in Reinickendorf</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.willkommensbuendnis-steglitz-zehlendorf.de/">Willkommensbündnis für Flüchtlinge Steglitz-Zehlendorf</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.lichtenbergerbuendnis.de/">Lichtenberger Bündnis für Demokratie und Toleranz</a></p>
<p><a href="https://bunterwind.wordpress.com/">Bunter Wind für Lichtenberg</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.willkommen-im-westend.de/">Willkommen im Westend &#8211; Refugees Welcome</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.zentrum-für-demokratie.de/">Netzwerk für Flüchtlinge in Treptow-Köpenick</a></p>
<p><a href="http://multitude_tk@riseup.net">Multitude Gruppe Köpenick</a> (for German speakers only &#8211; German language instruction)</p>
<p><a href="https://arbeitsgruppefluchtundmenschenrechte.wordpress.com/">Arbeitsgruppe Flucht und Menschenrechte Treptow-Köpenick</a></p>
<p><a href="http://uffmucken-schoeneweide.de/">Initiative &#8220;Uffmucken Schöneweide&#8221;</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.buendnis-neukoelln.de/">Bündnis Neukölln</a></p>
<p><a href="http://fluechtlingshilfe@britzerinitiative.de">Aktionsbündnis Flüchtlingshilfe Britz</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.multitude-berlin.de/">Initiative Multitude e.V.</a> (for German speakers only &#8211; German language instruction in Spandau, Westend, Lichtenberg, Marzahn, Prenzlauer Berg)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.pankow-hilft.de/">Willkommensnetzwerk &#8220;Pankow Hilft!&#8221;</a> (Pankow, Prenzlauer Berg, Weissensee, Buch)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Fl%C3%BCchtlinge-willkommen-in-Buch-und-Karow/1481160482158156">Flüchtlinge willkommen in Buch und Karow</a></p>
<p><a href="http://u_strassburger@posteo.de">Unterstützer_innenkreis Flüchtlingsunterkunft Prenzlauer Berg</a></p>
<p>Initiative &#8220;Wedding Hilft&#8221; [wedding.hilft(at)gmail.com]</p>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/moabithilft">Initiative &#8220;Moabit Hilft&#8221;</a></p>
<p><a href="http://neuenachbarschaft.wordpress.com/">Initiative &#8220;Neue Nachbarschaft Moabit&#8221;</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.willkommensbuendnis-steglitz-zehlendorf.de/">Willkommensbündnis für Flüchtlinge in Steglitz-Zehlendorf</a></p>
<p><a href="http://bglbb.blogsport.de/">Bündnis gegen Lager Berlin-Brandenburg</a></p>
<p><a href="http://asylstrikeberlin.wordpress.com/">Oranienplatz</a></p>
<p>For those without immediate time to spare but keen on staying informed on actions and opportunities as they develop, track the activities of  the <a href="http://www.fluechtlingsrat-berlin.de/">Flüchtlingsrat-Berlin</a> (the local office of the nation-wide &#8220;refugee council&#8221; model) and <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">GiveSomethingBacktoBerlin</a> (a community platform for volunteer engagement, including frequent posts from groups seeking participants in visits to and on-going projects within <em>Flüchtlingsheime</em>).</p>
<p>Of course, this type of on-site involvement is not for everyone. The type of validation that often comes with structured community engagement projects is not likely to be found here. And, although I am a fan of &#8220;showing up&#8221; and getting one&#8217;s hands dirty, applying pressure on policy-makers and raising awareness to the need for asylum and immigration reform remain incredibly important contributions. Here are a few resources on direct actions and politics-oriented digital activism; these options are great for those further afield who would like to participate in some way, even if just with a click:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/367018126842745,%20http://www.amnesty.de/2015/4/20/massensterben-im-mittelmeer-stoppen-seenotrettung-jetzt">Amnesty International Germany&#8217;s campaign against </a><em><a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/367018126842745,%20http://www.amnesty.de/2015/4/20/massensterben-im-mittelmeer-stoppen-seenotrettung-jetzt">Massensterben im Mittelmeer</a> (</em>flash-mobs and rallies around the offices of Parliament and Executive Government)</p>
<p><a href="http://action.amnesty.de/l/ger/p/dia/action3/common/public/?action_KEY=9703&amp;d=1">#SOSEurope Amnesty International petition</a> (calling upon Merkel&#8217;s government to reform immigration and asylum policy)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.proasyl.de/de/home/seenotrettung-jetzt/">ProAsyl petition</a> (for more EU member-state support of rescue efforts in the Mediterranean)</p>
<p>Donate to the organization <a href="http://www.proasyl.de/de/">Pro Asyl:</a> perhaps the best way to assist the many asylum-applicants residing in Germany and other EU member states by way of a great and highly-effective organization. Pro Asyl coordinates volunteer activities, contributes to accurate reporting and research on asylum in the EU, and offers legal counsel to asylum-applicants, among many other great services.</p>
<p><strong>Why local interventions matter</strong></p>
<p>A <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/media/2015-05-16_EFA-Forschungsbericht_Endfassung.pdf">study</a> was just released by the new <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/">Berlin Institute for Empirical Migration and Integration Research</a>* (BIM) on Berlin-based volunteer engagement  in support of asylum-applicants and resettled refugees. It points to severe deficits in state services for which the unpaid contributions of volunteers strive to remedy. In particular, without the engagement of what the study deems predominately secular, middle-class females, many asylum-applicants would have great difficulty communicating with those agencies charged with the processing and, ultimately, the acceptance or rejection of their claim to refugee status. Additionally, despite the <em>Trägerschaft </em>structure, in which third-party organizations assume partial financial responsibility and full operational responsibility for these housing facilities, many goods and services would otherwise be sorely lacking without the donation-drives and supply deliveries of volunteers. The study describes the especially integral role of volunteers in assisting in the navigation of Germany&#8217;s complex bureaucratic structures: something necessary for immigrants of any sort to successfully remain in the country.</p>
<div id="attachment_3995" style="width: 498px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3995" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3995" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider-488x650.jpg" alt="Source: Pro Asyl" width="488" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider.jpg 488w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider-225x300.jpg 225w" sizes="(max-width: 488px) 100vw, 488px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3995" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Pro Asyl</p></div>
<p>And even the simple opportunity for social interaction, which comes with visits from the outside, can have a great effect on an asylum-applicant&#8217;s success, encouraging language and intercultural skills through everyday relationships that will serve them well in the future. From building the capacity to make one&#8217;s case successfully to a judge to preparing for integration into the local job-market once status, whether temporary or permanent, has been granted, seeing to the wellness of a <em>Flüchtlingsheim&#8217;s </em>residents is a powerful intervention in an often bleak process. In the end, it is the state that decides who may be called a &#8220;refugee&#8221; and who might have a chance at a better life, but volunteers may prove to be one of the deciding factors in who will be welcomed.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>As already mentioned, please submit your comments or write us an email with suggestions or changes, so that this can become a helpful and accurate resource for months to come. And please share with your various networks. The more informed our communities, the better activists we can be!</em></p>
<p>*Technically, certain conventions of the European Union (such as the oft-cited Dublin III agreement) requires that migrants seeking asylum, i.e. refugee status, apply for and receive asylum for the first EU country on which they are said to have set foot. In practice, however, Dublin III is inconsistently enforced, thus allowing asylum-applicants to submit a claim in an economically prosperous country like Germany.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/04/30/refugees-welcome-local-interventions-for-an-eu-dilemma/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: On Leaving Home(s)</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/03/23/lens-on-leaving-homes/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 15:32:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[family]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vienna]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3869</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Last month, Kelly wrote about the implications of "collecting ourselves" to make a move back home. While wrought with complications in its own right, returning to where one grew up, has family, or holds full political and legal rights is a move that Makes Sense. One chapter closes, and however painful or messy, the next begins...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3881 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-650x487.jpg" alt="2014-11-16 13.46.44" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Last month, Kelly wrote about the implications of &#8220;<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/02/13/lens-leaving-berlin/">collecting ourselves</a>&#8221; to make a move back home. While wrought with complications in its own right, returning to where one grew up, has family, or holds full political and legal rights is a move that Makes Sense. One chapter closes, and however painful or messy, the next begins.</p>
<p>After graduate school, I started losing the ability to picture my life in chapters. My decisions were no longer dictated by a series of steps culminating in clear milestones. I suddenly felt accosted by the need to figure out what I wanted to Do and Be&#8230; this time for the long run. And, given my international experiences and dual citizenship, the question of &#8220;What&#8221; promptly extended to one of &#8220;Where&#8221;.</p>
<p>So I moved to Berlin.</p>
<p>When I booked my flight to Germany in fall 2011, &#8220;two years&#8221; was my default timeline. &#8220;A couple years,&#8221; I responded confidently when someone asked how long I planned to be gone. &#8220;I should give the job a good two years,&#8221; I thought when I got hired six months in. &#8220;We&#8217;ll all still be here at least two more years,&#8221; I reassured myself about my circle of expat* friends another six months after that.</p>
<p>How foolish I was, to believe that two years would ever be enough. How <span class="st">naïve</span>,<em> </em>to assume there would be a clear demarcation between this chapter and the next.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3885 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-650x487.jpg" alt="2015-01-31 14.28.03-1" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Now almost three and a half years in, I feel firmly entrenched in my world of bilingual conversations, narrow streets, weekend jaunts around the continent, ubiquitous public transport, social welfare nets, and crusty bread. But these roots of mine are flighty. They wiggle at something as simple as a chat with a friend back home, when she catches me up on her life and I realize how much I&#8217;ve missed. When my sister or father leaves for the airport after a visit, they are pulled halfway out of the earth and end up lodged in the middle of my throat. Every time I get on a plane and head back across the ocean, a part of me fears they will be ripped out entirely. Because no matter how long I stay in Europe and embrace the rights my German passport affords me, I will always also be American. No matter how incredible a life I build for myself on this side of the Atlantic, there will always be a Life Back Home.</p>
<p>I was not aware of how much I had internalized this feeling until last summer, when my mother and I visited relatives in northwestern Germany. Sipping coffee on a sunny terrace, a family friend commented, &#8220;I could never do what you&#8217;re doing, be so far away from my family&#8230; I&#8217;m too close to them.&#8221; My reaction to her declaration was nothing short of primal. Of course I missed my family! Of course I felt close to them! I was not away <em>because</em> of, but rather, <em>in spite of</em> them &#8211; an unpleasant reality I struggle with on a near daily basis.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3892 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-650x518.jpg" alt="11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n" width="650" height="518" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-650x518.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-300x239.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Modern advances in travel and technology have enabled more and more people to adopt lifestyles fueled by wanderlust and adventure. But not all of us who leave home are <a href="http://elitedaily.com/life/culture/wanderlust-like-travel-much-no-real-home/959705/">perpetual wanderers with nomadic spirits</a>. Some of us are searching for somewhere to settle. Some of us are even surprised to find ourselves making a life away from where we grew up, away from the ones we love. I know I am.</p>
<p>I consider myself, by nature, to be a sensitive homebody. I crave being close to the people I love and place great importance on maintaining my relationships, both near and far. This explains why any time I am &#8220;away&#8221;, my pack mentality kicks in and I seek out a local community almost immediately. But I concurrently possess the intrinsic need to push myself and explore. For me, this has meant travel. Whether I credit <a href="https://psychologyblogaimee.wordpress.com/2013/12/04/wanderlust-a-genetic-basis-to-a-globetrotting-fanatic/">genetics</a> for this (nope) or my international upbringing, mixed with a little courage and a lot of privilege (that&#8217;s more like it), is not the point. The ups and downs of living somewhere other than where I grew up have become an integral part of my identity and understanding of growth and independence. They just don&#8217;t make the leaving part any easier.</p>
<p>The thing is, leaving is rarely the easy choice, even with the prospect of Something Great on the other side.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3887 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-650x487.jpg" alt="2015-02-21 16.37.36-1" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>While I never expected moving to Berlin to be easy, I did anticipate a gradual ease, and more importantly, clarity, with time. Reality proved instead to be emphatically non-linear. Rough patches hit me sporadically and without warning. My homesickness became a swelling wave, pulling in and out of shore, threatening at its peak to wash me out entirely. What if this chapter never ended? What if I never left my new home and went back to my old one? And now that I live in Vienna, my current home because of work, is my &#8220;old home&#8221; Washington, DC or Berlin? In countless discussions with fellow expat friends on the topics of home and belonging, the resounding theme has been similar: one of overwhelming choice and uncertainty.</p>
<p>A couple months ago, Kelly and I were at a close friend&#8217;s 30th birthday dinner in Berlin. Huddled in the kitchen over bottles of Spanish Temperanillo and mismatched plates of pizza and crudit<span class="st">és</span>, someone proposed we guess where the birthday boy would be 30 years from now. We had plenty of ideas for the &#8220;What&#8221;: running his own cooking school, teaching his kids how to do science experiments, maintaining his impressive beard. It was on the &#8220;Where&#8221; that we got stuck. &#8220;Italy?&#8221; we posed as the obvious choice (where he&#8217;s from). He resolutely shook his head &#8220;no&#8221;. &#8220;Germany?&#8221; He shrugged his shoulders, unsure &#8211; just like the majority of us in the room about our own futures.</p>
<p>Once you&#8217;ve opened yourself up to the world and seen first-hand that you can live, and maybe even thrive, somewhere else, it becomes increasingly difficult to know when or where to stop searching. The list of potential Something Greats becomes never-ending. And with it, the accompanying list of goodbyes.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By</em> <strong><em>Sophia Burton</em></strong></p>
<p>*My choice of the term &#8220;expat&#8221; was deliberate, as it popularly denotes migrants with privilege and mobility. For more on &#8220;expat&#8221; vs. &#8220;immigrant&#8221;, check out <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/global-development-professionals-network/2015/mar/13/white-people-expats-immigrants-migration?CMP=fb_gu">this Guardian article</a>.</p>
<p><em>All photos taken by me, in Vienna and Berlin.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
