<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Our Lens &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/category/our-lens/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Women Only: The Frauenraum</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 15:42:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gender]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4385</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I'm at Rathaus Wilmersdorf, a former city hall building turned refugee home in Berlin, where I teach a literacy class once a week. The home initially opened its doors to 178 refugees in September 2015, following Merkel's famous "Wir schaffen das" ("We can do it") declaration that sidestepped the Dublin Regulation and opened up Germany's borders to thousands of asylum seekers.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4394 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-01-27 12.51.04" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>It&#8217;s Thursday at 10:55, and I&#8217;m running late. I rush up to the security guards and hand over my ID. <em>Helfer?</em> (&#8220;volunteer?&#8221;) they ask. <em>Ja</em>, I answer, and wait for them to scribble down my name and give me a number so I can sign out later. I thank them and head inside to the office to sign for the room keys and get my name tag. Then it&#8217;s through the foyer and up three floors to room 3092. When breakfast is running late, the right half of the stairwell is still filled by a neat line of people waiting for their turn in the cafeteria. I squeeze by, ruffling the hair of the kids I recognize.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m at Rathaus Wilmersdorf, a former city hall building turned refugee home in Berlin, where I teach a literacy class once a week. The home initially opened its doors to <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/berlin/bezirke/kudamm/notunterkunft-fuer-fluechtlinge-in-berlin-im-rathaus-wilmersdorf-fehlen-duschen-und-dolmetscher/12199798.html">178 refugees</a> in September 2015, following Merkel&#8217;s famous &#8220;Wir schaffen das&#8221; (&#8220;We can do it&#8221;) declaration that <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/germany/11821822/Germany-drops-EU-rules-to-allow-in-Syrian-refugees.html">sidestepped the Dublin Regulation</a> and opened up Germany&#8217;s borders to thousands of asylum seekers.</p>
<p>Today, over 1400 refugees live in the Rathaus &#8211; mostly from Syria, Afghanistan, and Iraq &#8211; and there is talk of opening up an adjacent building to house an additional 900. As is the case all over the city, this home simply wouldn&#8217;t function without the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/">on-going assistance of volunteers</a> who help out with everything from interpretation and teaching to administrative and kitchen support.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4456 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-01-08 10.34.54" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Over the past eight months, Rathaus Wilmersdorf has become somewhat of a success story as far as refugee accommodations in Berlin go. It&#8217;s been visited by President Joachim Gauck and American actor Ben Stiller, as well as received significant media praise for its leadership and facilities. <a href="http://www.morgenpost.de/berlin/article207089933/Vachroi-verabschiedet-sich-als-Heimleiter-in-Wilmersdorf.html">One article</a> listed off the home&#8217;s impressive amenities, which include medical and midwife services, a laundry room, a hair salon, an internet <span class="st">café</span>, and yes, even our literacy class.</p>
<p>The literacy class, or &#8220;AB class&#8221; as we call it, does go beyond what many other refugee homes in Berlin offer. But what the article&#8217;s authors fail to mention (and are likely unaware of), is that the course comes with a complicated backstory that is indicative of a larger debate surrounding refugees in Germany today.</p>
<p>It all started early this year, after one volunteer noticed that a group of women were not showing up for the German class offered on the home&#8217;s fourth floor. These women were mostly Afghan and the majority also illiterate. However, a bit of digging (and a heavy dose of interpretation) revealed that they weren&#8217;t avoiding the class because the level was too difficult, as originally suspected. They weren&#8217;t going because, in the fourth floor class, there were men present. Or depending on who tells the story, “Because their husbands wouldn’t let them”.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4600 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-05-19 12.43.22" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>The decision was therefore made to start a new class on the third floor, taught and attended exclusively by women. The class was to be an extension of the adjacent <em>Frauenraum</em> or &#8220;women&#8217;s room&#8221;. At Rathaus Wilmersdorf, the <em>Frauenraum</em> is a standing room open almost daily, so long as there are volunteers present. At the refugee home in former Tempelhof airport, the <em>Frauenraum</em> operates on a weekly project basis, led by a volunteer platform called <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">Give Something Back to Berlin</a>.</p>
<p>Regardless of the format, the concept remains the same: The <em>Frauenraum</em> is a safe place where women can be amongst themselves. In Rathaus Wilmersdorf, they sew, practice German, or just hang out and have a cup of tea. Small children are allowed, but men are forbidden from entering. We&#8217;ve even had to throw out a male journalist on occasion. The home&#8217;s former director described it as a place where &#8220;<a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/berlin/warum-thomas-de-vachroi-der-perfekte-aufbauhelfer-fuer-fluechtlingsheime-ist-23775578">female residents are enjoying their freedom and unveiling themselves.</a>&#8221; I can only assume he meant this both literally and figuratively, as not all the women wear headscarves, but some who do do indeed take them off when in the <em>Frauenraum</em> or during class.</p>
<p>I fell into the role of literacy teacher by way of the <em>Frauenraum</em>, where I started volunteering in January. The class was already up and running but they wanted to offer it on more days and were having trouble finding willing teachers. Other <em>Frauenraum</em> volunteers, I was told, had flatly refused to teach out of principle, scoffing at the idea that a separate class be created when there was a perfectly good one already on offer. This is Germany, after all, a country where men and women are presumably equal and interact on all levels of society. If the husbands had a problem with that, tough. Isn&#8217;t it in the best interest of these women that we integrate them into our way of life as quickly as possible?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4460 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-05-12 11.42.50" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>These days, it is difficult to have a discussion in Germany about refugees that doesn&#8217;t include a question about gender. <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/02/08/not-our-women-from-cologne-to-berlin/">Post-Cologne</a>, it is near impossible. Despite the fact that the attacks on New Year&#8217;s Eve were carried out by a more diverse group than originally portrayed in the media, that night&#8217;s unfortunate events have marked a turning point in attitudes towards refugees.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.focus.de/politik/deutschland/zdf-umfrage-offenbart-so-haben-die-silvester-uebergriffe-beeinflusst-was-deutsche-ueber-fluechtlinge-denken_id_5213962.html">One poll</a> showed that, between December 2015 and January 2016 alone, the number of Germans who felt the country couldn&#8217;t handle the influx of refugees rose from 46% to 60%. Thirty-three percent stated that Cologne had &#8220;fundamentally changed&#8221; their opinions about refugees. And the ring-wing <span class="st"><em>Alternative für Deutschland</em></span> (AfD) party, which initially emerged in opposition to the euro, has placed anti-refugee sentiment at the core of their increasingly popular platform. Their leader has controversially <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/alternative-for-germany-shows-its-true-right-wing-colors-a-1076259.html">called for the use of firearms against incoming refugees</a>.</p>
<p>This is the same country that was at the forefront of Europe&#8217;s refugee response only nine months ago. The same country that led the continent&#8217;s discourse on establishing a common European solution. The same country that initiated what became globally lauded as <em>Wilkommenskultur</em> (welcome culture).</p>
<p>So, what&#8217;s changed?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4401 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-650x650.jpg" alt="2016-02-10 11.59.46" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-300x300.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>When the “refugee crisis” hit Germany last summer, hundreds of residents felt compelled to slather butter on rolls and pass them out to refugees arriving at train stations. This was by all accounts heart-warming and admirable, but it was also the easy part. The conversation we are having now is a more complicated one, one that even the seemingly simple question of whether to offer a female-only literacy class echoes:</p>
<p>What happens next and how might our society change as a result?</p>
<p>One could blame Cologne, but the foundation for this confrontation was laid long before. A staggering <a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article147280667/Fuer-die-meisten-gehoert-der-Islam-nicht-zu-Deutschland.html">60% of the country</a> is of the opinion that Islam does not belong in Germany. (It is also worth noting that Germans consistently overestimate the number of Muslims living in the country. The real figure, while one of the highest in the EU, <a href="http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2015/11/17/5-facts-about-the-muslim-population-in-europe/">is still only 5.8%</a>.)</p>
<p>There is an underlying preconception in Germany, as in many Western countries, that Islam is synonymous with misogyny and a lack of female rights. That “<a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article149756193/Wie-Sumtes-Wutbuerger-lernten-Fluechtlinge-zu-lieben.html">according to their religion, women are nothing</a>” or even more extreme, that &#8220;<a href="http://www.vice.com/de/read/fluechtlinge-vergewaltigen-deutsche-kinder-wie-rassisten-versuchen-stimmung-gegen-alle-nicht-deutschen-zu-machen-775">these young men will come and rape our daughters</a>&#8220;. This preconception likely stems from a variety of factors: images we see in the media, politicians portraying Muslims as backward or extremist, or current conflicts within the Middle East. An argument heard less often is made by <a href="http://ideas.time.com/2013/11/01/do-muslim-women-need-saving/">Columbia University Professor Lila Abu-Lughod</a>, who explores the conflation of religion and socioeconomic status. Gender inequality within Muslim majority societies stems mainly from economic inequality, and migrants in Germany have traditionally been low-skilled. Therefore what we may label as clashes due to religion may have stronger roots in poverty and lack of opportunity.</p>
<p>Earlier this year in Berlin, <a href="http://www.rbb-online.de/politik/beitrag/2016/04/berlin-kopftuch-streit-vor-arbeitsgericht-keine-guetliche-einigung.html">a young teacher went to court</a> because she was denied a teaching post due to her headscarf (the case was thrown out on grounds of the state&#8217;s Neutrality Act). More recently in Switzerland, a <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-36382596">regional authority ruled</a> that two teenage brothers must shake the hands of their female teachers despite it being against their religious beliefs to touch women they are not related to. Traditionally receiving societies such as Germany are perpetually learning how to manage integration in the face of growing diversity. Unfortunately, we seem insistent on concentrating on how &#8220;their values&#8221; may threaten &#8220;ours&#8221;, rather than on what type of society we want to live in together.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4406 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-02-17 12.07.15" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>To be fair, my own engagement at the Rathaus has not come without challenges. On my first day teaching, I swallowed a lot of frustration as another volunteer and I watched the women turn to their husbands for approval before following us to class. <em>Nur Frauen</em> (&#8220;only women&#8221;), we tried to communicate to the more skeptical looking of the men with a smile, while I stifled the urge to roll my eyes.</p>
<p>We&#8217;ve also heard a host of disturbing stories by way of the interpreters. Rape, abuse, threats of divorce. Some stories are from Afghanistan while others allegedly took place here in Berlin. At times, I am ashamed to find myself relieved that I can&#8217;t talk to the women directly about what I&#8217;ve heard, for fear it might affect the way I interact with them. For now, our exchanges are limited to topics like telling time and types of fruit &#8211; they&#8217;re big fans of banana and pineapple &#8211; as well as the apparently always shocking and never boring topic of me being a 30 year old woman without a husband or children (some of my students have 6, 7, even 9 children).</p>
<p>But until we&#8217;re able to have those more in-depth conversations, I remain convinced that offering a class under imperfect circumstances is better than offering no women&#8217;s class at all. For what, I&#8217;ve asked myself, will give these women more independence than the ability to navigate the city on their own? And what will give them a better chance of being able to navigate the city on their own than the ability to read and write?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4405 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-04-20 10.14.53" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Nothing exhibited this more clearly to me than a few weeks ago, when we held an arts project week for our women. The week consisted of two trips to separate parks so they could learn about various plant types and practice drawing them. The excitement of the women was palpable. They got to have a Middle Eastern picnic, a real treat after months of bland cafeteria fare. They got to pick flowers in the woods to take back to the home. There was laughing, there was dancing, and there were so many selfies.</p>
<p>We later found out through interpreters that, for several of the women, it was their first time in a park without a husband or male relative.</p>
<p>At the end of the week, a local artist took the womens&#8217; drawings and stenciled them onto power boxes near the Rathaus. On the Friday, we took a stroll around the neighborhood together to see them for the first time. The Farsi-speaking volunteer asked the women to point out their drawings and explain why they chose to draw them specifically. &#8220;Who drew this?&#8221; she asked when we got to the second box, pointing to a beautiful palm tree. &#8220;Me,&#8221; answered one of our students, &#8220;I drew it because it reminds me of home. And if you cut off the head, the whole plant dies.&#8221;</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The Frauenraum at Rathaus Wilmersdorf is looking for volunteers. To get involved, sign up at https://volunteer-planner.org/.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>For another take on the headscarf, I recommend watching <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/video/2015/jun/24/hijab-not-oppression-feminist-statement-video">this Guardian video</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>All photos my own.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: Four Hours at Lageso</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2015 00:01:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bureaucracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moabit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4145</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is Lageso (Das Landesamt für Gesundheit und Soziales), the State Office for Health and Social Affairs. This is Berlin's primary registration center for the initial reception of asylum seekers. This is Germany's most infamous symbol of the refugee crisis. Two days prior I had signed up to volunteer on a website called Volunteer Planner. After a cursory registration process, a click of a button was all it took to commit to a shift at a registration center, refugee home, or other institution in the city where help is needed (read: basically everywhere).  ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4323 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-650x319.png" alt="boys_lageso" width="650" height="319" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-650x319.png 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-300x147.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>A curly-haired two year old hangs from my hip. His modest number of pounds start to wear on my side as I spin us back and forth in the narrow space. By some stroke of luck he has yet to start crying (this doesn&#8217;t last). He giggles, bouncing up and down, as if we are playing a game. &#8220;He seems to like you,&#8221; a volunteer next to me looks on and smiles, &#8220;almost like he wants to go home with you.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;He may have to,&#8221; I mutter in response. It has been a long ten minutes since I last saw his mother. I try desperately to remember her face &#8211; or at least the color of her headscarf. My voice starts to crack and I realize in horror a cold is coming on (&#8220;Am I infecting hundreds of refugees?&#8221;). A few minutes later we find her, a pair of black shoes in her hands. She holds them up proudly and points to herself. We are only supposed to be finding clothes for her son and she knows it, but I let her take the shoes and boy (now crying), and go.</p>
<p>Curly-haired boy and his mother are my latest charges from the never-ending mass of parents and children waiting to be accompanied down the hallway of donated clothing. This group is only a microcosm of the larger crowd waiting outside in the evening twilight where volunteers pass out hot tea and coffee. Kids get <em>Kinderschokolade </em>and granola bars. The building entrance is guarded to ensure not everyone infiltrates the chaos at once.</p>
<p>Back inside, a winter jacket and pair of warm shoes are the big prizes. Our chief responsibility is to make sure each child walks out with just one of each. I negotiate with parents: &#8220;She can have that coat, but you&#8217;ll need to give me the one she&#8217;s wearing now.&#8221; When language fails, I make a trading gesture with my hands or remove the jacket from the child&#8217;s back myself. How quickly the urge to be generous is superseded by pragmatism (&#8220;Even <em>I</em> could get by with only one coat&#8221;).</p>
<p>&#8220;You have to be careful,&#8221; a middle-aged female volunteer warns me as I re-fold a stack of jeans, &#8220;Roma families sneak in to take clothing and then sell it at the flea market.&#8221; I nod but am at a loss as to what to do with the information. Is she advocating that we start using racial profiling? Regardless of the Roma, some families may have already taken their turn down the hallway. Others could be successfully registered and in possession of their <a href="http://www.euronews.com/2015/09/16/which-european-countries-offer-the-most-social-benefits-to-migrants/">monthly stipend</a>. There&#8217;s really no way to tell.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4321 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_0599" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Our makeshift shopping strip consists of one narrow hallway and a back room for sorting and storage. On either side of the hallway are smaller rooms the size of coat checks, one holding clothing for adults and the other medicine and hygienic articles. It is very cramped. Fathers plea with volunteers for their family&#8217;s turn down the hallway. Once in, mothers rip clothing off hangers to hold up to their children and approximate size. Some kids are fussy about colors; others peer up with wide eyes and tightly pressed lips. Volunteers buzz by in a flurry of aspired productivity and surveillance, their name-tags as frayed as their nerves.</p>
<p>A cameraman waltzes in with his crew. The bright lens focuses on me as I kneel down to re-velcro a young boy&#8217;s shoes. We have yet to find boots that fit; these blue sandals are the ones in which he arrived to Germany, completely ill-suited for the looming winter. We both turn, squint, and smile anyway. This is the shot they want, and they are gone within the minute.</p>
<p>This is Lageso (<em>Das Landesamt </em><span class="st"><em>für Gesundheit und Soziales)</em>, the State Office for Health and Social Affairs</span>. This is <span class="st">Berlin&#8217;s primary registration center for the initial reception of asylum seekers. This is Germany&#8217;s most infamous symbol of the refugee crisis.</span></p>
<p>Two days prior I had signed up to volunteer on a website called <a href="https://volunteer-planner.org/">Volunteer Planner</a>. After a cursory registration process, a click of a button was all it took to commit to a shift at a registration center, refugee home, or other institution in the city where help is needed (read: basically everywhere).  An impressive resource to get people engaged quickly, though seemingly lacking any accountability for volunteers who fail to show up or for organizations advertising shifts that fall through or no longer exist (the day before I was turned away from a home in Schöneberg because the coordinator was not present).</p>
<p>In addition to locations, one can select specific tasks. This is an all-hands-on-deck scenario and there is something for everyone, from Arabic and Farsi interpretation (in high demand) to kitchen assistance and coffee distribution. At Lageso, I sign up to be a <em>Springer/in </em>or &#8220;Jumper&#8221;, who, according to the website, &#8220;helps wherever is most needed, is assigned to a team, and will be led by hand to their task.&#8221;</p>
<p>But upon arrival I am not assigned to a team nor led anywhere, let alone by hand. After finding a sticker on which to scribble my name, I walk around aimlessly until a smiley blond girl takes pity on me and leads me to the storage room. A few minutes later I am with a new girl who is in a room within this room, sorting through boxes of clothing donations in the dark. I glance at the heaps of dusty sweaters and immediately regret not having brought my allergy medicine.</p>
<p>We start unpacking boxes of blankets. &#8220;Is there somewhere specific we should put these?&#8221; I ask my sorting partner. She shrugs. &#8220;On those shelves, I think,&#8221; she says, pointing to the overstuffed racks behind us. Ten minutes later, another volunteer: &#8220;No, don&#8217;t unpack the blankets,&#8221; he instructs us in a mix of German and English. &#8220;Put them in a corner so we can take them to a refugee home later.&#8221;</p>
<p>I give up on the blankets and turn my attention to the clothes. Thankfully, some boxes are categorized, and I pick up one marked &#8220;children&#8221;. I plan to sort the contents and add them to the shelves, which are loosely organized by gender and size. In one pair of pants I notice a bulge in the pocket and pull out a knife. I pass it along to a guy with a clipboard who looks like he knows what he is doing. He turns and sets it on another shelf, near a box of children&#8217;s toys.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4322 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_0600" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>I&#8217;m finally getting into a groove when another volunteer comes up behind me, visibly frustrated. &#8220;I spent days putting this together and now everyone&#8217;s destroying it,&#8221; she complains to clipboard guy, motioning to the overflowing shelves. He glances up over his glasses. &#8220;We&#8217;ll discuss it at Monday&#8217;s meeting,&#8221; he promises. I don&#8217;t know what I&#8217;ve done wrong, but I am sure of two things: We are all working on top of one another and there is no one in charge.</p>
<p>When the refugee crisis became front page news this past summer, thousands of Germany&#8217;s residents jumped to provide clothing and supplies, offer short-term housing solutions, or pass out sandwiches to refugees as they poured into train stations around the country. Many continue to help, some using vacation days to do so. On a civilian level, the outpouring of support in Germany has been heart-warming, encouraging, even pride-inducing.</p>
<p>Charitable and non-profit initiatives also abound. Groups have launched fundraising efforts to help those in particularly dire situations, like this <a href="https://www.betterplace.org/de/projects/37503-hilfe-fur-familie-ahmed">Iraqi father who suffered a heart attack</a>. There are <a href="http://www.unhcr.org/5655d27f6.html">bike riding lessons</a> for women and <a href="http://www.abendblatt-berlin.de/2015/12/03/ein-zirkus-fuer-die-gute-sache/">circus activities</a> for kids. A local photographer has started a &#8220;<a href="https://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.400616063468410.1073741835.295071407356210&amp;type=3">Humans of Lageso&#8221; page</a> to shed light on individual refugee stories. Herbert Grönemeyer, a famous German singer, has <a href="http://www.stern.de/lifestyle/leute/lageso-in-berlin---herbert-groenemeyer-finanziert-waermebusse-fuer-fluechtlinge-6605406.html">financed heated buses</a> so those waiting to register at Lageso can take turns warming up.</p>
<p><span class="st">But civilian good-will and a display of <span class="st"><em>Willkommenskultur</em></span> (welcome culture) can only go so far in serving the approximately 800,000 asylum seekers that Germany will receive this year &#8211; a figure that is <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/sep/06/refugee-crisis-germany-response-heartwarming-will-pressures-show">more a projection than a guest list</a>. What some in Berlin may call growing pains in learning to accommodate unprecedented waves of refugees, others deem a failure of the system and local leadership. German towns such as Passau, a Bavarian town of 50,000, have cited <a href="http://nmd.bn02750.bethemd.wayport.net/index.adp?MacAddr=68%3aA8%3a6D%3a4B%3a7A%3a8C&amp;IpAddr=10.128.29.239&amp;Ip6Addr=&amp;vsgpId=&amp;vsgId=41975&amp;UserAgent=&amp;ProxyHost=&amp;TunnelIfId=95270&amp;VlanId=20">much more success in handling the inflow</a>.</span></p>
<p><span class="st">The press have reported on the turbulent conditions at Lageso ad nauseam, both locally and <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/11/27/world/europe/germany-berlin-migrants-refugees.html?_r=0">internationally</a>. Refugees wait for weeks if not months to be registered. They line up for hours each day, often beginning the night before. People sleep in the streets. Most don&#8217;t receive enough to eat and drink. Heated tents were only made available <a href="http://www.stilinberlin.de/2015/12/fugeela-refugees-in-berlin-6-html.html">a few days ago</a>. &#8220;Refugee crisis? More like bureaucratic crisis!&#8221; protesters chanted <a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/1678473329031122/">on November 29th</a>, calling the local government to action. Understaffed and overworked employees have anonymously <a href="http://www.rbb-online.de/politik/thema/fluechtlinge/berlin/2015/12/lageso-innenansichten-mitarbeiter.html">detailed the on-going chaos</a> to the press. On December 10th, the Head of Lageso, Franz Allert, was <a href="http://www.focus.de/politik/deutschland/migration-lageso-chef-tritt-zurueck_id_5143744.html">pushed into resignation</a>. </span></p>
<p>Curly-haired boy and his mom are back outside, but at least now with warmer feet and some chocolate in their bellies. I pull my phone out of my pocket: three and a half hours have passed. There isn&#8217;t an eight hour work day in recent memory I can remember having been more exhausting. Admiration for the other volunteers &#8211; many of whom do this regularly, including night shifts &#8211; rushes within me. As does panic. The support is incredible, but is it sustainable?</p>
<p>We need to get this right, and not just in the short-term.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By<strong> Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>For up to date information in English on the refugee situation in Berlin, we recommend reading the <a href="http://www.stilinberlin.de/?s=FuGeeLa">FuGeeLa updates</a> by Stil in Berlin. <a href="http://www.findingberlin.com/how-to-help-refugees-in-berlin-winter-2015/">Finding Berlin</a> also provides comprehensive resources for how to help. </em></p>
<p><em>To sign up for volunteer shifts in Berlin, try <a href="https://volunteer-planner.org/helpdesk/">Volunteer Planner</a> (in German) or look for opportunities through <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">Give Something Back to Berlin</a> (in English). <a href="http://moabit-hilft.com/">MoabitHilft</a> is very engaged at Lageso and many of the regular volunteers at the center are affiliated with this organization.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>If you are donating clothing to refugee homes, please do your best to package them by type (e.g. age and size) and consider buying socks which are often in short supply. Even better: check first with the home to see what is most needed!</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: On Leaving Home(s)</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/03/23/lens-on-leaving-homes/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 15:32:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[family]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vienna]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3869</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Last month, Kelly wrote about the implications of "collecting ourselves" to make a move back home. While wrought with complications in its own right, returning to where one grew up, has family, or holds full political and legal rights is a move that Makes Sense. One chapter closes, and however painful or messy, the next begins...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3881 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-650x487.jpg" alt="2014-11-16 13.46.44" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Last month, Kelly wrote about the implications of &#8220;<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/02/13/lens-leaving-berlin/">collecting ourselves</a>&#8221; to make a move back home. While wrought with complications in its own right, returning to where one grew up, has family, or holds full political and legal rights is a move that Makes Sense. One chapter closes, and however painful or messy, the next begins.</p>
<p>After graduate school, I started losing the ability to picture my life in chapters. My decisions were no longer dictated by a series of steps culminating in clear milestones. I suddenly felt accosted by the need to figure out what I wanted to Do and Be&#8230; this time for the long run. And, given my international experiences and dual citizenship, the question of &#8220;What&#8221; promptly extended to one of &#8220;Where&#8221;.</p>
<p>So I moved to Berlin.</p>
<p>When I booked my flight to Germany in fall 2011, &#8220;two years&#8221; was my default timeline. &#8220;A couple years,&#8221; I responded confidently when someone asked how long I planned to be gone. &#8220;I should give the job a good two years,&#8221; I thought when I got hired six months in. &#8220;We&#8217;ll all still be here at least two more years,&#8221; I reassured myself about my circle of expat* friends another six months after that.</p>
<p>How foolish I was, to believe that two years would ever be enough. How <span class="st">naïve</span>,<em> </em>to assume there would be a clear demarcation between this chapter and the next.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3885 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-650x487.jpg" alt="2015-01-31 14.28.03-1" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Now almost three and a half years in, I feel firmly entrenched in my world of bilingual conversations, narrow streets, weekend jaunts around the continent, ubiquitous public transport, social welfare nets, and crusty bread. But these roots of mine are flighty. They wiggle at something as simple as a chat with a friend back home, when she catches me up on her life and I realize how much I&#8217;ve missed. When my sister or father leaves for the airport after a visit, they are pulled halfway out of the earth and end up lodged in the middle of my throat. Every time I get on a plane and head back across the ocean, a part of me fears they will be ripped out entirely. Because no matter how long I stay in Europe and embrace the rights my German passport affords me, I will always also be American. No matter how incredible a life I build for myself on this side of the Atlantic, there will always be a Life Back Home.</p>
<p>I was not aware of how much I had internalized this feeling until last summer, when my mother and I visited relatives in northwestern Germany. Sipping coffee on a sunny terrace, a family friend commented, &#8220;I could never do what you&#8217;re doing, be so far away from my family&#8230; I&#8217;m too close to them.&#8221; My reaction to her declaration was nothing short of primal. Of course I missed my family! Of course I felt close to them! I was not away <em>because</em> of, but rather, <em>in spite of</em> them &#8211; an unpleasant reality I struggle with on a near daily basis.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3892 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-650x518.jpg" alt="11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n" width="650" height="518" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-650x518.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-300x239.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Modern advances in travel and technology have enabled more and more people to adopt lifestyles fueled by wanderlust and adventure. But not all of us who leave home are <a href="http://elitedaily.com/life/culture/wanderlust-like-travel-much-no-real-home/959705/">perpetual wanderers with nomadic spirits</a>. Some of us are searching for somewhere to settle. Some of us are even surprised to find ourselves making a life away from where we grew up, away from the ones we love. I know I am.</p>
<p>I consider myself, by nature, to be a sensitive homebody. I crave being close to the people I love and place great importance on maintaining my relationships, both near and far. This explains why any time I am &#8220;away&#8221;, my pack mentality kicks in and I seek out a local community almost immediately. But I concurrently possess the intrinsic need to push myself and explore. For me, this has meant travel. Whether I credit <a href="https://psychologyblogaimee.wordpress.com/2013/12/04/wanderlust-a-genetic-basis-to-a-globetrotting-fanatic/">genetics</a> for this (nope) or my international upbringing, mixed with a little courage and a lot of privilege (that&#8217;s more like it), is not the point. The ups and downs of living somewhere other than where I grew up have become an integral part of my identity and understanding of growth and independence. They just don&#8217;t make the leaving part any easier.</p>
<p>The thing is, leaving is rarely the easy choice, even with the prospect of Something Great on the other side.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3887 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-650x487.jpg" alt="2015-02-21 16.37.36-1" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>While I never expected moving to Berlin to be easy, I did anticipate a gradual ease, and more importantly, clarity, with time. Reality proved instead to be emphatically non-linear. Rough patches hit me sporadically and without warning. My homesickness became a swelling wave, pulling in and out of shore, threatening at its peak to wash me out entirely. What if this chapter never ended? What if I never left my new home and went back to my old one? And now that I live in Vienna, my current home because of work, is my &#8220;old home&#8221; Washington, DC or Berlin? In countless discussions with fellow expat friends on the topics of home and belonging, the resounding theme has been similar: one of overwhelming choice and uncertainty.</p>
<p>A couple months ago, Kelly and I were at a close friend&#8217;s 30th birthday dinner in Berlin. Huddled in the kitchen over bottles of Spanish Temperanillo and mismatched plates of pizza and crudit<span class="st">és</span>, someone proposed we guess where the birthday boy would be 30 years from now. We had plenty of ideas for the &#8220;What&#8221;: running his own cooking school, teaching his kids how to do science experiments, maintaining his impressive beard. It was on the &#8220;Where&#8221; that we got stuck. &#8220;Italy?&#8221; we posed as the obvious choice (where he&#8217;s from). He resolutely shook his head &#8220;no&#8221;. &#8220;Germany?&#8221; He shrugged his shoulders, unsure &#8211; just like the majority of us in the room about our own futures.</p>
<p>Once you&#8217;ve opened yourself up to the world and seen first-hand that you can live, and maybe even thrive, somewhere else, it becomes increasingly difficult to know when or where to stop searching. The list of potential Something Greats becomes never-ending. And with it, the accompanying list of goodbyes.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By</em> <strong><em>Sophia Burton</em></strong></p>
<p>*My choice of the term &#8220;expat&#8221; was deliberate, as it popularly denotes migrants with privilege and mobility. For more on &#8220;expat&#8221; vs. &#8220;immigrant&#8221;, check out <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/global-development-professionals-network/2015/mar/13/white-people-expats-immigrants-migration?CMP=fb_gu">this Guardian article</a>.</p>
<p><em>All photos taken by me, in Vienna and Berlin.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: Leaving Berlin, collecting ourselves</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/02/13/lens-leaving-berlin/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2015 11:23:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ex-pat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3817</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Leaving Berlin might mean losing some connection to the tangible trek between dreams, realizations, and moments of vulnerability that is our movement through years, our aging and maturation, in any sense. But it is only temporary. Indeed, collecting ourselves means leaving ourselves. But only for now...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Before coming to Berlin, I was an archivist at an educational institution in Seattle, slowly working my way through a collection of artifacts that had been donated largely from Holocaust survivors and their families. Charged with accessioning (and/or digitally cataloging) over fifteen years of diffuse and often inconsistent records, I found myself forced to establish uncomfortable hierarchies. Collections are the result of measured calculations of value, often assessing the significance of one form of memory over another.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/memory_revised.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-3827 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/memory_revised.jpg" alt="memory_revised" width="742" height="603" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/memory_revised.jpg 742w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/memory_revised-300x243.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/memory_revised-650x528.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 742px) 100vw, 742px" /></a></p>
<p>Any museum has to be painfully selective; time, space, and targeted mission result in a lot of rejection. Pure and simple, refusing to &#8216;collect&#8217; something belonging to a victim of the Holocaust or a veteran of WWII means embarking on tricky, emotional terrain.</p>
<p>Despite its challenge, I learned a lot from this experience &#8211; knowledge that has served me well in a different city, a different country. For it was not by chance that my first foot in any of Berlin&#8217;s rapidly revolving doors was in an institution that appraised, tracked, and managed large quantities of objects: an art gallery. Yet, to my relief, I was no longer responsible for the task of sorting, accepting, and rejecting. The hierarchy already existed. I simply had to regularly tighten its nuts and bolts.</p>
<p>Now, I am tasked with doing a little of both. Because, you see, I am eagerly awaiting to learn whether or not any of the PhD fellowships I applied for last year will take me. Did I mention that these programs are in the United States? So, as I chew through a new set of nails and amend an ever-lengthening scroll of plan b&#8217;s, I am mentally and physically preparing for the Great Move Back. By default, this involves packing up what will have been a four-year ride in what I can best &#8211; and momentarily, as I am sure this will change &#8211; describe as a lesson in patience, adaptation, and even &#8216;failure&#8217;.</p>
<p>This is the archivist&#8217;s ultimate challenge: collecting oneself.</p>
<p>It is easier to apply some value equation to the memories of others, a different story entirely when each beloved stage of your life is on the chopping block.</p>
<p><a href="http://faculty.georgetown.edu/irvinem/theory/Clifford-OnCollectingArtandCulture.pdf">According to the anthropologist Clifford Geertz</a>, &#8216;collecting&#8217; is an almost universal process across cultures. Some  sort of &#8220;gathering&#8221; of the objects of both the everyday and the past is an important part of what he calls &#8220;marking off a domain of self&#8221;. Just as meaning, value, and story are carefully created in museums, galleries, and other institutions of public curation and display, so our lives become careful practices in determining what is now important, what might fall away, and what is to follow us to our next (literal and figurative) destination.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3837" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon-650x487.jpg" alt="Wohnwagon" width="580" height="435" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px" /></a></p>
<p>I could not agree more with Clifford Geertz. As I plan which &#8216;artifacts&#8217; to take with me and which to disregard, I am accounting for who I once was, who I am now, and which stages of transformation are important to catalog into the future fabric of my life. Most importantly, I want to make sure I remember what this &#8220;Kelly&#8221; was like as a foreigner, as a U.S. national in the European Union, or as an &#8216;ex-pat resident&#8217; in a city like Berlin. And I want to be able to tangibly review and understand, perhaps again and again, how these stages and categories underwent change.</p>
<p>Thus, I need to &#8220;mark my domain&#8221; and &#8220;gather myself&#8221;.</p>
<p>It should be no surprise that immigrants, in particular, are constantly renegotiating hierarchies of value and meaning. Usually due to the constraints of geography and financial practicality, the contents of one&#8217;s home must be down-sized, even partly abandoned. Inevitably, pieces of childhood and/or integral moments of budding adulthood are left behind. Imagine that: deciding which family albums to send to a distant aunt for storage, which heirlooms to pass on to those who may never know what it is like to say goodbye to the literal bulk of memory, or which books to put up for sale, never-mind the story behind the inscriptions.</p>
<p>And yet, returning to the proverbial bassinet, to the place that promises comfort in familiarity, might be just as difficult for immigrants as was leaving it.</p>
<p>For me, this seems to be increasingly the case. The longer I live apart from the places where material comforts and their consumer habits formed and enveloped my surroundings, the more I recognize significance in those fewer objects I have come to possess. Less has, in this case, become truly more.</p>
<p>In the end, the way in which the self relates to &#8216;stuff&#8217; is, over time, subject to drastic change. The way in which these objects may shape who we think we are in the world does too. And this complicates the process of collection.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/IMG_66181.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3835" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/IMG_66181.jpg" alt="IMG_6618" width="580" height="435" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/IMG_66181.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/IMG_66181-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/IMG_66181-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px" /></a></p>
<p>In an <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/16/lens-going-away/">article</a> I wrote here more than a year ago (on my challenging but enriching relationship with family, friends, and self on both sides of the Atlantic), I mentioned that the two-sided sense of home one experiences living abroad indefinitely affects one&#8217;s purchasing decisions. Towels, for example, fell into this category of things somehow neglected in the everyday of my Berlin consumerism. Now, one year later, I have quite an assortment of towels (thanks, Juri), in addition to newly minted whisky glasses, books both recently bought and borrowed, certainly more dishware, and a growing pile of greeting cards and heartfelt letters I don&#8217;t think will ever land entirely in the recycling.</p>
<p>And so the collecting, the sorting, the hierarchy of value begins. And with it, the worries of abandoning something I won&#8217;t miss until it&#8217;s no longer there.</p>
<p>For who will receive my salvaged desk with its coffee stains and dents &#8211; from years of free-lance, home-bound labor; my ever-growing tropical tree of a houseplant &#8211; a gift from my dear roommates; my antiquated but charming boombox &#8211; discovered in a damp basement; my IKEA comfy-chair &#8211; hauled in two-go&#8217;s from the south of Berlin? Will their future recipients understand what they signify? What they meant, to me?</p>
<p>More recently, I have tried to reconstruct the contents of the pack I first brought with me to Berlin, its meager (if not forced) element of chosen austerity: three pairs of shoes, two copies of classic literature, two copies of hard-knock poetry, one folder of important personal documents,  toothpaste and a toothbrush, a miniature Ganesha statue, a laptop &#8211; you get the picture. Establishing some sort of a contrast is helping me, now, to re-collect.</p>
<p>To complete this act of comparison, I rummaged through boxes of the miscellaneous items one learns to hold on to after more than three years of lived life in a cosmopolitan metropolis, with all the adventures in between: ticket stubs, letters, newspaper clippings (so antiquated-adorable, I know), event flyers, various city maps. What I have found is that the &#8220;Kelly&#8221; from three years ago might have expected to uncover herself in the objects she could fit in one suitcase, while this &#8220;Kelly&#8221; &#8211; as the more recent product of the European Union, parts of the German social system, and a fragmented but very resilient city of complex diversity &#8211; would never expect such a thing.</p>
<p>I am just too different; my surroundings are just too different, too complex even. But perhaps it has always been this way. And it has just taken me three years to see it.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/foot_revised1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3836 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/foot_revised1-556x650.jpg" alt="foot_revised" width="556" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/foot_revised1.jpg 556w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/foot_revised1-256x300.jpg 256w" sizes="(max-width: 556px) 100vw, 556px" /></a></p>
<p>In this exercise of trying to curate the display of current me to future life, I have become (relatively) certain of one thing: that much of what I will take with me and much of what I will leave behind will become obsolete in the years to come. Because our hierarchies of what matters and what matters Right Now are constrained by time and its passage. Because we grow older. And so does our stuff, its significance and relationship to memory fading.</p>
<p>Leaving Berlin might mean losing some connection to the tangible trek between dreams, realizations, and moments of vulnerability that is our movement through years, our aging and maturation, in any sense. But it is only temporary. Indeed, collecting ourselves means leaving ourselves.</p>
<p>But only for now.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>All photos were taken by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: London and other transplants</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/09/29/beyond-berlin-london-and-other-transplants/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/09/29/beyond-berlin-london-and-other-transplants/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 15:22:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ex-pat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[London]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3278</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This past week, I visited my good friend D who, like me, is an American transplant. D lives in East London, where the corner store owner greets you in an upbeat banter and the sign to a ‘Carolina Fried Chicken’ joint dances in the light from the neighboring gastropub. Multicultural, maybe. But London’s multiculturalism has a few faces and facades. And, in the end, it’s the people that matter more than the cultural installation: So, who is actually 'making' it here?...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This past week, I visited my good friend D who, like me, is an American transplant*. We have similar trajectories and political ponderings, though his roots lie far from mine in the American Deep South (here’s a <a href="http://www.orionmagazine.org/index.php/place_where_you_live/view/chunky_mississippi_7753/">beautiful piece</a> he wrote about his home in Mississippi). D now lives in East London, where the corner store owner greets you in an upbeat banter and the sign to a ‘Carolina Fried Chicken’ joint dances in the light from the neighboring gastropub. Multicultural, maybe. But London’s multiculturalism has a few faces and facades. And, in the end, it’s the people that matter more than the cultural installation.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1031-e1413145767969.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3351 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1031-e1413145767969.jpg" alt="img_1031-e1413145767969" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1031-e1413145767969.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1031-e1413145767969-300x199.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>My first night in London, over pints at a very hip and haptic microbrewery – the tables grainy and splitting with moisture – D and I discuss our common struggles: We chat about how so-called experiences ‘abroad’ are, in the end, defined by labor market restrictions and the particular brand of our passport. Three years ago I would have insisted that these things are fluid. But even with a class degree from a class English university, a work allowance is hard to come by if not impossible in an academic job market already squeezed by its nationals, he shares. I can only nod, my plunge into the newest Berlin job search looming at the edge of my half-empty pint.</p>
<p>Berlin, like London, is full of transplants, both temporary and permanent. Why so many? For the case of my friend D and me, why did we, in particular, take these leaps? Why do so many of our generation (and even those generations before us) move to cities in countries we have no <i>de facto</i> right to be in? Across the ocean, <i>jus soli</i>, <i>jus sanguinus</i>, <i>jus</i> whatever does, indeed, determine much of what is possible.</p>
<p>The U.K, though London, in particular, invites dreams and dreamers. Multiculturalism results, in part, from the diversity of all those who believe in possibility; immigrants churn up new identities and make places we feel right to inhabit. In the case of Americans in London, maybe it’s the common language, the similar sarcastic humor, or the attachment to butter-heavy things like pie and cookies, but it just makes sense to come here.</p>
<p>In D’s apartment, a short assemblage of brick and concrete in the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London_Borough_of_Hackney">Hackney neighborhood</a>, I meet a few other fellow Americans. In many words, we all speak of the hurdles one must leap (in stride) for the right to not only remain but to earn an income at that, to really participate in a place one might co-construct but for which legal rights are lacking. One of them, a recent graduate of the London School of Economics, is tirelessly working to bend a clause or make a rule that will allow him to stay. There is a sense of marathon-running in the air, trying and trying until you can’t try anymore. Particularly palpable in a generation used to succeeding at most things, or told it is possible anyway.</p>
<p>But sometimes, it just doesn’t work out, at least temporarily, and many of those who come have to return to the places they left behind. But D seems optimistic.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/dylan_3.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3350 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/dylan_3-464x650.jpg" alt="dylan_3" width="464" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/dylan_3.jpg 464w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/dylan_3-214x300.jpg 214w" sizes="(max-width: 464px) 100vw, 464px" /></a></p>
<p>This matters because cities like London and Berlin actively foster the transplant spirit, but this doesn’t mean that these places work to sustain it. According to recent research <a href="http://books.google.de/books?id=Cy7FAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PR2&amp;lpg=PR2&amp;dq=%22migrants+or+expatriates+americans+in+europe%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=bX6_r-fwO2&amp;sig=4Si_8b_0M8yuiU9Ti6hBkJ_Ijs8&amp;hl=de&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=M8IqVJW1IsbWPZzygOAN&amp;ved=0CEYQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">on so-called American expatriates in Europe</a>, many transplants struggle for years at poorly paid jobs that are taken just to remain in the country. In Berlin, nearly half are underemployed and another third report contract-to-contract work (hustling, in other words). And yet, despite difficulties, many stay, which may be part financial, the costs of rehabilitating a life somewhere else, for example, and part mythical, i.e. what it means to constantly imagine future potential, then find it too difficult to forgo what might have been.</p>
<p>In any case, staying has a lot to do with the appearance of things. For how much of the transplant culture results from what one sees or experiences upon arriving, regardless of the actual rules of the game, even in spite of real barriers to inclusion? Put simply, if I see other Americans making it, or just a plethora of other nationalities making it, is it wrong to think I’ll make it?</p>
<p>Of course, the particular brand of passport produces a variety of experiences, but very few of us have a free-pass (excluding what D jokingly refers to as ‘fake Americans’ in London who legally remain in the country under an inherited European passport). Now, sitting in D’s kitchen with a liter of freshly brewed coffee (not tea), he tells me another story, one of a good friend’s predicament – an EU citizen, married to a Mexican national. In short, the immigration authorities of the U.K. have decided that the couple fails to meet requirements for residency in London, he tells me. Mexico is a country not seen favorably for transplantation; a hierarchy of acceptable migrants certainly does exist. But this all feels strangely hypothetical – this game of planning a life beyond borders, making moves and readying oneself for the counter. It is a lesson in rectifying a roster of rules with a vibrant diversity suggestive of more flexibility, more fluidity, than might be the case.</p>
<p>We leave the apartment and its conversation for a walk. Outside, it’s humid but pleasant, and the streets of D’s neighborhood are bursting with an eclecticism even beyond what the NY Times recently featured in ‘<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/04/29/travel/36-hours-in-east-london.html">36 hours in East London</a>‘ (as if the region needed its own holiday, apart from the financial men and women in suits of central London or the manicured streets of the West). Here, social housing projects tower above quaint town homes, neighbors trimming their rose bushes, bass piling out of a high window onto a long set of shears. Just down the road, one of London’s most bubbling food bazaars – a foodie’s scene of cultural consumption – is in full swing. Broadway Market: where German sausages, and meat pies, and lox bagels, and Persian kebab, and samosas, and ramen-to-go find frequent (young) patrons. We both delight in the anything-but-discordant multilingualism this variety yields.</p>
<p>In a pod of food carts just blocks from the market’s main drag, I find the best burrito I’ve had outside of the Western United States – a man with an air of L.A. dishing up marinated legumes, sauces streaming out of all sides of the tortilla like a blessing. A neighboring kiosk serves up what they call Filipino wraps (pork belly, assorted greens, tangy sauce), D’s favorite. As I walk to peruse other flavors, D shares his visa predicament with the owner of the wraps, explaining that this sandwich will be his last after a year of patronage. The owner offers to sponsor his visa, chuckling but serious, D tells me. Maybe he should take him up on his offer we joke, meaning it. D smiles.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/pork-belly.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3349" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/pork-belly-488x650.jpg" alt="pork-belly" width="400" height="532" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/pork-belly-488x650.jpg 488w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/pork-belly-225x300.jpg 225w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/pork-belly.jpg 489w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a></p>
<p>It’s easy to feel welcomed here.</p>
<p>Far away from East London, I find myself in the kitchen of a German transplant on the ground floor of an elderly but charming home in a neighborhood near Kensington.  From my luggage I unload mustard I’ve carted across the channel, tubes I was almost not allowed to take onto the plane. <i>You just can’t find this here</i>, my host says, that certain spicy mustard.</p>
<p>Her friends are all from somewhere else, she shares, <i>but the problem with transplants is that they all leave eventually, and then, all of a sudden, you don’t have any friends</i>. She is slowly rebuilding the circle, <i>but it’s hard</i>, she tells me, <i>when everyone is from somewhere else.</i></p>
<p>As we leave the far West neighborhood, its quiet lanes juxtaposed with newer blocks of community housing and industrial outgrowth, we pass an office for remittances – transplants from East Africa sending their earnings back ‘home’. Even here, some people are making it.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wp_20140919_001.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3347 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wp_20140919_001.jpg" alt="wp_20140919_001" width="640" height="360" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wp_20140919_001.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wp_20140919_001-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wp_20140919_001-310x174.jpg 310w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>My last day in London, my travel companion and I board a train to Brick Lane, snaking above a meat market, halal lambs hanging like carpets and voices rising up into numbers. Brick Lane, a curated experience of all that London attracts, the object of film, book, and tourism, is the sharpened edge of the city’s sale of eclecticism. It is a blend of curry houses and backdoor sweets shops for tourists and locals alike; it is the contrast between posh chocolatiers and wholesale textile vendors or between grunge coffee houses and chic boutiques. But it is not what is seen here that inspires but what is implied: that this – reproduction of home, community-making in memory – is possible. Even if it always isn’t.</p>
<p>After another burrito, this time seasoned with garam masala, we chat with an artist crafting overt social commentary, something he calls ‘the Prejudice Project’. With a long beard and dark eyes, he has likely faced that which his project targets. His bright smile opens up to pure optimism as we discuss diversity politics, however. But things can be difficult, indeed: In London, it’s not as free as in Berlin, he shares, a place he once inhabited, squatting in Köpenick and composing works that now hang in this design outlet just off Brick Lane. <i>The folks here are different</i>, he says, pausing, belonging to a <i>certain type</i>. He gives me a postcard, <i>a token to remember our conversation</i>: ‘#Paradise’ printed on a white surface, a glimpse of blue sky in the background.</p>
<p>D is moving back to the United States. After a preliminary job search and the weight of a different kind of bureaucracy on his shoulders, it seems like the best thing, for now. As he prepares for his departure to Philadelphia he looks mournful, visiting his favorite food carts and bookshop, the dingy canal with folks living out of boats – the air thick with oil and wet brush – before it all becomes just another place where he once lived. <i>I’d like to come back</i>, he says, <i>but then I just walk around and look at all the people here and want to go up and ask ‘like, how do you live here? What do you do?’</i> Perhaps, many of them are themselves transplants, just figuring it out as they go, leaving eventually for another place.</p>
<p>It’s hard to say, given the look of things.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1035.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3348 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1035.jpg" alt="img_1035" width="640" height="295" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1035.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1035-300x138.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>&#8211; <i>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></i></p>
<p><i>For more background on London as a city of immigration check out this 2013 </i> Times<i> <a href="http://www.thetimes.co.uk/tto/public/postcard/article3757989.ece">article</a>, which provides a concise run-down on the various groups and waves that make up London’s diversity. But even better:</i>the Guardian <i>has put together a</i><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/series/london"><i> </i><i>nifty collection</i></a><i> </i><i>of resources for exploring the many religious, culinary, and all-around cultural traditions that make up the city, although nothing beats exploring it on your own, if time and purse strings allow.</i></p>
<p>*I am using this word “transplant” intentionally, avoiding terms such as “expat” or even “immigrant”, as they are often bogged down with allusions to class, privilege, and assumptions about the irrelevance of borders or passports for certain members of the global community. When it comes to migration, the language is tricky but important. It helps to start with words that we feel we truly inhabit or experience, even if imperfectly.</p>
<p>All photos were taken by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/09/29/beyond-berlin-london-and-other-transplants/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rave: the California Breakfast Slam Effect</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/30/rave-the-california-breakfast-slam-effect/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2014 12:17:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[expats]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2510</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Identity and belonging are closely intertwined with the foods we eat. The California Breakfast Slam, or CABslam, originally a pop-up breakfast establishment celebrating Americana classics like hash browns and maple syrup-drenched bacon, now hosts an unassuming 'Beta' restaurant space at the far edge of Neukölln's Reuterkiez. A visit allows for the giddy return to childhood memories that lead to goosebumps and pride, or a combination of both. Let's call this the California Breakfast Slam effect...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The relationship between food and identity, or simply food and a sense of belonging, is well-known to those of us who have sought out Hass avocados or Toll House chocolate chips (often in vain) in places beyond the United States. For me, there is something ultimately gratifying, even safe, about opening that jar of Adam&#8217;s peanut butter or letting the smell of buttermilk biscuits fill my Berlin apartment. At once, giving in to &#8216;old urges&#8217; is washed with self-realization. I also just really love buttermilk biscuits.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01329.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2518" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01329.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01329" width="640" height="426" /></a></p>
<p>While critically testing Berlin&#8217;s newest &#8216;American breakfast&#8217; joint a few weekends ago, I had the overwhelming sense that &#8220;hey, I&#8217;m allowed to do this [more than anyone else here]!&#8221;. These are processes of identity and belonging at work.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.facebook.com/cabslam">California Breakfast Slam</a>, or CABslam, originally a pop-up breakfast establishment celebrating Americana classics like hash browns and maple syrup-drenched bacon, now hosts an unassuming &#8216;Beta&#8217; restaurant space at the far edge of Neukölln&#8217;s Reuterkiez. A visit allows for the giddy return to childhood memories that lead to goosebumps and pride or a combination of both. Let&#8217;s call this the California Breakfast Slam effect.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01342.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2531 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01342.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01342" width="640" height="960" /></a></p>
<p>Not all patrons of CABslam&#8217;s new digs are from the Western coast of the United States like myself, but there certainly exists a clientele of the North American variety, motivated more by feelings (or longings) than by taste, I dare to conjecture. Put simply, who knew that a plate full of pancakes, browned potato shavings, bacon, and a fried egg would make one feel so secure? So &#8216;you&#8217; in your own maple-craving skin? This is the CABslam effect.</p>
<p>Anthropologists would suggest that our food choices constitute a large part of how we position ourselves in the world, particularly in a foreign context. In a country for which one possesses no legal or innate right to reside, one learns to miss the general social acceptance and security provided in that <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/16/lens-going-away/">place left behind</a>. Ethnographical studies* of immigrants around the world &#8211; Turkish immigrants vending kebap to keep the nostalgic grill burning, taco trucks re-connecting small towns to distant landscapes, Punjabi import shops outlining a community in the anonymous city &#8211; form an extensive literature in support of this role of food as an identity-maker. Food ways, what and how we eat, often serve to reclaim a definition of self that may be threatened by the indifferent surroundings of the foreign.</p>
<p>Interesting to reflect upon, however, is how much of these positive associations are, in fact, related to the food itself. In other words, is it the constitution and consistency of the yogurt that reminds the Turkish immigrant of home (see <a href="http://www.businessweek.com/articles/2013-01-31/at-chobani-the-turkish-king-of-greek-yogurt">the Chobani story</a>)? Is the sugar content of my peanut butter a key determinant of my sense of belonging &#8211; of how I affirm and embody my American identity in Germany?</p>
<p>One of my father&#8217;s favorite activities, as of late, is going to the local mom &amp; pop diner located just around the corner from his home. He has always loved waffles, bacon, eggs &#8211; preferences I inherited, minus the bacon for environmental reasons (goodbye bacon bowls).</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_20041.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2555 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_20041.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_2004" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>At this local breakfast spot in Vancouver (WA), one sits in a cozy corner &#8211; on that particular kind of squeaky upholstery reserved for diners &#8211; and receives bottom-less coffee and a pint of the good, brown sticky stuff within moments of arriving, without needing to have asked. Luxury and simplicity come together in a routinized ritual that completes a Saturday morning.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_20051.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2556 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_20051.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_2005" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>A visit to Neukölln&#8217;s diner-ish mock up, CABslam, offers a similar experience, albeit with wood in place of the traditional synthetic materials. The waitresses greet guests in English with a smile, a touch of accent on the tongue; plates of meat, starch, and sugar pass through the spacious, half-finished space, disturbed only by the squeal of espresso. Oh, American breakfast in Europe: such a strange delicacy, indeed.</p>
<p>If I were to come upon a similar diner anywhere in the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/">Pacific Northwest</a>, I would be confused by 1. the small portions, 2. the texture of the syrup, 3. the small portions, 4. the fancy coffee, and 5. the small portions. But while in that strange space of not always quite fitting in and not being quite sure how to amend the problem, one takes any moment of assured (if strangely assembled) belonging and identity one can get.</p>
<p>And so I ordered French toast, Juri ordered the original California Breakfast Slam, and I ate his pancakes and felt thoroughly pleased with the entire situation.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01335.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2524" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01335.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01335" width="640" height="960" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01335.jpg 433w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01335-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>Glancing around the perhaps far-too spacious-to-be-cozy restaurant-in-progress, plates of beans and eggs (Huevos Rancheros!),  yellow sauce and bread (Eggs Benedict!), and hearty scrambles made it all just believable enough&#8230;even if it is not possible to get a side of sweet &#8216;Amish bread&#8217; here, as is the case with my favorite diner in Seattle, <a href="http://www.bethscafe.com/index.php">Beth&#8217;s Cafe</a>. Beginnings are always a bit modest, anyway.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01336.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2525 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01336.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01336" width="640" height="426" /></a></p>
<p>After our plates had been cleared, all sauces sopped up with available eatable utensils, I pondered my just-consumed identity and belonging with a nice long sip of espresso. Though perhaps still a bit hungry for American-diner standards, the starvation for the validation that comes from truly fitting in &#8211; in this case, the belonging that comes from just understanding the absurdly starchy rituals that constitute American breakfast &#8211; was momentarily gone.</p>
<p>This felt quite good.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01340.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2529" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01340.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01340" width="640" height="960" /></a></p>
<p>While consuming something in the morning hours that would otherwise be reserved for a combination of dessert, second dessert, and holidays in Germany, the recognition that &#8220;yes, this is perhaps not the healthiest but yes, this is delicious, and I will enjoy it&#8221; bubbles up, almost unexpectedly.</p>
<p>American food culture is shaped and even manipulated by advertising&#8217;s exploitation of this very urge to give-in, indulge, and consume &#8216;freedom&#8217; as embodied in a fried-chicken-pizza or a Big Gulp &#8211; as nicely laid out in an <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/currency/2014/04/fast-food-doubles-down.html">article on the success of such fast-food antics in America</a> in this past week&#8217;s issue of <em>The</em> <em>New Yorker</em>.</p>
<p>But looking around at the improvisational furniture and faux diner fixtures at CABslam, the abstract and even fictive nature of such an experience became strikingly clear: The setting did not necessarily fit my expectations, but the frame was just large enough to allow textures, smells, and memories to gently assemble a replica of &#8216;home&#8217;. Minus the Amish bread.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01326.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2515" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01326.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01326" width="640" height="426" /></a></p>
<p>If one were to survey immigrants and/or expats around the world, one thing would surely be held in common &#8211; a lust after the foods of whence one has come. This does not mean that these foods are objectively good or even at the top of my list. But this is not the point. Even though the mere idea of many American delights makes me a little uneasy and sad for the state of national nutrition (see &#8220;<a href="http://www.takepart.com/place-at-the-table">A Place at the Table</a>&#8221; for the full story), I delight just a little in being associated with such a cuisine. Because it is familiar and mine, in a way intimately intertwined with memory and what identity makes of it.</p>
<p>More than anything else, the moments at my childhood-dream-table, where chocolate-chip pancakes were the best reward and hash browns the coveted snack, are the things that bring me the simplest of glee in a situation that is often colored by uncertainty. And that, folks, is the CABslam effect.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01323.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2533" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01323.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01323" width="640" height="426" /></a></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>Cabslam is located at Innstraße 47, 12045 Neukölln, open (now also for lunch and dinner) Mo-So 11:00-midnight. Their <a href="http://www.cabslam.com/">official website</a> is currently under construction, so best use the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/cabslam/info">facebook page</a> for more information on their rotating menu, as well as to make reservations. Long live American breakfast! All photos by <a href="http://jurigottschau.com/">Juri Gottschau</a>.</p>
<p><em>*If the mention of ethnographical studies sparked your interest, here is some further reading on immigrant identity, diaspora memory, and &#8211; you guessed it &#8211; food, brought to you by the wonderful discipline of sociocultural anthropology:</em><br />
Bahloul, J. 1989, &#8220;From a Muslim banquet to a Jewish seder: food ways and ethnicity among North African Jews&#8221;, in <em>Jews Among Arabs: Contacts and Boundaries</em>, ed. Cohen, M. Camp; A. Udovitch.<br />
Buckser A. 1999, <em>Keeping kosher: eating and social identity among the Jews of Denmark</em>, <em>Ethnology</em>, vol. 38.<br />
Chapman et al. 2011, &#8220;Meanings of food, eating and health in Punjabi families living in Vancouver, Canada&#8221;,<em>Health Education Journal</em>, vol. 70, no. 1.<br />
Harbottle, L. 1997, &#8220;Taste and embodiment: the food preferences of Iranians in Britain&#8221;, in <em>Food Preference and Taste: Continuity and Change</em>, ed. MacBeth, H.<br />
Holtzman, John D. 2006, &#8220;Food and Memory&#8221;, <em>Annual Review of Anthropology</em>, no. 35.<br />
Mankekar, P. 2002, “&#8217;India shopping&#8217;: Indian grocery stores and transnational conﬁguration of belonging&#8221;, <em>Ethnos</em>, vol. 67, no. 1.<br />
Lee, SSJ. 2000, &#8220;Dys-appearing tongues and bodily memories: the aging of ﬁrst-generation resident Koreans in Japan&#8221;, <em>Ethos</em>, vol. 28, no. 2.<br />
Ray, K. 2004, <em>The Migrant’s Table: Meals and Memories in Bengali-American Households</em>.<br />
Şebnem, Timur Ögüt 2008, &#8220;Turkish restaurants in London: An ethnographic study on representation of cultural identity through design&#8221;, <em>ITU A|Z</em>, vol. 5.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Collidoscope Manifesto</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/22/the-collidoscope-manifesto/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/22/the-collidoscope-manifesto/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[collidoscopeks]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 09:45:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cities]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2395</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A couple months ago, Collidoscope Berlin was invited to write its first guest post for the Global Citizens Initiative - an organization that aims “to build a network of people who see themselves as global citizens and want to build a better world”. Part of the task was to connect what we do here to the significance of borders. “Borders?”, we wondered, unsure how to proceed but mostly questioning why we had never concretely addressed the topic before...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_6374.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2441 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_6374.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_6374" width="640" height="426" /></a></strong></p>
<p><strong>A couple months ago, Collidoscope Berlin was invited to write its first guest post for the <a href="http://us5.campaign-archive2.com/?u=34e2670d2b1df6a04603724fa&amp;id=3a6a8f6948&amp;e=b0926c0e88">Global Citizens Initiative</a> </strong>&#8211; an organization that aims &#8220;to build a network of people who see themselves as global citizens and want to build a better world&#8221;. Part of the task was to connect what we do here to the significance of borders. &#8220;Borders?&#8221;, we wondered, unsure how to proceed but mostly questioning why we had never concretely addressed the topic before. What kind of immigration project doesn&#8217;t discuss borders?</p>
<p>When we launched this project in April of last year, we knew we wanted to do something <em>different </em>related to the topic of<em> difference. </em>We knew of groups that promoted and celebrated cultural and ethnic diversity. We had worked for institutions that research and analyze immigrant integration. Our goal was to do something in between, producing articles and commentary that both told a story and provided facts and context. And we wanted to do this through the lens of one city that, although formed by a unique historical and political context, could perhaps provide lessons for others.</p>
<p><strong>A few days ago, Collidoscope Berlin turned one-year old </strong>&#8211; and as we took the opportunity to reflect back, we realized that not talking about borders was, in fact, making a statement about borders. It wasn&#8217;t that we thought borders were unimportant or that we were advocating their complete erosion. Rather, we were advocating for the idea that every city <span style="letter-spacing: 0;">is home to its very own “collision” of cultures and thus has <em>unique</em> stories about diversity and difference. Through the lens of migration &#8211; the movement and coming together of people &#8211; we believe that we can understand more about what makes &#8216;us&#8217; who we are on the individual, local, and global scales. Through our personal lens of moving and living across borders, we aim to make sense of what defines and shapes the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/26/lens-coming-home/">places we call home</a>, as well as the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/16/lens-going-away/">places we leave</a>. Cities, as a reflection of &#8216;the we&#8217;, are a good place to start.</span></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/cropped-2012-08-22-19-03-431.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-18" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/cropped-2012-08-22-19-03-431.jpg?w=640" alt="cropped-2012-08-22-19-03-431.jpg" width="640" height="221" /></a></p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>The Collidoscope Manifesto </strong></span></p>
<p><em>Originally published as a guest post for the <a href="http://us5.campaign-archive2.com/?u=34e2670d2b1df6a04603724fa&amp;id=3a6a8f6948&amp;e=b0926c0e88">Global Citizens Initiative</a><strong><br />
</strong></em></p>
<p>Individuals are born within borders. On a map, these borders seem relatively arbitrary: meandering lines awkwardly encircling blurbs of land. And yet in our lives, the purpose they are meant to serve is anything but, as borders demarcate political, legal, and bureaucratic spaces, as much as they do geographic ones. For it is not geography &#8211; the land itself &#8211; that keeps us from coming and going. It is our (hu)man-made political systems and governments that determine who is permitted to enter or leave, to immigrate or emigrate, to belong or not to belong.</p>
<p>Despite the presence of these borders, we all make our way across these lines one way or another. Whether through relationships abroad, use of technology, involvement in international groups, or participation in the global economy: our lives are increasingly global and less tied to the borders in which we were born or reside. While this does not automatically make us all global citizens (which necessitates awareness and action), it fosters connections across borders that reinforce the idea of a world community. How can we reconcile this ever-present reality with our understanding of borders and restrictions on an individual’s freedom of movement?</p>
<p>The majority of us – more than ever before &#8211; lives in cities. Thanks largely to migration, modern cities have become microcosms of the global community, home to spectacular cultural, ethnic, and religious diversity. While this “collision” of cultures can pose challenges, it is also a tremendous opportunity for growth and enrichment. If we begin to view our cities’ pockets and spaces of difference as opportunities – becoming more empathetic, inclusive, and participatory in the process – we can begin to realize global values within local communities.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_0388.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2577 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719-650x433.jpg" alt="Collidoscope Berlin Manifesto" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Berlin, Germany is one example: a city with a long history of attracting those who are “different”, where 1 in every 4 residents is of foreign origin and 138 countries are represented. A city that is undergoing constant transformation, while undertaking the challenge of integrating not only newcomers, but the 2nd and 3rd generations. A city that is brimming with rich diversity and teeming with opportunities. <span style="letter-spacing: 0;">Collidoscope Berlin is a celebration of these stories and opportunities, a conversation-starter, a democratic and inclusive view of the many peoples, spaces, and settings that constitute the modern city. </span></p>
<p><strong>Lessons from Berlin: </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/">Ramadan with Neighbors</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/12/20/happy-weekend-review-an-old-new-christmas-market/">The Thai Park</a>,<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/12/20/happy-weekend-review-an-old-new-christmas-market/"> An Old-New Christmas Market</a></p>
<p><strong>Lessons from Beyond: </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/29/beyond-berlin-the-istanbul-connection/">The Istanbul Connection</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/">The American Northwest</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/03/beyond-berlin-difference-on-the-blessed-isle/">Difference in Sri Lanka </a></p>
<p><strong>What is Multiculturalism? </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/">Diversity &amp; the Big City</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/10/whose-multikulti-is-it-the-elusive-definition-of-multiculturalism/">Whose Multikulti is it?</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/18/happy-weekend-karneval-der-kulturen-carnival-of-cultures/">Carnival of Cultures</a></p>
<p><strong>Our Stories: </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/16/lens-going-away/">Going Away</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/26/lens-coming-home/">Coming Home</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/29/lens-linsanity-and-linguine/">Linsanity and Linguine</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/25/lens-lamb-on-fridays/">Lamb on Fridays</a></p>
<p><strong>Local Stories:</strong> <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/09/interview-ali-zoe-and-the-gentrification-debate/">Ali &amp; Zoe</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/">Orhan</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/21/lens-warm-nights-are-for-cricket/">Warm Nights are for Cricket</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">Moran &amp; Tommy</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/30/interview-hamid-stardom-and-the-difference-threshold/">Hamid</a></p>
<p><strong>We&#8217;d like to conclude this anniversary post by thanking everyone who has been part of the discussion this past year</strong> &#8211; reading, commenting, critiquing, supporting, following, contributing photos and story ideas and event announcements &#8211; we appreciate it all and look forward to another year of <span class="userContent">diversity, difference, and positive discourse!</span></p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By</em> <em><strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em> <em>and</em> <em><strong>Kelly Miller</strong> </em></p>
<p>First photo by Anna Meister, second photo by Collidoscope Berlin, third photo by <a href="http://jurigottschau.com/">Juri Gottschau</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/22/the-collidoscope-manifesto/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: An Ode to the Maybachufer</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/20/lens-an-ode-to-the-maybachufer/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/20/lens-an-ode-to-the-maybachufer/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2014 11:53:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gentrification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1853</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[From Berlin's "problem district" to more expensive than spießig Charlottenburg: Kreuzberg's made quite the transformation over the decades, but migration continues to shape its identity and reputation as a district. The bulk of Kreuzberg's diversity stems from the '50s and '60s, when guest workers were recruited by West Germany to fill labor shortages after World War II*. Kreuzberg's dilapidated housing became home to guest workers, primarily from Turkey...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From Berlin&#8217;s &#8220;problem district&#8221; to <a href="http://www.bz-berlin.de/aktuell/berlin/kreuzberg-teurer-als-charlottenburg-article1398469.html">more expensive</a> than <em>spießig</em> Charlottenburg: Kreuzberg&#8217;s made quite the transformation over the decades, but migration continues to shape its identity and reputation as a district.</p>
<p>The bulk of Kreuzberg&#8217;s diversity stems from the &#8217;50s and &#8217;60s, when guest workers were recruited by West Germany to fill labor shortages after World War II*. Kreuzberg&#8217;s dilapidated housing became home to guest workers, primarily from Turkey. The district soon came to be known as &#8220;Little Istanbul&#8221;. In 2014 you would still be hard pressed to find a block without a <em>Döner</em> <em>Kebab </em>stand or five, but the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/">district&#8217;s diversity</a> extends far past Anatolia.</p>
<p>Along with districts like Neukölln and Wedding, Kreuzberg is renowned for its <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/11/happy-weekend-its-not-about-integration-or-isnt-it/">immigrant integration</a> challenges that include low educational attainment and poor German language skills, high unemployment rates, crime and drug abuse, and gentrification. At the same time, the area has become increasingly attractive to <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/">students</a>, hip expats, and young families. The result is a veritable array of nationalities, cuisines, houses of worship, and attires, as vivid as the graffiti gracing the walls of its gray housing and slender canals.</p>
<p>There are many popular spots in Kreuzberg, but the Maybachufer canal is perhaps one that most poignantly displays the cultural fusion that makes Kreuzberg a very special place to call home.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/swans.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/swans.jpg" alt="swans" width="594" height="594" /></a></p>
<p><strong>An Ode to the Maybachufer</strong></p>
<p>If I go away, I&#8217;ll remember the swans. And the walls of graffiti they floated along.</p>
<p>Rows of satellite dishes, speckled across gray concrete. Lingerers outside Kaiser&#8217;s, empty bottles at their feet.</p>
<p>Men huddled over pear-shaped glasses of Çay. Girls in tiny shorts and tights, snags in their thighs.</p>
<p>A market with only two rows, but infinite choice. Vendors calling &#8220;lecka! lecka!&#8221;, hints of somewhere else in their voice.</p>
<p>Hair smothered by scarves or impossibly fake dye. Individuals by words: &#8220;expat&#8221;, &#8220;immigrant&#8221;. You or I.</p>
<p>Where &#8220;German&#8221; ends and &#8220;other&#8221; begins, we futilely try to decide.</p>
<p>But the swans. They just keep floating by.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The Maybachufer Turkish Market (U1-Kottbusser Tor or U8-Schoenleinstrasse) runs on Tuesdays and Fridays from approximately 12pm-6pm. Go for the cheap produce and spinach-cheese <em>Gözleme. </em><br />
</em></p>
<p>* West Germany recruited 14 million guest workers between 1955 and 1973 during the post World War II &#8220;economic miracle&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>For more on Turks in Germany and guest worker programs:</strong></p>
<p>http://www.azcentral.com/news/articles/global-immigration-germany.html?nclick_check=1</p>
<p><strong>For more on Kreuzberg:  </strong></p>
<p>http://www.fhxb-museum.de/</p>
<p>http://travel.michelin.com/web/destination/Germany-Berlin/news-Kreuzberg_forever-Reichenberger_Str_177</p>
<p>http://www.humanityinaction.org/knowledgebase/32-in-kreuzberg-there-are-no-foreigners-scrutinizing-berlin-s-diversity</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/20/lens-an-ode-to-the-maybachufer/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: Difference on the Blessed Isle</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/03/beyond-berlin-difference-on-the-blessed-isle/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2014 17:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[exoticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sri Lanka]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[travel]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2018</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For about three weeks this holiday season, I explored the small tear-shaped island of Sri Lanka with a close friend from Berlin. Though Sri Lanka and the South Asia region were new terrain for us both, this wasn't our first backpacking rodeo. We were experienced enough travelers to expect the ups and downs that a trip of this magnitude would throw our way. We reveled in the highs - a school of fish gracefully drifting past us 12m deep into the Indian Ocean, the exquisitely pungent scents and colors of turmeric and homemade roasted curry powder...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>How do you notice difference in a place, when you expect <em>everything</em> to be different? </strong></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/2013-12-29-13-33-30.jpg"><img loading="lazy" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/2013-12-29-13-33-30.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-12-29 13.33.30" width="634" height="537" /></a></p>
<p>For about three weeks this holiday season, I explored the small tear-shaped island of Sri Lanka with a close friend from Berlin. Though Sri Lanka and the South Asia region were new terrain for us both, this wasn&#8217;t our first backpacking rodeo. We were experienced enough travelers to expect the ups and downs that a trip of this magnitude would throw our way. We reveled in the highs &#8211; a school of fish gracefully drifting past us 12m deep into the Indian Ocean, the exquisitely pungent scents and colors of turmeric and homemade roasted curry powder, a 360 degree view of the greenest green imaginable in tea plantation territory, a monk whipping out his iPad to snap a photo of us hiking. And we did our best to laugh through the lows &#8211; a seven hour train ride on the ground by the toilets, being followed and sexually propositioned by a strange man on a dark road, accidentally paying our safari jeep driver twice, the ruthless mosquitos that left me with infected foot wounds I&#8217;m still watching heal.</p>
<p>But these moments were the superlatives, the stand-outs. When traveling in a place where we expect everything to be different, we may become so focused on the exotic and extreme that we overlook the &#8220;in-between&#8221;: the nuances that expose intricate relationships and interconnections, diversity within diversity, and differences among difference.</p>
<p><strong>Nuances matter<br />
</strong></p>
<p>It took one quick glance at a <em>Sari</em> for me to have an idea about modesty in Sri Lankan female dress (&#8220;they can show their bellies and backs but not their shoulders and knees?!&#8221;). One trip to the bathroom with an unusually low toilet seat had me wondering if Sri Lankans were all very short (&#8220;are all toilets going to be like this?!&#8221;). In other words, I had made my first assumptions about Sri Lankan culture before even leaving the airport. Correction: <em>Before leaving passport control</em>. A few minutes upon arrival and my brain was on overdrive, actively seeking out the exciting, frantically trying to affirm preconceived ideas and make connections. Maybe fatigue, definitely curiosity, likely a survival instinct. I desperately wanted to &#8220;understand&#8221; the place in which I was going to be spending the next three weeks of my life, but I was primarily doing so on a larger, generalizing scale. While my mind naturally looks for nuances and intricacy at home, it took an active effort to protest generalizing abroad. Otherwise my mind would have continued to host its very own <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/18/happy-weekend-karneval-der-kulturen-carnival-of-cultures/"><em>Karneval der Kulturen</em></a>, watching a parade of one-toned diversity go by and glossing over the subtleties.</p>
<div id="attachment_2046" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/2014-01-02-11-28-25.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2046" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-2046" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/2014-01-02-11-28-25.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-01-02 11.28.25" width="640" height="480" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2046" class="wp-caption-text">Looking for the in-between in Tangalle</p></div>
<p><strong><strong>It&#8217;s sometimes not about what we say, but what we don&#8217;t<br />
</strong></strong></p>
<p>Once we made it out of the airport, Anna and I encountered the &#8220;Your country?&#8221; or &#8220;Madame, you are from?&#8221; question at a rate of approximately once per hour. While I would ponder how to put &#8220;Well actually, we met in Buenos Aires, Anna is German but spent half her life in England, I grew up in the U.S. but have a German passport, we live in Germany but speak English together&#8221; into one concise thought, Anna was usually quick to respond with &#8220;Germany&#8221;. Considering how much <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/">this type of question can provoke discussion and bother me at home</a>, I was surprised at how quickly I followed suit and resigned myself to the &#8220;put me in a box&#8221; game. On top of that, I was doing the same in return, never going beyond the &#8220;do you come from this town?&#8221; question with locals. Granted, not every conversation while traveling has to be life-altering, and language often poses a barrier, but opportunities were surely missed to explore our understanding of identity and (inter-)nationality. The one-word response was convenient not only because it was quick &#8211; it facilitated our interactions and put them at a comfortable status quo. &#8220;I am a German tourist and you are a Sri Lankan local&#8221; was never the whole story, but it was story enough. But what about the stories we missed?</p>
<div id="attachment_2042" style="width: 622px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/2014-01-09-13-42-23.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2042" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2042 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/2014-01-09-13-42-23.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-01-09 13.42.23" width="612" height="589" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2042" class="wp-caption-text">Tuk Tuking in Colombo</p></div>
<p><strong>Relationships are often more complex than we expect<br />
</strong></p>
<p>&#8220;Ahhhhaaaa,&#8221; the Tuk-Tuk driver or waiter would say after we answered the above, a knowing smile on his face, &#8220;<em>Alles klar</em>?&#8221; The surprise of Sri Lankans speaking a few words of German faded rapidly as we realized the extent of German tourism to Sri Lanka (It&#8217;s the <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2013-06-17/sri-lanka-s-may-tourist-arrivals-by-country-table-.html">third largest visitor-generating market</a> to Sri Lanka after India and the UK). We spent two fateful days on Beruwala beach experiencing the extent of Teutonic tourism: in a German-run resort surrounded by a predominantly German clientele eating from a menu complete with &#8220;German specialities&#8221; (Schnitzel with a view, anyone?), marking their beach-chair territory at the break of dawn, and interacting with Sri Lankans only when they needed their next smoothie.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/2014-01-05-10-13-31.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2081" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/2014-01-05-10-13-31.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-01-05 10.13.31" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>Yet tourism turned out to be only the tip of the Sri Lankan-German-Iceberg. More often than not, our Sri Lankan inquirer would proceed to tell us about his brother who works in a restaurant in Düsseldorf, his university studies in Heidelberg, her father&#8217;s German friends who came to visit every year, his decision to pursue science thanks to Einstein, even that we looked like we came from Munich (ouch). One guesthouse employee donned a shirt with German and Sri Lankan flags that he got from the local German-run <em>Kinderheim.</em> On one bus ride, we rolled by a station donated by Germans. In Galle, a shopkeeper recited the last eight German Chancellors to us in chronological order. The relationship between these two countries repeatedly smacked us in the face, each day and in every which direction.</p>
<div style="width: 622px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/2014-01-08-16-19-45.jpg"><img loading="lazy" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/2014-01-08-16-19-45.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-01-08 16.19.45" width="612" height="612" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Punctuality not included?</p></div>
<p><strong>Just because a relationship exists, doesn&#8217;t make it two-sided<br />
</strong></p>
<p>The Sri Lankans we encountered were much more aware of Germany and Germans than we had expected. But what about the reverse &#8211; the German perception of this dynamic, continually evolving, and surprisingly multifaceted bi-national relationship? My instinct is that when Germans think of Sri Lanka, they picture pristine beaches, coconut trees, people eating with their hands, and maybe a country re-emerging after the longest war in Asia&#8217;s history. I&#8217;m less confident that they see a legacy of exchange, generation-long friendships, or a cab driver studying science because of Einstein. My hopes remain low after the doctor inspecting my foot wounds back in Berlin asked if they &#8220;also speak Indian there?&#8221;, and I was unable to find any substantial information online about Sri Lankans in Berlin, other than <a href="http://www.berlin.de/restaurants/kueche/?atgrp=Sri-lankisch&amp;atpg=0#atlist1647158">this list of restaurants</a>. It may not be visible, but a Sri Lankan community in Berlin does exist (<a href="https://www.statistik-berlin-brandenburg.de/Publikationen/Stat_Berichte/2013/SB_A01-05-00_2012h02_BE.pdf">1,113 Sri Lankan nationals</a> as of the end of 2012) and is conceivably more diverse than we think.</p>
<p>After three weeks in the most &#8220;exotic&#8221; place I&#8217;ve ever visited, my most striking take-away is that an authentic travel experience must extend beyond exoticism. To really understand what it means to be Sri Lankan, German, or anything else, it is perhaps the nuances that count the most.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>All photos by yours truly. For more information on Sri Lankans in Berlin, check out the <a href="http://www.srilankans-berlin.de/">Sri Lankan Association Berlin</a></em>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: Difference in the Wet Country</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2014 12:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[provincial]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1986</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For nearly a month this holiday season, I explored the social fabric surrounding my US origins with a German national, who had never before been to the land of plenty. Through the fresh eyes of 'the foreigner', I saw my part of America unfold under a curious and critical lens. America is a country that defines itself by historical narratives of migration and manifest destiny. What one encounters on the road in its northwestern corner, however, is a bit more mundane. At closer glance, emptiness and the prosaic everyday give food for thought, in regards to locating and valuing difference wherever it bubbles up...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>How do you notice difference in a city, in which you yourself are different?</strong></p>
<div id="attachment_1992" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1992" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1992 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-1.jpg" alt="Portland, OR steel-bridge" width="640" height="360" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1992" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>For nearly a month this holiday season, I explored the social fabric surrounding my US origins with a German national, who had never before been to the land of plenty. Through the fresh eyes of &#8216;the foreigner&#8217;, I saw my part of America unfold under a curious and critical lens. Given this blog&#8217;s weekly critical handling of all things multicultural in the big city, why not talk about diversity in an American context? This context proves to be quite different from the aspiring-cosmopolitan intersections of the German capital, as shocking as that may or may not be.</p>
<p>America is a country that defines itself by historical narratives of migration and manifest destiny. What one encounters on the road in its northwestern corner, however, is a bit more mundane. At closer glance, emptiness and the prosaic everyday give food for thought, in regards to locating and valuing difference wherever it bubbles up.</p>
<p><strong>Geography matters</strong></p>
<p>Somehow, when we talk of diversity in society, the role of space therein is a side note. In fact, where we live, work, play, learn, and heal in many ways determines our belonging to or exclusion from social and economic groups that are important in ensuring opportunity.</p>
<p>Maps tell us a lot about how different ways of life can exist cohesively together. Maps may miss, however (<a href="http://www.npr.org/censusmap/#4.00/39.00/-84.00">see NPR&#8217;s US census map</a>), where difference pops up beyond the packed hotbeds for multiculturalism of the city, leaving our eyes to experience what the provinces, the forgotten towns, and the coastal sticks have to offer firsthand.</p>
<div id="attachment_1989" style="width: 311px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1989" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1989 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg" alt="Rebecca Vincent" width="301" height="300" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg 301w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent-300x299.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 301px) 100vw, 301px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1989" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Rebecca Vincent</p></div>
<p>In the Pacific Northwest, like many other regions, cartography shows the urban as an array of ever-revolving grids, residences dotting the margins of concrete webs and precise civil engineering, greenery contained, parks splashed with beige and lived-in browns. One passes through these strange boundaries of growth, as if moving through the trunk of a tree to reach its core, each ring giving way to new densities and shapes of living, suburbia giving way to semi-rural apartment clusters and neatly arranged town homes.</p>
<div id="attachment_2001" style="width: 471px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2001" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2001  " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png?w=640" alt="portland map" width="461" height="347" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png 646w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map-300x226.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map-80x60.png 80w" sizes="(max-width: 461px) 100vw, 461px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2001" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Mappery.com</p></div>
<p>Apart from the patterns and markings of cities, great expanses of forest or farmland separate bundles of life from one another. Beyond the edge of the urban, an emptiness emerges. Where cities end, mountain pass truck-stops, wine-making valleys, flat dairy country, coastal trailer parks, and retired logging towns begin. Vehicles connect what trains used to. Marks on the map created for the movement between these revolving grids begin to surface like geometric occurrences of ink. Here humans somehow ended up, often fairly alone with only the company of a gas station and a corner store.</p>
<div id="attachment_2002" style="width: 476px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2002" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2002   " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png?w=640" alt="oregon map" width="466" height="375" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png 749w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map-300x241.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map-650x522.png 650w" sizes="(max-width: 466px) 100vw, 466px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2002" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Oregon Office of Rural Health</p></div>
<p>Passing through such places on the road from one side of the state of Oregon to the next, the new set of eyes saw only distance, forged together by oil rigs and spinning tires. <em>Density can be an advantage, when it comes to social and cultural encounters needed for intercultural understandings to take root</em>, I thought, as we searched for a place to eat on a long stretch that seemed to allow only signage, fast food, and campgrounds.</p>
<div id="attachment_1990" style="width: 471px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-2.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1990" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-1990 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-2.jpg" alt="Portland, OR steel-bridge " width="461" height="614" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1990" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>And yet, the migrant worker shantytown in Southwest Washington, the Korean BBQ embedded in the Tillamook state forest, the sushi bar near Mt. Hood’s base, the taco trucks at truck-stops, the Chinese waiter at the roadside diner all suggest that even in more expansive geographies, difference can occur.</p>
<p><strong>Just because it is there, doesn&#8217;t mean we will notice it</strong></p>
<p>On our way to the valley of the Rogue River, our over-sized vehicle wound down the Pacific Highway, hugging cliffs of the sea and the edges of a strange poverty. We saw mile after mile of rotting cottages, mobile homes made more mobile by landslides, empty villages with the local pub serving bento, tacos, and chowder, and liquor stores the size of the local church beside it. Catholic churches sprouted up in these towns, in the basin of the interstate or at the rim of the sea &#8211; something I did not take notice of at first, but which suggested some shift, an immigration. Those who find ships in the right season or canneries with need for cheaply-bought hands make their way back to the Saints to thank them for their providence, or so it seemed.</p>
<p>In the foggy valleys of dead logging towns, the basin of the interstate, the depressed dairy lands and empty harbors: here the German traveler experienced my part of America with its shady diners where breakfast and hot sauce are served all day, roadside shacks with a For Sale sign, Walmart’s to nowhere. And in between the lines, difference was there, simply glossed over by the mundanity of its appearance, bearing more than John Wayne&#8217;s Americana.</p>
<div id="attachment_1994" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/streeet.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1994" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-1994 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/streeet.jpg?w=640" alt="street Portland, OR" width="640" height="360" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1994" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>The churches that never cease to be obvious and enormous on major highways; the Mexican restaurants with happy signs and plenty of American families digging into re-fried beans and rice, as if it were the national dish; the Japanese restaurants with pictures of majestic mountains that could be local; medical advertisements with black patients and Asian doctors; a South Asian newscaster in a suit just like everybody else; a black reporter stuck to sports on the local news station: these things I may not have noticed without the presence of the new perspective next to me.</p>
<p><strong>It is not about what we say, but about what is heard</strong></p>
<div id="attachment_1991" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/diner-pwf-0066.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1991" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-1991" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/diner-pwf-0066.jpg?w=300" alt="Photo source: Paul Winch-Furness" width="300" height="199" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1991" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Paul Winch-Furness</p></div>
<p>For the German&#8217;s second breakfast in America, we took him to a local diner in southwest Washington with the classic booths and red upholstery, simple fried numbers, and a healthy rotation of pies. As he ordered, his slight accent turned the words into mildly different sounds, his tongue pushing just a bit too far back for the &#8216;l&#8217; and the &#8216;th&#8217; sticking to the front of his teeth. The letters may have come together in a way that did not quite fit the frames we have learned to repeat, but one could and can simply understand. And so &#8216;the waffle special&#8217; was transmitted to the kitchen with no questions asked. And after we had told the waitress in her darling little apron that it was his first time in an American diner, she beamed at the foreigner sitting there in front of the simple white dishware and the paper napkin. She whispered to the other waitress, who, blushing, came over to our table to pour coffee and welcome him to town.</p>
<p>It is not about the sounds being right. It is about our understanding them.</p>
<p><strong>Being an outsider can come in handy, as I have learned on the other side of the Atlantic</strong></p>
<p>Growing up in the far corner of the Western United States, I am familiar with the figures and curves of this particular landscape and society. I have, however, sorely taken for granted what it means to have tacos in the middle of nowhere, to celebrate Persian New Year with friends, or to consider Phở as American as bratwurst (I can thank Seattle for that). In many ways, difference was a natural part of my private and public education, the neighborhoods where I lived, the sports teams I played on, and the churches I attended. I cannot say that I have consciously valued these experiences for what I learned from them. If such encounters and relationships had popped up in my Berlin world, I would have celebrated them. This is largely due to the ways in which diversity is or is not celebrated by society at large and how we might attempt to remedy this fact.</p>
<p>But what is most striking and assuredly the take-away from this tale is that campaign-worthy diversity in the big city is not all there is, nor is it of greater value than the outcroppings of difference at truck-stops off the interstate. This might be where it counts the most.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Ethno-cultural diversity is changing the face of the rural United States, including states like Oregon and Washington. For a great visual of this transformation, see the <a href="http://www.ers.usda.gov/media/176091/page7.pdf">United States Department of Agriculture&#8217;s map from its Rural Population and Migration Brieﬁng Room</a>. As the roadside taco trucks and shantytowns demonstrate, a large wave of migration from Latin America to the Pacific Northwest region has characterized rural growth from 2000-2012, according to the <a href="http://www.ers.usda.gov/amber-waves/2011-december/hispanics-contribute-to-increasing-diversity.aspx#.Ut5lnRA1iM8">USDA&#8217;s recent report</a> on demography. Reflective of this shift to the out-country from the urban heart, is the <a href="http://www.oregonlive.com/pacific-northwest-news/index.ssf/2011/04/in_portlands_heart_diversity_dwindles.html">dwindling diversity in the heart of Portland, OR</a>. Difference is, thus, not always where you expect to find it.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
