<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Nazi &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/nazi/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Review: &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; and the White Audience</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2014 14:00:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Afrodeutsch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nazi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[segregation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theater]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2248</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One attends a play about an Afro-German living in the years of Nazism and Jim Crow not because of the dramaturgy. One buys the ticket because of the topic's near absence in the German discourse. This is not a review of the play, but rather a continuation of the discussion with the cast that followed. As one of the cast-members remarked, it all comes down to audience: "Black folks probably wouldn't go to the theater to see this play in the U.S., let alone have enough money for the ticket. And here, we have a white audience. So, who are we really talking to here? Who is seeing this play?"...
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>As a student of my own history and place in this world, nothing is more difficult for me than to write about issues of privilege, white-ness, black-ness, and justice in one sitting, because there is so much that can go wrong, so many terms that can be mis-used or mis-assigned, and so many truths that cannot be conveyed in one text. I have done my best. And with all my socio-anthropological know-how, I may still miss the point or offend, for which I am sorry: so is the nature of the subject.</em></p>
<p>One attends a play about an <em>Afrodeutscher* &#8211; </em>Afro-German &#8211; living in the years of Nazism and Jim Crow not because of the dramaturgy. One buys the ticket because of the topic, i.e. its novelty and near absence in the German discourse. &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221;, &#8220;Made Black&#8221;, at the <a href="http://www.etberlin.de/">English Theatre Berlin</a> explores the rich text of race in 1930s Berlin through the experience of Klaus, an unknowing Afro-German &#8211; a word that still spikes the air with rarity, German-ness still seen by many as a monopoly of the white-skinned.</p>
<p>But Klaus&#8217;s character and his experience of targeted exclusion are not that far from the present, as a conversation with the cast will demonstrate.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_4.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_4.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht" width="640" height="1016" /></a></p>
<p>The play&#8217;s dense telling of a complicated history of race, citizenship, and post-colonialism through dialogue is impressive. Equally worthy of praise is the playwright&#8217;s collaboration with a well-versed historian.  The Afro-German actor, with a biography startlingly similar to the protagonist he portrays, is also seemingly extraordinary. The most important element, however, relates to its audience and what this means for theater as a medium of cultural critique.</p>
<p>This is not a review of the play, per se, on which the curtains closed this past Sunday. Rather, this is a review of the discussion with the cast, playwright, and director that came after, the sentiments of which will remain prominent and powerful in my mind, long after audience members have discarded their ticket stubs.</p>
<p><strong>The Conversation</strong></p>
<p>Thursday night, we, a primarily white audience, wait patiently for the cast to take their places at the foot of the stage. The protagonist of the play, the actor to play the American jazz musician, the actor to play the German politician, the playwright (Alexander Thomas), and the director file into folding chairs. <strong>&#8220;Black folks probably wouldn&#8217;t go to the theater to see this play in the U.S., let alone have enough money for the ticket. And here, we have a white audience. So, who are we really talking to here? Who is seeing this play?&#8221;</strong>, says the actor who plays the Black American musician &#8211; the play&#8217;s connective thread to Jim Crow.<strong> </strong>The scene seems to agree.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_3.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2259" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_3.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht theater cast" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>Daniel Brunet, the mustached upstate New Yorker who produces the <a href="http://www.etberlin.de/producing-series/the-lab/">LAB series</a> for the English Theatre and directed this play, chimes in about the lack of representation of certain &#8220;communities&#8221; in cultural institutions. The problem of equitable, fair representation is something sure to resound for both American and German audiences, though certainly in different ways.</p>
<p>This problem is an old one. But it rattles and recalls Berlin&#8217;s more recent debates on multiculturalism, intercultural politics, and the integration &#8211; or just plain tolerance &#8211; of difference. &#8220;The topic of being German <em>and </em>of<em> </em>being a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Person_of_color">person of color</a> (p.o.c.) continues, often with little progress&#8221;, a p.o.c. from the audience remarks, a hint of a German accent in the throat. This topic is contemporary, indeed.</p>
<p><strong>Can theater change these parameters? Can theater ask for more diversity from institutions that have no incentive to include them?</strong></p>
<p>The playwright, a Black American married to a white German woman, wrote &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; as a way to process &#8220;the complexity of these issues&#8221;. And yet, as he makes perfectly clear, representing his own stereotypes of Germans and &#8220;the lack of place in [his] mind for an Other of color in Germany&#8221; is central to the play. &#8220;Otherwise, I would have been acting dishonestly&#8221;, he says, looking into the glare, behind which fragments of the audience, of us, must appear.</p>
<p>The protagonist of the play, himself an Afro-German, speaks, his English flooded with German vowels, his mannerisms oddly similar to his character, who re-asserts his German identity proudly throughout the play in deference to the Othering looks of those around him. This Other, created by the Black American writer, is somehow a reflection of himself, he states, admitting how through rehearsals he struggled to read his lines, even bursting into tears; how the first time he read the play, he felt personally implicated and stripped bare. <strong>&#8220;I am German, my father left when I was three years old, I grew up with my mother, was born in Hamburg, that is all I have ever known”</strong>, he says. The biographies are nearly identical, minus 80 years and a certain regime.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2311.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2255" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2311.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht stage" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>The anger he enacts in the play now takes hold of his voice: the desperation and frustration. <strong>“Once I read the script I knew it had to be done, we had to make this play. Though, during intermission, when I was sprawled on the stage in a pile of paper [the stage is composed mainly of bundles and bundles of blank paper], I sometimes thought ‘what am I doing here, who am I talking to&#8217;”</strong>.</p>
<p>Despite these questions of audience and representation, the play successfully sends a message, one of critique. It weaves the complicated history of American segregation and its sub-human treatment of Blacks with the messianic framing of America&#8217;s involvement in WWII. Through the diverse arrangement of its characters, the play scrutinizes American moral authority in the fight against Nazi ideology and fascism, drawing dramatic attention to Jim Crow and the commonalities between racist ideologies.</p>
<p><strong>The parallels between American oppression and Nazi tyranny become painfully clear, eliciting the following question from the audience: &#8220;Would you show this play in America? And under what conditions?&#8221;</strong></p>
<p>&#8220;We would just need a theater to show it&#8221;, the playwright says with a smile, confidently speaking for the work alone. &#8220;The play was actually meant for an American audience&#8221;, he adds, hence the translation of German passages and numerous references to American &#8216;race sciences&#8217;, details often omitted from textbooks. &#8220;This is a history of not only segregation but of a science [eugenics and race-based Social Darwinism] that many Americans do not know about&#8221;.</p>
<p>Such a truth of ignorance is reflected in the young woman in the play, who claims that the protagonist, Klaus, is not like &#8220;the other Negroes back home!&#8221;, though she has &#8220;never met one&#8221;.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2258" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_2.jpg?w=640" alt="colonialism Jim Crow" width="640" height="411" /></a></p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Theater approaches many controversial political topics in the United States, because it can. A very particular demographic is going to the theater; and that is where such issues can be discussed&#8221;</strong>, Brunet adds.</p>
<p>The playwright explains that he is willing to relinquish artistic license and allow others to define the scope and boundaries of the play&#8217;s possible interpretations. Some scenes are based on his own childhood, others on historical research and collaboration with the author of <em><a href="https://www.press.umich.edu/174272/other_germans">Other Germans</a>, </em>Tina M. Campt<em>, </em>about being a person of African heritage in Germany.</p>
<p>&#8220;But what is the point of the play?&#8221;, the jazz musician asks, perhaps to the audience, perhaps to no one present in this room. It is not about carving out identity from the crowd, asserting the value of the image in the attic mirror, but rather &#8220;about convincing society – the powerful – that exclusion is harmful and degrading to human beings. Now, and back then!&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;The point is, speaking truth to power&#8221;</strong>, he says, referencing, most notably, <a href="http://www.cornelwest.com/">Dr. Cornel West</a>, a giant in the continued civil rights movement for people of color, for the exploited lower classes.</p>
<p>Theater is not a dialogue with the masses, nor a dialogue with society in general, however. &#8220;Like cultural media and cultural politics, it is a dialogue with the powerful and their ideas&#8221;, says Brunet. The rest is some trickle down effect or, as the p.o.c. from the audience adds, &#8220;a change in consciousness&#8221;.</p>
<p>The camera man, a towering Black man with an equally large voice, speaks to the political or &#8220;transformative nature of the play&#8221;: <strong>“Most people ask themselves the question, are things really that different now? That is what this play does, it asks that question again of the powerful&#8221;.</strong></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5em;">With these words, I instantly feel implicated by my privilege, the things afforded to me on the basis of the position and body I was born into. The room shrinks. I shift in my seat.</span></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5em;">We are the audience. We are the ones who should see this play. We shape the discourse, often to the detriment of those who do not fit the desired mold. Theater might be a chance to reflect on <a href="http://www.taz.de/!116745/">critical whiteness</a>, even on its limitations.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2296.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2250" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2296.jpg?w=640" alt="English Theatre Berlin" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>One of the members of the cast remarks, perhaps to break a long 15 seconds of silence, <strong>&#8220;Can we imagine a black actor playing Romeo? A white actor playing Othello? Is it bad that we can&#8217;t?&#8221;</strong> For the sake of this question, &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; should be produced in another season, maybe in another city, as a voice in a room with too few listeners.</p>
<p>I sincerely hope that it might be staged in the United States, a country, where diversity often means tolerating the one that is different but disrespecting him or her just the same. As <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/ta-nehisi-coates/">Ta-Nehisi-Coates</a> wrote in <em>The Atlantic</em> this Tuesday, <strong>&#8220;We are in America, where our absence of virtue is presumed, and we must eat disrespect in sight of our sons.<em> </em>And who can be mad in America? Racism is just the wind, here. Racism is but the rain.&#8221; </strong></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*After the Nazi dust had cleared the German capital and West German society had taken root, the Black American poet and activist Audrey Lorde began to popularize the term <em>Afrodeutsche(r) </em>or Afro-German,<em> </em>during <a href="http://www.audrelorde-theberlinyears.com/">her years in the city</a>, effectively building a movement that at least gave a name to an almost invisible population.</p>
<p><em>For more information on Afro-German history in English, click <a href="http://german.about.com/od/culture/a/blackhistger.htm">here</a>. For more information on Afro-German organizations in Berlin and in all of Germany: <a href="http://isdonline.de/">Initiative schwarze Menschen in Deutschland</a>, <a href="http://www.afro-deutsche.de/">Afrodeutsche e.V</a>, <a href="http://www.adefra.com/">Schwarze deutsche Frauen und schwarze Frauen in Deutschland</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>For an interesting twist, check out our <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/">article on Black Germans</a> (the change of language here was intentional) growing up in the United States to adoptive parents, often in the segregated South. </em></p>
<p>Photo source: Kelly Miller and <a href="http://jurigottschau.com/">Juri Gottschau</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rave: Why Remembering the Holocaust is Good for Immigrants</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2013 08:43:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GDR-DDR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Holocaust]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jewish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[museums]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nazi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1353</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In 2005, Germany officially became an immigration country with the establishment of its federal office for migration. The question - who are the Germans anyway? - has become increasingly important in deciding what to impart to these newcomers set to stay. Expats are good at constructing Germanness for the Germans themselves, often leaving out the Holocaust in such a description of 'German identity', however. Today's Germany - an immigration country - is a republic built on tragic events like the Holocaust, just as France is a country built on colonialism. Everything has a context, and it is this context that immigrants to Germany should learn to understand for the sake of a more complete country - a civic society which respects differences and celebrates them...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p dir="ltr">In 2005, Germany officially became an immigration country with the establishment of its federal office for migration (<a href="http://www.bamf.de/EN/Startseite/startseite-node.html">BAMF</a>). A wave of new laws and institutions were to follow, set to absorb those meant to stay &#8211; not just <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gastarbeiter">guest-workers</a>, not temporary migrants, not <a href="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vertragsarbeiter">comrades</a> (so-called <em>Vertragsarbeiter</em> from communist countries), but immigrants. In turn, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">German identity </a>has been shoved into the limelight. This country and its residents have witnessed plenty of change and adjustment, but redefining self and country after the fall of the Berlin Wall (even during the student <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protests_of_1968">protests of 1968</a>) had little to do with defining oneself in opposition to a foreign but stationary Other. Although individuals and families with non-German origins have been coming for centuries, confronting what will be an official change in what it means to be German is rather new, rather fresh.</p>
<div style="width: 600px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b038669g"><img loading="lazy" class=" " title="Justin Rowlatt and his wife Bee set out to live like a typical German family" src="http://images.dailyexpress.co.uk/img/dynamic/20/590x/make-me-a-german-420020.jpg" alt="Justin-Rowlatt-and-his-wife-Bee-set-out-to-live-like-a-typical-German-family" width="590" height="350" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Who are the Germans anyway? A BBC series answers this question by-doing</p></div>
<p dir="ltr">The question &#8211; who are the Germans anyway? &#8211; becomes increasingly important when deciding what to impart to newcomers. Which traditions deserve saving? What is important? The answers to these questions are not as simple as good bread or Hefeweizen. Expats with an outsider perspective are not shy in constructing simple &#8216;Germanness&#8217; for the Germans themselves. The BBC reality TV series &#8220;<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/tv-and-radio/2013/aug/07/make-me-german-tv-review">Make Me a German</a>&#8221; plays with stereotypes and assumptions about what is <em>typisch deutsch</em> (typically German); the viral blog post <a href="http://www.uberlin.co.uk/what-i-know-about-germans/"><em>What I know about Germans </em></a>is just one example of trendy list-making of all things &#8216;German&#8217; by temporary residents; Berlin-based comedy writer <a href="http://adam-fletcher.co.uk/">Adam Fletcher</a> has created an entire <a href="http://store.hipstery.com/">brand</a> just based on the funny categorization of ‘Germanness’. On a tote bag in Fletcher’s line of nifty and hilarious merchandise: an engineer’s instruments, a watch, whole wheat, nude culture, asparagus. But where is the concentration camp in these lists, this series, or this fashion line? Where is the Holocaust?</p>
<div id="attachment_1362" style="width: 522px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218225820494823.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1362" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-1362" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218225820494823.png?w=640" alt="Aviary Photo_130218225820494823" width="512" height="682" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1362" class="wp-caption-text">Entrance to Sachsenhausen concentration camp, Oranienburg, DE</p></div>
<p dir="ltr">This past weekend, I embarked on a day-long tour of the former <a href="http://www.stiftung-bg.de/gums/en/index.htm">Sachsenhausen concentration camp</a> with a good friend here in Berlin &#8211; a friend, who just happens to be Jewish and originally from Ukraine.  We were a small group for an English speaking tour, minuscule in comparison to the masses of Italian and Spanish tour groups all heading to the same location. Two Taiwanese students, an American-Spanish couple on vacation from their residence in Saudi Arabia, a Brazilian student traveling Europe for the first time, a Bulgarian engineer, and Max and I (both Americans). We met our guide Alex, exchanged small talk, in part to find out why we all were willing to commit seven hours on a Sunday to hearing about tragedy, visiting the haunted, vast expanses of Sachsenhausen &#8211; a concentration camp just right on the edge of Berlin, reachable with the S-Bahn (public transit).</p>
<p dir="ltr">In contemporary political discussions about integration of immigrants into ‘German society’, no one claims that integration requires learning the lessons of the Holocaust. And yet, federal integration programs combined with international perception of Germanness say just that. The public concept of historical memorialization and its application, called <em>Vergangenheitsbewältigung, </em>is just as important to living in German society as <em>v</em><em>ollkorn Brötchen </em>or <em>Oktoberfest. </em></p>
<p dir="ltr">On our tour&#8217;s long walk from <a href="http://www.oranienburg.de/texte/seite.php?id=91511">Oranienburg</a> station to the gates of the camp, passing average-looking &#8216;German&#8217; homes with gardens neatly segregated from the street by high fences, I spoke with Natalia (the student from São Paulo) about Germany, the Germans, and the Holocaust. She brought up an interesting point: “How do the Germans feel about it &#8211; that people go to Venice to see the canals and to Berlin to see the Holocaust? I can imagine they don’t like it”. A man jogged past us in bright running-gear, his dog trotting behind him, just passing the entrance to the camp. This is part of being German &#8211; accepting that this is how you are seen in the world, that this history is an indivisible part of any sense of being German, it seemed.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218225935786183.png"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1363" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218225935786183.png?w=640" alt="Aviary Photo_130218225935786183" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p dir="ltr">For new residents of Berlin, the past still matters and maybe even more than integration programs can provide for. My Ukrainian-American-Jewish friend Max (gotta love them hyphens) and his family left Kiev when he was five, in part due to Antisemitism. His great-great-grandparents were killed in the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Babi_Yar">Babi Yar massacre</a> of 1941. The precarious relationship of the German government to its new status as an immigration country, let alone the way it classifies its non-German residents, is very much familiar to Max. &#8220;So, how does that make you feel as a Jew in Germany?&#8221;, I asked a bit sheepishly, recognizing the change of context from friendly chatter we usually entertain to rrrrrreal real fast. Many Jewish immigrants to Germany have likely heard this question before. “Antisemitism is more the exception than the rule. I don’t feel confronted by it in daily life&#8230;but I know it’s there”, he concluded. He is supportive of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-Fascist_Action">Antifa</a> movements, aware that being Jewish in Germany is complicated but totally do-able, requiring a little finesse. Berlin, of course, has all kinds of finesse.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Our tour entered Sachsenhausen through the renovated watchtower and its metal gates, a construction bearing the architectural legacy of the post-war custodians of the camp and many others &#8211; the (East) German Democratic Republic. A stream of other visitors followed our trail, audio devices pressed to their ears. I felt strange, almost supportive of an odd form of tourism, securing Natalia&#8217;s comment about the connection of Holocaust tourism to German identity in reality.</p>
<p dir="ltr" style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3419" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_1302182256975699431.png" alt="aviary-photo_130218225697569943" width="606" height="606" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_1302182256975699431.png 606w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_1302182256975699431-300x300.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 606px) 100vw, 606px" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">A cacophony of languages could be heard as we moved from one monument within the camp to another &#8211; Swedish, Japanese, British English, French &#8211; all reading the same saddening information on plaques or biographical exhibition panels, all bearing witness to tragedy and an integral part (if not the deciding event) of this country&#8217;s history and present.</p>
<p dir="ltr">We moved to the far edge of the camp, heading toward the restored Barrack 38: the Jewish barrack turned memorial documentation center. As we entered the small structure, the smell of charred wood was unmistakable, paint peeling from the siding of the latrine and sleeping porch. Arson. In 1992, German identity was thrust under international limelight after reunification and the growing pains that followed, further exacerbated by the rise of Neonazism in the former East. Arson was a key expression of this tension. This same year of the attack on Barrack 38, Neonazis set fire to a refugee housing facility not too far from Berlin, terrorizing residents in the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Riot_of_Rostock-Lichtenhagen">riot of Rostock-Lichtenhagen</a>. The political activities of parties and movements, such as the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Democratic_Party_of_Germany">NPD</a> (German Nationalist Party with strong Neonazi ties), as well as the recent <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/topic/national_socialist_underground/">Neonazi terror-cell</a> and its string of xenophobic murders across Germany, point to a  contemporary relevance of the Nazi past to Germany’s future as a country of immigration. The Holocaust and its constitutive role in Germany identity has been part of the country&#8217;s historical development ever since. What to teach immigrants &#8211; remember the Holocaust.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3420" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226423822983-650x487.png" alt="aviary-photo_130218226423822983" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226423822983-650x487.png 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226423822983-300x225.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226423822983-80x60.png 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226423822983.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">We left the camp in a drizzle of rain, boarding the S-Bahn back to Berlin. As our guide Alex (speaking a high variety of the King&#8217;s English) began to share an illustrative vignette about the end of the war and deterioration of Nazi moral power in Germany, passengers in the train appeared perturbed. A woman with fiery hair shook her head in disgust; she furled insults in German in our guide&#8217;s direction (understood only by me at the time). Another stern-faced German woman entered shortly after, raising her voice to replace that of the recently exited red-haired woman. Her lips quivering, she looked to be my mother’s age, the veins in her neck traumatically flinching, exposed. “Why don’t you just stop talking. It is rude what you are doing. It is not right what you are doing. We don’t need to be lectured to! You must stop&#8221;, she said abruptly in English.</p>
<p dir="ltr">German trains and buses are anything but loud, each keeping to his or herself in a very strong show of privacy. This may be a stereotype, but it illuminates the particular conflict that ensued quite well.</p>
<p dir="ltr">With eyes closed in shock, our guide explained that we were on an educational tour of the concentration camp, that he had been doing this for years and had never had such a negative reaction. He kept calm and showed no sign of anger or distress. The female companion of the pulsing-veined woman responded loudly with perhaps the only words she knew: &#8220;shut uppp!&#8221;, popping the &#8216;p&#8217; just at the end.</p>
<p dir="ltr">My friend Max intervened &#8211; asked our guide to have a seat, standing to allow him to do so. With hands shaking and eyes kept closed, Alex continued his narrative: the time after the war, the protests of 1968, de-Nazification in educational and political institutions, current movements of young people, general skepticism toward patriotism in Germany ever since &#8211; all forming parts of a whole history that has never really come to a close.</p>
<p dir="ltr">As we exited the train, the pulsing-veined woman ran to Alex, extending her hand to graze his: &#8220;I agree with everything you said!&#8221;, she said, &#8220;but you were just speaking so loud for a public place! It is a train, not a classroom. Your voice was really just too loud for all of us, so for next time, just speak quieter.&#8221; She paused, Alex thanked her. And then with one last quiver of the lip: &#8220;I was one of those Germans you talked about, one of those students with guilt for something I wasn&#8217;t even old enough to have participated in. So thank you for what you said&#8230;&#8221;</p>
<p dir="ltr">&#8220;I don’t want anyone thinking ‘oh these horrible Germans’. I don’t want you all leaving thinking that,&#8221; the woman added as we had nearly let the train doors shut behind us, her eyes directed at all of us in a show of penetrating honesty. Education about the past does more than just memorialize or prevent reoccurrence: it avoids essentialization of historical events and preserves the complexity of it all.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3421" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226704073063-650x487.png" alt="aviary-photo_130218226704073063" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226704073063-650x487.png 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226704073063-300x225.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226704073063-80x60.png 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226704073063.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">With the new immigration status of 2005 and the integration programs that followed, came the creation of an <a href="http://www.bamf.de/EN/Willkommen/DeutschLernen/Integrationskurse/InhaltAblauf/inhaltablauf-node.html">&#8216;integration curriculum&#8217;</a>, including cultural orientation that included this very facet of Germanness: the Holocaust. Immigrants participating in the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">integration courses </a>visit historical institutions designed to communicate the significance of the Nazi period for Germany as both a modern state and as a group of transnational or transethnic individuals.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Official curriculum including Holocaust field-trips doesn&#8217;t answer all questions, however. Politicians are still scratching their heads at the &#8216;German question&#8217; &#8211; each party choosing which elements it wants to claim for the imagined &#8216;nation&#8217;, some famously campaigning for a <em>Leitkultur (</em>one central guiding culture for Germany by Germans). Such a sentiment has been heavily criticized by most politicians outside of the leading conservative party (CDU), including the head of the Jewish Council of Germany, Paul Spiegel. In a speech to Parliament, Spiegel said <em><a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/archiv/leitkultur---die-scharfe-kritik-von-paul-spiegel-am--verbalen-zuendeln-der-politiker--hat-die-union-aufgeschreckt--der-bundesrat-stimmte-dem-antrag-auf-ein-verbot-der-rechtsextremen-npd-zu--merz-versuchte-zu-intervenieren,10810590,9851008.html">&#8220;Ist es etwa deutsche Leitkultur, Fremde zu jagen, Synagogen anzuzünden, Obdachlose zu töten?&#8221;</a>, &#8220;is it &#8216;German culture&#8217; to hunt down foreigners, to light synagogues on fire, to kill the homeless</em>?&#8221; The Holocaust is not far from these debates about Germanness, thus it is no wonder that it is included at least in educational programs to include newcomers in German society.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Today&#8217;s Germany &#8211; an immigration country &#8211; is a republic built on tragic events like the Holocaust, just as France is a country built on colonialism. This is not to say that countries and their residents are reducible to history. Rather it is to say that institutions and individuals are still intimately connected to what came before. It is about understanding how one can relate to such a history in its contemporary place, shaping either collective guilt or political activism (in the likes of Antifa) just the same. Everything has a context, and it is this context that immigrants to Germany should learn to understand for the sake of a more complete country &#8211; a civic society which respects differences and celebrates them. For Germany is not just for those who were once classified as &#8216;ethnically German&#8217;, it is for anyone that chooses to reside in Germany. Becoming German* is understanding history and what it might mean for the present, regardless of ethnicity.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><em>-By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>*Not sure, if you are German? Take this funny quiz from none other than Adam Fletcher <a href="http://www.thegermanquiz.com/">here</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>Our free tour to Sachsenhausen concentration camp was provided by <a href="http://www.viveberlintours.de/en/tours/sachsenhausen">Vive Berlin Tours</a></em>, <em>meeting Tuesdays, Fridays, and Sundays at 10am at Balzac Coffee on Potsdamer Platz year-round. Our guide, <a href="http://www.viveberlintours.de/en/guides">Alex</a>, comes highly recommended, as does this cooperative-style tour company which prides itself on expertise and narrative, as well as fairness for its employees. </em></p>
<p>Photo source: first image linked to source, otherwise taken by Kelly Miller</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The N-Word</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2013 12:20:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nazi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=658</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When I posted the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/">Who's/Whose Normal?</a> article a few weeks ago, I expected the "N-word" of interest to be<em> Neger</em>, a term that falls somewhere between "negro" and "nigger" on the translation and offensiveness spectrum. Instead, the strongest reactions came in response to another N-Word: Nazi...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;">When I posted the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/">Who&#8217;s/Whose Normal?</a> article a few weeks ago, I expected the &#8220;N-word&#8221; of interest to be<em> Neger</em>, a term that falls somewhere between &#8220;negro&#8221; and &#8220;nigger&#8221; on the translation and offensiveness spectrum. Instead, the strongest reactions came in response to another N-Word: Nazi.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/thenword.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-756" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/thenword.png" alt="thenword" width="546" height="366" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">For those who haven&#8217;t read the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/">original post</a>, the controversy stemmed from a comparison I made between a Berlin storefront poster campaign and Nazi propaganda (on an aesthetic &#8211; not political &#8211; basis). On second thought, I shouldn&#8217;t put that last bit in parentheses, because it&#8217;s the essence of my point. Despite Berlin being <strong>Germany&#8217;s most ethnically and culturally diverse city</strong>, these particular <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/2013-04-11-09-35-05.jpg">storefront posters</a> feature <em>only</em> heterosexual Caucasian families. On an aesthetic basis (skin tone, facial features, body build), they don&#8217;t differ much from the fair blond couples on Nazi posters. A couple brunettes are included here or there, but I don&#8217;t consider that diversity. The bad man himself was a brunette, no? That&#8217;s probably not going to make me any friends either.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">While I am in no way comparing the people from this store to Nazis (I repeat: in no way!), I was disappointed by these posters and the message they send. On multiple posters and within an <a href="http://www.leiser.de/frontend/startseite.htm">entire website</a>, I find it disconcerting to see only one type of ethnicity, sexuality, and idea of beauty. And both creative process scenarios &#8211; whether <em>Leiser</em> consciously made this decision or didn&#8217;t realize that this is what they were doing &#8211; are also disconcerting.</p>
<p>Although many agreed with me that the images were problematic, my Nazi comparison was not as well-received. In the spirit of promoting discourse and &#8220;seeing things from every lens&#8221;, I thought it critical to share a selection of these reactions. Disclaimer: All German comments have been loosely translated by yours truly.</p>
<p><strong>German Commenter 1:</strong> In the U.S., you use the term &#8220;Nazi&#8221; as a joke, e.g. &#8220;You&#8217;re a cleaning Nazi&#8221;, just like we say the term <em>Negerküss</em> [Nigger-kiss]. Neither group considers the history and context of the other. In Germany, we only call really evil and abominable people Nazis, people who seem to be OK with what the Nazis did. It is the worst insult you can give someone. That&#8217;s why it&#8217;s such a hard pill for me to swallow when &#8220;normal&#8221; people (even if they are racist or discriminatory) are compared with Nazis, just like it is hard for Americans when they hear us use the term <em>Neger</em>.</p>
<p><strong>German Commenter 2:</strong> Sophia, you have to be really careful with the use of the term &#8220;Nazi&#8221;. Your comparison [of the storefront posters] to Nazi propaganda goes too far. Germans have a total complex when it comes to our history and you can&#8217;t just make that sort of comparison. As an American, you can&#8217;t understand how hard it is growing up with this history&#8230; You&#8217;re not exactly going to make friends with this sort of comparison.</p>
<p><strong>German/American Commenter in response to above:</strong> Is being critical un-German? Isn&#8217;t that how the Germans got into the Nazi/Holocaust mess to begin with?</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>American Commenter in response to above:</strong> Oh my god! Do these people seriously believe that anti-black racism is the same as calling someone &#8220;a cleaning Nazi&#8221;?? And that you can&#8217;t possibly understand that because you didn&#8217;t grow up there? WTF! I&#8217;m not jumping in because I don&#8217;t want to hijack a thread and you&#8217;re being much more diplomatic than I would be, but dude! What the hell!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-767 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes.jpg" alt="yikes" width="592" height="437" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes-300x221.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 592px) 100vw, 592px" /></a><strong>Me after reading the comments</strong></p>
<p>What these comments have made clear is that context is paramount in the interpretation of language. Perhaps more importantly, however, it has made clear that one shouldn&#8217;t limit themselves to only their immediate context. We can&#8217;t always dissect every word to see if it may offend someone, but we should be more mindful of the political, cultural, and historical contexts of other groups when using potentially hurtful language.</p>
<p>I&#8217;ve often heard that Americans are more PC (politically-correct) than Europeans. Yet, this discussion has shown me that that is not necessarily the case. All nations have sore spots in their histories &#8211; some more recent than others, some that should be sorer than they seem to be &#8211; where we need to tread lightly. We also handle these sensitive topics differently. There&#8217;s still no slavery memorial in Washington, DC, but the German capital is laden with memorials and museums acknowledging their &#8220;black mark on history&#8221;. Americans are known for being the kings (&amp; queens!) of PC language, but the Germans actually came up with a dictionary of Nazi terms to promote awareness of their use.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/350_b22810-2_u1d.gif"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/350_b22810-2_u1d.gif" alt="350_B22810-2_U1D" width="350" height="469" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>&#8220;A &#8216;Coming To Terms With The Past&#8217; Dictionary: The use of Nazi language in public speech&#8221; (</strong><a href="http://www.google.de/imgres?um=1&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sa=N&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;hl=de&amp;biw=1540&amp;bih=844&amp;tbm=isch&amp;tbnid=Ynymf1mQ2JxEDM:&amp;imgrefurl=http://www.wbg-wissenverbindet.de/WBGShop/php/Proxy.php%3Fpurl%3D/wbg/products/show,29637.html&amp;docid=VJO4nm_T0fhTJM&amp;itg=1&amp;imgurl=http://www.wbg-wissenverbindet.de/WBGShop/resources/cover/350_B22810-2_U1D.gif&amp;w=350&amp;h=469&amp;ei=WDWvUYqbB4bTtAapy4C4BA&amp;zoom=1&amp;iact=rc&amp;dur=292&amp;page=1&amp;tbnh=133&amp;tbnw=99&amp;start=0&amp;ndsp=60&amp;ved=1t:429,r:5,s:0,i:99&amp;tx=83&amp;ty=83">Source</a><strong>)</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Yes, the Germans have a word for &#8220;coming to terms with the past&#8221;: <em>Vergangenheitsbewältigung.</em> <em>Vergangenheit</em> simply means &#8220;the past&#8221;, but <em>bewältigen </em>can translate to several verbs, including &#8220;to overcome&#8221;<em>. </em><strong>What does it mean &#8211; as nations and people -to overcome difficult periods in our history?</strong> Does it mean erecting public memorials and monuments? Does it mean holding companies responsible for the images that they portray and promote? Does it mean never using the &#8220;N-word&#8221; or, alternately, being able to use it as a joke? I&#8217;m all ears and mindful speech.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Prejudice with Condiments: understanding Schwabenhass</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/29/prejudice-with-condiments-understanding-schwabenhass/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/29/prejudice-with-condiments-understanding-schwabenhass/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2013 19:46:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GDR-DDR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gentrification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nazi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Schwaben]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=606</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The ketchup- or cheese-smeared faces of Swabian and Berliner icons are just one small part of a culture war between imagined identities and exaggerated actors, i.e. the alternative Berliner vs. the fancy-schmancy Swabian. The worst part in this so-called <em>Spätzlekrieg </em>or 'Spätzel war'  is the escalation from humorous prodding to line-crossing slogans. Parallels between Nazi persecution of the Jews, particularly in the insignia of <a href="http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/online/kristallnacht/frame.htm"><em>Kristallnacht</em></a>, can be found across the city. Berlin is a city rife with history; is its memory this short? ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As an immigrant of a certain type, one often converses with, discusses, and reads about other so-called ex-patriots. It&#8217;s easy to feel like the world revolves around you, which must be why it&#8217;s easy to assume that we &#8211; the largely English-speaking, often temporary immigrants &#8211; are at the heart of the gentrification debate in Berlin. There&#8217;s no shortage of talk about how we don&#8217;t (or won&#8217;t) learn German, how we move into traditionally poorer neighborhoods and contribute to rising rent costs, and how we waltz into the corner cafe demanding a fancy latte rather than a good ol&#8217; Milchkaffee.</p>
<p>But what I had forgotten about were <strong>the rich and educated Germans &#8211; the <em>Schwaben</em>, for that matter, </strong>migrants from Southern Germany charged with gentrifying Berlin, essentially the root of the careless economic change sweeping the city. <em>Schwaben </em>have begun to <strong>represent a German crisis of identity, one acted out between markets and their effects on long-standing communities</strong>. Emblematic of this crisis is the &#8216;vandalism&#8217; of the statues of one famous <em>Schwaben</em> splattered with <em>Currywurst</em> (the iconic dish of Berlin) and one famous <em>Berlinerin</em> splattered with <em>Spätzle</em> (the icon dish of Swabia), as pictured below.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/3-format36.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-607 alignnone" style="margin: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/3-format36.jpg" alt="3-format36" width="384" height="288" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/3-format36.jpg 712w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/3-format36-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/3-format36-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/3-format36-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 384px) 100vw, 384px" /></a><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/4-format15.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-615 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/4-format15.jpg" alt="4-format15" width="326" height="330" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/4-format15.jpg 544w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/4-format15-296x300.jpg 296w" sizes="(max-width: 326px) 100vw, 326px" /></a></p>
<p>The ketchup- or cheese-smeared faces of Swabian icons are just one small part of a culture war between imagined identities and exaggerated actors, i.e. the alternative Berliner vs. the fancy-schmancy Swabian. The worst part in this so-called <em>Spätzlekrieg </em>or &#8216;Spätzel war&#8217;  is the escalation from humorous prodding to line-crossing slogans. <strong>Parallels between Nazi persecution of the Jews, particularly in the insignia of <a href="http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/online/kristallnacht/frame.htm"><em>Kristallnacht</em></a>, can be found across the city.</strong> Berlin is a city rife with history; is its memory this short?</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/berliner-spaetzlekrieg-eskaliert_artikelquer.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/berliner-spaetzlekrieg-eskaliert_artikelquer.jpg" alt="Berliner-Spaetzlekrieg-eskaliert_ArtikelQuer" width="404" height="270" /></a></p>
<p><img class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/b3a73-naziterrorindeutschland1933gesch25c325a4ftj25c325bcdisch.png" alt="" /></p>
<p>Sprayed on storefronts around some of Berlin&#8217;s gentrifying neighborhoods are the words <em>Kauf nicht bei Schwab&#8217;n</em>, Don&#8217;t buy from Schwaben, a direct usage of the tags in the period of escalation before German deportation of its Jewish population, as pictured in this image above from <em>Kristallnacht</em>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.morgenpost.de/berlin-aktuell/article115879959/Wowereit-verurteilt-Schwabenhass-in-Berlin.html"><em>Schwabenhass</em></a>, hatred of <em>Schwaben</em>, may be a problem of discrimination and unjust intimidation, but it is not necessarily as extreme as this graffiti demonstrates. Like the Neo-Nazi presence in Berlin, it is hopefully a minority of enraged individuals sending such messages, not ordinary Berliners participating so overtly in a culture war run on Nazi taglines. Yet, as Germany&#8217;s <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/nov/18/how-german-neo-nazis-evaded-police">scandal of right-wing terror</a> unfolds in court for the world to see, even a little bit of rage and misplaced language should be taken seriously and cautiously. <strong>Language and the explanations it provides for socioeconomic change can be as powerful as policy in determining public opinion. </strong>In the efforts of understanding and taming this condiment-covered beast of a crisis between Berlin and the incoming <em>Schwaben</em>, let us deconstruct a bit.</p>
<p>Hatred does not come out of the mist of Neverland, nor do <em>Schwaben</em>. So, who are <em>Schwaben</em> really, why are they now the object of aggressive criticism?</p>
<p><em>Schwaben</em> stem from the imagined community of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swabia">Swabia</a> or technically from the state of Baden-Württemberg. Located in Southwestern Germany, this traditionally <em>Schwäbisch</em>-speaking group within Germany has historically stretched as far as Bavaria. <strong>Accuracy of geographic or linguistic boundaries aside, <em>Schwaben</em> in Berlin have come to represent an ideological and historical conflict &#8211; a crisis &#8211; within Germany, one that has become particularly salient and searing since the fall of the wall in 1989.</strong></p>
<p>This period between 1989 and 1990 is what Germans refer to as <em>die</em> <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Die_Wende">Wende</a>, </em>the big change, in which a reunited Germany faced the fusion of a strict socialist economic system with an Americanized capitalist machine, to put it simply and dramatically. Rapidly following the change of power, bananas became available in the East, pickles came in more than one kind of jar, and automobiles came in models that didn&#8217;t just start with the letter &#8220;T&#8221;. The effects of this shift to a market economy in the East, however, were not as rosy as this example of consumerism demonstrates. <strong>High rates of unemployment, closure of factories and schools, dissolution of livelihoods and promised pensions sent ripples through the former East.</strong> For the many of the residents subject to these unanticipated changes, longing for the old days &#8211; a phenomenon nicely called <em>Ostalgie</em> (nostalgia for the East) &#8211; became a prevalent response to the <em>BRD</em>&#8216;s (Federal German Republic) sweeping policies. Contrasts were drawn and enemies were created, <em>Feindbilder</em>, as they say in German: a concept of the enemy.</p>
<p>Representative of much of this change and the trauma and tumult that resulted are the cities of Frankfurt and Stuttgart (one could even throw Munich in, for good measure). Both of these financial capitals in Germany, where men and women in Western business attire can be seen entering America-styled skyscrapers, embody many of these latent <strong>East vs. West differences</strong>. As a product of history, these cities and the residents that stem from them also embody the animosities and frustrations of geographic and ideological division. High-rise glass structures and the minions that occupy them have come to represent a struggle with history and an uncertain present, mow imported via its Swabian personnel to the streets of Berlin.</p>
<p>The tensions between market-induced change and struggling communities are particularly palpable in Berlin, as a  reunited city familiar to hardships and class differences. It is currently the poorest capital relative to its country&#8217;s GDP within the EU, hence Klaus Wowereit&#8217;s tagline <em>Berlin ist arm aber sexy</em>, <a href="http://www.economist.com/node/7953479">poor but sexy</a>. Despite flashy art openings and fashion shows, there are plenty of <a href="http://www.dw.de/poverty-study-a-further-blow-to-poor-berlin/a-597767-1">residents on welfare</a>, children <a href="http://www.statistik-berlin-brandenburg.de/Publikationen/Aufsaetze/2011/HZ_201104-08.pdf">struggling to acquire adequate nutrition</a>, and financial debacles like a severely unfinished airport and inadequate educational institutions to paint quite an un-sexy picture.</p>
<p><strong>Berlin isn&#8217;t Frankfurt or Stuttgart with its sparkling streets and mowed lawns, where <em>Schwaben</em> (often inaccurately grouped together) run the show. It is a city struggling to remake itself and accommodate both newcomers, the unwelcome immigrants (<em>Gastarbeiter</em>) of yore, and <em>Urberliner</em> (old time residents), all while keeping its precarious budget afloat.</strong> Problems abound in the process, including the false assignment of priorities, such as a focus on <a href="http://www.megaspree.de/">temporary media projects</a> that provide snaz for short-term residents but do nothing to fix long-term structural problems.  Newcomers with higher incomes and chicer haircuts also contribute to 1. rent increases in a city without a rent floor or ceiling and 2. price increases in everything from theater tickets to bread. Gentrification, the buzzword seeping through the city like the yellow fog through T.S. Eliot&#8217;s &#8220;The Love Song of J. Alfred Prufrock&#8221;, draws many rapid and unfair conclusions in response to these problems.</p>
<p>Enter the undesired <em>Schwaben, </em>the Swabian enemy. These <em>Schwaben</em> may in fact distort real estate value,  but no one group can be charged with single-handedly transforming quaint alternative neighborhoods into Stuttgart-look-alikes, let alone Berlin into a money-making machine for the affluent. The problems of uncontrolled markets and post-GDR reconstruction will not fix themselves, nor will they be solved by aggressive prejudice or hatred toward a supposed enemy, created, after all, for the purpose of simply needing one. A little dialogue, historical perspective, and vigilance toward language and actors is in order. Maybe even a conversation with one of these <em>Schwaben.</em></p>
<p>After all, <em>Spätzle</em> is eaten everywhere. Even in Berlin.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>-By</em><strong><em> Kelly Miller</em></strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>To get this conversation started, the Kulturbrauerei is hosting performances of </em><a href="http://kulturbrauerei.de/de/programm?field_zeit_value%5Bvalue%5D%5Bdate%5D=29-05-2013&amp;uid=&amp;field_kategorie_veranstaltung_value_many_to_one=All&amp;title=Schwabenhatz">Schwabenhatz</a> &#8211;<em> a play about the </em>Spätzle<em> war, its stereotypes, and its ridiculously strange foundation for conflict. The show runs until 25.06. And for the record, the first image of the Spätzle-flinging was meant to be a joke. The last few, however, are anything but.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Photos used were found in an article and accompanying photo gallery in the <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/berlin/schwabenfeindlichkeit-in-berlin-hegel-statue-mit-currywurst-beschmiert/8198828.html"><em>Tagesspiegel</em></a> and in the <a href="http://www.ushmm.org/research/collections/photo/">United States Holocaust Memorial Museum&#8217;s public archives</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/29/prejudice-with-condiments-understanding-schwabenhass/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
