<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Informed Tourism &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/category/informed-tourism/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: Scotland and the question of borders</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/10/28/beyond-berlin-question-borders/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/10/28/beyond-berlin-question-borders/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2014 10:30:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Scotland]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3442</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Coming off an evening with Invisible Borders that was all about transcending boundaries, it was an eye-opening juxtaposition to visit a country that had just explored creating more stagnant borders of their own. This was to be my first trip to Scotland, but as I had visited England and Ireland in the past I wasn&#8217;t expecting much in the way of culture shock. I had heard something about an exotic concoction called Haggis, anticipated equal amounts difficulty and delight navigating the Scottish accent, and was prepared for plaid. Oh, and rain. Lots and lots of rain. So during my short stint in Edinburgh and the Highlands, I was especially interested to delve into what it was the Scots themselves believed distinguished them from the rest of the UK enough to merit separating themselves off with tighter borders. Did it really have anything to do with national identity, the sentiment conjured up by media images of teenagers covered in blue and white paint? Or was it really more for economic reasons, tied to access to finite resources like North Sea Oil? Scotland&#8217;s recent independence referendum, arising from a sweeping win by the Scottish National Party in the 2011 Parliament elections, was [...]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Coming off an evening with <a href="http://invisible-borders.com/">Invisible Borders</a> that was all about transcending boundaries, it was an eye-opening juxtaposition to visit a country that had just explored creating more stagnant borders of their own.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-11.58.20-11.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3507 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-11.58.20-11-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-06 11.58.20-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-11.58.20-11.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-11.58.20-11-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>This was to be my first trip to Scotland, but as I had visited England and Ireland in the past I wasn&#8217;t expecting much in the way of culture shock. I had heard something about an exotic concoction called <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haggis">Haggis</a>, anticipated equal amounts difficulty and delight navigating the Scottish accent, and was prepared for plaid. Oh, and rain. Lots and lots of rain. So during my short stint in Edinburgh and the Highlands, I was especially interested to delve into what it was the Scots themselves believed distinguished them from the rest of the UK enough to merit separating themselves off with tighter borders. Did it really have anything to do with national identity, the sentiment conjured up by media images of teenagers covered in blue and white paint? Or was it really more for economic reasons, tied to access to finite resources like North Sea Oil?</p>
<p>Scotland&#8217;s recent independence referendum, arising from a sweeping win by the Scottish National Party in the 2011 Parliament elections, was historic but not exceptional. Separatist movements exist all over the world, including the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/">people of Kurdistan</a> who make up a region of four Middle Eastern countries, Spain&#8217;s economic powerhouse, Catalonia, and Germany&#8217;s conservative southern state, Bavaria. Some may even surprise you &#8211; for example, Venice, where an <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2014/03/europes-latest-secession-movement-venice/284562/">unofficial referendum</a> in May of this year showed the vast majority in favor of secession from Italy. Supporters of more active movements around the globe watched closely as the Scots went to the polls this past September 18th, eager to follow suit or fuel their respective campaigns. The results held weight. After 55.3% of Scotland voted &#8220;no&#8221;, Catalonia cancelled their planned referendum, originally set for November 9th of this year.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.40.09-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3451 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.40.09-1-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-05 15.40.09-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.40.09-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.40.09-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>There are over 20 active separatist movements around the world, the majority in Europe and Asia. Of these, about a third are violent*, due primarily to ethnic and religious tensions. While some fight for human rights or religious freedom, others strive for economic power, control over resources, or wealth potential. The Scotland independence debate was rife with discussions about tax distribution, North Sea Oil, currency, and jobs. &#8220;Scotland is a very wealthy country &#8211; let&#8217;s make it feel like it!&#8221; proclaimed the homepage of the official &#8220;Yes Scotland&#8221; campaign. Meanwhile, Turkey&#8217;s Kurds have been engaged in armed struggle against the Turkish government since 1984, resulting in thousands of deaths. It is therefore an impossible and reductionist task to speak of secessionist movements as a homogenous entity. Yet regardless of the nature of the struggle &#8211; political, economic, social, ethnic, violent, peaceful, or a combination of the above &#8211; when one discusses borders, one is inherently embarking on a discussion about community, belonging, and identity.</p>
<p>As links between countries become stronger through migration, technology, economic trade, and political unions, the idea of separating oneself from the &#8220;global community&#8221; can appear unmodern, backward, even futile. &#8220;I voted no,&#8221; my Airbnb host, a documentary filmmaker originally from England, revealed as we strolled to the supermarket together my first night in rainy Edinburgh, &#8220;not because I&#8217;m against independence for the Scots, but because I believe in a borderless world.&#8221;</p>
<p>At the same time, retreating into a stronger sense of place and identity, as our world becomes more globalized, can feel almost like an instinctive reaction. An exercise in protection, preservation, even control. &#8220;It may have worked in the past, but the way the centralized government in London makes decisions for us now does not reflect who we are anymore,&#8221; my Highlands tour guide explained as we stood at the foot of Stirling Castle, &#8220;I just can&#8217;t be proud of a country that isn&#8217;t its own.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>Which begs the question: how can we embrace the inevitable (and often beneficial) changes that crossing and opening borders may bring, while simultaneously protecting what makes our home(s) &#8220;our own&#8221;?</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.42.39-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3452 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.42.39-1-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-05 15.42.39-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.42.39-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.42.39-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>For starters, the concept of a world with more open borders is conceivably less radical than many perceive it to be. &#8220;Open&#8221; does not mean &#8220;none&#8221;, nor does it mean a lawless world where people come and go as they please without screens or supervision. Within the field of migration, the concept of &#8220;open borders&#8221; generally refers to a reversal from what is, by default, an exclusionary policy, e.g. countries finding a reason to <em>let someone in. </em>Instead, the policy would switch to one of de facto inclusion, e.g. countries finding a reason to <em>keep someone out</em>. Reasons for excluding potential immigrants would lie more with criminal records and health concerns than they would with economic prospects or integration potential. Open borders is also not commensurate with the idea of open citizenship: in a world with open borders, countries could still deem individual qualifications and requirements for acquiring full citizenship rights.</p>
<p>The idea of open borders has gained traction in recent years (think &#8220;No Human is Illegal&#8221;) with the rise in global migration. Many see current immigration restrictions as inconsistent with basic egalitarian principles, such as equal opportunity, human rights, and moral obligations. On the more pragmatic end of the spectrum, there are those who advocate for open borders as a catalyst for economic growth and innovation, responding to phenomena such as lower birth rates and skilled worker shortages in more developed countries.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-13.22.05.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3450 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-13.22.05-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-05 13.22.05" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-13.22.05.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-13.22.05-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>But do questions about opening borders and globalization shifts weaken the importance of nationalism and identity? For many, despite the fact that we all interact with the global community in one form or another, place still matters most. A staggering 70% of those polled who voted &#8220;yes&#8221; to an independent Scotland claimed they did so because of &#8220;<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2014/sep/20/scottish-independence-lord-ashcroft-poll">the principle that all decisions about Scotland should be taken in Scotland</a>.&#8221;</p>
<p>This thinking was reflected in the voting demographics of the Scottish independence vote &#8211; eligible voters were only those currently residing in Scotland and Commonwealth or EU citizens. So while my Airbnb host was included despite being born in England, her Scottish friends living abroad were not (there are approximately <a href="http://worldpopulationreview.com/countries/scotland-population/">2 million Scots</a> living in other parts of the UK), nor were thousands of immigrant residents without the right passport.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-14.42.18-2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3478 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-14.42.18-2-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-06 14.42.18-2" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-14.42.18-2.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-14.42.18-2-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Although the official &#8220;yes&#8221; campaign in Scotland was largely pro-migration (<a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/scottish-independence/11035389/Scottish-immigration-has-to-increase-by-14000-to-meet-Salmond-target.html">mainly for economic reasons</a>) and may have adopted a more open policy than the rest of the UK, the independence vote brought up many questions about the future of migration and refugee policy, as well as citizenship laws. Who would be considered a citizen from &#8220;day one&#8221; of independence? What would the process be like for the foreign-born who wished to become citizens? What would dual citizenship policy look like for Scots living abroad? Would those living on the border, working on one side and living on the other, still have freedom of movement? What legal hurdles would immigrant families have to endure to visit family members spread out across the region?</p>
<p>As we lay out in <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/about/a-manifesto/">our manifesto</a>, borders hold meanings both conceptual and literal. They demarcate ideas of home and kinship as much as they do political, legal, and bureaucratic spaces. They bring people together around shared systems, laws, traditions, languages, and goals, but they also divide, separate, and limit. They influence and make statements about our engagement with local and global communities. They determine how seamlessly we can navigate having more than one home, a reality for an increasing number of us around the globe. But on the most basic level, for many, they simply represent what is possible and what isn&#8217;t.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>*Figures as of 2008. For a comprehensive account of the history of separatist movements and self-determination around the world, click <a href="http://online.sfsu.edu/swilcox/Swilcox/Shelleys_webpage_files/Wilcox,%20The%20Open%20Borders%20Debate%20on%20Immigration.pdf">here</a>.</p>
<p>For a shorter round-up on active secession movements, click <a href="http://www.dnaindia.com/world/report-7-separatist-movements-that-are-closely-watching-scotland-s-independence-referendum-2019372">here</a>.</p>
<p>All photos by yours truly from her recent trip to Edinburgh.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/10/28/beyond-berlin-question-borders/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: London and other transplants</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/09/29/beyond-berlin-london-and-other-transplants/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/09/29/beyond-berlin-london-and-other-transplants/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 15:22:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ex-pat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[London]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3278</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This past week, I visited my good friend D who, like me, is an American transplant. D lives in East London, where the corner store owner greets you in an upbeat banter and the sign to a ‘Carolina Fried Chicken’ joint dances in the light from the neighboring gastropub. Multicultural, maybe. But London’s multiculturalism has a few faces and facades. And, in the end, it’s the people that matter more than the cultural installation: So, who is actually 'making' it here?...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This past week, I visited my good friend D who, like me, is an American transplant*. We have similar trajectories and political ponderings, though his roots lie far from mine in the American Deep South (here’s a <a href="http://www.orionmagazine.org/index.php/place_where_you_live/view/chunky_mississippi_7753/">beautiful piece</a> he wrote about his home in Mississippi). D now lives in East London, where the corner store owner greets you in an upbeat banter and the sign to a ‘Carolina Fried Chicken’ joint dances in the light from the neighboring gastropub. Multicultural, maybe. But London’s multiculturalism has a few faces and facades. And, in the end, it’s the people that matter more than the cultural installation.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1031-e1413145767969.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3351 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1031-e1413145767969.jpg" alt="img_1031-e1413145767969" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1031-e1413145767969.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1031-e1413145767969-300x199.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>My first night in London, over pints at a very hip and haptic microbrewery – the tables grainy and splitting with moisture – D and I discuss our common struggles: We chat about how so-called experiences ‘abroad’ are, in the end, defined by labor market restrictions and the particular brand of our passport. Three years ago I would have insisted that these things are fluid. But even with a class degree from a class English university, a work allowance is hard to come by if not impossible in an academic job market already squeezed by its nationals, he shares. I can only nod, my plunge into the newest Berlin job search looming at the edge of my half-empty pint.</p>
<p>Berlin, like London, is full of transplants, both temporary and permanent. Why so many? For the case of my friend D and me, why did we, in particular, take these leaps? Why do so many of our generation (and even those generations before us) move to cities in countries we have no <i>de facto</i> right to be in? Across the ocean, <i>jus soli</i>, <i>jus sanguinus</i>, <i>jus</i> whatever does, indeed, determine much of what is possible.</p>
<p>The U.K, though London, in particular, invites dreams and dreamers. Multiculturalism results, in part, from the diversity of all those who believe in possibility; immigrants churn up new identities and make places we feel right to inhabit. In the case of Americans in London, maybe it’s the common language, the similar sarcastic humor, or the attachment to butter-heavy things like pie and cookies, but it just makes sense to come here.</p>
<p>In D’s apartment, a short assemblage of brick and concrete in the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London_Borough_of_Hackney">Hackney neighborhood</a>, I meet a few other fellow Americans. In many words, we all speak of the hurdles one must leap (in stride) for the right to not only remain but to earn an income at that, to really participate in a place one might co-construct but for which legal rights are lacking. One of them, a recent graduate of the London School of Economics, is tirelessly working to bend a clause or make a rule that will allow him to stay. There is a sense of marathon-running in the air, trying and trying until you can’t try anymore. Particularly palpable in a generation used to succeeding at most things, or told it is possible anyway.</p>
<p>But sometimes, it just doesn’t work out, at least temporarily, and many of those who come have to return to the places they left behind. But D seems optimistic.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/dylan_3.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3350 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/dylan_3-464x650.jpg" alt="dylan_3" width="464" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/dylan_3.jpg 464w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/dylan_3-214x300.jpg 214w" sizes="(max-width: 464px) 100vw, 464px" /></a></p>
<p>This matters because cities like London and Berlin actively foster the transplant spirit, but this doesn’t mean that these places work to sustain it. According to recent research <a href="http://books.google.de/books?id=Cy7FAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PR2&amp;lpg=PR2&amp;dq=%22migrants+or+expatriates+americans+in+europe%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=bX6_r-fwO2&amp;sig=4Si_8b_0M8yuiU9Ti6hBkJ_Ijs8&amp;hl=de&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=M8IqVJW1IsbWPZzygOAN&amp;ved=0CEYQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">on so-called American expatriates in Europe</a>, many transplants struggle for years at poorly paid jobs that are taken just to remain in the country. In Berlin, nearly half are underemployed and another third report contract-to-contract work (hustling, in other words). And yet, despite difficulties, many stay, which may be part financial, the costs of rehabilitating a life somewhere else, for example, and part mythical, i.e. what it means to constantly imagine future potential, then find it too difficult to forgo what might have been.</p>
<p>In any case, staying has a lot to do with the appearance of things. For how much of the transplant culture results from what one sees or experiences upon arriving, regardless of the actual rules of the game, even in spite of real barriers to inclusion? Put simply, if I see other Americans making it, or just a plethora of other nationalities making it, is it wrong to think I’ll make it?</p>
<p>Of course, the particular brand of passport produces a variety of experiences, but very few of us have a free-pass (excluding what D jokingly refers to as ‘fake Americans’ in London who legally remain in the country under an inherited European passport). Now, sitting in D’s kitchen with a liter of freshly brewed coffee (not tea), he tells me another story, one of a good friend’s predicament – an EU citizen, married to a Mexican national. In short, the immigration authorities of the U.K. have decided that the couple fails to meet requirements for residency in London, he tells me. Mexico is a country not seen favorably for transplantation; a hierarchy of acceptable migrants certainly does exist. But this all feels strangely hypothetical – this game of planning a life beyond borders, making moves and readying oneself for the counter. It is a lesson in rectifying a roster of rules with a vibrant diversity suggestive of more flexibility, more fluidity, than might be the case.</p>
<p>We leave the apartment and its conversation for a walk. Outside, it’s humid but pleasant, and the streets of D’s neighborhood are bursting with an eclecticism even beyond what the NY Times recently featured in ‘<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/04/29/travel/36-hours-in-east-london.html">36 hours in East London</a>‘ (as if the region needed its own holiday, apart from the financial men and women in suits of central London or the manicured streets of the West). Here, social housing projects tower above quaint town homes, neighbors trimming their rose bushes, bass piling out of a high window onto a long set of shears. Just down the road, one of London’s most bubbling food bazaars – a foodie’s scene of cultural consumption – is in full swing. Broadway Market: where German sausages, and meat pies, and lox bagels, and Persian kebab, and samosas, and ramen-to-go find frequent (young) patrons. We both delight in the anything-but-discordant multilingualism this variety yields.</p>
<p>In a pod of food carts just blocks from the market’s main drag, I find the best burrito I’ve had outside of the Western United States – a man with an air of L.A. dishing up marinated legumes, sauces streaming out of all sides of the tortilla like a blessing. A neighboring kiosk serves up what they call Filipino wraps (pork belly, assorted greens, tangy sauce), D’s favorite. As I walk to peruse other flavors, D shares his visa predicament with the owner of the wraps, explaining that this sandwich will be his last after a year of patronage. The owner offers to sponsor his visa, chuckling but serious, D tells me. Maybe he should take him up on his offer we joke, meaning it. D smiles.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/pork-belly.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3349" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/pork-belly-488x650.jpg" alt="pork-belly" width="400" height="532" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/pork-belly-488x650.jpg 488w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/pork-belly-225x300.jpg 225w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/pork-belly.jpg 489w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a></p>
<p>It’s easy to feel welcomed here.</p>
<p>Far away from East London, I find myself in the kitchen of a German transplant on the ground floor of an elderly but charming home in a neighborhood near Kensington.  From my luggage I unload mustard I’ve carted across the channel, tubes I was almost not allowed to take onto the plane. <i>You just can’t find this here</i>, my host says, that certain spicy mustard.</p>
<p>Her friends are all from somewhere else, she shares, <i>but the problem with transplants is that they all leave eventually, and then, all of a sudden, you don’t have any friends</i>. She is slowly rebuilding the circle, <i>but it’s hard</i>, she tells me, <i>when everyone is from somewhere else.</i></p>
<p>As we leave the far West neighborhood, its quiet lanes juxtaposed with newer blocks of community housing and industrial outgrowth, we pass an office for remittances – transplants from East Africa sending their earnings back ‘home’. Even here, some people are making it.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wp_20140919_001.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3347 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wp_20140919_001.jpg" alt="wp_20140919_001" width="640" height="360" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wp_20140919_001.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wp_20140919_001-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wp_20140919_001-310x174.jpg 310w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>My last day in London, my travel companion and I board a train to Brick Lane, snaking above a meat market, halal lambs hanging like carpets and voices rising up into numbers. Brick Lane, a curated experience of all that London attracts, the object of film, book, and tourism, is the sharpened edge of the city’s sale of eclecticism. It is a blend of curry houses and backdoor sweets shops for tourists and locals alike; it is the contrast between posh chocolatiers and wholesale textile vendors or between grunge coffee houses and chic boutiques. But it is not what is seen here that inspires but what is implied: that this – reproduction of home, community-making in memory – is possible. Even if it always isn’t.</p>
<p>After another burrito, this time seasoned with garam masala, we chat with an artist crafting overt social commentary, something he calls ‘the Prejudice Project’. With a long beard and dark eyes, he has likely faced that which his project targets. His bright smile opens up to pure optimism as we discuss diversity politics, however. But things can be difficult, indeed: In London, it’s not as free as in Berlin, he shares, a place he once inhabited, squatting in Köpenick and composing works that now hang in this design outlet just off Brick Lane. <i>The folks here are different</i>, he says, pausing, belonging to a <i>certain type</i>. He gives me a postcard, <i>a token to remember our conversation</i>: ‘#Paradise’ printed on a white surface, a glimpse of blue sky in the background.</p>
<p>D is moving back to the United States. After a preliminary job search and the weight of a different kind of bureaucracy on his shoulders, it seems like the best thing, for now. As he prepares for his departure to Philadelphia he looks mournful, visiting his favorite food carts and bookshop, the dingy canal with folks living out of boats – the air thick with oil and wet brush – before it all becomes just another place where he once lived. <i>I’d like to come back</i>, he says, <i>but then I just walk around and look at all the people here and want to go up and ask ‘like, how do you live here? What do you do?’</i> Perhaps, many of them are themselves transplants, just figuring it out as they go, leaving eventually for another place.</p>
<p>It’s hard to say, given the look of things.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1035.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3348 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1035.jpg" alt="img_1035" width="640" height="295" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1035.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1035-300x138.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>&#8211; <i>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></i></p>
<p><i>For more background on London as a city of immigration check out this 2013 </i> Times<i> <a href="http://www.thetimes.co.uk/tto/public/postcard/article3757989.ece">article</a>, which provides a concise run-down on the various groups and waves that make up London’s diversity. But even better:</i>the Guardian <i>has put together a</i><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/series/london"><i> </i><i>nifty collection</i></a><i> </i><i>of resources for exploring the many religious, culinary, and all-around cultural traditions that make up the city, although nothing beats exploring it on your own, if time and purse strings allow.</i></p>
<p>*I am using this word “transplant” intentionally, avoiding terms such as “expat” or even “immigrant”, as they are often bogged down with allusions to class, privilege, and assumptions about the irrelevance of borders or passports for certain members of the global community. When it comes to migration, the language is tricky but important. It helps to start with words that we feel we truly inhabit or experience, even if imperfectly.</p>
<p>All photos were taken by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/09/29/beyond-berlin-london-and-other-transplants/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: the Klezmer Gentiles</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2014 09:55:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Holocaust]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jewish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[memory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Poland]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2468</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[International artists in Berlin occupy a semi-privileged position, able to ask critical questions of society without being publicly rebuked. An example of such an artist is Soliman Lawrence. Soli has been photographing the memorialization of Jewish culture in Poland for years, following the tracks of a new form of engagement with the past, as enacted by a more recent generation of Poles. In contrast to Poland, Germany now has its fair share of Jews. What might this mean for memory and its rituals?...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>An interview is never one-sided &#8211; in fact, it is a constructive conversation. I am as much a part of this piece as the artist who answered my questions. Without the contributions of the other, individual statements would hold little significance. So thanks, Soli, for letting me share our conversation. </em></p>
<p>International artists in Berlin are one category of newcomers who, although shaping the cultural politics and economic fabric of Berlin perhaps more than other groups of foreign residents (those without German citizenship), are often left out of the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/11/integration-in-berlin-research-for-a-desolate-landscape/">critical integration debate</a>. Whether or not they learn German or German constitutional law seems to matter little to the politicians and journalists fueling the heavily institutionalized, assimilating discourse. I have yet to meet an artist who has been pressured by the authorities to &#8216;integrate&#8217; him or herself, as is the case with members of different social and economic groups.</p>
<p>This semi-privileged position has its benefits: Berlin&#8217;s creatives are often able to ask critical questions of society without being publicly rebuked, far enough from local history to recognize nuance and apply cultural critique in a non-threatening fashion.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2684 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>An example of such an artist is an old friend <a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/">Soliman Lawrence</a>. Soli has been photographing the memorialization of Jewish culture in Poland for years, following the tracks of a new form of engagement with the past, as enacted by a more recent generation of Poles. His collection of work is titled &#8220;<a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/unquietplacesphoto.html">For those whose faith has been broken</a>&#8220;. They do so, as Soliman&#8217;s stories and their pictures explain, through ritual, one example of which is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Klezmer">Klezmer</a> music. The fascinating part of this story: there are few Jews to speak of in Poland.</p>
<p>Beyond a revived Klezmer tradition, Soliman photographs reconstructed synagogues, Jewish-themed festivals, hand-made figurines, the maintenance of Jewish cemeteries &#8211; all weaving a tale of things past, now re-born as an ode to matzo ball soup or rabbinical characters.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2681 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland" width="640" height="423" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11-300x198.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11-650x429.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>Soliman is not Jewish, though his choice of topic likely gets many thinking that personal biography must inform the interest. I met with Soliman at a little cafe in Neukölln to talk art, history, and memory. Parallels between German memorialization of Jewish culture in Berlin and that which is happening in Poland were not at the tip of his tongue; these parallels were on the tip of mine, however.</p>
<p>Soliman is American by passport, has been a Berlin resident for more than 8 years, making the nationality question a bit tricky. He studied philosophy in the United States, stems originally from the Northern part of Florida, and has a contemplative way about him &#8211; he seems to move slowly, take things in and digest them before forming an opinion.</p>
<p>His artistic career began with a camera, has now evolved into a sort of philosophical exploration of what it means to remember. <em>Memory is at the center of my work</em>, he tells me, <em>how people remember after something has passed, how they remember together</em>. He is interested in the idea of <em><a href="http://www.postmemory.net/">post-memory</a>, the ways in which memory stays alive without the original witnesses</em>. Photography serves a crucial purpose, documentation allowing for connection.</p>
<p>Soliman first started making trips to Poland in 2006, visiting the growing Klezmer festivals in places like Krakaw. <em>Here is the biggest and best festival in Poland</em>, he tells me. I imagine VW buses jammed full with young, alternative Poles, spending warm nights outdoors, not for the beat of electronic sounds but for renditions of clarinet and fiddle. Actually, <em>it is quite mixed</em>, he tells me: young/old, hip/not.</p>
<p><em>When I first showed up in Krakaw, I was taking pictures of everything. I assumed a lot of the stuff I was photographing had something to do with Antisemitism &#8211; graffiti on the walls somehow looked antisemitic to me, these little tiles in the main square with five-pointed stars</em>, <em>for example</em>, he says with a laugh. <em>Then I realized that these stars were actually six-pointed, so </em>not <em>necessarily</em> <em>antisemitic</em>. <em>Very often, one finds what one searches for</em>, I add. This is even more true for a photographer, able to capture and catalog what may be happenstance occurrence, curating images into some sort of narrative about a people or place.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2682 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>That doesn&#8217;t mean that Antisemitism isn&#8217;t present in Polish society, however: <em>it&#8217;s complicated</em>, he says. An interview with Soliman on Jewish memorial culture in Poland appeared in 2012 in <em>die</em> <i>Zeit Online </i>with the headline: &#8220;<em>Wie Nicht-Juden die jüdische Kultur Polens wiederbeleben/</em> &#8220;<a href="http://www.zeit.de/video/2012-12/2032360755001/holocaust-wie-nicht-juden-die-juedische-kultur-polens-wiederbeleben">How Non-Jews Are Resurrecting Poland&#8217;s Jewish Culture</a>&#8220;. I recall watching the interview then, having heard of the beginnings of his Polish adventures back in 2010, when Soli and I first met, and being struck by the oddity of it all, the sense of a manufactured experience to take the place of an entire culture now lost. And yet, it was impossible not to find parallels with the city we both share, I felt: the way in which memory of Jewish culture in Berlin is fractured between recreations of the diaspora experience, a come-back Jewish culture in Germany, and a newer wave of young Israelis.</p>
<p>Soli has given quite a number of interviews in Germany since his project first began to receive attention. A <a href="http://juedische-woche-dresden.de/veranstaltung-2013/items/108.html">recent exhibition of his work in Dresden</a> put him into more contact with the German media. <em>So, did any of these journalists ask about your thoughts on Jewish memorialization in Germany, in Berlin, or on any similarities between Poland and Germany?</em>, I ask. At first, he doesn&#8217;t understand my question, seems a bit perplexed. Then, <em>No</em>,<em> in fact, no one even got close to formulating that question. Interesting that you bring that up. </em></p>
<p>Jewish culture in Berlin is diffuse, hard to put a finger on, as &#8211; with Jews everywhere &#8211; there is no one way to be Jewish and certainly no one way to be Jewish in Berlin. A memorial culture is also difficult to construct, when Jews are in fact present. To boot, there is no <em>one</em> way to memorialize the Holocaust and the thriving Jewish culture in Germany that preceded it. At least no one way that would satisfy the diverse groups who were affected by the genocide. In Poland, very little has happened at an institutional, top-down level. And so revivals of classic Ashkenazi traditions like Klezmer have been a means of memorializing a lost sector of Polish life, many years after its musicians were made to disappear.</p>
<p><em>At my first Klezmer festival, I didn&#8217;t really know what to do with myself. People were dancing, it was celebratory, there was this feeling of community</em>, he says. He was a bit stand-offish, not understanding why active participation was required. <em>This is the ritual</em>, he explains, <em>it is through such a collective ritual that some form of memory is reconstructed and created for the next generation.</em> <em>Many of these young people probably have no real connection to contemporary Jewish people</em>, he adds,<em> but this type of memory doesn&#8217;t require personal connection, rather an attachment to space and a desire to make a place &#8211; a memorial &#8211; out of it.</em></p>
<p>In Berlin, there is a strong attention to memorial sites or objects &#8211; the <a href="http://www.stolpersteine-berlin.de/en/stolpersteine"><em>Stolpersteine</em></a>, <a href="http://www.holocaust-mahnmal.de/en"><em>Memorial to the Murdered Jews of Europe</em></a>, <a href="http://www.slowtravelberlin.com/touching-berlins-ghosts/"><em>Bayerisches Viertel</em></a>, to name a few. These are spaces that are visited and even organized by many but are perhaps not as interactive or collective as a Klezmer ritual. One might simply pass by its insignia, whereas Klezmer is somehow a more active process, Soli explains.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2685 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9-300x199.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9-650x432.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p><em>But are these Klezmer festivals in Poland really about remembering and mourning the Holocaust? </em>I ask. <em>Yes, it is about that but not only about that.</em> <em>It is about thinking about the Jews that were once here, by people who were too young to have had the chance</em>.</p>
<p>There is a tendency<em> </em>in memorializing activities to focus on objects and their stories; materiality is desired, physical connection reconstructed. The Holocaust documentation and education center where I used to work curated a collection called &#8220;<a href="http://www.wsherc.org/museum/everyday-objects">Everyday Objects</a>&#8220;, the National Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM) releases <a href="http://www.ushmm.org/information/exhibitions/curators-corner">weekly stories online from its archival vault of objects</a>, and even the recent <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/sportingscene/2014/04/memory-objects-commemorating-the-boston-marathon-bombings.html?utm_source=dlvr.it&amp;utm_medium=twitter">Boston Marathon bombings are being actively commemorated through the collection of ordinary things</a>.</p>
<p><em>When talking with journalists, they just don&#8217;t really understand why Klezmer music is so popular in Poland, </em>Soli comments, as if to emphasize the stark differences between the German memory process and that of the Poland he knows:<em> Memory is expressed differently across space.</em> <em>My work is about these different memory ways, memory forms. </em></p>
<p>Surprising to many, Berlin is home to a fair number of Jews, and not just returned German Jews or those that fled from the former Soviet Union, but Israeli Jews, secular Israelis, secular Diaspora Jews from Argentina etc. &#8211; colliding in one city, not necessarily finding community among one another, because why should they? To make the argument, however, that perhaps things aren&#8217;t as different as they seem, I add that one does see a sort of stereotypical Jewish culture in Berlin, from the <a href="http://www.exberliner.com/locations/luigi-zuckermann-deli/">classic deli</a><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> </span>serving pastrami sandwiches to the local bagel shop. Both places in mind are not run by anyone of Jewish heritage, catering to a historic Jewish culture, perhaps even to New York Jewry rather than Berlin. This is not to say that there are no Jewish delis or bagel shops in Berlin that are owned by Jews. <em>But might the more theatrical recreations be a form of memorial culture, similar to Klezmer festivals?</em> I ask. <em>Maybe</em>, he says, <em>but I know a  few Israelis, and they don&#8217;t necessarily eat bagels. They go to this one shop on </em>Sonnenallee<em> where they can get hummus served warm, like back home in Israel</em>.</p>
<p>The varied layers of Jewish culture, identity, and memory in the Berlin landscape prevent one from making any static comparison to the situation in Poland, it seems &#8211; a place with very few Jews to speak of and a history wrought with a non-institutionalized form of memory, at least until recently. The Israeli and general Jewish presence in Berlin further complicates a comparison between the memory culture of Poland and that of Berlin in a very real sense. To be the authors of a tradition that re-appropriates Jewish tradition means being responsible for potential misappropriation. In Poland, I doubt there are too many active members of the Jewish community who would heavily criticize the rebirth of Klezmer in this form. <em>There aren&#8217;t</em>, Soli says.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2683 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>If he feels strange about researching this issue as an American artist without Jewish descent &#8211; <em>No</em>. The Holocaust is a large part of how Americans understand Germany, I add, in order validate his work from a place of personal opinion. The past was certainly a key factor in my own interest in contemporary German politics and society, as my <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/">article on Sachsenhausen</a> demonstrates.</p>
<p>The question is, if such a connection between a bleak past and curious future can be made, productively, and with much room for nuance and reflection. Soliman Lawrence&#8217;s work allows for just that. Like other artists, he is able to describe memory ways as they are occurring, not overtly criticizing but allowing others to draw their own conclusions or parallels.</p>
<p>We all remember differently. The most important thing is simply to remember.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>Jewish identity in Berlin, Jews in Germany, Israelis in Berlin: there is no shortage of debate, public presence, or diversity. Here a recent <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/culture/2014/05/so-long-israel-hello-berlin.html">article from <em>The New Yorker</em></a> on this topic and a few articles from us, written from the most varied of positions:</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/">Why Remembering the Holocaust is Good for Immigrants</a> &#8211; integration policy and a visit to Sachsenhausen concentration camp</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/07/rant-or-rave-jew-in-a-box/">Rant or Rave? Jew in a Box</a> &#8211; a controversial exhibit at the Berlin Jewish Museum</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">Interview: TV, the Treasury Minister, and Third Culture Kids</a> &#8211; Israeli in Berlin</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/07/interview-three-dimensions-of-integration/">Interview: Three Dimensions of Integration</a> &#8211; Jewish-American artist in Berlin</p>
<p>Last but not least, a few links for finding that Jewish deli or that Israeli hummus: <a href="http://www.berlinfo.com/Lifetime/Shopping/food/jewish/, http://forward.com/articles/165718/berlins-jewish-comeback/?p=al">Berlins Jewish Comeback</a>, <a href="//www.hagalil.com/deutschland/berlin/gemeinde/kosher.htm">Hagalil</a>, <a href="http://www.jewish-berlin.com/kosher.php">Jewish-Berlin</a>, <a href="http://www.berlinjewish.com/tips-for-your-berlin-vacation">Jewish in Berlin</a>, <a href="http://www.exberliner.com/food/land-of-the-lox-can-you-get-deli-food-in-berlin/">ExBerliner deli food list</a>.</p>
<p><em>All images were graciously provided by Soliman Lawrence as part of the series &#8220;<a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/unquietplacesphoto.html">For those whose faith has been broken</a>&#8220;. To see some of Soliman&#8217;s newer projects, check out his homepage. </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Seeing Berlin Through The Homeless</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2014 12:22:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bureaucracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GDR-DDR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitte]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Schöneberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2398</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[They wait for the subway doors to close before they address the car with a rehearsed speech. "Excuse the interruption, I am one of Berlin's annoying homeless people"... it usually begins, as they peddle newspapers and scan the crowd for an outstretched hand holding change or food. The majority of us keep our hands tucked away or firmly gripping our phones. Some of us fall into convenient bouts of exhaustion, promptly leaning back and closing our eyes. In this moment, we are restricted to a shared space...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_2604" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2604" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2604 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-650x433.jpg" alt="hermannplatz" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2604" class="wp-caption-text">Photo by Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>In Berlin they are especially visible on the <em>Bahn</em>. They wait for the subway doors to close before they address the car with a rehearsed speech. <em>Excuse the interruption, I am one of Berlin&#8217;s annoying homeless people&#8230;</em> it usually begins, as they peddle newspapers and scan<em> </em>the crowd for an outstretched hand holding change or food. The majority of us keep our hands tucked away or firmly gripping our phones. Some of us fall into convenient bouts of exhaustion, promptly leaning back and closing our eyes. In this moment, we are restricted to a moving car, a shared space. We can&#8217;t dodge a corner or cross the street, but we still find ways to make them invisible. We don&#8217;t look up because we feel uncomfortable. We become frustrated at them for making us feel this way. We may even become angry &#8211; at them, at society, at ourselves.</p>
<p>How the simple presence of one person can incite so much emotion, judgement, and shame.</p>
<p>How it must feel, to be simultaneously so visible and invisible.</p>
<div id="attachment_2605" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2605" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2605 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-650x459.jpg" alt="eye" width="650" height="459" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-650x459.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-300x212.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2605" class="wp-caption-text">Photo by Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><em>It&#8217;s one of the worst things for homeless people, being treated as invisible. Answer them when they speak to you, make eye contact, acknowledge them!</em> our guide Carsten Voss urges us by the end of our walk. We are wrapping up a tour called &#8220;Obdachslose zeigen ihr Berlin&#8221; (The homeless present their Berlin), run by non-profit organization <em>Querstadtein. </em>The group offers tours in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Mitte that show the reality of homelessness in the city.</p>
<p>Our guide speaks from personal experience. Decked out in designer glasses and a well-fitting sweater, it&#8217;s challenging to picture this man as the subject of the powerful story he delivers in front of stately <span class="st">Viktoria-Luise-Platz</span>. Carsten worked 80+ hours a week as a manager of an international tradeshow before burning-out and falling into depression. First came the loss of his job, then his apartment. He refused help from loved ones, other than taking refuge in a friend&#8217;s shed for a few months. It would be a year before he clawed his way back out. He cites one defining moment: <em>I happened to glance into someone&#8217;s window from the street. The woman was cooking and the man was watching </em>Tagesschau<em> on TV&#8230; I realized that if I didn&#8217;t make a change then, I would never have that again.</em></p>
<p>That year Carsten counted among Berlin&#8217;s estimated 4,000 <em>Obdachslose</em> (literally translates to &#8220;without shelter&#8221;). Not to be confused with <em>Wohnungslose</em> (&#8220;house-less&#8221;), which refers to those without homes but still in the system, <em>Obdachslose</em> are no longer in the system and may or may not have a place to sleep. Berlin has Germany&#8217;s highest concentration of <em>Obdachslose, </em>both from within and outside of the country.</p>
<p><em>There are three main categories of </em>Obdachslose <em>in Berlin</em>, Carsten explains early on in the tour. <em>Former refugees from East Germany, those groups of young people who usually have dogs with them, and immigrants.<br />
</em></p>
<p><a href="http://ec.europa.eu/social/main.jsp?catId=1061&amp;langId=en">Migrant homelessness throughout the EU</a> has risen in recent years, exacerbated by the economic crisis. This may come as no great surprise, though it&#8217;s a blow to hear that many in Berlin<em> end up staying because they find the conditions of being homeless here better than their lives back home. </em>Carsten describes this group in three geographic waves: the first from Poland, second from the Baltics, and third from Bulgaria and Romania<em>. Of course they came here planning to find jobs, start families, create a life. Some make it, but many don&#8217;t. </em></p>
<div id="attachment_2586" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-23-14-33-35.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2586" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2586 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-23-14-33-35.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-23 14.33.35" width="640" height="480" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2586" class="wp-caption-text">Cold Weather Assistance for Berlin&#8217;s Homeless by District, Winter 2013/14</p></div>
<p>Berlin has a long tradition of homelessness. It&#8217;s a poor city &#8211; Germany&#8217;s poorest &#8211; but also equipped with robust social services. Berlin has a history of attracting those who are &#8220;different&#8221;, including many immigrants, due to its diversity and tolerant atmosphere. During the days of the Berlin Wall, it was also a haven for males escaping military conscription (which ended altogether in 2011). Carsten moved to Berlin for this reason, and says he and many others like him entered fields like social work and education. This, he claims, has contributed to the city&#8217;s liberal nature and strong social net.</p>
<p>Berlin&#8217;s homeless tend to cluster in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Charlottenburg, two districts in West Berlin now more associated with high rents and artisanal cafes than alternative lifestyles. Carsten guides us to Nollendorfplatz, Berlin&#8217;s LGBT hub and site of the annual pride parade, Christopher Street Day. We stand across from the colorful <em>Regenbogen-Stele, </em>a r<span class="userContent">ainbow column erected in 2000 to celebrate the area&#8217;s high concentration of homosexual residents and open-minded atmosp<span class="text_exposed_show">here. The statue itself carries two symbols: the rainbow flag for gay pride and the <em>Rosa Winkel</em>, a pink badge first used by Nazis to distinguish homosexuals in concentration camps, and what later became an international symbol for gay rights.<br />
</span></span></p>
<div id="attachment_2507" style="width: 538px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/2014-03-23-14-21-00-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2507" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2507" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/2014-03-23-14-21-00-1.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-23 14.21.00-1" width="528" height="528" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2507" class="wp-caption-text">Nollendorf Platz&#8217;s &#8220;Regenbogen-Stele&#8221; or rainbow column celebrating gay rights</p></div>
<p>As we inspect the square, Carsten points out what our untrained eyes fail to see: a 24-hour grocery store well-equipped with bottle deposit machines, a van selling the street newspaper, a well-lit intersection. <em>Homeless people are part of this neighborhood, they have a community here</em>, he says.</p>
<p>But another faction of the city&#8217;s homeless blend in so well that we don&#8217;t see them at all. <em>Most people have an image in mind of the bag lady (or guy), unkempt and dirty, pushing around a cart filled to the brim with random items, muttering crazy things to themselves.</em>.<em>. most homeless people don&#8217;t look or act like that. </em> Carsten estimates that 60% fall into this category, homeless people who look &#8220;normal&#8221; so they can use spaces and services within the city without being noticed. They schedule their day in such a way that they always have a place to be, something to eat, even a bed to sleep in. They know when the citizens&#8217; office opens and when they can grab a shower, when they can rest in the library or supermarket, who is offering a free lunch or haircut in the city. <em>It&#8217;s an exhausting life, they have to be very organized, and they are constantly in public</em>, Carsten emphasizes: <em>the only time they have to themselves is in the shower.</em></p>
<div id="attachment_2621" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-24-08-25-20.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2621" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2621 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-24-08-25-20.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-24 08.25.20" width="640" height="480" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2621" class="wp-caption-text">Assistance notice for homeless youth in Charlottenburg</p></div>
<p>Carsten&#8217;s happy ending is a welcome take-away from an otherwise harrowing topic, but he warns against the assumption that all homeless people are unhappy or need to be saved. While many do suffer from mental illness and drug and alcohol abuse, others have deliberately chosen this lifestyle. <em>Some people want to live this way, and we have to respect that. We have to recognize them as part of society.</em></p>
<p><span class="userContent"><span class="text_exposed_show">It&#8217;s easy to dodge corners and cross streets, to switch subway cars to avoid someone&#8217;s stench or words, to grip our phones and look down. </span></span></p>
<p>It&#8217;s not as easy to look up.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>The Querstadtein homeless tours (in German) take place in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Mitte, usually on Sundays and for approximately 2 hours. Tickets cost <span class="st">€</span>9,40, and <span class="st">€</span>5,40 for students, seniors, and individuals on welfare. More information can be found at <em>http://querstadtein.org/de/stadtfuehrungen/.<br />
</em></p>
<p>For more on the Querstadtein tours in English, click <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/zeitgeist/berlin-tour-gives-a-glimpse-of-berlin-as-seen-by-homeless-people-a-913758.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>For more on the increasing restrictions on public space for homeless people across Europe, <a href="http://www.surveillance-and-society.org/articles5%283%29/homelessness.pdf">click here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; and the White Audience</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2014 14:00:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Afrodeutsch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nazi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[segregation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theater]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2248</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One attends a play about an Afro-German living in the years of Nazism and Jim Crow not because of the dramaturgy. One buys the ticket because of the topic's near absence in the German discourse. This is not a review of the play, but rather a continuation of the discussion with the cast that followed. As one of the cast-members remarked, it all comes down to audience: "Black folks probably wouldn't go to the theater to see this play in the U.S., let alone have enough money for the ticket. And here, we have a white audience. So, who are we really talking to here? Who is seeing this play?"...
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>As a student of my own history and place in this world, nothing is more difficult for me than to write about issues of privilege, white-ness, black-ness, and justice in one sitting, because there is so much that can go wrong, so many terms that can be mis-used or mis-assigned, and so many truths that cannot be conveyed in one text. I have done my best. And with all my socio-anthropological know-how, I may still miss the point or offend, for which I am sorry: so is the nature of the subject.</em></p>
<p>One attends a play about an <em>Afrodeutscher* &#8211; </em>Afro-German &#8211; living in the years of Nazism and Jim Crow not because of the dramaturgy. One buys the ticket because of the topic, i.e. its novelty and near absence in the German discourse. &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221;, &#8220;Made Black&#8221;, at the <a href="http://www.etberlin.de/">English Theatre Berlin</a> explores the rich text of race in 1930s Berlin through the experience of Klaus, an unknowing Afro-German &#8211; a word that still spikes the air with rarity, German-ness still seen by many as a monopoly of the white-skinned.</p>
<p>But Klaus&#8217;s character and his experience of targeted exclusion are not that far from the present, as a conversation with the cast will demonstrate.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_4.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_4.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht" width="640" height="1016" /></a></p>
<p>The play&#8217;s dense telling of a complicated history of race, citizenship, and post-colonialism through dialogue is impressive. Equally worthy of praise is the playwright&#8217;s collaboration with a well-versed historian.  The Afro-German actor, with a biography startlingly similar to the protagonist he portrays, is also seemingly extraordinary. The most important element, however, relates to its audience and what this means for theater as a medium of cultural critique.</p>
<p>This is not a review of the play, per se, on which the curtains closed this past Sunday. Rather, this is a review of the discussion with the cast, playwright, and director that came after, the sentiments of which will remain prominent and powerful in my mind, long after audience members have discarded their ticket stubs.</p>
<p><strong>The Conversation</strong></p>
<p>Thursday night, we, a primarily white audience, wait patiently for the cast to take their places at the foot of the stage. The protagonist of the play, the actor to play the American jazz musician, the actor to play the German politician, the playwright (Alexander Thomas), and the director file into folding chairs. <strong>&#8220;Black folks probably wouldn&#8217;t go to the theater to see this play in the U.S., let alone have enough money for the ticket. And here, we have a white audience. So, who are we really talking to here? Who is seeing this play?&#8221;</strong>, says the actor who plays the Black American musician &#8211; the play&#8217;s connective thread to Jim Crow.<strong> </strong>The scene seems to agree.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_3.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2259" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_3.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht theater cast" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>Daniel Brunet, the mustached upstate New Yorker who produces the <a href="http://www.etberlin.de/producing-series/the-lab/">LAB series</a> for the English Theatre and directed this play, chimes in about the lack of representation of certain &#8220;communities&#8221; in cultural institutions. The problem of equitable, fair representation is something sure to resound for both American and German audiences, though certainly in different ways.</p>
<p>This problem is an old one. But it rattles and recalls Berlin&#8217;s more recent debates on multiculturalism, intercultural politics, and the integration &#8211; or just plain tolerance &#8211; of difference. &#8220;The topic of being German <em>and </em>of<em> </em>being a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Person_of_color">person of color</a> (p.o.c.) continues, often with little progress&#8221;, a p.o.c. from the audience remarks, a hint of a German accent in the throat. This topic is contemporary, indeed.</p>
<p><strong>Can theater change these parameters? Can theater ask for more diversity from institutions that have no incentive to include them?</strong></p>
<p>The playwright, a Black American married to a white German woman, wrote &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; as a way to process &#8220;the complexity of these issues&#8221;. And yet, as he makes perfectly clear, representing his own stereotypes of Germans and &#8220;the lack of place in [his] mind for an Other of color in Germany&#8221; is central to the play. &#8220;Otherwise, I would have been acting dishonestly&#8221;, he says, looking into the glare, behind which fragments of the audience, of us, must appear.</p>
<p>The protagonist of the play, himself an Afro-German, speaks, his English flooded with German vowels, his mannerisms oddly similar to his character, who re-asserts his German identity proudly throughout the play in deference to the Othering looks of those around him. This Other, created by the Black American writer, is somehow a reflection of himself, he states, admitting how through rehearsals he struggled to read his lines, even bursting into tears; how the first time he read the play, he felt personally implicated and stripped bare. <strong>&#8220;I am German, my father left when I was three years old, I grew up with my mother, was born in Hamburg, that is all I have ever known”</strong>, he says. The biographies are nearly identical, minus 80 years and a certain regime.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2311.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2255" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2311.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht stage" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>The anger he enacts in the play now takes hold of his voice: the desperation and frustration. <strong>“Once I read the script I knew it had to be done, we had to make this play. Though, during intermission, when I was sprawled on the stage in a pile of paper [the stage is composed mainly of bundles and bundles of blank paper], I sometimes thought ‘what am I doing here, who am I talking to&#8217;”</strong>.</p>
<p>Despite these questions of audience and representation, the play successfully sends a message, one of critique. It weaves the complicated history of American segregation and its sub-human treatment of Blacks with the messianic framing of America&#8217;s involvement in WWII. Through the diverse arrangement of its characters, the play scrutinizes American moral authority in the fight against Nazi ideology and fascism, drawing dramatic attention to Jim Crow and the commonalities between racist ideologies.</p>
<p><strong>The parallels between American oppression and Nazi tyranny become painfully clear, eliciting the following question from the audience: &#8220;Would you show this play in America? And under what conditions?&#8221;</strong></p>
<p>&#8220;We would just need a theater to show it&#8221;, the playwright says with a smile, confidently speaking for the work alone. &#8220;The play was actually meant for an American audience&#8221;, he adds, hence the translation of German passages and numerous references to American &#8216;race sciences&#8217;, details often omitted from textbooks. &#8220;This is a history of not only segregation but of a science [eugenics and race-based Social Darwinism] that many Americans do not know about&#8221;.</p>
<p>Such a truth of ignorance is reflected in the young woman in the play, who claims that the protagonist, Klaus, is not like &#8220;the other Negroes back home!&#8221;, though she has &#8220;never met one&#8221;.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2258" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_2.jpg?w=640" alt="colonialism Jim Crow" width="640" height="411" /></a></p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Theater approaches many controversial political topics in the United States, because it can. A very particular demographic is going to the theater; and that is where such issues can be discussed&#8221;</strong>, Brunet adds.</p>
<p>The playwright explains that he is willing to relinquish artistic license and allow others to define the scope and boundaries of the play&#8217;s possible interpretations. Some scenes are based on his own childhood, others on historical research and collaboration with the author of <em><a href="https://www.press.umich.edu/174272/other_germans">Other Germans</a>, </em>Tina M. Campt<em>, </em>about being a person of African heritage in Germany.</p>
<p>&#8220;But what is the point of the play?&#8221;, the jazz musician asks, perhaps to the audience, perhaps to no one present in this room. It is not about carving out identity from the crowd, asserting the value of the image in the attic mirror, but rather &#8220;about convincing society – the powerful – that exclusion is harmful and degrading to human beings. Now, and back then!&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;The point is, speaking truth to power&#8221;</strong>, he says, referencing, most notably, <a href="http://www.cornelwest.com/">Dr. Cornel West</a>, a giant in the continued civil rights movement for people of color, for the exploited lower classes.</p>
<p>Theater is not a dialogue with the masses, nor a dialogue with society in general, however. &#8220;Like cultural media and cultural politics, it is a dialogue with the powerful and their ideas&#8221;, says Brunet. The rest is some trickle down effect or, as the p.o.c. from the audience adds, &#8220;a change in consciousness&#8221;.</p>
<p>The camera man, a towering Black man with an equally large voice, speaks to the political or &#8220;transformative nature of the play&#8221;: <strong>“Most people ask themselves the question, are things really that different now? That is what this play does, it asks that question again of the powerful&#8221;.</strong></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5em;">With these words, I instantly feel implicated by my privilege, the things afforded to me on the basis of the position and body I was born into. The room shrinks. I shift in my seat.</span></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5em;">We are the audience. We are the ones who should see this play. We shape the discourse, often to the detriment of those who do not fit the desired mold. Theater might be a chance to reflect on <a href="http://www.taz.de/!116745/">critical whiteness</a>, even on its limitations.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2296.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2250" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2296.jpg?w=640" alt="English Theatre Berlin" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>One of the members of the cast remarks, perhaps to break a long 15 seconds of silence, <strong>&#8220;Can we imagine a black actor playing Romeo? A white actor playing Othello? Is it bad that we can&#8217;t?&#8221;</strong> For the sake of this question, &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; should be produced in another season, maybe in another city, as a voice in a room with too few listeners.</p>
<p>I sincerely hope that it might be staged in the United States, a country, where diversity often means tolerating the one that is different but disrespecting him or her just the same. As <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/ta-nehisi-coates/">Ta-Nehisi-Coates</a> wrote in <em>The Atlantic</em> this Tuesday, <strong>&#8220;We are in America, where our absence of virtue is presumed, and we must eat disrespect in sight of our sons.<em> </em>And who can be mad in America? Racism is just the wind, here. Racism is but the rain.&#8221; </strong></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*After the Nazi dust had cleared the German capital and West German society had taken root, the Black American poet and activist Audrey Lorde began to popularize the term <em>Afrodeutsche(r) </em>or Afro-German,<em> </em>during <a href="http://www.audrelorde-theberlinyears.com/">her years in the city</a>, effectively building a movement that at least gave a name to an almost invisible population.</p>
<p><em>For more information on Afro-German history in English, click <a href="http://german.about.com/od/culture/a/blackhistger.htm">here</a>. For more information on Afro-German organizations in Berlin and in all of Germany: <a href="http://isdonline.de/">Initiative schwarze Menschen in Deutschland</a>, <a href="http://www.afro-deutsche.de/">Afrodeutsche e.V</a>, <a href="http://www.adefra.com/">Schwarze deutsche Frauen und schwarze Frauen in Deutschland</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>For an interesting twist, check out our <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/">article on Black Germans</a> (the change of language here was intentional) growing up in the United States to adoptive parents, often in the segregated South. </em></p>
<p>Photo source: Kelly Miller and <a href="http://jurigottschau.com/">Juri Gottschau</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: An Ode to the Maybachufer</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/20/lens-an-ode-to-the-maybachufer/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/20/lens-an-ode-to-the-maybachufer/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2014 11:53:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gentrification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1853</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[From Berlin's "problem district" to more expensive than spießig Charlottenburg: Kreuzberg's made quite the transformation over the decades, but migration continues to shape its identity and reputation as a district. The bulk of Kreuzberg's diversity stems from the '50s and '60s, when guest workers were recruited by West Germany to fill labor shortages after World War II*. Kreuzberg's dilapidated housing became home to guest workers, primarily from Turkey...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From Berlin&#8217;s &#8220;problem district&#8221; to <a href="http://www.bz-berlin.de/aktuell/berlin/kreuzberg-teurer-als-charlottenburg-article1398469.html">more expensive</a> than <em>spießig</em> Charlottenburg: Kreuzberg&#8217;s made quite the transformation over the decades, but migration continues to shape its identity and reputation as a district.</p>
<p>The bulk of Kreuzberg&#8217;s diversity stems from the &#8217;50s and &#8217;60s, when guest workers were recruited by West Germany to fill labor shortages after World War II*. Kreuzberg&#8217;s dilapidated housing became home to guest workers, primarily from Turkey. The district soon came to be known as &#8220;Little Istanbul&#8221;. In 2014 you would still be hard pressed to find a block without a <em>Döner</em> <em>Kebab </em>stand or five, but the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/">district&#8217;s diversity</a> extends far past Anatolia.</p>
<p>Along with districts like Neukölln and Wedding, Kreuzberg is renowned for its <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/11/happy-weekend-its-not-about-integration-or-isnt-it/">immigrant integration</a> challenges that include low educational attainment and poor German language skills, high unemployment rates, crime and drug abuse, and gentrification. At the same time, the area has become increasingly attractive to <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/">students</a>, hip expats, and young families. The result is a veritable array of nationalities, cuisines, houses of worship, and attires, as vivid as the graffiti gracing the walls of its gray housing and slender canals.</p>
<p>There are many popular spots in Kreuzberg, but the Maybachufer canal is perhaps one that most poignantly displays the cultural fusion that makes Kreuzberg a very special place to call home.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/swans.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/swans.jpg" alt="swans" width="594" height="594" /></a></p>
<p><strong>An Ode to the Maybachufer</strong></p>
<p>If I go away, I&#8217;ll remember the swans. And the walls of graffiti they floated along.</p>
<p>Rows of satellite dishes, speckled across gray concrete. Lingerers outside Kaiser&#8217;s, empty bottles at their feet.</p>
<p>Men huddled over pear-shaped glasses of Çay. Girls in tiny shorts and tights, snags in their thighs.</p>
<p>A market with only two rows, but infinite choice. Vendors calling &#8220;lecka! lecka!&#8221;, hints of somewhere else in their voice.</p>
<p>Hair smothered by scarves or impossibly fake dye. Individuals by words: &#8220;expat&#8221;, &#8220;immigrant&#8221;. You or I.</p>
<p>Where &#8220;German&#8221; ends and &#8220;other&#8221; begins, we futilely try to decide.</p>
<p>But the swans. They just keep floating by.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The Maybachufer Turkish Market (U1-Kottbusser Tor or U8-Schoenleinstrasse) runs on Tuesdays and Fridays from approximately 12pm-6pm. Go for the cheap produce and spinach-cheese <em>Gözleme. </em><br />
</em></p>
<p>* West Germany recruited 14 million guest workers between 1955 and 1973 during the post World War II &#8220;economic miracle&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>For more on Turks in Germany and guest worker programs:</strong></p>
<p>http://www.azcentral.com/news/articles/global-immigration-germany.html?nclick_check=1</p>
<p><strong>For more on Kreuzberg:  </strong></p>
<p>http://www.fhxb-museum.de/</p>
<p>http://travel.michelin.com/web/destination/Germany-Berlin/news-Kreuzberg_forever-Reichenberger_Str_177</p>
<p>http://www.humanityinaction.org/knowledgebase/32-in-kreuzberg-there-are-no-foreigners-scrutinizing-berlin-s-diversity</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/20/lens-an-ode-to-the-maybachufer/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rave: the Political Berlinale</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/11/rave-the-political-berlinale/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2014 10:00:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[film]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2090</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The festival of the golden bear invites the local to become a voyeur and thereby, to recall the headlines, the paroles, the debates, the sagas of the last year - to make meaning of images and thus to make sense of things, or, at least, to just make some sense. In the spirit of the critical viewer and in celebration of themes close to Berlin migration politics, I give you this rave of timely films and the 3 local contexts that make them and this Berlinale so special...
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/logo_print.gif"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2102 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/logo_print.gif" alt="logo_print" width="207" height="82" /></a>Berlin&#8217;s most famous film festival (<a href="http://www.zeit.de/kultur/film/2014-02/fs-berlinale-festival-stars">George Clooney is here</a>, did you hear?) is not merely a competition for the best cinematography, script, or performance.  Like many other cultural events, politics are at play. For after all, the arts and the judging public are anything but impartial.</p>
<p>The festival of the golden bear invites the local to become a voyeur and thereby, to recall the headlines, the paroles, the debates, the sagas of the last year &#8211; to make meaning of images and thus to make sense of things, or, at least, to just make some sense. In the spirit of the critical viewer and in celebration of themes close to Berlin migration politics, I give you this rave of timely films and the three local contexts that make them and this Berlinale so special.</p>
<p><strong>1. Economic migration, so-called <em><a href="http://www.spiegel.de/politik/deutschland/armutseinwanderung-viviane-reding-sieht-roma-als-verusacher-a-952308.html">Armutszuwanderung</a>, </em>has captured local and national news as of late. <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/20/roma-in-berlin-bureaucracy-in-lichtenberg/">Berlin districts struggle to cope with what they perceive to be an impending crisis of immigrants</a> (read <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/01/happy-weekend-a-roma-reimage/">Roma</a>) from Eastern Europe. Here is a film for that:</strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="http://www.berlinale.de/external/de/filmarchiv/doku_pdf/20143562.pdf">The Forest is like the Mountains (Pâdurea e ca muntele, vezi?)</a></strong> (Romania, Forum) is a documentary by the German Christiane Schmidt and the Belgian Didier Guillain into the everyday life of a Roma village near the Sfântu Gheorghe district in Romania. Yes, there are tears from a young girl with the admission that &#8220;The Roma [have] never had any money&#8221;. This, however, is not the film&#8217;s baseline. Schlepping materials from the forest basin to the open pastures, pushing horses, playing among the thicket, enjoying the intimacy and stability of family: these elements enrich the plot to something beyond tenuous living conditions. Delivering any image, any experience, of life on the other side of a hyperbolic and vilified form of &#8220;Roma migration&#8221; may help to replace fear and political posturing with understanding. <a href="http://www.berlinale.de/de/programm/berlinale_programm/datenblatt.php?film_id=20143562#tab=video25">Tickets</a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/the-forest-is-like-the-mountains_berlinale_hff-munich.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2096" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/the-forest-is-like-the-mountains_berlinale_hff-munich.jpg?w=640" alt="The forest is like the mountains Berlinale film on Roma" width="640" height="360" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/the-forest-is-like-the-mountains_berlinale_hff-munich.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/the-forest-is-like-the-mountains_berlinale_hff-munich-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/the-forest-is-like-the-mountains_berlinale_hff-munich-650x365.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/the-forest-is-like-the-mountains_berlinale_hff-munich-310x174.jpg 310w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p><strong>2. With all the talk of economic crisis &#8211; the <a href="http://www.bildblog.de/tag/pleite-griechen/">disparaging criticism</a> of countries like Greece and Spain for not having managed their households &#8211; it must be difficult for the scores of young Spanish, Greek, Portuguese, and Italian (etc.) <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/jul/07/spanish-youth-germany-unemployment-crisis">immigrants coming to Berlin for an underpaid job</a>. Here are some films for that:</strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="http://www.berlinale.de/de/programm/berlinale_programm/datenblatt.php?film_id=20143250#tab=filmStills">At Home (Sto Spiti)</a> </strong>(Greece, Germany, Forum) follows Nadja, a Georgian housekeeper for an upper class Greek family, through a serious illness and the economic crisis that leaves her without a job in a country different from her home. As the catalog describes, Nadja&#8217;s suggested &#8220;misery is not apparent in the images&#8221;. This recalls the nearly invisible damage, which unruly socioeconomic change has inflicted, since the days the &#8220;cr&#8230;.&#8221; word first appeared in print. For countless numbers of workers abroad, from Georgia to Greece, from Madrid to Berlin, the compelling yet un-dramatized portrayal of insecurity elsewhere will resonate with many. <a href="http://www.berlinale.de/external/de/filmarchiv/doku_pdf/20143250.pdf">Tickets</a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/sto-spiti_j-m-louis-shnp3.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2097" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/sto-spiti_j-m-louis-shnp3.jpg?w=640" alt="Sto spiti Berlinale film on migrant worker" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/sto-spiti_j-m-louis-shnp3.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/sto-spiti_j-m-louis-shnp3-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/sto-spiti_j-m-louis-shnp3-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p><strong><a href="http://www.berlinale.de/external/de/filmarchiv/doku_pdf/20142387.pdf">ärtico</a></strong> (Spain, Generation 14 plus) seems like one of many of Spain&#8217;s answers to the statistics plastered in the media: numbers telling of the young, disillusioned, and unemployed (often Spanish). Directed by Gabriel Velázquez, this is a tale of a family struggling to keep all sides intact amid an economic slump that becomes something of its own expectant monster. Youth, accidental parenthood, angst &#8211; all moving into a space of nothing and nowhere to go, in a way that is captivating in its promise of the ordinary. Stills of emptiness and boredom wait for the impending drama that will end it, I would predict. <a href="http://www.berlinale.de/de/programm/berlinale_programm/datenblatt.php?film_id=20142387#tab=video25">Tickets</a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/20142387_1_img_543x305.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2098" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/20142387_1_img_543x305.jpg" alt="Berlinale film on Spanish youth" width="543" height="286" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/20142387_1_img_543x305.jpg 543w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/20142387_1_img_543x305-300x158.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 543px) 100vw, 543px" /></a></p>
<p><strong>4. Berlin, in particular, has been both actor and stage for the asylum-seeker debate sweeping Germany, i.e. the <a href="http://www.dw.de/german-neo-nazis-protest-at-refugee-center-in-berlin/a-17037793">Hellersdorf neo-Nazi</a> debacle and <a href="http://www.taz.de/!128096/">unorthodox refugee responses</a> to unpopular policies. &#8220;Asylum&#8221; could thus be the buzzword of Berlin&#8217;s 2013, a word that is both polemical and lacking in biography. Here&#8217;s a film for that:</strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="http://www.berlinale.de/external/de/filmarchiv/doku_pdf/20143697.pdf">Macondo</a> </strong>(Austria, Competition) sketches the (inter)personal dilemmas of life in a refugee camp on the fringes of Vienna, where 3000 asylum-seekers live closely together, 11-year old Ramasan from Chechnya among them. The reasons for flight are largely unknown to the young boy, other than the narrative of a father fallen to the Russians. Ramasan guards his family&#8217;s honor in the patriarch&#8217;s stead, a visitor arriving to challenge the stability of the narrative and the boy&#8217;s belief. According to the critics, director Sudabeh Mortezai  paints a Muslim childhood under strain, while telling a cliche-free story of flight, waiting, and doubt that might humanize a highly politicized debate. <a href="http://www.berlinale.de/de/programm/berlinale_programm/datenblatt.php?film_id=20143697#tab=filmStills">Tickets</a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/freibeuterfilm_macando_berlinale.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2099" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/freibeuterfilm_macando_berlinale.jpg?w=640" alt="Macando Berlinale film on asylum seeker in Berlin" width="640" height="343" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/freibeuterfilm_macando_berlinale.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/freibeuterfilm_macando_berlinale-300x161.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/freibeuterfilm_macando_berlinale-650x349.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>Click <a href="http://www.berlinale.de/de/programm/berlinale_programm/programmsuche.php">here</a> for the full Berlinale program. For more coverage of the festival in English, check out <a href="http://www.exberliner.com/topics/berlinale">Ex-Berliner&#8217;s tips and recommendations</a>.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Unless otherwise noted, the selected stills are © Berlinale.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: Difference on the Blessed Isle</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/03/beyond-berlin-difference-on-the-blessed-isle/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2014 17:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[exoticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sri Lanka]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[travel]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2018</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For about three weeks this holiday season, I explored the small tear-shaped island of Sri Lanka with a close friend from Berlin. Though Sri Lanka and the South Asia region were new terrain for us both, this wasn't our first backpacking rodeo. We were experienced enough travelers to expect the ups and downs that a trip of this magnitude would throw our way. We reveled in the highs - a school of fish gracefully drifting past us 12m deep into the Indian Ocean, the exquisitely pungent scents and colors of turmeric and homemade roasted curry powder...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>How do you notice difference in a place, when you expect <em>everything</em> to be different? </strong></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/2013-12-29-13-33-30.jpg"><img loading="lazy" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/2013-12-29-13-33-30.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-12-29 13.33.30" width="634" height="537" /></a></p>
<p>For about three weeks this holiday season, I explored the small tear-shaped island of Sri Lanka with a close friend from Berlin. Though Sri Lanka and the South Asia region were new terrain for us both, this wasn&#8217;t our first backpacking rodeo. We were experienced enough travelers to expect the ups and downs that a trip of this magnitude would throw our way. We reveled in the highs &#8211; a school of fish gracefully drifting past us 12m deep into the Indian Ocean, the exquisitely pungent scents and colors of turmeric and homemade roasted curry powder, a 360 degree view of the greenest green imaginable in tea plantation territory, a monk whipping out his iPad to snap a photo of us hiking. And we did our best to laugh through the lows &#8211; a seven hour train ride on the ground by the toilets, being followed and sexually propositioned by a strange man on a dark road, accidentally paying our safari jeep driver twice, the ruthless mosquitos that left me with infected foot wounds I&#8217;m still watching heal.</p>
<p>But these moments were the superlatives, the stand-outs. When traveling in a place where we expect everything to be different, we may become so focused on the exotic and extreme that we overlook the &#8220;in-between&#8221;: the nuances that expose intricate relationships and interconnections, diversity within diversity, and differences among difference.</p>
<p><strong>Nuances matter<br />
</strong></p>
<p>It took one quick glance at a <em>Sari</em> for me to have an idea about modesty in Sri Lankan female dress (&#8220;they can show their bellies and backs but not their shoulders and knees?!&#8221;). One trip to the bathroom with an unusually low toilet seat had me wondering if Sri Lankans were all very short (&#8220;are all toilets going to be like this?!&#8221;). In other words, I had made my first assumptions about Sri Lankan culture before even leaving the airport. Correction: <em>Before leaving passport control</em>. A few minutes upon arrival and my brain was on overdrive, actively seeking out the exciting, frantically trying to affirm preconceived ideas and make connections. Maybe fatigue, definitely curiosity, likely a survival instinct. I desperately wanted to &#8220;understand&#8221; the place in which I was going to be spending the next three weeks of my life, but I was primarily doing so on a larger, generalizing scale. While my mind naturally looks for nuances and intricacy at home, it took an active effort to protest generalizing abroad. Otherwise my mind would have continued to host its very own <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/18/happy-weekend-karneval-der-kulturen-carnival-of-cultures/"><em>Karneval der Kulturen</em></a>, watching a parade of one-toned diversity go by and glossing over the subtleties.</p>
<div id="attachment_2046" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/2014-01-02-11-28-25.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2046" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-2046" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/2014-01-02-11-28-25.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-01-02 11.28.25" width="640" height="480" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2046" class="wp-caption-text">Looking for the in-between in Tangalle</p></div>
<p><strong><strong>It&#8217;s sometimes not about what we say, but what we don&#8217;t<br />
</strong></strong></p>
<p>Once we made it out of the airport, Anna and I encountered the &#8220;Your country?&#8221; or &#8220;Madame, you are from?&#8221; question at a rate of approximately once per hour. While I would ponder how to put &#8220;Well actually, we met in Buenos Aires, Anna is German but spent half her life in England, I grew up in the U.S. but have a German passport, we live in Germany but speak English together&#8221; into one concise thought, Anna was usually quick to respond with &#8220;Germany&#8221;. Considering how much <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/">this type of question can provoke discussion and bother me at home</a>, I was surprised at how quickly I followed suit and resigned myself to the &#8220;put me in a box&#8221; game. On top of that, I was doing the same in return, never going beyond the &#8220;do you come from this town?&#8221; question with locals. Granted, not every conversation while traveling has to be life-altering, and language often poses a barrier, but opportunities were surely missed to explore our understanding of identity and (inter-)nationality. The one-word response was convenient not only because it was quick &#8211; it facilitated our interactions and put them at a comfortable status quo. &#8220;I am a German tourist and you are a Sri Lankan local&#8221; was never the whole story, but it was story enough. But what about the stories we missed?</p>
<div id="attachment_2042" style="width: 622px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/2014-01-09-13-42-23.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2042" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2042 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/2014-01-09-13-42-23.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-01-09 13.42.23" width="612" height="589" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2042" class="wp-caption-text">Tuk Tuking in Colombo</p></div>
<p><strong>Relationships are often more complex than we expect<br />
</strong></p>
<p>&#8220;Ahhhhaaaa,&#8221; the Tuk-Tuk driver or waiter would say after we answered the above, a knowing smile on his face, &#8220;<em>Alles klar</em>?&#8221; The surprise of Sri Lankans speaking a few words of German faded rapidly as we realized the extent of German tourism to Sri Lanka (It&#8217;s the <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2013-06-17/sri-lanka-s-may-tourist-arrivals-by-country-table-.html">third largest visitor-generating market</a> to Sri Lanka after India and the UK). We spent two fateful days on Beruwala beach experiencing the extent of Teutonic tourism: in a German-run resort surrounded by a predominantly German clientele eating from a menu complete with &#8220;German specialities&#8221; (Schnitzel with a view, anyone?), marking their beach-chair territory at the break of dawn, and interacting with Sri Lankans only when they needed their next smoothie.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/2014-01-05-10-13-31.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2081" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/2014-01-05-10-13-31.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-01-05 10.13.31" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>Yet tourism turned out to be only the tip of the Sri Lankan-German-Iceberg. More often than not, our Sri Lankan inquirer would proceed to tell us about his brother who works in a restaurant in Düsseldorf, his university studies in Heidelberg, her father&#8217;s German friends who came to visit every year, his decision to pursue science thanks to Einstein, even that we looked like we came from Munich (ouch). One guesthouse employee donned a shirt with German and Sri Lankan flags that he got from the local German-run <em>Kinderheim.</em> On one bus ride, we rolled by a station donated by Germans. In Galle, a shopkeeper recited the last eight German Chancellors to us in chronological order. The relationship between these two countries repeatedly smacked us in the face, each day and in every which direction.</p>
<div style="width: 622px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/2014-01-08-16-19-45.jpg"><img loading="lazy" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/2014-01-08-16-19-45.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-01-08 16.19.45" width="612" height="612" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Punctuality not included?</p></div>
<p><strong>Just because a relationship exists, doesn&#8217;t make it two-sided<br />
</strong></p>
<p>The Sri Lankans we encountered were much more aware of Germany and Germans than we had expected. But what about the reverse &#8211; the German perception of this dynamic, continually evolving, and surprisingly multifaceted bi-national relationship? My instinct is that when Germans think of Sri Lanka, they picture pristine beaches, coconut trees, people eating with their hands, and maybe a country re-emerging after the longest war in Asia&#8217;s history. I&#8217;m less confident that they see a legacy of exchange, generation-long friendships, or a cab driver studying science because of Einstein. My hopes remain low after the doctor inspecting my foot wounds back in Berlin asked if they &#8220;also speak Indian there?&#8221;, and I was unable to find any substantial information online about Sri Lankans in Berlin, other than <a href="http://www.berlin.de/restaurants/kueche/?atgrp=Sri-lankisch&amp;atpg=0#atlist1647158">this list of restaurants</a>. It may not be visible, but a Sri Lankan community in Berlin does exist (<a href="https://www.statistik-berlin-brandenburg.de/Publikationen/Stat_Berichte/2013/SB_A01-05-00_2012h02_BE.pdf">1,113 Sri Lankan nationals</a> as of the end of 2012) and is conceivably more diverse than we think.</p>
<p>After three weeks in the most &#8220;exotic&#8221; place I&#8217;ve ever visited, my most striking take-away is that an authentic travel experience must extend beyond exoticism. To really understand what it means to be Sri Lankan, German, or anything else, it is perhaps the nuances that count the most.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>All photos by yours truly. For more information on Sri Lankans in Berlin, check out the <a href="http://www.srilankans-berlin.de/">Sri Lankan Association Berlin</a></em>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: Difference in the Wet Country</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2014 12:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[provincial]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1986</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For nearly a month this holiday season, I explored the social fabric surrounding my US origins with a German national, who had never before been to the land of plenty. Through the fresh eyes of 'the foreigner', I saw my part of America unfold under a curious and critical lens. America is a country that defines itself by historical narratives of migration and manifest destiny. What one encounters on the road in its northwestern corner, however, is a bit more mundane. At closer glance, emptiness and the prosaic everyday give food for thought, in regards to locating and valuing difference wherever it bubbles up...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>How do you notice difference in a city, in which you yourself are different?</strong></p>
<div id="attachment_1992" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1992" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1992 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-1.jpg" alt="Portland, OR steel-bridge" width="640" height="360" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1992" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>For nearly a month this holiday season, I explored the social fabric surrounding my US origins with a German national, who had never before been to the land of plenty. Through the fresh eyes of &#8216;the foreigner&#8217;, I saw my part of America unfold under a curious and critical lens. Given this blog&#8217;s weekly critical handling of all things multicultural in the big city, why not talk about diversity in an American context? This context proves to be quite different from the aspiring-cosmopolitan intersections of the German capital, as shocking as that may or may not be.</p>
<p>America is a country that defines itself by historical narratives of migration and manifest destiny. What one encounters on the road in its northwestern corner, however, is a bit more mundane. At closer glance, emptiness and the prosaic everyday give food for thought, in regards to locating and valuing difference wherever it bubbles up.</p>
<p><strong>Geography matters</strong></p>
<p>Somehow, when we talk of diversity in society, the role of space therein is a side note. In fact, where we live, work, play, learn, and heal in many ways determines our belonging to or exclusion from social and economic groups that are important in ensuring opportunity.</p>
<p>Maps tell us a lot about how different ways of life can exist cohesively together. Maps may miss, however (<a href="http://www.npr.org/censusmap/#4.00/39.00/-84.00">see NPR&#8217;s US census map</a>), where difference pops up beyond the packed hotbeds for multiculturalism of the city, leaving our eyes to experience what the provinces, the forgotten towns, and the coastal sticks have to offer firsthand.</p>
<div id="attachment_1989" style="width: 311px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1989" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1989 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg" alt="Rebecca Vincent" width="301" height="300" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg 301w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent-300x299.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 301px) 100vw, 301px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1989" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Rebecca Vincent</p></div>
<p>In the Pacific Northwest, like many other regions, cartography shows the urban as an array of ever-revolving grids, residences dotting the margins of concrete webs and precise civil engineering, greenery contained, parks splashed with beige and lived-in browns. One passes through these strange boundaries of growth, as if moving through the trunk of a tree to reach its core, each ring giving way to new densities and shapes of living, suburbia giving way to semi-rural apartment clusters and neatly arranged town homes.</p>
<div id="attachment_2001" style="width: 471px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2001" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2001  " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png?w=640" alt="portland map" width="461" height="347" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png 646w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map-300x226.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map-80x60.png 80w" sizes="(max-width: 461px) 100vw, 461px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2001" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Mappery.com</p></div>
<p>Apart from the patterns and markings of cities, great expanses of forest or farmland separate bundles of life from one another. Beyond the edge of the urban, an emptiness emerges. Where cities end, mountain pass truck-stops, wine-making valleys, flat dairy country, coastal trailer parks, and retired logging towns begin. Vehicles connect what trains used to. Marks on the map created for the movement between these revolving grids begin to surface like geometric occurrences of ink. Here humans somehow ended up, often fairly alone with only the company of a gas station and a corner store.</p>
<div id="attachment_2002" style="width: 476px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2002" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2002   " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png?w=640" alt="oregon map" width="466" height="375" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png 749w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map-300x241.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map-650x522.png 650w" sizes="(max-width: 466px) 100vw, 466px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2002" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Oregon Office of Rural Health</p></div>
<p>Passing through such places on the road from one side of the state of Oregon to the next, the new set of eyes saw only distance, forged together by oil rigs and spinning tires. <em>Density can be an advantage, when it comes to social and cultural encounters needed for intercultural understandings to take root</em>, I thought, as we searched for a place to eat on a long stretch that seemed to allow only signage, fast food, and campgrounds.</p>
<div id="attachment_1990" style="width: 471px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-2.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1990" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-1990 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-2.jpg" alt="Portland, OR steel-bridge " width="461" height="614" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1990" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>And yet, the migrant worker shantytown in Southwest Washington, the Korean BBQ embedded in the Tillamook state forest, the sushi bar near Mt. Hood’s base, the taco trucks at truck-stops, the Chinese waiter at the roadside diner all suggest that even in more expansive geographies, difference can occur.</p>
<p><strong>Just because it is there, doesn&#8217;t mean we will notice it</strong></p>
<p>On our way to the valley of the Rogue River, our over-sized vehicle wound down the Pacific Highway, hugging cliffs of the sea and the edges of a strange poverty. We saw mile after mile of rotting cottages, mobile homes made more mobile by landslides, empty villages with the local pub serving bento, tacos, and chowder, and liquor stores the size of the local church beside it. Catholic churches sprouted up in these towns, in the basin of the interstate or at the rim of the sea &#8211; something I did not take notice of at first, but which suggested some shift, an immigration. Those who find ships in the right season or canneries with need for cheaply-bought hands make their way back to the Saints to thank them for their providence, or so it seemed.</p>
<p>In the foggy valleys of dead logging towns, the basin of the interstate, the depressed dairy lands and empty harbors: here the German traveler experienced my part of America with its shady diners where breakfast and hot sauce are served all day, roadside shacks with a For Sale sign, Walmart’s to nowhere. And in between the lines, difference was there, simply glossed over by the mundanity of its appearance, bearing more than John Wayne&#8217;s Americana.</p>
<div id="attachment_1994" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/streeet.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1994" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-1994 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/streeet.jpg?w=640" alt="street Portland, OR" width="640" height="360" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1994" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>The churches that never cease to be obvious and enormous on major highways; the Mexican restaurants with happy signs and plenty of American families digging into re-fried beans and rice, as if it were the national dish; the Japanese restaurants with pictures of majestic mountains that could be local; medical advertisements with black patients and Asian doctors; a South Asian newscaster in a suit just like everybody else; a black reporter stuck to sports on the local news station: these things I may not have noticed without the presence of the new perspective next to me.</p>
<p><strong>It is not about what we say, but about what is heard</strong></p>
<div id="attachment_1991" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/diner-pwf-0066.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1991" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-1991" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/diner-pwf-0066.jpg?w=300" alt="Photo source: Paul Winch-Furness" width="300" height="199" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1991" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Paul Winch-Furness</p></div>
<p>For the German&#8217;s second breakfast in America, we took him to a local diner in southwest Washington with the classic booths and red upholstery, simple fried numbers, and a healthy rotation of pies. As he ordered, his slight accent turned the words into mildly different sounds, his tongue pushing just a bit too far back for the &#8216;l&#8217; and the &#8216;th&#8217; sticking to the front of his teeth. The letters may have come together in a way that did not quite fit the frames we have learned to repeat, but one could and can simply understand. And so &#8216;the waffle special&#8217; was transmitted to the kitchen with no questions asked. And after we had told the waitress in her darling little apron that it was his first time in an American diner, she beamed at the foreigner sitting there in front of the simple white dishware and the paper napkin. She whispered to the other waitress, who, blushing, came over to our table to pour coffee and welcome him to town.</p>
<p>It is not about the sounds being right. It is about our understanding them.</p>
<p><strong>Being an outsider can come in handy, as I have learned on the other side of the Atlantic</strong></p>
<p>Growing up in the far corner of the Western United States, I am familiar with the figures and curves of this particular landscape and society. I have, however, sorely taken for granted what it means to have tacos in the middle of nowhere, to celebrate Persian New Year with friends, or to consider Phở as American as bratwurst (I can thank Seattle for that). In many ways, difference was a natural part of my private and public education, the neighborhoods where I lived, the sports teams I played on, and the churches I attended. I cannot say that I have consciously valued these experiences for what I learned from them. If such encounters and relationships had popped up in my Berlin world, I would have celebrated them. This is largely due to the ways in which diversity is or is not celebrated by society at large and how we might attempt to remedy this fact.</p>
<p>But what is most striking and assuredly the take-away from this tale is that campaign-worthy diversity in the big city is not all there is, nor is it of greater value than the outcroppings of difference at truck-stops off the interstate. This might be where it counts the most.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Ethno-cultural diversity is changing the face of the rural United States, including states like Oregon and Washington. For a great visual of this transformation, see the <a href="http://www.ers.usda.gov/media/176091/page7.pdf">United States Department of Agriculture&#8217;s map from its Rural Population and Migration Brieﬁng Room</a>. As the roadside taco trucks and shantytowns demonstrate, a large wave of migration from Latin America to the Pacific Northwest region has characterized rural growth from 2000-2012, according to the <a href="http://www.ers.usda.gov/amber-waves/2011-december/hispanics-contribute-to-increasing-diversity.aspx#.Ut5lnRA1iM8">USDA&#8217;s recent report</a> on demography. Reflective of this shift to the out-country from the urban heart, is the <a href="http://www.oregonlive.com/pacific-northwest-news/index.ssf/2011/04/in_portlands_heart_diversity_dwindles.html">dwindling diversity in the heart of Portland, OR</a>. Difference is, thus, not always where you expect to find it.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Happy Weekend Review: An Old-New Christmas Market</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/12/20/happy-weekend-review-an-old-new-christmas-market/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2013 14:39:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[consumerism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[food]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[holidays]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1906</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Let's just come right out with it: It's hard to beat Christmas in Germany. Glühwein, cookies, classic lights, decorations strewn across homes and street corners, a calendar that expects, nay, requires you eat a chocolate per day... it's simply wonderful. Though I grew up in the US, my family celebrated Christmas the Teutonic way. I have more than fond memories of hiding the Buttergebäck and Lebkuchen in the laundry room from our Opa so he wouldn't devour them in one sitting, ripping open a human-size Adventskalendar in the course of one night made by our Oma...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/rixdorfer1200.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter  wp-image-1907" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/rixdorfer1200.jpg" alt="Rixdorfer1200" width="627" height="351" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/rixdorfer1200-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/rixdorfer1200-310x174.jpg 310w" sizes="(max-width: 627px) 100vw, 627px" /></a></p>
<p>Let&#8217;s just come right out with it: It&#8217;s hard to beat Christmas in Germany. <a href="http://www.gluhweinmix.com/whatisgluhwein.htm"><em>Glühwein</em></a>, cookies, classic lights, decorations strewn across homes and street corners, a <a href="http://german.about.com/library/definitions/bldef_cmas0301.htm">calendar</a>that expects, nay, <em>requires </em>you eat a chocolate per day&#8230; it&#8217;s simply wonderful. Though I grew up in the US, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/26/lens-coming-home/">my family</a> celebrated Christmas the Teutonic way. I have more than fond memories of hiding the <em>Buttergebäck</em> and <em>Lebkuchen</em> in the laundry room from our <em>Opa </em>so he wouldn&#8217;t devour them in one sitting, ripping open a human-size <em>Adventskalendar</em> in the course of one night made by our <em>Oma</em>, and relishing the torture of opening presents one-by-one on Christmas Eve under the illuminated <em>Tannenbaum</em>.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/baum.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter  wp-image-1909" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/baum.jpg?w=640" alt="baum" width="604" height="604" /></a></p>
<p>The only thing that was missing on our side of the Atlantic &#8211; and perhaps the pinnacle of Germany&#8217;s Christmas genius &#8211; was the <em>Weihnachtsmarkt.</em> The magical, cheerful Christmas market that makes it socially acceptable to go for a <em>Glühwein</em> at lunch with colleagues and eat your weight in candied almonds and those heart-shaped cinnamon cookie necklaces with cheesy phrases on them (ok, no one <em>actually</em> eats the cookie necklaces). The Christmas market that is part amusement park, part shopping center, part bar, part concert, part house of worship. The Christmas market that makes standing outside for hours in winter a desirable activity.</p>
<p>But Christmas markets aren&#8217;t all about empty calories, booze, and decorations. They&#8217;re also not just there for music, gift shopping, and family/friend time. And &#8211; hear me out &#8211; they&#8217;re not just about religion on either end of the purely-Christian-to-overly-PC-spectrum. In its truest sense, a market is a space for community gathering, exchange, and learning. Which is why when I travel, the market is the first place I turn to for an inside look at a different culture and way of life. A Christmas market can be a place for opportunity as much as it is a place for celebration, regardless of religion, background, gender, age, or anything else. And like Kelly wrote this past summer, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/">it&#8217;s about showing up</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/santa.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1912" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/santa.jpg?w=640" alt="santa" width="640" height="640" /></a></p>
<p>Of course Christmas markets come in all shapes and sizes and with varying levels of kitsch and educational potential. In Berlin, there are the <em>über</em>-commercial markets at all major tourists points throughout the city that focus on food and fun: Alexanderplatz, Zoo, Potsdamer Platz. For those who want to class it up a bit, there&#8217;s Gendarmenmarkt and Schloss Charlottenburg. For a smaller-town feel, and if you&#8217;re willing to make the trek outside the <em>Ring</em>, there&#8217;s Spandau. There are even themed markets, like the <a href="http://www.kadre.de/">Designmarket</a> and <a href="http://weihnachten.tagesspiegel.de/schwedischer-weihnachtsbasar.html">Swedish Christmas Market</a>. There is certainly <em>something for everyone</em>, but I&#8217;ve only been to one Christmas market in Berlin that feels truly modern in its <em>inclusion of everyone</em>, and that&#8217;s the Alt-Rixdorfer Market in <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/">Neukölln</a>.<em><br />
</em></p>
<p>Funnily enough, the Alt-Rixdorfer market is more about the past than the future. <em>Alt</em> means &#8220;old&#8221; and is a nod to the neighborhood&#8217;s history which is played out with petroleum lighting, young men acting as the &#8220;town crier&#8221; with old-fashioned megaphones, and pony rides. <a href="http://www.slowtravelberlin.com/in-search-of-rixdorf/">Rixdorf</a> has a long and proud history as a Protestant bohemian refugee settlement from the 1700s and retains its old-fashioned and quaint feel to this day. Its identity is more that of small village than city neighborhood, especially when juxtaposed with the hustle and bustle of <em>Karl-Marx Strasse </em>around the corner.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/rixdorfdouble.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1918" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/rixdorfdouble.jpg" alt="rixdorfdouble" width="470" height="597" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/rixdorfdouble.jpg 470w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/rixdorfdouble-236x300.jpg 236w" sizes="(max-width: 470px) 100vw, 470px" /></a></p>
<p>But besides these touches of years ago, besides the ubiquitous pork products, candied apples, and singing, the Alt-Rixdorfer market offers something different. The stands are primarily run by local clubs, organizations, and charity groups who display and sell homemade wares, whip up international culinary delights, and advocate for their respective causes. And while the market is still predominantly Christian in framework, it&#8217;s not necessarily Christian in purpose. From where I was standing &#8211; bundled up and elbow-to-elbow with young families, Turkish and Arab youth, homosexual couples, a trail of wheelchairs, and my international friends &#8211; the purpose was inclusion, diversity, and participation. Crawling amongst the hoards from stand to stand, I learned about district issues, was served by special needs residents, bought a handmade card with a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamsa"><em>Hamsa</em></a> on it, munched on Korean fried veggies, and watched kids run around proudly to keep the petroleum lights ablaze. What a more meaningful experience than the usual attempt at diversifying such an event: a Dreidel in one corner and Döner stand in the other with everything else green, red, and factory produced inbetween.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/koreanstand.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1917" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/koreanstand.jpg" alt="koreanstand" width="640" height="640" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/koreanstand.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/koreanstand-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>&#8220;Inclusion&#8221; is a hot topic these days in Berlin, Germany, and beyond. Yet when it comes to who needs inclusion and where, people and politics tend to focus on &#8220;special needs students&#8221; and &#8220;the school&#8221;. What about the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/">open Iftar dinner</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/">woman led neighborhood tour</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/">public gallery</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/21/lens-warm-nights-are-for-cricket/">baseball field</a>, and Christmas market? These are also shared community spaces that can promote inclusion of all residents through interaction, learning, and participation. The Alt-Rixdorfer Market shows us that a small effort to include the entire neighborhood can not only make cold feel warm and old feel new, but make Christmas about community.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>First photo <a href="http://www.weihnachteninberlin.de/binaries/asset/image_assets/1322607/ratio_16_9/1380794288/570x321/">source;</a> Rixdorf photo <a href="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%C3%B6hmisch-Rixdorf">source</a>; Karl-Marx Strasse <a href="http://www.stadtentwicklung.berlin.de/staedtebau/foerderprogramme/aktive_zentren/pix/start/2011-karl-marx-str-003.jpg">source</a>; all other photos by Sophia Burton</p>
<p><em>The Alt-Rixdorfer Christmas market takes place in Neukölln&#8217;s Richardplatz  annually on the 2. Advent (usually the first or second weekend of December).</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
