<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Korea &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/korea/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Happy Weekend: &#8220;part Korean, part American, part German, all Kimchi&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/29/happy-weekend-part-korean-part-american-part-german-all-kimchi/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2013 10:21:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kimchi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Korea]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=910</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If the chance of rain deters participation in any of the street events or outdoor markets this weekend, I've got a solution: stuff your face with delicious Korean-fusion. In fact, why not learn a little about Lauren Lee AKA "<a href="http://fraeuleinkimchi.com/">Fräulein Kimchi</a>" - the proponent of the Korean taco and the Bavarian-Korean cooking course - whose appearances in Mauerpark and Markthalle 9 are bringing in the masses (even if the retelling of my Bimbibap obsession in my Seattle years elicits more often the "Bimbi - whaaa?" than an affirmative nod). This post comes from Jessica Jungbauer of <a href="http://www.bestwishesfromberlin.com/">Best Wishes from Berlin</a>, who seeks out the so-called "creatives" of the city, the culinary sort among them, initiating short auto-portraits for an interesting lens into one facet of creative engagement or another...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Though the skies may be darkened, the streets are not empty, and culinary excursions seem to be the thing to do. I can attest to this fact, as a giant blues-soul-rock montage of musicians are performing &#8217;round the clock on a stage just a few meters from my window as part of <a href="http://www.bergmannstrassenfest-kreuzbergjazzt.de/start.htm">Bergmannstraßenfest</a>. As a loving member of the Kiez, I can tolerate loud tunes and folks my parents&#8217; age sitting on my stoop, drinking mojitos out of plastic cups and chatting loudly about drum-circle politics. Stalls of South Indian fried goodies or Dutch mini pancakes make it hard to be frustrated. And if you can&#8217;t do such things in a Berlin summer, then when?</p>
<p>But if the chance of rain deters participation in any of the street events or outdoor markets this weekend, I&#8217;ve got a solution: stuff your face with delicious Korean-fusion. In fact, why not learn a little about Lauren Lee AKA &#8220;<a href="http://fraeuleinkimchi.com/">Fräulein Kimchi</a>&#8221; &#8211; the proponent of the Korean taco and the Bavarian-Korean cooking course &#8211; whose appearances in Mauerpark and Markthalle 9 are bringing in the masses (even if the retelling of my Bimbibap obsession in my Seattle years elicits more often the &#8220;Bimbi &#8211; whaaa?&#8221; than an affirmative nod).</p>
<p>This post comes from Jessica Jungbauer of <a href="http://www.bestwishesfromberlin.com/">Best Wishes from Berlin</a>, who seeks out the so-called &#8220;creatives&#8221; of the city, the culinary sort among them, initiating short auto-portraits for an interesting lens into one facet of creative engagement or another. This is about Lauren Lee, from Lauren Lee, whose motto says a lot about what is possible in a city that is becoming one blend of unexpected fusions after another: &#8220;part Korean, part American, part German, all Kimchi&#8221;. Happy weekend, eat some kimchi.</p>
<p><em>-By<strong> Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.bestwishesfromberlin.com/2013/06/lauren-lee-korea-usa-chef-and-founder.html"><span style="font-size: 1.17em; color: #333333;">Korea / USA,</span></a></p>
<h3>Lauren Lee, chef and founder of &#8216;<a href="http://fraeuleinkimchi.com/">Fräulein Kimchi kocht</a>&#8216;</h3>
<div></div>
<div id="post-body-6678086481718460569">
<table cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/0ff38-frc3a4uleinkimchi_740.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="border: 0;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/0ff38-frc3a4uleinkimchi_740.jpg" alt="" width="740" height="555" border="0" /></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lauren at her favorite place in Berlin, &#8216;Goldhahn &amp; Sampson&#8217; in Prenzlauer Berg</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<div></div>
<p><em>The day Korean chef Lauren Lee brought some kimchi of hers to Mauerpark in Berlin, she knew that &#8220;Berlin was finally ready for Korean-Fusion food&#8221;&#8230;</em></p>
<p>I first visited Berlin during a frosty February in 2006 and fell in love with the city. Considering that I came from Los Angeles and 25 degree weather, that was quite a feat. I decided quite spontaneously to move and 7 months later I landed in Tegel with 2 suitcases, a German-English dictionary and a lot of enthusiasm and naiveté.</p>
<p>What I love about Berlin is that there are still possibilities here as it is a city that is constantly in flux and reinventing itself and it allows me to change and grow with it. The Berlin I experienced 5 years ago when I first moved is quite a different place then the Berlin now and I suspect will be a new place again 5 years from today.</p>
<p>Originally I came to Berlin to study opera with a teacher I had met in New York and a few years ago I was helping to run a fringe opera company &#8211; Berlin International Opera &#8211; while studying and working. Of course I&#8217;ve always loved cooking and entertaining but it wasn&#8217;t until a medical reason forced me to quit singing for a while and I needed a new outlet for my creative energy.</p>
<p>One day I decided to wear one of my dirndls (I have a not so secret obsession with dirndls) and brought some kimchi to Mauerpark. I had a friend photograph people&#8217;s very fun reactions to eating kimchi for the first time and&#8230; voilà, &#8216;Fräulein Kimchi&#8217; was born. I got secretly obsessed with introducing Korean food to all those (poor) people who have had no experience with my native cuisine and whenever I travelled I always had a small package of Korean ingredients with me. (It&#8217;s the best way to get hosted on Couchsurfing if you offer to make people a home-cooked dinner!). I&#8217;ve cooked Korean food and made kimchi for people in Finland, Denmark, Norway, France, Austria, England, Ireland, Italy and of course all throughout Germany. In the meantime, back in Berlin I started teaching cooking classes at one of my favorite foodie stores &#8211; &#8216;Goldhahn &amp; Sampson&#8217; &#8211; and catering small parties and dinners for friends and acquaintances.</p>
<p>What always surprises me about Berlin is how much it feels like a small town for being such a large city. I&#8217;ve been lucky in getting to know people through various circles that have really helped me along the way with developing my food passions. I got to know Kavita Meelu through mutual contacts at &#8216;Goldhahn &amp; Sampson&#8217; and cooked for one of her &#8216;Mother&#8217;s Mother&#8217; meals last summer, which then led me to &#8216;Kitchensurfing&#8217; which led me to &#8216;Street Food Thursday&#8217; at the Martkhalle 9, well, I guess I&#8217;ve been blessed with being in the right place at the right time with some amazing people to support me.</p>
<p>Now I&#8217;m keeping busy with &#8216;Street Food Thursdays&#8217;, my kimchi making and weekly catering at &#8216;Soundcloud&#8217;. I am surprised at how well everything is going, but I guess Berlin is finally ready for Korean-Fusion food and&#8230; Korean Tacos, which has been my passion from the start. It&#8217;s pretty funny, when I first approached the guys at &#8216;Goldhahn &amp; Sampson&#8217; to let me teach my Korean-Mexican class a few years ago, they were fairly resistant to the idea. &#8220;Lauren,&#8221; they said, &#8220;No one will know what that is, what IS a Korean taco?&#8221; I&#8217;m happy to say, I ended up finally convincing them and now I teach my Korean-Bavarian class there as well.</p>
<p>In August I will be starting my own supperclub &#8211; &#8216;Fräulein Kimchi&#8217;s Delish Tisch&#8217;- in Prenzlauer Berg where I will offer seasonal menus with whimsical fusions between Korean, German and American food and I&#8217;m slowly, slowly toying with the idea of a &#8216;Fräulein Kimchi Café&#8217;&#8230;</p>
<p><em>For seat reservations to the &#8216;Delish Tisch&#8217; in August, please contact frauleinkimchi@gmail.com. Be sure to follow the journey of bringing Korean food to Berlin via <a href="https://de-de.facebook.com/FraeuleinKimchikocht">facebook</a> or the <a href="http://fraeuleinkimchi.com/">website</a>.</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.bestwishesfromberlin.com/2013/06/lauren-lee-korea-usa-chef-and-founder.html">Original post</a></p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
