<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>multiculturalism &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/multiculturalism/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Why Feminism and Hijab Go Together</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/12/04/feminism-hijab-go-together/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2016 09:30:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[feminism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hijab]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4704</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As Muslim refugees who choose to wear hijab become a lasting part of the societies of those European states that have taken them in, their right to be different must be defended. Most importantly, we must defend the right of women to choose. It is this choice that makes women free. This is why feminism and hijab go together.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Donald Trump will soon take over the most (seemingly) powerful office in the United States. In just one month,&nbsp;<em>Vogue</em> will launch&nbsp;its <a href="http://en.vogue.fr/fashion/fashion-news/articles/conde-nast-international-launches-vogue-arabia/43938">first ever Arabia edition</a>. These two events are related &#8211; by hijab.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Only hours after Trump was proclaimed victor by electoral vote, a certain fear took hold in minority populations in the United States. Fear of deportation, of political oppression, of social persecution. This fear has proven itself well-founded. The Southern Poverty Law Center recently reported </span><a href="http://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/hate-on-the-rise-after-trumps-election">a dramatic increase in hate crimes and xenophobic harassment</a>, since Trump’s victory.</p>
<div id="attachment_4711" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4711" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4711 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341-650x433.jpg" alt="reise_usa-2015-bearbeitet-341" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4711" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Given the President-elect’s verbal attacks on Islam and Muslims in (or coming to) America, this fear of emboldened hostility in the general populace is felt <a href="http://people.com/bodies/muslim-women-scared-wear-hijab-trump-win/">ever so acutely</a> by America’s diverse Muslim community. Muslim women, in particular, have expressed a new hesitation to wear hijab in public &#8211; the traditional headscarf &#8211; following the election. As </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">New York Magazine</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> reports, many young Muslima <a href="http://nymag.com/thecut/2016/11/after-trumps-win-muslim-women-are-afraid-to-wear-the-hijab.html">took this fear to twitter</a>. One young woman tweeted her devout mother’s words of caution, &#8220;Please don’t wear your hijab today,&#8221; only to be attacked by right-wing trolls, twitter’s escalating problem in this age of free speech and anti-democratic vitriol. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Whether or not a Trump presidency and its fallout will actually lead to physical harm of Muslim women is not something we can know, right now. But we can juxtapose this fear&nbsp;with hijab as an object of both identity and ridicule&nbsp;&#8211; an object that conservative movements and some European governments have taken outright offense to.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Editor-in-chief of Vogue<em> Arabia</em> is a Saudi princess, a self-professed queen of elegant women in any silhouette. She, </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Deena Aljuhani Abdulaziz, </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">is also a champion of the down-to-earth cat-walk. And she does not (perhaps no surprise here) actually live in the Kingdom</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Although D. Aljuhani Abdulaziz&nbsp;does not herself wear hijab, she supports women who do. According to her interview with </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The New York Times</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, the consumer preferences of Muslim women are <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/11/03/fashion/islamic-fashion-vogue-arabia.html">at the core of this <em>Vogue</em></a>. The magazine’s mission for women in the Muslim world, she explained, is to highlight dress in its femininity, its creativity, and its usage by everyday women across the Arab world, hijab or no hijab. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is not only Arab women living in Doha or Beirut who ascribe to the beauty norms of hijab-wearing models and hijab-based marketing, thus <em>Vogue Arabia</em>’s readership will surely not stay confined to the Arab world. It is published online in both English and Arabic and maintains an international aesthetic (both in branding and in the women who gloss its pages). The princess and Conde Nast seem cognizant of the status of women in hijab: they represent an established style and lifestyle, on a global scale. </span></p>
<div id="attachment_4712" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4712" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4712 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2-650x433.jpg" alt="reise_london-2014-bearbeitet-2" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4712" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This recognition is not limited to Big Money in the Arab world. Women in hijab have begun to take their place among trendsetting brands in countries in which they are decidedly the minority. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Even in Trump’s America, CoverGirl recently <a href="http://firsttoknow.com/meet-the-new-face-of-covergirl-hijab-wearing-beauty-blogger-nura-afia/?utm_source=contentad_backfill&amp;utm_campaign=meet-the-new-face-of-cov-211246&amp;pp=1&amp;utm_medium=180533">added a Muslima in hijab</a> to its blogosphere and promotional sites, a hijab-friendly designer <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-37381770">stole the show at this year’s New York Fashion Week</a>, a U.S. beauty pageant contestant&nbsp;did <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/goatsandsoda/2016/11/29/503729951/the-beauty-pageant-contestant-wore-a-burkini">the whole thing in burkini and hijab</a>, and (if you haven’t heard) Marvel released <a href="http://marvel.wikia.com/wiki/Kamala_Khan_(Earth-616)">its first Muslima superhero</a>. Yes, even superheroes can wear scarves, and <a href="https://mic.com/articles/125199/badass-muslim-superheroes-comics-tv">it doesn&#8217;t stop at Marvel</a>.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><em>Vogue</em> and these other agents of popular culture bring the hijab into a different type of mainstream &#8211; of fashion and femininity. In asserting that &#8220;Yes, this too is a woman,&#8221; a woman’s choice of what to wear is expanded. Bikinis were first <a href="http://content.time.com/time/photogallery/0,29307,1908353_1905442,00.html">popularized and freed from social taboo</a> by aggressive marketing campaigns and photo-shoots. So, why not hijab? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Perhaps the most important point, however, is not whether or not hijab can be normalized; it is whether or not such mainstreaming actually leads to more freedom. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the case of Muslima in increasingly hostile environments, such as the United States or any European state as of late, this freedom is being put to the test. Hijab or body-covering of any sort is increasingly becoming a marker of difference. With the rise of the populist Right, our societies are becoming more and more opposed to such difference. And the power of the masses has, historically, had something to say about women’s dress, women’s bodies, and, ultimately, women’s rights. For better or for worse.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Women’s heads have been the subject of political struggle for centuries. In this century, the forcible removal of hijab has corresponded with two trends, in particular: with Western influence in majority-Muslim countries or, as this summer’s burkini controversy demonstrated, with Western societies asserting nationalistic values and (patriarchal) identity. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;Freedom from&#8221; or &#8220;freedom to&#8221; are phrases associated with women’s behaviors, from dress to sexual activity to reproductive health, from France to Saudi Arabia. And we are often told to take a side: &#8220;Do you want women to be free from patriarchal oppression?&#8221; or &#8220;Do you want women to be free to wear whatever they choose?&#8221; </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But how does one think about the fight to wear hijab and the fight to be freed from hijab in one, unified thought? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Iran is a near perfect testament to such a thought. The country&#8217;s transition from Reza Shah Pahlavi to Ayatollah Khomeini provides an example of an apparent (and near perfect) paradox in practice.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the late 1920s in a still monarchical Iran, the Shah instituted what he called &#8220;a gradual process of hijab removal&#8221; from public institutions. The Shah’s friend and mentor, Turkey’s Mustafa Kemal Attatürk, espoused the view that head-covering reflected not only non-Western dress but non-Western thought. &#8220;Backwards women&#8221; stood for an undesirable social system, which extended into the confines of the home. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hijab was thus a stand-in or a symbol for the greater societal transformation each autocratic leader desired for the value system of his society. If Turkey and Iran were to join the rational, &#8220;enlightened&#8221; throngs of European history, in body and in mind, women had to remove their scarves.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Iran, in the period between these so-called modernization reforms and the Revolution, looked much like any other European country, with tanned youth in swimsuits smoking cigarettes on the beach, and Beatles records flying off the shelves. But in the late 1970s, frustration with the corrupt dictatorship of the Shah and the monarchy as a system of undemocratic government brought thousands of Iranian men and women out onto the streets. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the early days of 1979, secular and religious women alike protested for the right to ascribe to the value system of their choice. Whether Western or not, it was up to women to decide, not the Shah. </span></p>
<div id="attachment_4714" style="width: 510px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4714" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4714 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Iranian_Revolution_1979_marching_young_people.jpeg" alt="iranian_revolution_1979_marching_young_people" width="500" height="339" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Iranian_Revolution_1979_marching_young_people.jpeg 500w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Iranian_Revolution_1979_marching_young_people-300x203.jpeg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4714" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Wikimedia Commons</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As the revolution took a strident Islamic turn, women who did not wear hijab began to see the institution of the new state as a threat to their freedom of choice. Indeed, the &#8220;Islamic&#8221; in &#8220;Islamic Republic&#8221; now meant hijab, for all women. Iranian women were thus divided along ideological lines, and the new Islamic state was thus effective in reducing the voice and power of its most educated and mobile constituency: women.</span></p>
<p><iframe title="March 8, 1979 Iranian Women March Against Hijab and Islamic Laws" width="650" height="488" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/pxGYLk92edY?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With religious rule by Ayatollah Khomeini came moral rule in the homes and upon the bodies of women. Laws protecting women against the men of their family were eliminated. But as long as women were covered, they were able to obtain political office, attend university, and build a career. The hijab acted as a pass into the greater halls of society. It continues to act as the safeguard of a theocratic order, which exercises control while permitting necessary freedoms.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Iranian case is not so different from the European burkini fiasco last summer. The burkini &#8211; a full-body covering made of swimwear material, with an attached head covering like a swim cap &#8211; was banned in many French towns and cities for its subversion of secularist values. Women were to uphold the state’s belief in its own ideological abstention from religious practice in public life. Even while swimming. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The ban has since been <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-37198479">overturned at a federal level</a>, though some French municipalities claim that they will continue to enforce it. The mayor in the town where the ban made headlines, with police officers requiring a woman to remove her <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/08/28/world/europe/france-burkini-bikini-ban.html?_r=0">burkini on the beach</a>, called the ban an attempt to require &#8220;<a href="http://edition.cnn.com/2016/08/30/europe/french-mayor-cogolin-burkini-ban/">them to adopt our way of life.&#8221;</a> The &#8220;them&#8221; in this sentiment could be none other than Muslims, Europe&#8217;s favorite Other.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Liberal democracies, which respect the rights of minorities, demand pluralism &#8211; in lifestyle, in religious practice, in appearance, in ideology. Why does this pluralism extend only partially to women?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In France, the beach was briefly a battlefield. Muslim women were caught at the cross hairs of a power play between establishment norms and the liberty of choice that defines many arguments of cultural expression in other countries. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But the battlefield is an ideological one, surpassing the boundaries of nation and norms. It all comes down to the right to choose.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This is something women have been fighting for for centuries, from the ability to choose political leadership to the ability to choose a marital partner. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We can debate the merits behind the practice of the headscarf, its history in the Islamic world or even in the life of the prophet Muhammad, but what we should not debate is the ability of a woman to choose a practice, if it does no harm to her. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">France, in particular, makes the argument that the mere act of covering the body does harm to &#8220;the dignity and liberty&#8221; of said body. The issue of hijab is thus framed as one of protection, i.e. paternalism. A closer look at France’s relationship to identity politics and its systematic attempts to eliminate differences for the sake of the secular, homogeneous French state suggests that the protection enacted here is a fairly one-way street: There is &#8220;freedom from&#8221; but rarely &#8220;freedom to.&#8221;<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In Germany, a similar ban on head coverings for women exists. This ban is <a href="http://www.dw.com/en/can-muslim-women-wear-a-headscarf-at-work-in-germany/a-17953746">often a private and religious matter</a>, with church-based organizations or certain institutions able to decide when and if they will tolerate hijab. The attempts by school districts to ban headscarves in their teaching staff have been only partially successful, as German courts usually have the last word, overturning discriminatory practices, unless a specific legal conflict can be identified.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">German politicians have <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/08/19/germanys-potential-burqa-ban-has-a-problem-where-are-the-burqas/?utm_term=.947e281fb60a">also proposed a burqa ban</a>. The only problem is: hardly any women in Germany wear a burqa. Here, a moral stance is taken in preventing supposed harm before this harm could be said to occur. Ideology much? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Of course, the burqa is far from the burkini or the hijab. But it is no coincidence that the burqa ban discussion resurfaced and gained political momentum around the time of the burkini fiasco in France. Some European leaders may oppose France&#8217;s handling of the burkini on its beaches, but many have verbally and practically expressed their approval of policing Muslim women&#8217;s dress.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If one were to apply this&nbsp;logic of&nbsp;infringement of personal liberty to other arenas affecting the female body, one would end up with a long list of potential offenders, from beauty salons to botox offices to lingerie stores, where certain body parts are literally strapped down and constrained for the sake of smooth curvature. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;But these things make us feel good, make us feel pretty,&#8221; a French woman would likely respond. &#8220;And this is my right!&#8221;</span></p>
<div id="attachment_4715" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4715" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4715 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420-650x433.jpg" alt="berlin-bearbeitet-2014-420" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4715" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Type &#8220;hijab&#8221; into Pinterest and a fashion show will appear &#8211; women who use hijab as a way to present themselves in their way to the world. Stroll down the Turkish market at Berlin&#8217;s Maybachufer and you will encounter smiling groups of Muslima holding silk scarves up to their faces, matching patterns with dresses and jackets in mind, practicing new and different folds, depending on the material.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are wedding hijabs, hijabs for supermarket trips, and hijabs for dates, just as there are shoes for weddings, for nights out, or for lazy Saturdays.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hijab, like shoes, can make women feel good, because they make women feel pretty in a way that is also comfortable. It is both a lifestyle with religious and cultural roots and an identity mixed up with the many different conceptions humans have of beauty. Beauty: with all its socio-cultural baggage, the construct of forces beyond our individual minds and mirrors, forces that will always be a little bit oppressive but also a little bit fun, because they are familiar and somehow the product of our daily life within them. And this is their, our right.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As Trump ascends his throne to rule over the many who do not approve of or give license to his authoritarianism or assimilationist view of cultural differences, the hijab becomes one of those things that needs protection.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As Muslim refugees who choose to wear hijab become a lasting part of the societies of those European states that have taken them in, their right to be different must be defended. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Most importantly, we must defend the right of women to choose.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is this choice that makes women free. This is why feminism and hijab go together.</span></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>For more on the history of women in Iran, from hairstyles to political movements, see these sources: U.S. Institute of Peace&#8217;s <a href="http://iranprimer.usip.org/resource/womens-movement">Iran Primer: the Women&#8217;s Movement;</a> these pieces from a </em>New York Times<em>&nbsp;series &#8220;<a href="http://nytlive.nytimes.com/womenintheworld/2015/06/02/6-pervasive-misconceptions-about-iranian-women/">6 Pervasive Misconceptions about Iranian Women</a>&#8221; and &#8220;<a href="http://nytlive.nytimes.com/womenintheworld/2015/09/15/the-day-100000-iranian-women-protested-the-head-scarf/">The Day 100,000 Women Protested the Headscarf</a>&#8220;; this acclaimed book on the complexity of the Revolution: </em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Islamic-Utopian-Political-Biography-2000-06-03/dp/B019NRY9QG/ref=sr_1_3?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1480842551&amp;sr=1-3&amp;keywords=an+islamic+utopian+ali+shari%27ati">An Islamic Utopian: A Political Biography of Ali Shari&#8217;ati;</a><em> and the memoir, </em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/1400064708/?tag=thneyo0f-20">Iran Awakening</a><em>, by the Nobel-prize-winning activist Shirin Ebadi.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>And if you&#8217;re curious about women in hijab on the internet and in the fashion world, here are some people to watch: <a href="https://www.hautehijab.com/blogs/hijab-fashion">Haute Hijab</a> (U.S. fashion blogger with an entry titled &#8220;Embracing Our Identity in a Post 2016 Election World&#8221;), <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC_KQKeg7kNrlvrIXPnpwgEA">Dina Tokio</a> (U.K. vlogger and fashion designer), <a href="http://ww38.hipsterhijabis.com/about.html">Hipster Hijabis</a> (just what it sounds like), <a href="http://hanatajima.com/">Hana Tajima</a> (up-and-coming U.K. fashion designer), and <a href="http://hijablicious.com/">Hijablicious</a> (a site for &#8220;hijab with soul&#8221;).</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Women Only: The Frauenraum</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 15:42:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gender]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4385</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I'm at Rathaus Wilmersdorf, a former city hall building turned refugee home in Berlin, where I teach a literacy class once a week. The home initially opened its doors to 178 refugees in September 2015, following Merkel's famous "Wir schaffen das" ("We can do it") declaration that sidestepped the Dublin Regulation and opened up Germany's borders to thousands of asylum seekers.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4394 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-01-27 12.51.04" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>It&#8217;s Thursday at 10:55, and I&#8217;m running late. I rush up to the security guards and hand over my ID. <em>Helfer?</em> (&#8220;volunteer?&#8221;) they ask. <em>Ja</em>, I answer, and wait for them to scribble down my name and give me a number so I can sign out later. I thank them and head inside to the office to sign for the room keys and get my name tag. Then it&#8217;s through the foyer and up three floors to room 3092. When breakfast is running late, the right half of the stairwell is still filled by a neat line of people waiting for their turn in the cafeteria. I squeeze by, ruffling the hair of the kids I recognize.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m at Rathaus Wilmersdorf, a former city hall building turned refugee home in Berlin, where I teach a literacy class once a week. The home initially opened its doors to <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/berlin/bezirke/kudamm/notunterkunft-fuer-fluechtlinge-in-berlin-im-rathaus-wilmersdorf-fehlen-duschen-und-dolmetscher/12199798.html">178 refugees</a> in September 2015, following Merkel&#8217;s famous &#8220;Wir schaffen das&#8221; (&#8220;We can do it&#8221;) declaration that <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/germany/11821822/Germany-drops-EU-rules-to-allow-in-Syrian-refugees.html">sidestepped the Dublin Regulation</a> and opened up Germany&#8217;s borders to thousands of asylum seekers.</p>
<p>Today, over 1400 refugees live in the Rathaus &#8211; mostly from Syria, Afghanistan, and Iraq &#8211; and there is talk of opening up an adjacent building to house an additional 900. As is the case all over the city, this home simply wouldn&#8217;t function without the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/">on-going assistance of volunteers</a> who help out with everything from interpretation and teaching to administrative and kitchen support.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4456 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-01-08 10.34.54" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Over the past eight months, Rathaus Wilmersdorf has become somewhat of a success story as far as refugee accommodations in Berlin go. It&#8217;s been visited by President Joachim Gauck and American actor Ben Stiller, as well as received significant media praise for its leadership and facilities. <a href="http://www.morgenpost.de/berlin/article207089933/Vachroi-verabschiedet-sich-als-Heimleiter-in-Wilmersdorf.html">One article</a> listed off the home&#8217;s impressive amenities, which include medical and midwife services, a laundry room, a hair salon, an internet <span class="st">café</span>, and yes, even our literacy class.</p>
<p>The literacy class, or &#8220;AB class&#8221; as we call it, does go beyond what many other refugee homes in Berlin offer. But what the article&#8217;s authors fail to mention (and are likely unaware of), is that the course comes with a complicated backstory that is indicative of a larger debate surrounding refugees in Germany today.</p>
<p>It all started early this year, after one volunteer noticed that a group of women were not showing up for the German class offered on the home&#8217;s fourth floor. These women were mostly Afghan and the majority also illiterate. However, a bit of digging (and a heavy dose of interpretation) revealed that they weren&#8217;t avoiding the class because the level was too difficult, as originally suspected. They weren&#8217;t going because, in the fourth floor class, there were men present. Or depending on who tells the story, “Because their husbands wouldn’t let them”.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4600 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-05-19 12.43.22" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>The decision was therefore made to start a new class on the third floor, taught and attended exclusively by women. The class was to be an extension of the adjacent <em>Frauenraum</em> or &#8220;women&#8217;s room&#8221;. At Rathaus Wilmersdorf, the <em>Frauenraum</em> is a standing room open almost daily, so long as there are volunteers present. At the refugee home in former Tempelhof airport, the <em>Frauenraum</em> operates on a weekly project basis, led by a volunteer platform called <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">Give Something Back to Berlin</a>.</p>
<p>Regardless of the format, the concept remains the same: The <em>Frauenraum</em> is a safe place where women can be amongst themselves. In Rathaus Wilmersdorf, they sew, practice German, or just hang out and have a cup of tea. Small children are allowed, but men are forbidden from entering. We&#8217;ve even had to throw out a male journalist on occasion. The home&#8217;s former director described it as a place where &#8220;<a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/berlin/warum-thomas-de-vachroi-der-perfekte-aufbauhelfer-fuer-fluechtlingsheime-ist-23775578">female residents are enjoying their freedom and unveiling themselves.</a>&#8221; I can only assume he meant this both literally and figuratively, as not all the women wear headscarves, but some who do do indeed take them off when in the <em>Frauenraum</em> or during class.</p>
<p>I fell into the role of literacy teacher by way of the <em>Frauenraum</em>, where I started volunteering in January. The class was already up and running but they wanted to offer it on more days and were having trouble finding willing teachers. Other <em>Frauenraum</em> volunteers, I was told, had flatly refused to teach out of principle, scoffing at the idea that a separate class be created when there was a perfectly good one already on offer. This is Germany, after all, a country where men and women are presumably equal and interact on all levels of society. If the husbands had a problem with that, tough. Isn&#8217;t it in the best interest of these women that we integrate them into our way of life as quickly as possible?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4460 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-05-12 11.42.50" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>These days, it is difficult to have a discussion in Germany about refugees that doesn&#8217;t include a question about gender. <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/02/08/not-our-women-from-cologne-to-berlin/">Post-Cologne</a>, it is near impossible. Despite the fact that the attacks on New Year&#8217;s Eve were carried out by a more diverse group than originally portrayed in the media, that night&#8217;s unfortunate events have marked a turning point in attitudes towards refugees.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.focus.de/politik/deutschland/zdf-umfrage-offenbart-so-haben-die-silvester-uebergriffe-beeinflusst-was-deutsche-ueber-fluechtlinge-denken_id_5213962.html">One poll</a> showed that, between December 2015 and January 2016 alone, the number of Germans who felt the country couldn&#8217;t handle the influx of refugees rose from 46% to 60%. Thirty-three percent stated that Cologne had &#8220;fundamentally changed&#8221; their opinions about refugees. And the ring-wing <span class="st"><em>Alternative für Deutschland</em></span> (AfD) party, which initially emerged in opposition to the euro, has placed anti-refugee sentiment at the core of their increasingly popular platform. Their leader has controversially <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/alternative-for-germany-shows-its-true-right-wing-colors-a-1076259.html">called for the use of firearms against incoming refugees</a>.</p>
<p>This is the same country that was at the forefront of Europe&#8217;s refugee response only nine months ago. The same country that led the continent&#8217;s discourse on establishing a common European solution. The same country that initiated what became globally lauded as <em>Wilkommenskultur</em> (welcome culture).</p>
<p>So, what&#8217;s changed?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4401 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-650x650.jpg" alt="2016-02-10 11.59.46" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-300x300.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>When the “refugee crisis” hit Germany last summer, hundreds of residents felt compelled to slather butter on rolls and pass them out to refugees arriving at train stations. This was by all accounts heart-warming and admirable, but it was also the easy part. The conversation we are having now is a more complicated one, one that even the seemingly simple question of whether to offer a female-only literacy class echoes:</p>
<p>What happens next and how might our society change as a result?</p>
<p>One could blame Cologne, but the foundation for this confrontation was laid long before. A staggering <a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article147280667/Fuer-die-meisten-gehoert-der-Islam-nicht-zu-Deutschland.html">60% of the country</a> is of the opinion that Islam does not belong in Germany. (It is also worth noting that Germans consistently overestimate the number of Muslims living in the country. The real figure, while one of the highest in the EU, <a href="http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2015/11/17/5-facts-about-the-muslim-population-in-europe/">is still only 5.8%</a>.)</p>
<p>There is an underlying preconception in Germany, as in many Western countries, that Islam is synonymous with misogyny and a lack of female rights. That “<a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article149756193/Wie-Sumtes-Wutbuerger-lernten-Fluechtlinge-zu-lieben.html">according to their religion, women are nothing</a>” or even more extreme, that &#8220;<a href="http://www.vice.com/de/read/fluechtlinge-vergewaltigen-deutsche-kinder-wie-rassisten-versuchen-stimmung-gegen-alle-nicht-deutschen-zu-machen-775">these young men will come and rape our daughters</a>&#8220;. This preconception likely stems from a variety of factors: images we see in the media, politicians portraying Muslims as backward or extremist, or current conflicts within the Middle East. An argument heard less often is made by <a href="http://ideas.time.com/2013/11/01/do-muslim-women-need-saving/">Columbia University Professor Lila Abu-Lughod</a>, who explores the conflation of religion and socioeconomic status. Gender inequality within Muslim majority societies stems mainly from economic inequality, and migrants in Germany have traditionally been low-skilled. Therefore what we may label as clashes due to religion may have stronger roots in poverty and lack of opportunity.</p>
<p>Earlier this year in Berlin, <a href="http://www.rbb-online.de/politik/beitrag/2016/04/berlin-kopftuch-streit-vor-arbeitsgericht-keine-guetliche-einigung.html">a young teacher went to court</a> because she was denied a teaching post due to her headscarf (the case was thrown out on grounds of the state&#8217;s Neutrality Act). More recently in Switzerland, a <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-36382596">regional authority ruled</a> that two teenage brothers must shake the hands of their female teachers despite it being against their religious beliefs to touch women they are not related to. Traditionally receiving societies such as Germany are perpetually learning how to manage integration in the face of growing diversity. Unfortunately, we seem insistent on concentrating on how &#8220;their values&#8221; may threaten &#8220;ours&#8221;, rather than on what type of society we want to live in together.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4406 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-02-17 12.07.15" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>To be fair, my own engagement at the Rathaus has not come without challenges. On my first day teaching, I swallowed a lot of frustration as another volunteer and I watched the women turn to their husbands for approval before following us to class. <em>Nur Frauen</em> (&#8220;only women&#8221;), we tried to communicate to the more skeptical looking of the men with a smile, while I stifled the urge to roll my eyes.</p>
<p>We&#8217;ve also heard a host of disturbing stories by way of the interpreters. Rape, abuse, threats of divorce. Some stories are from Afghanistan while others allegedly took place here in Berlin. At times, I am ashamed to find myself relieved that I can&#8217;t talk to the women directly about what I&#8217;ve heard, for fear it might affect the way I interact with them. For now, our exchanges are limited to topics like telling time and types of fruit &#8211; they&#8217;re big fans of banana and pineapple &#8211; as well as the apparently always shocking and never boring topic of me being a 30 year old woman without a husband or children (some of my students have 6, 7, even 9 children).</p>
<p>But until we&#8217;re able to have those more in-depth conversations, I remain convinced that offering a class under imperfect circumstances is better than offering no women&#8217;s class at all. For what, I&#8217;ve asked myself, will give these women more independence than the ability to navigate the city on their own? And what will give them a better chance of being able to navigate the city on their own than the ability to read and write?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4405 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-04-20 10.14.53" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Nothing exhibited this more clearly to me than a few weeks ago, when we held an arts project week for our women. The week consisted of two trips to separate parks so they could learn about various plant types and practice drawing them. The excitement of the women was palpable. They got to have a Middle Eastern picnic, a real treat after months of bland cafeteria fare. They got to pick flowers in the woods to take back to the home. There was laughing, there was dancing, and there were so many selfies.</p>
<p>We later found out through interpreters that, for several of the women, it was their first time in a park without a husband or male relative.</p>
<p>At the end of the week, a local artist took the womens&#8217; drawings and stenciled them onto power boxes near the Rathaus. On the Friday, we took a stroll around the neighborhood together to see them for the first time. The Farsi-speaking volunteer asked the women to point out their drawings and explain why they chose to draw them specifically. &#8220;Who drew this?&#8221; she asked when we got to the second box, pointing to a beautiful palm tree. &#8220;Me,&#8221; answered one of our students, &#8220;I drew it because it reminds me of home. And if you cut off the head, the whole plant dies.&#8221;</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The Frauenraum at Rathaus Wilmersdorf is looking for volunteers. To get involved, sign up at https://volunteer-planner.org/.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>For another take on the headscarf, I recommend watching <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/video/2015/jun/24/hijab-not-oppression-feminist-statement-video">this Guardian video</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>All photos my own.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: &#8220;I&#8217;m a Human Being&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 11:21:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Austria]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[family]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Taiwan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vienna]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4019</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Vienna. Seat of the former Austro-Hungarian Empire. Widely considered the gateway to Eastern Europe. Home to a United Nations headquarters and numerous international companies and universities. The Austrian capital has long been a city of immigration – even when politics have told a different story – and a staggering 50% of the population has what’s referred to as a “migration background”. So it’s not as if I expected Vienna to not be multicultural...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_4028" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4028" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4028 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-650x581.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender" width="650" height="581" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-650x581.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-300x268.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender.jpg 728w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4028" class="wp-caption-text">Sophia, Christina, and Suzi at the 2015 Vienna Pride Parade</p></div>
<p>Vienna. Seat of the former Austro-Hungarian Empire. Widely considered the gateway to Eastern Europe. Home to a United Nations headquarters and numerous international companies and universities. The Austrian capital has long been a city of immigration – even when politics have told a different story – and a staggering <a href="https://www.wien.gv.at/english/social/integration/basic-work/facts-figures.html">50% of the population</a> has what’s referred to as a “migration background”.</p>
<p>So it’s not as if I expected Vienna to <em>not</em> be multicultural.</p>
<p>What I didn’t expect when <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/03/23/lens-on-leaving-homes/">moving to Vienna from Berlin</a> was to encounter some of the most fascinating “mixes” of my life: A half-Indian, half-Italian who grew up in the US and lives in Vienna with her half-Austrian, half-French boyfriend? A Chinese-American who fell in love with her German boyfriend in Hong Kong? A half-Austrian, half-Sicilian who met her Indian husband in London? The combinations are unexpected, beautiful, and dare I say, collidoscopic? (And their potential future children even more so).</p>
<div id="attachment_4031" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4031" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4031 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-650x475.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(3)" width="650" height="475" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-650x475.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-300x219.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4031" class="wp-caption-text">Christina poses with a cow in Austria on a family roadtrip</p></div>
<p>Christina, the first close friend I made in Vienna, is no different. Born in Taiwan to a Taiwanese mother and Austrian father, at age three her family moved to San Jose, California, where her younger brother was born. Kindergarten was spent in Vienna, where she lived with her father and grandparents while mom and brother stayed in the US. At age six the entire family moved to Taiwan for four years. Then it was back west to Seattle from ages 10-16 where Christina spent the longest stretch of her childhood, what she calls her &#8220;most formative years&#8221;. Her last two years of high school were completed in Taipei, where she graduated with the globally recognized International Baccalaureate Diploma.</p>
<p>“I was missing roots as a kid, our family was always bouncing around,&#8221; she tells me.</p>
<p>This triangular ping ponging between nations resulted in three different passport combinations within a family of four: Christina’s brother, born in the US, is a dual Austrian-American citizen but “avoids Austria now because of the mandatory military service.” Mom is dual Taiwanese-Austrian, “but never felt completely comfortable in Austria”. And Christina and her father are purely Austrian, on paper anyway.</p>
<p>&#8220;A long time ago my dad had the chance to become an American citizen but decided against it,&#8221; she says smirking, &#8220;He&#8217;s a proud Austrian.”</p>
<div id="attachment_4057" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4057" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4057 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_9365" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4057" class="wp-caption-text">Christina with her parents in Taiwan</p></div>
<p>It is to her father and his “pride” that Christina attributes her last 16 years in Vienna. &#8220;My dream was to go to Georgetown [University],&#8221; Christina tells me one warm evening in the <em>Museumsquartier</em>, her fingers tapping the stem of her <em>Hugospritz</em>. &#8220;I applied and got in… my mom supported it, but my dad kept saying I had to go to university in Austria. It was always really important to him that, as the oldest child, I embrace my Austrian roots.&#8221;</p>
<p>Christina ended up moving to Vienna against her will: “I didn&#8217;t have any connection to Austria at that time other than having spent the occasional summer there with my grandparents.” The first year, she expressed her anger by skipping class in favor of exploring the city and having fun.</p>
<p>“And then I got pregnant,” she says laughing, “the biggest rebellion of all!”</p>
<div id="attachment_4059" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4059" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4059 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371-650x650.jpg" alt="IMG_9371" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4059" class="wp-caption-text">Mother-daughter surfing trip in Morocco</p></div>
<p>Christina’s daughter Illeana (Illy) was born when she was 20. She raised Illy as a single mother while completing her degrees in Economics and Sinology, with “lots of help” from friends with similar bi-cultural backgrounds. She counts half-Austrian friends from South Africa and Bolivia among her closest, along with a half-Kosovan, half-Czech hair salon owner named Suzi. “None of us knew what we were doing… it was experimental parenting. I think if I raised a child now I’d be much more nervous!”</p>
<p>After making it over the hump of her first year, Vienna started to feel like home. “I began to realize how much I love it here,” Christina reflects. Now one could say Christina is as Austrian as they come. Her German is flawless and chock full of colloquialisms, she sings along to Austrian <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schlager_music">Schlager</a></em>, and her drink of choice is the ubiquitous <em><a href="http://austrianwineusa.com/2013/12/20/12-days-of-austrian-wine-enjoy-a-gspritzer/">Weisser Spritzer</a></em>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4064" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4064" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4064 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-650x602.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(7)" width="650" height="602" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-650x602.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-300x278.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7.jpg 701w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4064" class="wp-caption-text">Christina skiing in Kaprun, Austria</p></div>
<p>None of that, however, stops her from craving Taiwanese ‘Three-Cups Chicken’ or her favorite American cereal, ‘Lucky Charms’. “I’m biracial and tri-cultural,” she states without hesitation. And while rewarding on personal and professional levels (she’s also fluent in Mandarin), Christina’s background has not gone unchallenged in a city that still struggles to see itself as a place of migration and diversity.</p>
<p>Christina has encountered countless variations of the “<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/">But where are you <em>really</em> from?</a>” question over the years. “When I first got to Vienna, there were fewer minorities and diversity didn&#8217;t work very well,” she remarks, “I remember meeting one guy who could not comprehend why I looked the way I did but had a very common German last name,&#8221; she rolls her eyes at the memory. &#8220;I literally had to spell it out for him by saying, &#8216;If you, an Austrian, had a baby with a Taiwanese woman, the result would be me!’”</p>
<div id="attachment_4034" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4034" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4034 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-650x488.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(6)" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4034" class="wp-caption-text">Christina&#8217;s 3rd Birthday in Los Angeles, California</p></div>
<p>This phenomenon isn’t limited to Vienna. In Japan, a newly crowned biracial beauty queen has been fielding questions on a regular basis about what parts of her are “Japanese”. <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/30/world/asia/biracial-beauty-queen-strives-for-change-in-mono-ethnic-japan.html">“But I am a Japanese,”</a> is her response. On the other side of the world, in the US, Rachel Dolezal was recently exposed for her elaborate deception as a Black woman – a &#8220;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/18/opinion/charles-blow-the-delusions-of-dolezal.html?smid=fb-share">one-directional privilege</a>&#8221; that could never have been successful the other way around, due to socially constructed perceptions of race. The recurring theme? If you are one drop of minority, we will question your Belonging to the majority.</p>
<p>Christina acknowledges that even she is not immune to societal attitudes about migrants in Austria. &#8220;I&#8217;ve learned that, in Austria, migrants get classified into &#8216;good&#8217; and &#8216;bad&#8217;,&#8221; she explains.</p>
<p>&#8220;Asians are considered ‘good’ because they’re quiet, stay out of trouble, and work hard. Turkish people are unpopular because a lot of them refuse to adapt to the Austrian way of life and bring hordes of family members over, all the while claiming benefits from the Austrian government. Blacks have it the worst, though, probably because they stand out the most and are still viewed by many locals as low-lifes and drug dealers.&#8221;</p>
<div id="attachment_4029" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4029" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4029 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-650x472.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(1)" width="650" height="472" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-650x472.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-300x218.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4029" class="wp-caption-text">Christina riding a (fake) bull at Glacier National Park, Montana</p></div>
<p>While Christina is well aware that the US has its own challenges regarding diversity, she does view it as more progressive: “In the US, people at least get it when you tell them that you&#8217;re biracial.”</p>
<p>It was 1999 when Christina was last in the US, before Illy&#8217;s birth and before the 9/11 attacks. While she’s now seriously considering a move back, it&#8217;s unclear when she will be able to. Christina is not a US citizen and needs a green card. Her most recent attempt at the <a href="http://travel.state.gov/content/visas/english/immigrate/diversity-visa/instructions.html">Diversity Visa Lottery</a> was unsuccessful. “My dad told me he is reconsidering becoming an American citizen just so that he can help get us over there,” Christina recently shared. <a href="http://www.migrationpolicy.org/article/family-reunification">Family reunification</a> is one of the four major pathways for foreigners to become legal residents of the US.</p>
<p>Legal challenges are also not Christina’s only concern. “Sometimes I worry that people in the US will annoy me with their ignorance,” she says laughing. At the same time, she is drawn to the lifestyle. She observes her American friends move to houses with pools, which, compared to Viennese city apartments, seem like mansions. Illy, a recovering Justin Bieber addict who recently graduated to a One Direction obsession, is thrilled with the prospect. “A typical Austrian teenager,” Christina chuckles.</p>
<p>You could call Christina many things: A transnational, an immigrant, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">a third-culture kid</a>, a foreigner, a native, an expat. But none of these categories really fit given the fluidity of her upbringing and identity. We use labels to establish connections and try to make sense of things, but they can also dilute the intricacy and beauty of reality.</p>
<p>&#8220;I&#8217;m not 100% of anything,&#8221; is how Christina describes it. &#8220;Sometimes when people ask what I am, I just answer that I&#8217;m a human being.&#8221;</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Photos provided by Christina and Sophia.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Circumcision at the Jewish Museum Berlin</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/12/05/review-circumcision-jewish-museum-berlin/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2014 13:14:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Judaism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3532</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Circumcision has a history of being used to make distinctions between 'us' and 'them', particularly in Germany. In the United States the debate on foreskin or no-foreskin looks much different, citing hygiene rather than religious freedom. This begs the question if arguments against a religious practice, such as the one raised in the German context, can ever be purely about legal arguments - for the rights of children, as German courts have decreed - when strong divisions between those of Christian heritage and those of Muslim and/or Jewish heritage remain. This question was the inspiration for the newest exhibition at the Jewish Museum Berlin, a timely one, at that...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Circumcision has a long history of enabling Othering processes, i.e. society defining itself on the basis of what it is not. According the Duke anthropologist <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/william-m-obarr/celebrating-circumcision_1_b_1902275.html">William O’Barr</a>, the absence of circumcision in Michelangelo’s famous <em>David</em> exemplifies this bit: Despite David’s well-known Jewish roots, let alone his place as a key protagonist in the Jewish scriptural tradition, his foreskin remains seemingly intact; this David seems more Florentine, more like the dominant Europeans at the time, than Jewish.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/books/2011/jul/29/david-mary-hoffman-review"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3537" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/David-Michelangelo-007.jpg" alt="David Michelangelo" width="487" height="293" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/David-Michelangelo-007.jpg 459w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/David-Michelangelo-007-300x180.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 487px) 100vw, 487px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Michelangelo likely had little experience with circumcision, given that this practice was historically reserved for the Jewish minority. The lack of foreskin thus served as a point from which the fringe of majority culture could be measured. Most Europeans at the time were simply <em>not </em>circumcised.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">In Germany, circumcision is still a practice attributed to members of the Jewish and Islamic traditions. Given Germany&#8217;s immigration history, the practice also serves largely to distinguish more recent immigrants from your German with either Catholic or Protestant roots. In kind, the debate as to the legality and humanity of the removal of a child&#8217;s foreskin has taken on an us vs. them quality. The discussion has also tended to position &#8216;reason and modernity&#8217; against &#8216;antiquated tradition&#8217;, as this<a href="http://www.taz.de/!98008/"> interview</a> with a German Green Party member indicates (a party, which gave strong support to legislation banning the practice among infants and young children). Just two years ago, a Cologne court ruled against the circumcision of youngsters. The decision was presented as an act in favor of the human rights of children &#8211; this logic continues to dominate.</p>
<p>In the United States, approx. 79% of men are circumcised, <a href="http://www.cdc.gov/hiv/pdf/prevention_research_malecircumcision.pdf">according to the Center for Disease Control</a>. Many of these men do not belong to religious traditions that prescribe the practice; I doubt many parents would cite compliance with God&#8217;s covenant as the reason for their son’s procedure. Since its introduction during WWII as a matter of (presumed) <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2788411/">hygiene</a>, it never had time to become a pronounced public marker of difference.</p>
<div id="attachment_3565" style="width: 541px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://www.guggenheim.org/new-york/collections/collection-online/artwork/3478"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3565" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3565 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/circumcision-january1.jpg" alt="circumcision-january pollock" width="531" height="450" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/circumcision-january1.jpg 531w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/circumcision-january1-300x254.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 531px) 100vw, 531px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3565" class="wp-caption-text">Jackson Pollock 1946, &#8220;Circumcision&#8221;</p></div>
<p>But even in the United States, the practice has more recently come under a critical knife, though more medical than cultural, as a recent <em>Atlantic </em><a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2014/12/foreskin-keep-or-cut/383362/">article</a> on the subject illustrates. The more contemporary critique in the United States seems to be little more than an attempt to re-evaluate the merits of bodily modification, without going so far as to refer to this practice as &#8216;mutilation&#8217; on the part of fundamentalist religions.</p>
<p>Given this background, the importance of context is undeniable in evaluating the discourse on circumcision from one place to another. In other words, the &#8216;who&#8217;s who&#8217; in <em>beschnitten</em> vs. <em>unbeschnitten</em> may say much more about the state of society (and its latent tensions) than medical-ethical arguments against the practice immediately reveal. This begs the question if arguments against a religious practice, such as this one, can ever be purely about the rights of children, as German courts have decreed and German politicians argued. This question and the delicate history from which it emerges were the inspiration for the newest exhibition at the <a href="http://www.jmberlin.de/main/EN/homepage-EN.php">Jewish Museum Berlin</a> – an institution known for <a href="http://www.jmberlin.de/main/EN/03b-Academy/04-Academy-Programs/00-academy-programs.php">programming</a> on inclusion/diversity topics that extends beyond the docket of Jewish history and culture.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Haut-Ab.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-3569 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Haut-Ab.jpg" alt="Haut Ab" width="330" height="374" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Haut-Ab.jpg 330w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Haut-Ab-264x300.jpg 264w" sizes="(max-width: 330px) 100vw, 330px" /></a></p>
<p>The exhibit, &#8220;<a href="http://www.jmberlin.de/main/DE/01-Ausstellungen/02-Sonderaustellungen/2014/brit-mila.php">Haut ab!</a>&#8221; or &#8220;<a href="http://www.jmberlin.de/main/EN/01-Exhibitions/02-Special-Exhibitions/2014/brit-milah.php">Snip it!</a>&#8220;, opened a little more than one month ago. Days before the exhibit’s scheduled reveal, I had the opportunity to take part in a preview for bloggers and tweeters. Our tour guide was the exhibition’s co-curator, an expert in Judaica. In addition to the objects&#8217; historical significance, her comments revealed a recognition of the tightly-stretched contemporary fabric upon which the exhibit rests. The careful placement of artifacts, soundbites, and images transmits a similar message of a need to explain and take stock of a (perhaps unnecessarily) tension-filled topic, in light and because of history.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3539 size-large aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004-650x365.jpg" alt="WP_20141022_004" width="650" height="365" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004-650x365.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Entering through the exhibit&#8217;s initial darkened spaces &#8211; final preparations being made, lighting not quite right &#8211; a historical narrative of a religion&#8217;s genesis and later adaptations in diaspora forms a quilt of impressions. The next rooms give way to the ritual&#8217;s place in Islam and the stark move from Christianity&#8217;s embrace of old Jewish tradition &#8211; as being sacredly tied to the life and times of Jesus &#8211; to artists&#8217; depictions of Othered violence, even savagery, against children. Juxtaposed with a historical development are artifacts from the Islamic ceremony in which a young boy is inducted into a long Muslim lineage. For all Berliners, the following image is a familiar one: costumes for a &#8216;little prince&#8217;, complete with scepter and golden cap. But how many recognize this as part of a fundamental <em>rite de passage, </em>the commanded removal of foreskin? Images of the sons of German guest workers in the 1970s, little princes in-waiting, place the practice further back in German heritage than the media tends to convey. As Germany&#8217;s immigration history indicates, circumcision is nothing new. But this photograph of an eager little boy could have been taken last week, swimming in a hat much too big among a happy mass of friends and family.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3558 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016-650x365.jpg" alt="WP_20141022_016" width="650" height="365" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016-650x365.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>The final room of the exhibit greets visitors with an interactive arrangement of outside discourses on circumcision, clips taken primarily from American television. Images and audio insert diverse perspectives into what our guide calls &#8216;the polemical German frame&#8217;. Familiar cartoons and sitcoms cast blue light onto the carpeted floor. Scenes from South Park, Judge Judy. As we exit, a final work, the oeuvre of commentary, salutes its visitors: three figures, bodies identical, if not for the flags draped over three sets of genitalia.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-3557 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021-365x650.jpg" alt="WP_20141022_021" width="350" height="623" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021-365x650.jpg 365w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021-168x300.jpg 168w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021.jpg 366w" sizes="(max-width: 350px) 100vw, 350px" /></a></p>
<p>One could make the case that circumcision in Germany is more a stand-in for society&#8217;s difficult grappling with religious difference and demographic change. Perhaps more background is needed to do so, however. So to be more specific, as a <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/politik/deutschland/studie-belegt-grosse-vorbehalte-gegenueber-muslimen-a-1006332.html">recent study</a> by the <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/en/welcome/">Berlin Institute for Empirical Migration and Integration Research</a> indicates, a majority of Germans polled continue to see Islam as un-German &#8211; this despite the approx. 5+ million Muslims who have made Germany their home. To complicate things, Germany is one of the most secular countries in Europe, with most of its residents of so-called Christian heritage bearing little association to either church or faith in their daily lives. There is also a history of a certain institutional religiosity despite public secularism: for example, the prominence of the CDU Party (Christian Democratic Union) and the obligatory church-tax to Protestant or Catholic churches, even synagogues, while blatantly excluding Muslim houses of prayer.</p>
<p>As this new exhibit at the Jewish Museum Berlin demonstrates, circumcision in Germany is complicated, deeply embedded in <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/28/world-cup-fever-how-malleable-is-german-identity/">the question of German identity</a> and the norms that demarcate such a thing. I wonder, though, if the constant discussion serves only to create scandal out of culture. For where is Othered difference, when there is no longer spectacle?</p>
<p>&#8220;Snip it&#8221;/&#8221;Haut ab&#8221; at the Jewish Museum Berlin runs until March 1. It&#8217;s worth a visit.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>All images are linked to original source or were otherwise taken by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: London and other transplants</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/09/29/beyond-berlin-london-and-other-transplants/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/09/29/beyond-berlin-london-and-other-transplants/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 15:22:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ex-pat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[London]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3278</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This past week, I visited my good friend D who, like me, is an American transplant. D lives in East London, where the corner store owner greets you in an upbeat banter and the sign to a ‘Carolina Fried Chicken’ joint dances in the light from the neighboring gastropub. Multicultural, maybe. But London’s multiculturalism has a few faces and facades. And, in the end, it’s the people that matter more than the cultural installation: So, who is actually 'making' it here?...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This past week, I visited my good friend D who, like me, is an American transplant*. We have similar trajectories and political ponderings, though his roots lie far from mine in the American Deep South (here’s a <a href="http://www.orionmagazine.org/index.php/place_where_you_live/view/chunky_mississippi_7753/">beautiful piece</a> he wrote about his home in Mississippi). D now lives in East London, where the corner store owner greets you in an upbeat banter and the sign to a ‘Carolina Fried Chicken’ joint dances in the light from the neighboring gastropub. Multicultural, maybe. But London’s multiculturalism has a few faces and facades. And, in the end, it’s the people that matter more than the cultural installation.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1031-e1413145767969.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3351 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1031-e1413145767969.jpg" alt="img_1031-e1413145767969" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1031-e1413145767969.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1031-e1413145767969-300x199.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>My first night in London, over pints at a very hip and haptic microbrewery – the tables grainy and splitting with moisture – D and I discuss our common struggles: We chat about how so-called experiences ‘abroad’ are, in the end, defined by labor market restrictions and the particular brand of our passport. Three years ago I would have insisted that these things are fluid. But even with a class degree from a class English university, a work allowance is hard to come by if not impossible in an academic job market already squeezed by its nationals, he shares. I can only nod, my plunge into the newest Berlin job search looming at the edge of my half-empty pint.</p>
<p>Berlin, like London, is full of transplants, both temporary and permanent. Why so many? For the case of my friend D and me, why did we, in particular, take these leaps? Why do so many of our generation (and even those generations before us) move to cities in countries we have no <i>de facto</i> right to be in? Across the ocean, <i>jus soli</i>, <i>jus sanguinus</i>, <i>jus</i> whatever does, indeed, determine much of what is possible.</p>
<p>The U.K, though London, in particular, invites dreams and dreamers. Multiculturalism results, in part, from the diversity of all those who believe in possibility; immigrants churn up new identities and make places we feel right to inhabit. In the case of Americans in London, maybe it’s the common language, the similar sarcastic humor, or the attachment to butter-heavy things like pie and cookies, but it just makes sense to come here.</p>
<p>In D’s apartment, a short assemblage of brick and concrete in the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London_Borough_of_Hackney">Hackney neighborhood</a>, I meet a few other fellow Americans. In many words, we all speak of the hurdles one must leap (in stride) for the right to not only remain but to earn an income at that, to really participate in a place one might co-construct but for which legal rights are lacking. One of them, a recent graduate of the London School of Economics, is tirelessly working to bend a clause or make a rule that will allow him to stay. There is a sense of marathon-running in the air, trying and trying until you can’t try anymore. Particularly palpable in a generation used to succeeding at most things, or told it is possible anyway.</p>
<p>But sometimes, it just doesn’t work out, at least temporarily, and many of those who come have to return to the places they left behind. But D seems optimistic.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/dylan_3.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3350 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/dylan_3-464x650.jpg" alt="dylan_3" width="464" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/dylan_3.jpg 464w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/dylan_3-214x300.jpg 214w" sizes="(max-width: 464px) 100vw, 464px" /></a></p>
<p>This matters because cities like London and Berlin actively foster the transplant spirit, but this doesn’t mean that these places work to sustain it. According to recent research <a href="http://books.google.de/books?id=Cy7FAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PR2&amp;lpg=PR2&amp;dq=%22migrants+or+expatriates+americans+in+europe%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=bX6_r-fwO2&amp;sig=4Si_8b_0M8yuiU9Ti6hBkJ_Ijs8&amp;hl=de&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=M8IqVJW1IsbWPZzygOAN&amp;ved=0CEYQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">on so-called American expatriates in Europe</a>, many transplants struggle for years at poorly paid jobs that are taken just to remain in the country. In Berlin, nearly half are underemployed and another third report contract-to-contract work (hustling, in other words). And yet, despite difficulties, many stay, which may be part financial, the costs of rehabilitating a life somewhere else, for example, and part mythical, i.e. what it means to constantly imagine future potential, then find it too difficult to forgo what might have been.</p>
<p>In any case, staying has a lot to do with the appearance of things. For how much of the transplant culture results from what one sees or experiences upon arriving, regardless of the actual rules of the game, even in spite of real barriers to inclusion? Put simply, if I see other Americans making it, or just a plethora of other nationalities making it, is it wrong to think I’ll make it?</p>
<p>Of course, the particular brand of passport produces a variety of experiences, but very few of us have a free-pass (excluding what D jokingly refers to as ‘fake Americans’ in London who legally remain in the country under an inherited European passport). Now, sitting in D’s kitchen with a liter of freshly brewed coffee (not tea), he tells me another story, one of a good friend’s predicament – an EU citizen, married to a Mexican national. In short, the immigration authorities of the U.K. have decided that the couple fails to meet requirements for residency in London, he tells me. Mexico is a country not seen favorably for transplantation; a hierarchy of acceptable migrants certainly does exist. But this all feels strangely hypothetical – this game of planning a life beyond borders, making moves and readying oneself for the counter. It is a lesson in rectifying a roster of rules with a vibrant diversity suggestive of more flexibility, more fluidity, than might be the case.</p>
<p>We leave the apartment and its conversation for a walk. Outside, it’s humid but pleasant, and the streets of D’s neighborhood are bursting with an eclecticism even beyond what the NY Times recently featured in ‘<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/04/29/travel/36-hours-in-east-london.html">36 hours in East London</a>‘ (as if the region needed its own holiday, apart from the financial men and women in suits of central London or the manicured streets of the West). Here, social housing projects tower above quaint town homes, neighbors trimming their rose bushes, bass piling out of a high window onto a long set of shears. Just down the road, one of London’s most bubbling food bazaars – a foodie’s scene of cultural consumption – is in full swing. Broadway Market: where German sausages, and meat pies, and lox bagels, and Persian kebab, and samosas, and ramen-to-go find frequent (young) patrons. We both delight in the anything-but-discordant multilingualism this variety yields.</p>
<p>In a pod of food carts just blocks from the market’s main drag, I find the best burrito I’ve had outside of the Western United States – a man with an air of L.A. dishing up marinated legumes, sauces streaming out of all sides of the tortilla like a blessing. A neighboring kiosk serves up what they call Filipino wraps (pork belly, assorted greens, tangy sauce), D’s favorite. As I walk to peruse other flavors, D shares his visa predicament with the owner of the wraps, explaining that this sandwich will be his last after a year of patronage. The owner offers to sponsor his visa, chuckling but serious, D tells me. Maybe he should take him up on his offer we joke, meaning it. D smiles.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/pork-belly.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3349" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/pork-belly-488x650.jpg" alt="pork-belly" width="400" height="532" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/pork-belly-488x650.jpg 488w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/pork-belly-225x300.jpg 225w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/pork-belly.jpg 489w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a></p>
<p>It’s easy to feel welcomed here.</p>
<p>Far away from East London, I find myself in the kitchen of a German transplant on the ground floor of an elderly but charming home in a neighborhood near Kensington.  From my luggage I unload mustard I’ve carted across the channel, tubes I was almost not allowed to take onto the plane. <i>You just can’t find this here</i>, my host says, that certain spicy mustard.</p>
<p>Her friends are all from somewhere else, she shares, <i>but the problem with transplants is that they all leave eventually, and then, all of a sudden, you don’t have any friends</i>. She is slowly rebuilding the circle, <i>but it’s hard</i>, she tells me, <i>when everyone is from somewhere else.</i></p>
<p>As we leave the far West neighborhood, its quiet lanes juxtaposed with newer blocks of community housing and industrial outgrowth, we pass an office for remittances – transplants from East Africa sending their earnings back ‘home’. Even here, some people are making it.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wp_20140919_001.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3347 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wp_20140919_001.jpg" alt="wp_20140919_001" width="640" height="360" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wp_20140919_001.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wp_20140919_001-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wp_20140919_001-310x174.jpg 310w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>My last day in London, my travel companion and I board a train to Brick Lane, snaking above a meat market, halal lambs hanging like carpets and voices rising up into numbers. Brick Lane, a curated experience of all that London attracts, the object of film, book, and tourism, is the sharpened edge of the city’s sale of eclecticism. It is a blend of curry houses and backdoor sweets shops for tourists and locals alike; it is the contrast between posh chocolatiers and wholesale textile vendors or between grunge coffee houses and chic boutiques. But it is not what is seen here that inspires but what is implied: that this – reproduction of home, community-making in memory – is possible. Even if it always isn’t.</p>
<p>After another burrito, this time seasoned with garam masala, we chat with an artist crafting overt social commentary, something he calls ‘the Prejudice Project’. With a long beard and dark eyes, he has likely faced that which his project targets. His bright smile opens up to pure optimism as we discuss diversity politics, however. But things can be difficult, indeed: In London, it’s not as free as in Berlin, he shares, a place he once inhabited, squatting in Köpenick and composing works that now hang in this design outlet just off Brick Lane. <i>The folks here are different</i>, he says, pausing, belonging to a <i>certain type</i>. He gives me a postcard, <i>a token to remember our conversation</i>: ‘#Paradise’ printed on a white surface, a glimpse of blue sky in the background.</p>
<p>D is moving back to the United States. After a preliminary job search and the weight of a different kind of bureaucracy on his shoulders, it seems like the best thing, for now. As he prepares for his departure to Philadelphia he looks mournful, visiting his favorite food carts and bookshop, the dingy canal with folks living out of boats – the air thick with oil and wet brush – before it all becomes just another place where he once lived. <i>I’d like to come back</i>, he says, <i>but then I just walk around and look at all the people here and want to go up and ask ‘like, how do you live here? What do you do?’</i> Perhaps, many of them are themselves transplants, just figuring it out as they go, leaving eventually for another place.</p>
<p>It’s hard to say, given the look of things.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1035.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3348 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1035.jpg" alt="img_1035" width="640" height="295" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1035.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/img_1035-300x138.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>&#8211; <i>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></i></p>
<p><i>For more background on London as a city of immigration check out this 2013 </i> Times<i> <a href="http://www.thetimes.co.uk/tto/public/postcard/article3757989.ece">article</a>, which provides a concise run-down on the various groups and waves that make up London’s diversity. But even better:</i>the Guardian <i>has put together a</i><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/series/london"><i> </i><i>nifty collection</i></a><i> </i><i>of resources for exploring the many religious, culinary, and all-around cultural traditions that make up the city, although nothing beats exploring it on your own, if time and purse strings allow.</i></p>
<p>*I am using this word “transplant” intentionally, avoiding terms such as “expat” or even “immigrant”, as they are often bogged down with allusions to class, privilege, and assumptions about the irrelevance of borders or passports for certain members of the global community. When it comes to migration, the language is tricky but important. It helps to start with words that we feel we truly inhabit or experience, even if imperfectly.</p>
<p>All photos were taken by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/09/29/beyond-berlin-london-and-other-transplants/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: Three Dimensions of Integration</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/07/interview-three-dimensions-of-integration/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/07/interview-three-dimensions-of-integration/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2014 07:14:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ex-pat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kreuzberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theater]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2212</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It's easy (and admittedly amusing) to reduce expats to stereotypes, as if we all neatly fall into one or the other category based on which country we hail from, what we do for a living, or where we party and eat brunch. Reality is always more nuanced and multi-dimensional. Dare we even say, interesting?...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Immigrant integration and identity can be very personal subjects and not everyone wishes for their views and experiences to be made public. Though all the stories in this interview are true, names and some cities have been changed to protect the artist&#8217;s identity, per his request.</em></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_0609.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_0609.jpg?w=640" alt="Admiralbruecke in Kreuzberg" width="604" height="604" /></a></p>
<p>It&#8217;s easy (<a href="http://www.uberlin.co.uk/stereotypes-different-expats-youll-meet-berlin/">and admittedly amusing</a>) to reduce expats to stereotypes, as if we all neatly fall into one or the other category based on which country we hail from, what we do for a living, or where we party and eat brunch. Reality is always more nuanced and multi-dimensional. Dare we even say, interesting?</p>
<p>Take Alex, American-born artist and documentary filmmaker living in Berlin. On first sight, the dual American-Polish citizen may appear to fit into a few niches: creative type with a studio in <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/20/lens-an-ode-to-the-maybachufer/">trendy Kreuzberg</a>, one of a rapidly growing number of young <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/07/rant-or-rave-jew-in-a-box/">Jews in Berlin</a>, jetsetter popping between speaking engagements in Europe and gigs in Los Angeles and Seattle. But Alex&#8217;s life in Berlin was more happy accident than predestined by career or background. The idea came from a professor who happened to hear him &#8220;complaining in the hallway about wanting to leave [his homestate] Illinois” and suggested a semester program in Offenbach near Frankfurt, Germany.</p>
<p>In 2003, Alex left the U.S. for Germany, and in the past decade, has spent time in Frankfurt, Stuttgart, and Karlsruhe. For the past six years he has been Berlin-based.</p>
<p><a href="http://friedrichshainblog.de/santa-maria-gutes-mexikanisches-restaurant-in-berlin-kreuzberg/"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2225" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/santa-maria-mexikaner-kreuzberg.jpg" alt="santa maria in kreuzberg" width="600" height="450" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/santa-maria-mexikaner-kreuzberg.jpg 600w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/santa-maria-mexikaner-kreuzberg-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/santa-maria-mexikaner-kreuzberg-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></a></p>
<p>I meet Alex in his studio on Adalbertstraße, where he shows me some clips of his documentary films and tells me start-ups are starting to take-over former artist space in the building. &#8220;Do you feel integrated?&#8221; I ask later over habanero-spiked food and aguas frescas at Oranienstraße&#8217;s Santa Maria Restaurant. &#8220;You&#8217;re really making me think here,&#8221; Alex ponders, slicing into his pumpkin burrito, &#8220;it&#8217;s a top-heavy question though, isn&#8217;t it? Depends on what you mean by &#8216;integrated&#8217;.&#8221;</p>
<p>Alex isn&#8217;t a fan of dichotomies, the idea that every question always has a right or wrong answer. He prefers to see the world in three dimensions, which he describes as &#8220;the pause in-between inhaling and exhaling&#8221;. Fittingly, by the end of our conversation, he&#8217;s given us three dimensions through which to consider integration.</p>
<p><strong>The Dance Performance</strong></p>
<p>Alex recently attended a dance performance by Wang Ramirez, a pair that works between Berlin, Paris, and London and are &#8220;<a href="http://wangramirez.com/">as diverse as the cultures that clashed and harmonized when its founders met</a>.&#8221;</p>
<p>“She is ethnically Korean but grew up in Germany, and he grew up in France but has Spanish roots,” Alex explains. &#8220;At one part during the evening&#8217;s program, a woman comes on stage and asks them one of those typical questions about language and identity. How their backgrounds influence their performance and such. Wang and Ramirez respond in a mix of languages and movements, getting progressively more incoherent, to show how essentially absurd and futile that question can be.&#8221;</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://vimeo.com/79000095"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter  wp-image-2223" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/wangramirez.jpg" alt="wangramirez" width="601" height="335" /></a><br />
<strong>The Jewish Guilt</strong></p>
<p>While attending a conference in Weimar to hear a professor friend of his speak, Alex was approached by a young German student looking for participants in a Jewish identity project.&#8221;He had just found out that he had some Jewish ancestry,&#8221; Alex recounts. &#8220;He wanted to do a photography project on young Jews in Germany to acknowledge this, and asked us if we would participate. Later, when my friend and I were alone and could discuss openly, we realized this project, like so many others, was focused on the past. My friend said, &#8216;why doesn&#8217;t he focus on Germany&#8217;s future instead, as a multicultural country? Perhaps learning Turkish would be a more meaningful contribution.’&#8221;</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>The Subway Encounter</strong></p>
<p>One late night on the U-Bahn, Alex found himself among a group of young Turkish-Germans. &#8220;People can&#8217;t usually tell where I&#8217;m from right off the bat. These guys in the U-Bahn asked me. My grandfather was a Sephardic Jew from Beirut, so I just told them I had a Lebanese grandfather and left out the rest. Once they thought I was Arab they started on how they love everyone and all religions&#8230; <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/">Muslims</a>, Christians, Jews, etc. Later I wondered how the conversation would have been different if I had said I was Jewish.&#8221;</p>
<p><a href="http://www.aviatorsandacamera.com/travel/nye-art-technology-in-berlin-part-2/"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter  wp-image-2224" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/ubahn.jpg" alt="berlin u-bahn" width="533" height="397" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/ubahn.jpg 259w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/ubahn-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 533px) 100vw, 533px" /></a></p>
<p>&#8212;&#8211;</p>
<p>&#8220;Berlin is a great place to come and figure out who you are and what you want to do. It&#8217;s just not the best place to make that happen, funding and opportunity wise,&#8221; Alex explains. &#8220;I always say Berlin is a city full of possibility, but not necessarily potential.&#8221; Alex, like many expats, is not sure what the future holds, other than it being a transnational one. No matter how much opportunity exists on the West Coast, it seems he will always be tied to Germany and, more specifically, Berlin. &#8220;Berlin is a city that breaks my heart,&#8221; he reminisces, &#8220;it broke my heart even before I lived here. Just the thought that a place like this even exists.”</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>First image by Sophia Burton, all others linked to sources.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/07/interview-three-dimensions-of-integration/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: An Ode to the Maybachufer</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/20/lens-an-ode-to-the-maybachufer/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/20/lens-an-ode-to-the-maybachufer/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2014 11:53:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gentrification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1853</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[From Berlin's "problem district" to more expensive than spießig Charlottenburg: Kreuzberg's made quite the transformation over the decades, but migration continues to shape its identity and reputation as a district. The bulk of Kreuzberg's diversity stems from the '50s and '60s, when guest workers were recruited by West Germany to fill labor shortages after World War II*. Kreuzberg's dilapidated housing became home to guest workers, primarily from Turkey...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From Berlin&#8217;s &#8220;problem district&#8221; to <a href="http://www.bz-berlin.de/aktuell/berlin/kreuzberg-teurer-als-charlottenburg-article1398469.html">more expensive</a> than <em>spießig</em> Charlottenburg: Kreuzberg&#8217;s made quite the transformation over the decades, but migration continues to shape its identity and reputation as a district.</p>
<p>The bulk of Kreuzberg&#8217;s diversity stems from the &#8217;50s and &#8217;60s, when guest workers were recruited by West Germany to fill labor shortages after World War II*. Kreuzberg&#8217;s dilapidated housing became home to guest workers, primarily from Turkey. The district soon came to be known as &#8220;Little Istanbul&#8221;. In 2014 you would still be hard pressed to find a block without a <em>Döner</em> <em>Kebab </em>stand or five, but the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/">district&#8217;s diversity</a> extends far past Anatolia.</p>
<p>Along with districts like Neukölln and Wedding, Kreuzberg is renowned for its <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/11/happy-weekend-its-not-about-integration-or-isnt-it/">immigrant integration</a> challenges that include low educational attainment and poor German language skills, high unemployment rates, crime and drug abuse, and gentrification. At the same time, the area has become increasingly attractive to <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/">students</a>, hip expats, and young families. The result is a veritable array of nationalities, cuisines, houses of worship, and attires, as vivid as the graffiti gracing the walls of its gray housing and slender canals.</p>
<p>There are many popular spots in Kreuzberg, but the Maybachufer canal is perhaps one that most poignantly displays the cultural fusion that makes Kreuzberg a very special place to call home.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/swans.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/swans.jpg" alt="swans" width="594" height="594" /></a></p>
<p><strong>An Ode to the Maybachufer</strong></p>
<p>If I go away, I&#8217;ll remember the swans. And the walls of graffiti they floated along.</p>
<p>Rows of satellite dishes, speckled across gray concrete. Lingerers outside Kaiser&#8217;s, empty bottles at their feet.</p>
<p>Men huddled over pear-shaped glasses of Çay. Girls in tiny shorts and tights, snags in their thighs.</p>
<p>A market with only two rows, but infinite choice. Vendors calling &#8220;lecka! lecka!&#8221;, hints of somewhere else in their voice.</p>
<p>Hair smothered by scarves or impossibly fake dye. Individuals by words: &#8220;expat&#8221;, &#8220;immigrant&#8221;. You or I.</p>
<p>Where &#8220;German&#8221; ends and &#8220;other&#8221; begins, we futilely try to decide.</p>
<p>But the swans. They just keep floating by.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The Maybachufer Turkish Market (U1-Kottbusser Tor or U8-Schoenleinstrasse) runs on Tuesdays and Fridays from approximately 12pm-6pm. Go for the cheap produce and spinach-cheese <em>Gözleme. </em><br />
</em></p>
<p>* West Germany recruited 14 million guest workers between 1955 and 1973 during the post World War II &#8220;economic miracle&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>For more on Turks in Germany and guest worker programs:</strong></p>
<p>http://www.azcentral.com/news/articles/global-immigration-germany.html?nclick_check=1</p>
<p><strong>For more on Kreuzberg:  </strong></p>
<p>http://www.fhxb-museum.de/</p>
<p>http://travel.michelin.com/web/destination/Germany-Berlin/news-Kreuzberg_forever-Reichenberger_Str_177</p>
<p>http://www.humanityinaction.org/knowledgebase/32-in-kreuzberg-there-are-no-foreigners-scrutinizing-berlin-s-diversity</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/20/lens-an-ode-to-the-maybachufer/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: Difference in the Wet Country</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2014 12:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[provincial]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1986</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For nearly a month this holiday season, I explored the social fabric surrounding my US origins with a German national, who had never before been to the land of plenty. Through the fresh eyes of 'the foreigner', I saw my part of America unfold under a curious and critical lens. America is a country that defines itself by historical narratives of migration and manifest destiny. What one encounters on the road in its northwestern corner, however, is a bit more mundane. At closer glance, emptiness and the prosaic everyday give food for thought, in regards to locating and valuing difference wherever it bubbles up...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>How do you notice difference in a city, in which you yourself are different?</strong></p>
<div id="attachment_1992" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1992" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1992 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-1.jpg" alt="Portland, OR steel-bridge" width="640" height="360" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1992" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>For nearly a month this holiday season, I explored the social fabric surrounding my US origins with a German national, who had never before been to the land of plenty. Through the fresh eyes of &#8216;the foreigner&#8217;, I saw my part of America unfold under a curious and critical lens. Given this blog&#8217;s weekly critical handling of all things multicultural in the big city, why not talk about diversity in an American context? This context proves to be quite different from the aspiring-cosmopolitan intersections of the German capital, as shocking as that may or may not be.</p>
<p>America is a country that defines itself by historical narratives of migration and manifest destiny. What one encounters on the road in its northwestern corner, however, is a bit more mundane. At closer glance, emptiness and the prosaic everyday give food for thought, in regards to locating and valuing difference wherever it bubbles up.</p>
<p><strong>Geography matters</strong></p>
<p>Somehow, when we talk of diversity in society, the role of space therein is a side note. In fact, where we live, work, play, learn, and heal in many ways determines our belonging to or exclusion from social and economic groups that are important in ensuring opportunity.</p>
<p>Maps tell us a lot about how different ways of life can exist cohesively together. Maps may miss, however (<a href="http://www.npr.org/censusmap/#4.00/39.00/-84.00">see NPR&#8217;s US census map</a>), where difference pops up beyond the packed hotbeds for multiculturalism of the city, leaving our eyes to experience what the provinces, the forgotten towns, and the coastal sticks have to offer firsthand.</p>
<div id="attachment_1989" style="width: 311px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1989" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1989 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg" alt="Rebecca Vincent" width="301" height="300" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg 301w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent-300x299.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 301px) 100vw, 301px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1989" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Rebecca Vincent</p></div>
<p>In the Pacific Northwest, like many other regions, cartography shows the urban as an array of ever-revolving grids, residences dotting the margins of concrete webs and precise civil engineering, greenery contained, parks splashed with beige and lived-in browns. One passes through these strange boundaries of growth, as if moving through the trunk of a tree to reach its core, each ring giving way to new densities and shapes of living, suburbia giving way to semi-rural apartment clusters and neatly arranged town homes.</p>
<div id="attachment_2001" style="width: 471px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2001" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2001  " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png?w=640" alt="portland map" width="461" height="347" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png 646w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map-300x226.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map-80x60.png 80w" sizes="(max-width: 461px) 100vw, 461px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2001" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Mappery.com</p></div>
<p>Apart from the patterns and markings of cities, great expanses of forest or farmland separate bundles of life from one another. Beyond the edge of the urban, an emptiness emerges. Where cities end, mountain pass truck-stops, wine-making valleys, flat dairy country, coastal trailer parks, and retired logging towns begin. Vehicles connect what trains used to. Marks on the map created for the movement between these revolving grids begin to surface like geometric occurrences of ink. Here humans somehow ended up, often fairly alone with only the company of a gas station and a corner store.</p>
<div id="attachment_2002" style="width: 476px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2002" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2002   " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png?w=640" alt="oregon map" width="466" height="375" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png 749w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map-300x241.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map-650x522.png 650w" sizes="(max-width: 466px) 100vw, 466px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2002" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Oregon Office of Rural Health</p></div>
<p>Passing through such places on the road from one side of the state of Oregon to the next, the new set of eyes saw only distance, forged together by oil rigs and spinning tires. <em>Density can be an advantage, when it comes to social and cultural encounters needed for intercultural understandings to take root</em>, I thought, as we searched for a place to eat on a long stretch that seemed to allow only signage, fast food, and campgrounds.</p>
<div id="attachment_1990" style="width: 471px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-2.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1990" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-1990 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-2.jpg" alt="Portland, OR steel-bridge " width="461" height="614" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1990" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>And yet, the migrant worker shantytown in Southwest Washington, the Korean BBQ embedded in the Tillamook state forest, the sushi bar near Mt. Hood’s base, the taco trucks at truck-stops, the Chinese waiter at the roadside diner all suggest that even in more expansive geographies, difference can occur.</p>
<p><strong>Just because it is there, doesn&#8217;t mean we will notice it</strong></p>
<p>On our way to the valley of the Rogue River, our over-sized vehicle wound down the Pacific Highway, hugging cliffs of the sea and the edges of a strange poverty. We saw mile after mile of rotting cottages, mobile homes made more mobile by landslides, empty villages with the local pub serving bento, tacos, and chowder, and liquor stores the size of the local church beside it. Catholic churches sprouted up in these towns, in the basin of the interstate or at the rim of the sea &#8211; something I did not take notice of at first, but which suggested some shift, an immigration. Those who find ships in the right season or canneries with need for cheaply-bought hands make their way back to the Saints to thank them for their providence, or so it seemed.</p>
<p>In the foggy valleys of dead logging towns, the basin of the interstate, the depressed dairy lands and empty harbors: here the German traveler experienced my part of America with its shady diners where breakfast and hot sauce are served all day, roadside shacks with a For Sale sign, Walmart’s to nowhere. And in between the lines, difference was there, simply glossed over by the mundanity of its appearance, bearing more than John Wayne&#8217;s Americana.</p>
<div id="attachment_1994" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/streeet.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1994" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-1994 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/streeet.jpg?w=640" alt="street Portland, OR" width="640" height="360" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1994" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>The churches that never cease to be obvious and enormous on major highways; the Mexican restaurants with happy signs and plenty of American families digging into re-fried beans and rice, as if it were the national dish; the Japanese restaurants with pictures of majestic mountains that could be local; medical advertisements with black patients and Asian doctors; a South Asian newscaster in a suit just like everybody else; a black reporter stuck to sports on the local news station: these things I may not have noticed without the presence of the new perspective next to me.</p>
<p><strong>It is not about what we say, but about what is heard</strong></p>
<div id="attachment_1991" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/diner-pwf-0066.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1991" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-1991" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/diner-pwf-0066.jpg?w=300" alt="Photo source: Paul Winch-Furness" width="300" height="199" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1991" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Paul Winch-Furness</p></div>
<p>For the German&#8217;s second breakfast in America, we took him to a local diner in southwest Washington with the classic booths and red upholstery, simple fried numbers, and a healthy rotation of pies. As he ordered, his slight accent turned the words into mildly different sounds, his tongue pushing just a bit too far back for the &#8216;l&#8217; and the &#8216;th&#8217; sticking to the front of his teeth. The letters may have come together in a way that did not quite fit the frames we have learned to repeat, but one could and can simply understand. And so &#8216;the waffle special&#8217; was transmitted to the kitchen with no questions asked. And after we had told the waitress in her darling little apron that it was his first time in an American diner, she beamed at the foreigner sitting there in front of the simple white dishware and the paper napkin. She whispered to the other waitress, who, blushing, came over to our table to pour coffee and welcome him to town.</p>
<p>It is not about the sounds being right. It is about our understanding them.</p>
<p><strong>Being an outsider can come in handy, as I have learned on the other side of the Atlantic</strong></p>
<p>Growing up in the far corner of the Western United States, I am familiar with the figures and curves of this particular landscape and society. I have, however, sorely taken for granted what it means to have tacos in the middle of nowhere, to celebrate Persian New Year with friends, or to consider Phở as American as bratwurst (I can thank Seattle for that). In many ways, difference was a natural part of my private and public education, the neighborhoods where I lived, the sports teams I played on, and the churches I attended. I cannot say that I have consciously valued these experiences for what I learned from them. If such encounters and relationships had popped up in my Berlin world, I would have celebrated them. This is largely due to the ways in which diversity is or is not celebrated by society at large and how we might attempt to remedy this fact.</p>
<p>But what is most striking and assuredly the take-away from this tale is that campaign-worthy diversity in the big city is not all there is, nor is it of greater value than the outcroppings of difference at truck-stops off the interstate. This might be where it counts the most.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Ethno-cultural diversity is changing the face of the rural United States, including states like Oregon and Washington. For a great visual of this transformation, see the <a href="http://www.ers.usda.gov/media/176091/page7.pdf">United States Department of Agriculture&#8217;s map from its Rural Population and Migration Brieﬁng Room</a>. As the roadside taco trucks and shantytowns demonstrate, a large wave of migration from Latin America to the Pacific Northwest region has characterized rural growth from 2000-2012, according to the <a href="http://www.ers.usda.gov/amber-waves/2011-december/hispanics-contribute-to-increasing-diversity.aspx#.Ut5lnRA1iM8">USDA&#8217;s recent report</a> on demography. Reflective of this shift to the out-country from the urban heart, is the <a href="http://www.oregonlive.com/pacific-northwest-news/index.ssf/2011/04/in_portlands_heart_diversity_dwindles.html">dwindling diversity in the heart of Portland, OR</a>. Difference is, thus, not always where you expect to find it.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: With Wings, Roots, and Sweaty Hands</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2013 11:56:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1678</guid>

					<description><![CDATA["Punctual. Exact. Productive. Closed off. Careful. Inflexible. Humorless." And some "Goethe" and "Einstein" thrown in for good measure. Was this really all a group of seemingly well-educated professionals had to say about German identity? No wonder the facilitator had started to draw sad faces on the list...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;">&#8220;Punctual. Exact. Productive. Closed off. Careful. Inflexible. Humorless.&#8221; And some &#8220;Goethe&#8221; and &#8220;Einstein&#8221; thrown in for good measure. Was this really all a group of seemingly well-educated professionals had to say about <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/">German identity</a>? No wonder the facilitator had started to draw sad faces on the list.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/2013-11-08-14-16-29-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1682" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/2013-11-08-14-16-29-1.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-11-08 14.16.29-1" width="640" height="640" /></a></p>
<p><em>My hands get sweaty when I hear this sort of talk</em>, a woman piped up from the front row, a shred of anger in her voice. <em>Is this really all we identify with, as Germans?</em></p>
<p>I shared her frustration. We were over three hours into the &#8220;German Identity and Identities in Germany&#8221; workshop, having already watched a documentary clip and listened to a panel discussion on the nuances of (im)migration, national identity, and belonging. Yet when asked by our facilitator <em>What is German?</em>, all we could come up with were stereotypes or nothing at all. I was in the latter camp, sitting quietly in the corner, scribbling down notes, the occasional eyebrow raise or eye roll gracing my face. An older man on the other side of the room began criticizing globalization and everything &#8220;becoming the same&#8221;, proclaiming that when it comes down to it, identity is tied to region. <em>I have fire in my belly,</em> my friend whispered to me, leaning over. <em>So do I</em>, I thought, but I wasn&#8217;t sure what to do with it. On some level our hybrid-identities felt under attack, as if our <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/26/lens-coming-home/">sense of home</a> tied to people, language, and experience was not as legitimate as one tied to geography. As if we weren&#8217;t quite part of the discussion in the same way as the others.</p>
<div id="attachment_1683" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/2013-11-08-15-31-39-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1683" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-1683" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/2013-11-08-15-31-39-1.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-11-08 15.31.39-1" width="640" height="640" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1683" class="wp-caption-text">Making friends at the workshop</p></div>
<p>I was surprised at myself. For years I&#8217;d been navigating a slew of cultures, confidently code-switching, getting by and blending in pretty much anywhere with relative ease and advantage. Dual citizen, trilingual, well-traveled, ethnically ambiguous, international education professional, American-German-Jewish-Algerian mutt. I&#8217;d always felt <em>just different enough</em>, rather than <em>too different</em>. I&#8217;m a pretty ruthless cherry-picker, highlighting a particular part of my background when it suits the moment. <em>My dad&#8217;s Jewish and I went on Birthright</em>, I declare to Israeli airport security. <em>My mom&#8217;s German and I&#8217;m a dual citizen,</em> I respond when asked why I live in Berlin. <em>I&#8217;m part Algerian</em>, I say proudly to a cute Arab-German on a date. <em>I also grew up with two languages and have trouble with German</em>, I share with the Vietnamese girls I tutor. I&#8217;d positioned my international identity as the centerpiece of my life a long time ago, letting it guide me both personally and professionally. Perhaps it&#8217;s self-serving or even greedy, but it&#8217;s always felt like my choice.</p>
<p>Others have their choice ripped from them with one ostensibly innocent question: &#8220;<strong>But where are you from from?&#8221; </strong><em><strong>Wo kommst du wirklich her? </strong></em>Translation: &#8220;You must come from somewhere other than here, because you look/sound/pray/move/eat/celebrate differently than <em>we</em> do.&#8221; The plight of the &#8220;<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DWynJkN5HbQ">perpetual foreigner</a>&#8220;.</p>
<p>During my past two years in Berlin I&#8217;d started to get a little taste of what that felt like, an after-taste really. <em>No, I&#8217;m not Spanish</em>, I find myself saying at least once a week to those who wonder out-loud or even just start speaking to me in Spanish. I get it, there are an increasing number of Spaniards in Berlin (and Germany). I get it, I have darker features. But whereas I would normally enjoy talking about my background, I now find myself getting irritated and defensive having to explain myself against a recurrent assumption.</p>
<p><em>&#8220;People always ask how my German is so good. I tell them I&#8217;ll try to speak worse German from now on,&#8221; a Vietnamese immigrant says ironically in his studio.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>&#8220;I know people expect me to be a certain way, or have ideas about what type of person I am, of what I&#8217;m capable of, based on how I look,&#8221; a young Eritrean girl ponders at the window.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>&#8220;I&#8217;m not really Turkish, and I&#8217;m not really German. I identify as a Turkish-German, which is something else,&#8221; reflects a woman from her apartment.<br />
</em></p>
<p>[paraphrased quotes from the &#8220;with WINGS and ROOTS&#8221; documentary]</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/withwingsandroots_reimaginebelonging_website_small.png"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1709" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/withwingsandroots_reimaginebelonging_website_small.png?w=640" alt="withWINGSandROOTS_reimagineBelonging_website_small" width="640" height="344" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/withwingsandroots_reimaginebelonging_website_small.png 720w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/withwingsandroots_reimaginebelonging_website_small-300x161.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/withwingsandroots_reimaginebelonging_website_small-650x349.png 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.withwingsandroots.com/">Source</a></p>
<p>While the woman with the sweaty hands was perhaps frustrated by the selection of adjectives on the list, I realized I was worked up about why there had to be a list at all. For the first time in two years in Berlin, I not only wondered, but cared, whether the others in the room considered me German. Or even German enough.</p>
<p><em>I grew up with German culture, speak the language, have the passport, and now live here</em>, I finally summoned up the courage and coherence to say. <em>But I&#8217;m only one fourth German &#8220;ethnically&#8221;. I know people back in the US who have more German blood than I but have no connection to the country, language, people, history. I don&#8217;t fit everything on that list, but neither do any of you.<br />
</em></p>
<p>Identity is a social construction, I wanted to go on. A fluid and on-going process on both the individual and national level. Increased levels of migration and diversity often spark an instinct to distinguish, retreat, and protect- on both the &#8220;native&#8221; and &#8220;(im)migrant&#8221; sides. But it&#8217;s also an opportunity to reflect, learn, and reinvent. By the end of the workshop, we were getting there.</p>
<p><em>What is your vision for a modern perception of &#8220;Germanness&#8221;?</em> the facilitator prompted us.</p>
<p>&#8220;Being open. Intercultural understanding from authorities. Focusing on plurality. Promoting language proficiency. Fostering awareness. Accepting (not only tolerating) others. Self-reflection.&#8221;</p>
<p>A list of adjectives can only put us into a box. A list of actions lets us move forward.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>How serendipitous: a fantastic article on the same topic just came out in Spiegel. Read <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/essay-on-racism-growing-up-turkish-in-germany-a-932154.html">here</a> about one woman&#8217;s reality of growing up as a third-generation Turkish-German in Hamburg and being asked about everything from circumcision, staying out late, and being a &#8220;different Turk&#8221;. </em></p>
<p><em>The documentary clip we watched is from &#8220;with WINGS and ROOTS&#8221; that juxtaposes the realities of (im)migrant life, national identity, and belonging in Berlin and New York City. You can watch the trailer <a href="http://www.withwingsandroots.com/video/trailer">here</a> and <strong>support the project <a href="http://www.withwingsandroots.com/get-involved/donate">here</a></strong><strong>.</strong> According to representatives from the film at the workshop there will be new ways of getting involved in January, so stay tuned! </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Multiculturalism, Diversity, and the Big City</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2013 18:48:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kreuzberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1358</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[With my back to them at the street-side café I felt like a judge on "<a href="http://www.nbc.com/the-voice/">The Voice</a>", straining my neck for any hint of where they were from or what they looked like, resisting the urge to swirl around and start dancing on my chair. Truth be told my ears had perked up as soon as the trio plopped down at the table behind me, switching between topics like gentrification in Kreuzberg and the cultural difference between <em>Kaffee</em> and "coffee" as quickly as they were switching between German and English...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/photo-1-2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/photo-1-2.jpg" alt="photo-1 (2)" width="640" height="640" /></a></p>
<p>With my back to them at the street-side café I felt like a judge on &#8220;<a href="http://www.nbc.com/the-voice/">The Voice</a>&#8220;, straining my neck for any hint of where they were from or what they looked like, resisting the urge to swirl around and start dancing on my chair. Truth be told my ears had perked up as soon as the trio plopped down at the table behind me, switching between topics like gentrification in Kreuzberg and the cultural difference between <em>Kaffee</em> and &#8220;coffee&#8221; as quickly as they were switching between German and English.</p>
<p>Voice #1: &#8220;I speak differently when I speak to you, or to Brits, or to other Americans. I’m speaking much slower right now and I explain things differently.&#8221; <em> Aha! A fellow American. Is she a teacher? Is this a language class? </em><em>&#8220;</em>Wait, were you just speaking in English or German?&#8221; <em>Hmm, maybe not a teacher. Did she also grow up with both languages? Is that a slight accent I detect? </em></p>
<p>Voice #2: &#8220;My name, Uyen&#8230; well for us the middle name is actually the main name, the name before that is just to make the name more beautiful. And my last name is unique, a combination of my mother&#8217;s and father&#8217;s names. Even my sisters don&#8217;t have it because the province where I was born doesn&#8217;t have the same rules like they do here.&#8221; &#8216;<em>Uyen&#8217;&#8230; is that Vietnamese? Germany has <a href="http://www.germany.info/Vertretung/usa/en/05__Legal/02__Directory__Services/04__Family__Matters/__Name.html">laws</a> about children&#8217;s names.. maybe she was born in Vietnam and then her family moved to Germany and her sisters were born here?</em></p>
<p>Voice #3: &#8220;In another language it&#8217;s always different, the, the&#8230; how do you say <em>Betonung auf Englisch</em>?&#8221; <em>The others are struggling to find the translation, should I interject&#8230;? No that&#8217;d be rude, though maybe they&#8217;d appreciate the&#8230;</em></p>
<p>SLAM! Down went my button and I whirled around.</p>
<p>&#8220;Emphasis!&#8221; I yelped, nearly toppling over on the cobblestones. &#8220;Sorry&#8230; for, uh, listening in on your conversation,&#8221; I continued a bit sheepishly, trying to redeem myself, &#8220;It was just really interesting!&#8221;</p>
<p>Lucky for me they were not only open to the vocabulary assistance but also for a chat with the lady who&#8217;d been shamelessly eavesdropping on them (and typing up parts of their conversation, they&#8217;d later learn).  Ten minutes later it was clear that while my sleuthing wasn&#8217;t entirely off the mark, it wasn&#8217;t the whole picture either. Voice #1 belonged to Lea: originally born in Serbia but living in the US for most of her life, currently pursuing a Master&#8217;s degree in Social Work in Boston, but had spent a few years of her upbringing in Germany. Her German, just like mine, was fluent and <em>almost</em> accent free but peppered by the occasional grammar mistake or forgotten vocabulary word. Voice #2 was Uyen: Vietnamese-German (or <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">German-Vietnamese</a>) as I suspected. Born in Vietnam, grew up in Berlin, also currently studying. And Voice #3 was Nicole&#8217;s: A German also working toward her degree in Social Work. The three were in a class together but it wasn&#8217;t a language one. Instead they were enrolled in an international summer course called &#8220;Diversity in the Big City&#8221;. A course focused on diversity in urban environments for those working in social professions and partly financed by the Federal Foreign Office in cooperation with the DAAD, Germany&#8217;s Academic Exchange Service. The course examines diversity through four lenses: social participation, social structure and urban development, migration and integration, and education.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-22-16-28-54.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-22-16-28-54.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-08-22 16.28.54" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>This is one of those moments I wish Chancellor Angela Merkel had been around to see. Not that I think about Merkel all that often or necessarily consider her a fun café partner, but it would&#8217;ve been satisfying to show the politician who proclaimed that &#8220;<a href="http://www.thenewamerican.com/world-news/europe/item/8685-sarkozy-joins-cameron-merkel-condemns-multiculturalism">multiculturalism has utterly failed</a>&#8221; this positive example of multiculturalism in the everyday.</p>
<p>And there we go again with one of our favorite words, &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221;. If we were so inclined, we could spend this whole damn blog analyzing that term. We wouldn&#8217;t mind so much actually &#8211; Kelly can&#8217;t even use the term &#8220;culture&#8221; without first defining it and I could happily talk your ears off about the relationship between cultural capital and educational achievement. Thankfully we&#8217;re savvy enough to realize it wouldn&#8217;t make things very fun for all of you. <em>Or would it?</em> No, of course it wouldn&#8217;t. Moving on. But write us if it might.</p>
<p>To be fair, it&#8217;s pretty near impossible to create a definitive understanding of &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221;.  The word&#8217;s become increasingly loaded as countries face burgeoning levels of immigration and struggle to incorporate diverse populations within their borders. In turn it&#8217;s dissected by academics, used strategically to shape policy, and tossed around in the everyday. It&#8217;s elusive and as some like to call it, a &#8220;moving target&#8221;. Kelly hit the nail on the head in one of <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/10/whose-multikulti-is-it-the-elusive-definition-of-multiculturalism/">her posts</a> and then bolded that nail so you&#8217;d pay attention: &#8220;The various meanings of <em>Multikulti</em> are just as ‘multi’ as the differences the word aims to describe&#8221;<strong>.</strong></p>
<p>I think we can start by agreeing that there is a stark difference between <em>saying</em> you&#8217;re something and actually <em>doing</em> something. Sociology Professor and Harvard PhD Irene Bloemraad has packaged this difference into a neat little theory called &#8220;symbolic&#8221; vs. &#8220;material&#8221; multiculturalism. In other words, talking the talk vs. walking the walk.</p>
<p>The United States, for example, is all about <em>symbolic multiculturalism</em>. Whichever food related metaphor you prefer &#8211; &#8220;melting pot&#8221;, &#8220;salad bowl&#8221;, or &#8220;ethnic stew&#8221; (yup, people say that) &#8211; the country&#8217;s national identity is forever tied to immigration and diversity. Yet as Bloemraad rightly points out, the US&#8217;s support of multiculturalism is more social than political: the country <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2NpHwYrIXWY">embraces multiculturalism</a> and individual expression but is not big on providing institutionalized resources toward integration and the political participation of immigrants.</p>
<p><em>Material multiculturalism</em> on the other hand is the government stepping in and addressing immigrant integration in an institutionalized way. Merkel&#8217;s certainly right that Germany is far from being a beacon of multiculturalism, but let&#8217;s not ignore the positive &#8220;material&#8221; work the country has recently embarked on: <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">integration courses</a>, new citizenship laws, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/18/rave-education-per-square-kilometer/">educational initiatives</a>, etc. Lea, Uyen, and Nicole&#8217;s &#8220;Diversity in the Big City&#8221; course is another example of how a small effort can promote multiculturalism both symbolically and materially: creating a space for international students to study diversity is a symbolic acknowledgement that those working in social spheres should gain this perspective. Funding these courses through the government is a material backing of this acknowledgement.</p>
<p>Much work still needs to be done, and I&#8217;m the first to acknowledge that four highly educated women chatting diversity over cappuccinos is a far cry from the challenges many other groups face in regards to integration. But whatever &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221; is, may, or should be, it hasn&#8217;t failed. It&#8217;s a symbolic and material work in progress. <em>Our</em> work in progress.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The adorable café pictured above is called</em> <a href="http://www.schoenescafe.de/">schönes café</a> <em>and is located in Kreuzberg&#8217;s Graefekiez. For more information on the &#8220;Diversity in the Big City&#8221; course and others run by DAAD, click <a href="https://www.daad.de/deutschland/studienangebote/sommerkurse/en/?ipp=50&amp;seite=1&amp;sk_akademie=0&amp;skchapter=0&amp;skduration=0&amp;skenter=&amp;skid=841&amp;sksubject=12&amp;skterm=&amp;sktown=&amp;stipendiate=0">here</a>. </em></p>
<p>Non-professional photos by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
