<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Sophia Burton &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/author/sophia-burton/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Women Only: The Frauenraum</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 15:42:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gender]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4385</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I'm at Rathaus Wilmersdorf, a former city hall building turned refugee home in Berlin, where I teach a literacy class once a week. The home initially opened its doors to 178 refugees in September 2015, following Merkel's famous "Wir schaffen das" ("We can do it") declaration that sidestepped the Dublin Regulation and opened up Germany's borders to thousands of asylum seekers.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4394 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-01-27 12.51.04" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>It&#8217;s Thursday at 10:55, and I&#8217;m running late. I rush up to the security guards and hand over my ID. <em>Helfer?</em> (&#8220;volunteer?&#8221;) they ask. <em>Ja</em>, I answer, and wait for them to scribble down my name and give me a number so I can sign out later. I thank them and head inside to the office to sign for the room keys and get my name tag. Then it&#8217;s through the foyer and up three floors to room 3092. When breakfast is running late, the right half of the stairwell is still filled by a neat line of people waiting for their turn in the cafeteria. I squeeze by, ruffling the hair of the kids I recognize.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m at Rathaus Wilmersdorf, a former city hall building turned refugee home in Berlin, where I teach a literacy class once a week. The home initially opened its doors to <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/berlin/bezirke/kudamm/notunterkunft-fuer-fluechtlinge-in-berlin-im-rathaus-wilmersdorf-fehlen-duschen-und-dolmetscher/12199798.html">178 refugees</a> in September 2015, following Merkel&#8217;s famous &#8220;Wir schaffen das&#8221; (&#8220;We can do it&#8221;) declaration that <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/germany/11821822/Germany-drops-EU-rules-to-allow-in-Syrian-refugees.html">sidestepped the Dublin Regulation</a> and opened up Germany&#8217;s borders to thousands of asylum seekers.</p>
<p>Today, over 1400 refugees live in the Rathaus &#8211; mostly from Syria, Afghanistan, and Iraq &#8211; and there is talk of opening up an adjacent building to house an additional 900. As is the case all over the city, this home simply wouldn&#8217;t function without the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/">on-going assistance of volunteers</a> who help out with everything from interpretation and teaching to administrative and kitchen support.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4456 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-01-08 10.34.54" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Over the past eight months, Rathaus Wilmersdorf has become somewhat of a success story as far as refugee accommodations in Berlin go. It&#8217;s been visited by President Joachim Gauck and American actor Ben Stiller, as well as received significant media praise for its leadership and facilities. <a href="http://www.morgenpost.de/berlin/article207089933/Vachroi-verabschiedet-sich-als-Heimleiter-in-Wilmersdorf.html">One article</a> listed off the home&#8217;s impressive amenities, which include medical and midwife services, a laundry room, a hair salon, an internet <span class="st">café</span>, and yes, even our literacy class.</p>
<p>The literacy class, or &#8220;AB class&#8221; as we call it, does go beyond what many other refugee homes in Berlin offer. But what the article&#8217;s authors fail to mention (and are likely unaware of), is that the course comes with a complicated backstory that is indicative of a larger debate surrounding refugees in Germany today.</p>
<p>It all started early this year, after one volunteer noticed that a group of women were not showing up for the German class offered on the home&#8217;s fourth floor. These women were mostly Afghan and the majority also illiterate. However, a bit of digging (and a heavy dose of interpretation) revealed that they weren&#8217;t avoiding the class because the level was too difficult, as originally suspected. They weren&#8217;t going because, in the fourth floor class, there were men present. Or depending on who tells the story, “Because their husbands wouldn’t let them”.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4600 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-05-19 12.43.22" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>The decision was therefore made to start a new class on the third floor, taught and attended exclusively by women. The class was to be an extension of the adjacent <em>Frauenraum</em> or &#8220;women&#8217;s room&#8221;. At Rathaus Wilmersdorf, the <em>Frauenraum</em> is a standing room open almost daily, so long as there are volunteers present. At the refugee home in former Tempelhof airport, the <em>Frauenraum</em> operates on a weekly project basis, led by a volunteer platform called <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">Give Something Back to Berlin</a>.</p>
<p>Regardless of the format, the concept remains the same: The <em>Frauenraum</em> is a safe place where women can be amongst themselves. In Rathaus Wilmersdorf, they sew, practice German, or just hang out and have a cup of tea. Small children are allowed, but men are forbidden from entering. We&#8217;ve even had to throw out a male journalist on occasion. The home&#8217;s former director described it as a place where &#8220;<a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/berlin/warum-thomas-de-vachroi-der-perfekte-aufbauhelfer-fuer-fluechtlingsheime-ist-23775578">female residents are enjoying their freedom and unveiling themselves.</a>&#8221; I can only assume he meant this both literally and figuratively, as not all the women wear headscarves, but some who do do indeed take them off when in the <em>Frauenraum</em> or during class.</p>
<p>I fell into the role of literacy teacher by way of the <em>Frauenraum</em>, where I started volunteering in January. The class was already up and running but they wanted to offer it on more days and were having trouble finding willing teachers. Other <em>Frauenraum</em> volunteers, I was told, had flatly refused to teach out of principle, scoffing at the idea that a separate class be created when there was a perfectly good one already on offer. This is Germany, after all, a country where men and women are presumably equal and interact on all levels of society. If the husbands had a problem with that, tough. Isn&#8217;t it in the best interest of these women that we integrate them into our way of life as quickly as possible?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4460 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-05-12 11.42.50" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>These days, it is difficult to have a discussion in Germany about refugees that doesn&#8217;t include a question about gender. <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/02/08/not-our-women-from-cologne-to-berlin/">Post-Cologne</a>, it is near impossible. Despite the fact that the attacks on New Year&#8217;s Eve were carried out by a more diverse group than originally portrayed in the media, that night&#8217;s unfortunate events have marked a turning point in attitudes towards refugees.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.focus.de/politik/deutschland/zdf-umfrage-offenbart-so-haben-die-silvester-uebergriffe-beeinflusst-was-deutsche-ueber-fluechtlinge-denken_id_5213962.html">One poll</a> showed that, between December 2015 and January 2016 alone, the number of Germans who felt the country couldn&#8217;t handle the influx of refugees rose from 46% to 60%. Thirty-three percent stated that Cologne had &#8220;fundamentally changed&#8221; their opinions about refugees. And the ring-wing <span class="st"><em>Alternative für Deutschland</em></span> (AfD) party, which initially emerged in opposition to the euro, has placed anti-refugee sentiment at the core of their increasingly popular platform. Their leader has controversially <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/alternative-for-germany-shows-its-true-right-wing-colors-a-1076259.html">called for the use of firearms against incoming refugees</a>.</p>
<p>This is the same country that was at the forefront of Europe&#8217;s refugee response only nine months ago. The same country that led the continent&#8217;s discourse on establishing a common European solution. The same country that initiated what became globally lauded as <em>Wilkommenskultur</em> (welcome culture).</p>
<p>So, what&#8217;s changed?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4401 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-650x650.jpg" alt="2016-02-10 11.59.46" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-300x300.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>When the “refugee crisis” hit Germany last summer, hundreds of residents felt compelled to slather butter on rolls and pass them out to refugees arriving at train stations. This was by all accounts heart-warming and admirable, but it was also the easy part. The conversation we are having now is a more complicated one, one that even the seemingly simple question of whether to offer a female-only literacy class echoes:</p>
<p>What happens next and how might our society change as a result?</p>
<p>One could blame Cologne, but the foundation for this confrontation was laid long before. A staggering <a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article147280667/Fuer-die-meisten-gehoert-der-Islam-nicht-zu-Deutschland.html">60% of the country</a> is of the opinion that Islam does not belong in Germany. (It is also worth noting that Germans consistently overestimate the number of Muslims living in the country. The real figure, while one of the highest in the EU, <a href="http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2015/11/17/5-facts-about-the-muslim-population-in-europe/">is still only 5.8%</a>.)</p>
<p>There is an underlying preconception in Germany, as in many Western countries, that Islam is synonymous with misogyny and a lack of female rights. That “<a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article149756193/Wie-Sumtes-Wutbuerger-lernten-Fluechtlinge-zu-lieben.html">according to their religion, women are nothing</a>” or even more extreme, that &#8220;<a href="http://www.vice.com/de/read/fluechtlinge-vergewaltigen-deutsche-kinder-wie-rassisten-versuchen-stimmung-gegen-alle-nicht-deutschen-zu-machen-775">these young men will come and rape our daughters</a>&#8220;. This preconception likely stems from a variety of factors: images we see in the media, politicians portraying Muslims as backward or extremist, or current conflicts within the Middle East. An argument heard less often is made by <a href="http://ideas.time.com/2013/11/01/do-muslim-women-need-saving/">Columbia University Professor Lila Abu-Lughod</a>, who explores the conflation of religion and socioeconomic status. Gender inequality within Muslim majority societies stems mainly from economic inequality, and migrants in Germany have traditionally been low-skilled. Therefore what we may label as clashes due to religion may have stronger roots in poverty and lack of opportunity.</p>
<p>Earlier this year in Berlin, <a href="http://www.rbb-online.de/politik/beitrag/2016/04/berlin-kopftuch-streit-vor-arbeitsgericht-keine-guetliche-einigung.html">a young teacher went to court</a> because she was denied a teaching post due to her headscarf (the case was thrown out on grounds of the state&#8217;s Neutrality Act). More recently in Switzerland, a <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-36382596">regional authority ruled</a> that two teenage brothers must shake the hands of their female teachers despite it being against their religious beliefs to touch women they are not related to. Traditionally receiving societies such as Germany are perpetually learning how to manage integration in the face of growing diversity. Unfortunately, we seem insistent on concentrating on how &#8220;their values&#8221; may threaten &#8220;ours&#8221;, rather than on what type of society we want to live in together.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4406 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-02-17 12.07.15" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>To be fair, my own engagement at the Rathaus has not come without challenges. On my first day teaching, I swallowed a lot of frustration as another volunteer and I watched the women turn to their husbands for approval before following us to class. <em>Nur Frauen</em> (&#8220;only women&#8221;), we tried to communicate to the more skeptical looking of the men with a smile, while I stifled the urge to roll my eyes.</p>
<p>We&#8217;ve also heard a host of disturbing stories by way of the interpreters. Rape, abuse, threats of divorce. Some stories are from Afghanistan while others allegedly took place here in Berlin. At times, I am ashamed to find myself relieved that I can&#8217;t talk to the women directly about what I&#8217;ve heard, for fear it might affect the way I interact with them. For now, our exchanges are limited to topics like telling time and types of fruit &#8211; they&#8217;re big fans of banana and pineapple &#8211; as well as the apparently always shocking and never boring topic of me being a 30 year old woman without a husband or children (some of my students have 6, 7, even 9 children).</p>
<p>But until we&#8217;re able to have those more in-depth conversations, I remain convinced that offering a class under imperfect circumstances is better than offering no women&#8217;s class at all. For what, I&#8217;ve asked myself, will give these women more independence than the ability to navigate the city on their own? And what will give them a better chance of being able to navigate the city on their own than the ability to read and write?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4405 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-04-20 10.14.53" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Nothing exhibited this more clearly to me than a few weeks ago, when we held an arts project week for our women. The week consisted of two trips to separate parks so they could learn about various plant types and practice drawing them. The excitement of the women was palpable. They got to have a Middle Eastern picnic, a real treat after months of bland cafeteria fare. They got to pick flowers in the woods to take back to the home. There was laughing, there was dancing, and there were so many selfies.</p>
<p>We later found out through interpreters that, for several of the women, it was their first time in a park without a husband or male relative.</p>
<p>At the end of the week, a local artist took the womens&#8217; drawings and stenciled them onto power boxes near the Rathaus. On the Friday, we took a stroll around the neighborhood together to see them for the first time. The Farsi-speaking volunteer asked the women to point out their drawings and explain why they chose to draw them specifically. &#8220;Who drew this?&#8221; she asked when we got to the second box, pointing to a beautiful palm tree. &#8220;Me,&#8221; answered one of our students, &#8220;I drew it because it reminds me of home. And if you cut off the head, the whole plant dies.&#8221;</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The Frauenraum at Rathaus Wilmersdorf is looking for volunteers. To get involved, sign up at https://volunteer-planner.org/.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>For another take on the headscarf, I recommend watching <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/video/2015/jun/24/hijab-not-oppression-feminist-statement-video">this Guardian video</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>All photos my own.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: Four Hours at Lageso</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2015 00:01:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bureaucracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moabit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4145</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is Lageso (Das Landesamt für Gesundheit und Soziales), the State Office for Health and Social Affairs. This is Berlin's primary registration center for the initial reception of asylum seekers. This is Germany's most infamous symbol of the refugee crisis. Two days prior I had signed up to volunteer on a website called Volunteer Planner. After a cursory registration process, a click of a button was all it took to commit to a shift at a registration center, refugee home, or other institution in the city where help is needed (read: basically everywhere).  ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4323 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-650x319.png" alt="boys_lageso" width="650" height="319" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-650x319.png 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-300x147.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>A curly-haired two year old hangs from my hip. His modest number of pounds start to wear on my side as I spin us back and forth in the narrow space. By some stroke of luck he has yet to start crying (this doesn&#8217;t last). He giggles, bouncing up and down, as if we are playing a game. &#8220;He seems to like you,&#8221; a volunteer next to me looks on and smiles, &#8220;almost like he wants to go home with you.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;He may have to,&#8221; I mutter in response. It has been a long ten minutes since I last saw his mother. I try desperately to remember her face &#8211; or at least the color of her headscarf. My voice starts to crack and I realize in horror a cold is coming on (&#8220;Am I infecting hundreds of refugees?&#8221;). A few minutes later we find her, a pair of black shoes in her hands. She holds them up proudly and points to herself. We are only supposed to be finding clothes for her son and she knows it, but I let her take the shoes and boy (now crying), and go.</p>
<p>Curly-haired boy and his mother are my latest charges from the never-ending mass of parents and children waiting to be accompanied down the hallway of donated clothing. This group is only a microcosm of the larger crowd waiting outside in the evening twilight where volunteers pass out hot tea and coffee. Kids get <em>Kinderschokolade </em>and granola bars. The building entrance is guarded to ensure not everyone infiltrates the chaos at once.</p>
<p>Back inside, a winter jacket and pair of warm shoes are the big prizes. Our chief responsibility is to make sure each child walks out with just one of each. I negotiate with parents: &#8220;She can have that coat, but you&#8217;ll need to give me the one she&#8217;s wearing now.&#8221; When language fails, I make a trading gesture with my hands or remove the jacket from the child&#8217;s back myself. How quickly the urge to be generous is superseded by pragmatism (&#8220;Even <em>I</em> could get by with only one coat&#8221;).</p>
<p>&#8220;You have to be careful,&#8221; a middle-aged female volunteer warns me as I re-fold a stack of jeans, &#8220;Roma families sneak in to take clothing and then sell it at the flea market.&#8221; I nod but am at a loss as to what to do with the information. Is she advocating that we start using racial profiling? Regardless of the Roma, some families may have already taken their turn down the hallway. Others could be successfully registered and in possession of their <a href="http://www.euronews.com/2015/09/16/which-european-countries-offer-the-most-social-benefits-to-migrants/">monthly stipend</a>. There&#8217;s really no way to tell.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4321 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_0599" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Our makeshift shopping strip consists of one narrow hallway and a back room for sorting and storage. On either side of the hallway are smaller rooms the size of coat checks, one holding clothing for adults and the other medicine and hygienic articles. It is very cramped. Fathers plea with volunteers for their family&#8217;s turn down the hallway. Once in, mothers rip clothing off hangers to hold up to their children and approximate size. Some kids are fussy about colors; others peer up with wide eyes and tightly pressed lips. Volunteers buzz by in a flurry of aspired productivity and surveillance, their name-tags as frayed as their nerves.</p>
<p>A cameraman waltzes in with his crew. The bright lens focuses on me as I kneel down to re-velcro a young boy&#8217;s shoes. We have yet to find boots that fit; these blue sandals are the ones in which he arrived to Germany, completely ill-suited for the looming winter. We both turn, squint, and smile anyway. This is the shot they want, and they are gone within the minute.</p>
<p>This is Lageso (<em>Das Landesamt </em><span class="st"><em>für Gesundheit und Soziales)</em>, the State Office for Health and Social Affairs</span>. This is <span class="st">Berlin&#8217;s primary registration center for the initial reception of asylum seekers. This is Germany&#8217;s most infamous symbol of the refugee crisis.</span></p>
<p>Two days prior I had signed up to volunteer on a website called <a href="https://volunteer-planner.org/">Volunteer Planner</a>. After a cursory registration process, a click of a button was all it took to commit to a shift at a registration center, refugee home, or other institution in the city where help is needed (read: basically everywhere).  An impressive resource to get people engaged quickly, though seemingly lacking any accountability for volunteers who fail to show up or for organizations advertising shifts that fall through or no longer exist (the day before I was turned away from a home in Schöneberg because the coordinator was not present).</p>
<p>In addition to locations, one can select specific tasks. This is an all-hands-on-deck scenario and there is something for everyone, from Arabic and Farsi interpretation (in high demand) to kitchen assistance and coffee distribution. At Lageso, I sign up to be a <em>Springer/in </em>or &#8220;Jumper&#8221;, who, according to the website, &#8220;helps wherever is most needed, is assigned to a team, and will be led by hand to their task.&#8221;</p>
<p>But upon arrival I am not assigned to a team nor led anywhere, let alone by hand. After finding a sticker on which to scribble my name, I walk around aimlessly until a smiley blond girl takes pity on me and leads me to the storage room. A few minutes later I am with a new girl who is in a room within this room, sorting through boxes of clothing donations in the dark. I glance at the heaps of dusty sweaters and immediately regret not having brought my allergy medicine.</p>
<p>We start unpacking boxes of blankets. &#8220;Is there somewhere specific we should put these?&#8221; I ask my sorting partner. She shrugs. &#8220;On those shelves, I think,&#8221; she says, pointing to the overstuffed racks behind us. Ten minutes later, another volunteer: &#8220;No, don&#8217;t unpack the blankets,&#8221; he instructs us in a mix of German and English. &#8220;Put them in a corner so we can take them to a refugee home later.&#8221;</p>
<p>I give up on the blankets and turn my attention to the clothes. Thankfully, some boxes are categorized, and I pick up one marked &#8220;children&#8221;. I plan to sort the contents and add them to the shelves, which are loosely organized by gender and size. In one pair of pants I notice a bulge in the pocket and pull out a knife. I pass it along to a guy with a clipboard who looks like he knows what he is doing. He turns and sets it on another shelf, near a box of children&#8217;s toys.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4322 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_0600" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>I&#8217;m finally getting into a groove when another volunteer comes up behind me, visibly frustrated. &#8220;I spent days putting this together and now everyone&#8217;s destroying it,&#8221; she complains to clipboard guy, motioning to the overflowing shelves. He glances up over his glasses. &#8220;We&#8217;ll discuss it at Monday&#8217;s meeting,&#8221; he promises. I don&#8217;t know what I&#8217;ve done wrong, but I am sure of two things: We are all working on top of one another and there is no one in charge.</p>
<p>When the refugee crisis became front page news this past summer, thousands of Germany&#8217;s residents jumped to provide clothing and supplies, offer short-term housing solutions, or pass out sandwiches to refugees as they poured into train stations around the country. Many continue to help, some using vacation days to do so. On a civilian level, the outpouring of support in Germany has been heart-warming, encouraging, even pride-inducing.</p>
<p>Charitable and non-profit initiatives also abound. Groups have launched fundraising efforts to help those in particularly dire situations, like this <a href="https://www.betterplace.org/de/projects/37503-hilfe-fur-familie-ahmed">Iraqi father who suffered a heart attack</a>. There are <a href="http://www.unhcr.org/5655d27f6.html">bike riding lessons</a> for women and <a href="http://www.abendblatt-berlin.de/2015/12/03/ein-zirkus-fuer-die-gute-sache/">circus activities</a> for kids. A local photographer has started a &#8220;<a href="https://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.400616063468410.1073741835.295071407356210&amp;type=3">Humans of Lageso&#8221; page</a> to shed light on individual refugee stories. Herbert Grönemeyer, a famous German singer, has <a href="http://www.stern.de/lifestyle/leute/lageso-in-berlin---herbert-groenemeyer-finanziert-waermebusse-fuer-fluechtlinge-6605406.html">financed heated buses</a> so those waiting to register at Lageso can take turns warming up.</p>
<p><span class="st">But civilian good-will and a display of <span class="st"><em>Willkommenskultur</em></span> (welcome culture) can only go so far in serving the approximately 800,000 asylum seekers that Germany will receive this year &#8211; a figure that is <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/sep/06/refugee-crisis-germany-response-heartwarming-will-pressures-show">more a projection than a guest list</a>. What some in Berlin may call growing pains in learning to accommodate unprecedented waves of refugees, others deem a failure of the system and local leadership. German towns such as Passau, a Bavarian town of 50,000, have cited <a href="http://nmd.bn02750.bethemd.wayport.net/index.adp?MacAddr=68%3aA8%3a6D%3a4B%3a7A%3a8C&amp;IpAddr=10.128.29.239&amp;Ip6Addr=&amp;vsgpId=&amp;vsgId=41975&amp;UserAgent=&amp;ProxyHost=&amp;TunnelIfId=95270&amp;VlanId=20">much more success in handling the inflow</a>.</span></p>
<p><span class="st">The press have reported on the turbulent conditions at Lageso ad nauseam, both locally and <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/11/27/world/europe/germany-berlin-migrants-refugees.html?_r=0">internationally</a>. Refugees wait for weeks if not months to be registered. They line up for hours each day, often beginning the night before. People sleep in the streets. Most don&#8217;t receive enough to eat and drink. Heated tents were only made available <a href="http://www.stilinberlin.de/2015/12/fugeela-refugees-in-berlin-6-html.html">a few days ago</a>. &#8220;Refugee crisis? More like bureaucratic crisis!&#8221; protesters chanted <a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/1678473329031122/">on November 29th</a>, calling the local government to action. Understaffed and overworked employees have anonymously <a href="http://www.rbb-online.de/politik/thema/fluechtlinge/berlin/2015/12/lageso-innenansichten-mitarbeiter.html">detailed the on-going chaos</a> to the press. On December 10th, the Head of Lageso, Franz Allert, was <a href="http://www.focus.de/politik/deutschland/migration-lageso-chef-tritt-zurueck_id_5143744.html">pushed into resignation</a>. </span></p>
<p>Curly-haired boy and his mom are back outside, but at least now with warmer feet and some chocolate in their bellies. I pull my phone out of my pocket: three and a half hours have passed. There isn&#8217;t an eight hour work day in recent memory I can remember having been more exhausting. Admiration for the other volunteers &#8211; many of whom do this regularly, including night shifts &#8211; rushes within me. As does panic. The support is incredible, but is it sustainable?</p>
<p>We need to get this right, and not just in the short-term.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By<strong> Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>For up to date information in English on the refugee situation in Berlin, we recommend reading the <a href="http://www.stilinberlin.de/?s=FuGeeLa">FuGeeLa updates</a> by Stil in Berlin. <a href="http://www.findingberlin.com/how-to-help-refugees-in-berlin-winter-2015/">Finding Berlin</a> also provides comprehensive resources for how to help. </em></p>
<p><em>To sign up for volunteer shifts in Berlin, try <a href="https://volunteer-planner.org/helpdesk/">Volunteer Planner</a> (in German) or look for opportunities through <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">Give Something Back to Berlin</a> (in English). <a href="http://moabit-hilft.com/">MoabitHilft</a> is very engaged at Lageso and many of the regular volunteers at the center are affiliated with this organization.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>If you are donating clothing to refugee homes, please do your best to package them by type (e.g. age and size) and consider buying socks which are often in short supply. Even better: check first with the home to see what is most needed!</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: &#8220;I&#8217;m a Human Being&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 11:21:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Austria]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[family]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Taiwan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vienna]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4019</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Vienna. Seat of the former Austro-Hungarian Empire. Widely considered the gateway to Eastern Europe. Home to a United Nations headquarters and numerous international companies and universities. The Austrian capital has long been a city of immigration – even when politics have told a different story – and a staggering 50% of the population has what’s referred to as a “migration background”. So it’s not as if I expected Vienna to not be multicultural...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_4028" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4028" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4028 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-650x581.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender" width="650" height="581" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-650x581.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-300x268.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender.jpg 728w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4028" class="wp-caption-text">Sophia, Christina, and Suzi at the 2015 Vienna Pride Parade</p></div>
<p>Vienna. Seat of the former Austro-Hungarian Empire. Widely considered the gateway to Eastern Europe. Home to a United Nations headquarters and numerous international companies and universities. The Austrian capital has long been a city of immigration – even when politics have told a different story – and a staggering <a href="https://www.wien.gv.at/english/social/integration/basic-work/facts-figures.html">50% of the population</a> has what’s referred to as a “migration background”.</p>
<p>So it’s not as if I expected Vienna to <em>not</em> be multicultural.</p>
<p>What I didn’t expect when <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/03/23/lens-on-leaving-homes/">moving to Vienna from Berlin</a> was to encounter some of the most fascinating “mixes” of my life: A half-Indian, half-Italian who grew up in the US and lives in Vienna with her half-Austrian, half-French boyfriend? A Chinese-American who fell in love with her German boyfriend in Hong Kong? A half-Austrian, half-Sicilian who met her Indian husband in London? The combinations are unexpected, beautiful, and dare I say, collidoscopic? (And their potential future children even more so).</p>
<div id="attachment_4031" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4031" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4031 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-650x475.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(3)" width="650" height="475" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-650x475.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-300x219.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4031" class="wp-caption-text">Christina poses with a cow in Austria on a family roadtrip</p></div>
<p>Christina, the first close friend I made in Vienna, is no different. Born in Taiwan to a Taiwanese mother and Austrian father, at age three her family moved to San Jose, California, where her younger brother was born. Kindergarten was spent in Vienna, where she lived with her father and grandparents while mom and brother stayed in the US. At age six the entire family moved to Taiwan for four years. Then it was back west to Seattle from ages 10-16 where Christina spent the longest stretch of her childhood, what she calls her &#8220;most formative years&#8221;. Her last two years of high school were completed in Taipei, where she graduated with the globally recognized International Baccalaureate Diploma.</p>
<p>“I was missing roots as a kid, our family was always bouncing around,&#8221; she tells me.</p>
<p>This triangular ping ponging between nations resulted in three different passport combinations within a family of four: Christina’s brother, born in the US, is a dual Austrian-American citizen but “avoids Austria now because of the mandatory military service.” Mom is dual Taiwanese-Austrian, “but never felt completely comfortable in Austria”. And Christina and her father are purely Austrian, on paper anyway.</p>
<p>&#8220;A long time ago my dad had the chance to become an American citizen but decided against it,&#8221; she says smirking, &#8220;He&#8217;s a proud Austrian.”</p>
<div id="attachment_4057" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4057" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4057 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_9365" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4057" class="wp-caption-text">Christina with her parents in Taiwan</p></div>
<p>It is to her father and his “pride” that Christina attributes her last 16 years in Vienna. &#8220;My dream was to go to Georgetown [University],&#8221; Christina tells me one warm evening in the <em>Museumsquartier</em>, her fingers tapping the stem of her <em>Hugospritz</em>. &#8220;I applied and got in… my mom supported it, but my dad kept saying I had to go to university in Austria. It was always really important to him that, as the oldest child, I embrace my Austrian roots.&#8221;</p>
<p>Christina ended up moving to Vienna against her will: “I didn&#8217;t have any connection to Austria at that time other than having spent the occasional summer there with my grandparents.” The first year, she expressed her anger by skipping class in favor of exploring the city and having fun.</p>
<p>“And then I got pregnant,” she says laughing, “the biggest rebellion of all!”</p>
<div id="attachment_4059" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4059" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4059 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371-650x650.jpg" alt="IMG_9371" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4059" class="wp-caption-text">Mother-daughter surfing trip in Morocco</p></div>
<p>Christina’s daughter Illeana (Illy) was born when she was 20. She raised Illy as a single mother while completing her degrees in Economics and Sinology, with “lots of help” from friends with similar bi-cultural backgrounds. She counts half-Austrian friends from South Africa and Bolivia among her closest, along with a half-Kosovan, half-Czech hair salon owner named Suzi. “None of us knew what we were doing… it was experimental parenting. I think if I raised a child now I’d be much more nervous!”</p>
<p>After making it over the hump of her first year, Vienna started to feel like home. “I began to realize how much I love it here,” Christina reflects. Now one could say Christina is as Austrian as they come. Her German is flawless and chock full of colloquialisms, she sings along to Austrian <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schlager_music">Schlager</a></em>, and her drink of choice is the ubiquitous <em><a href="http://austrianwineusa.com/2013/12/20/12-days-of-austrian-wine-enjoy-a-gspritzer/">Weisser Spritzer</a></em>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4064" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4064" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4064 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-650x602.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(7)" width="650" height="602" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-650x602.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-300x278.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7.jpg 701w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4064" class="wp-caption-text">Christina skiing in Kaprun, Austria</p></div>
<p>None of that, however, stops her from craving Taiwanese ‘Three-Cups Chicken’ or her favorite American cereal, ‘Lucky Charms’. “I’m biracial and tri-cultural,” she states without hesitation. And while rewarding on personal and professional levels (she’s also fluent in Mandarin), Christina’s background has not gone unchallenged in a city that still struggles to see itself as a place of migration and diversity.</p>
<p>Christina has encountered countless variations of the “<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/">But where are you <em>really</em> from?</a>” question over the years. “When I first got to Vienna, there were fewer minorities and diversity didn&#8217;t work very well,” she remarks, “I remember meeting one guy who could not comprehend why I looked the way I did but had a very common German last name,&#8221; she rolls her eyes at the memory. &#8220;I literally had to spell it out for him by saying, &#8216;If you, an Austrian, had a baby with a Taiwanese woman, the result would be me!’”</p>
<div id="attachment_4034" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4034" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4034 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-650x488.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(6)" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4034" class="wp-caption-text">Christina&#8217;s 3rd Birthday in Los Angeles, California</p></div>
<p>This phenomenon isn’t limited to Vienna. In Japan, a newly crowned biracial beauty queen has been fielding questions on a regular basis about what parts of her are “Japanese”. <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/30/world/asia/biracial-beauty-queen-strives-for-change-in-mono-ethnic-japan.html">“But I am a Japanese,”</a> is her response. On the other side of the world, in the US, Rachel Dolezal was recently exposed for her elaborate deception as a Black woman – a &#8220;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/18/opinion/charles-blow-the-delusions-of-dolezal.html?smid=fb-share">one-directional privilege</a>&#8221; that could never have been successful the other way around, due to socially constructed perceptions of race. The recurring theme? If you are one drop of minority, we will question your Belonging to the majority.</p>
<p>Christina acknowledges that even she is not immune to societal attitudes about migrants in Austria. &#8220;I&#8217;ve learned that, in Austria, migrants get classified into &#8216;good&#8217; and &#8216;bad&#8217;,&#8221; she explains.</p>
<p>&#8220;Asians are considered ‘good’ because they’re quiet, stay out of trouble, and work hard. Turkish people are unpopular because a lot of them refuse to adapt to the Austrian way of life and bring hordes of family members over, all the while claiming benefits from the Austrian government. Blacks have it the worst, though, probably because they stand out the most and are still viewed by many locals as low-lifes and drug dealers.&#8221;</p>
<div id="attachment_4029" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4029" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4029 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-650x472.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(1)" width="650" height="472" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-650x472.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-300x218.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4029" class="wp-caption-text">Christina riding a (fake) bull at Glacier National Park, Montana</p></div>
<p>While Christina is well aware that the US has its own challenges regarding diversity, she does view it as more progressive: “In the US, people at least get it when you tell them that you&#8217;re biracial.”</p>
<p>It was 1999 when Christina was last in the US, before Illy&#8217;s birth and before the 9/11 attacks. While she’s now seriously considering a move back, it&#8217;s unclear when she will be able to. Christina is not a US citizen and needs a green card. Her most recent attempt at the <a href="http://travel.state.gov/content/visas/english/immigrate/diversity-visa/instructions.html">Diversity Visa Lottery</a> was unsuccessful. “My dad told me he is reconsidering becoming an American citizen just so that he can help get us over there,” Christina recently shared. <a href="http://www.migrationpolicy.org/article/family-reunification">Family reunification</a> is one of the four major pathways for foreigners to become legal residents of the US.</p>
<p>Legal challenges are also not Christina’s only concern. “Sometimes I worry that people in the US will annoy me with their ignorance,” she says laughing. At the same time, she is drawn to the lifestyle. She observes her American friends move to houses with pools, which, compared to Viennese city apartments, seem like mansions. Illy, a recovering Justin Bieber addict who recently graduated to a One Direction obsession, is thrilled with the prospect. “A typical Austrian teenager,” Christina chuckles.</p>
<p>You could call Christina many things: A transnational, an immigrant, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">a third-culture kid</a>, a foreigner, a native, an expat. But none of these categories really fit given the fluidity of her upbringing and identity. We use labels to establish connections and try to make sense of things, but they can also dilute the intricacy and beauty of reality.</p>
<p>&#8220;I&#8217;m not 100% of anything,&#8221; is how Christina describes it. &#8220;Sometimes when people ask what I am, I just answer that I&#8217;m a human being.&#8221;</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Photos provided by Christina and Sophia.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: On Leaving Home(s)</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/03/23/lens-on-leaving-homes/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 15:32:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[family]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vienna]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3869</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Last month, Kelly wrote about the implications of "collecting ourselves" to make a move back home. While wrought with complications in its own right, returning to where one grew up, has family, or holds full political and legal rights is a move that Makes Sense. One chapter closes, and however painful or messy, the next begins...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3881 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-650x487.jpg" alt="2014-11-16 13.46.44" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Last month, Kelly wrote about the implications of &#8220;<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/02/13/lens-leaving-berlin/">collecting ourselves</a>&#8221; to make a move back home. While wrought with complications in its own right, returning to where one grew up, has family, or holds full political and legal rights is a move that Makes Sense. One chapter closes, and however painful or messy, the next begins.</p>
<p>After graduate school, I started losing the ability to picture my life in chapters. My decisions were no longer dictated by a series of steps culminating in clear milestones. I suddenly felt accosted by the need to figure out what I wanted to Do and Be&#8230; this time for the long run. And, given my international experiences and dual citizenship, the question of &#8220;What&#8221; promptly extended to one of &#8220;Where&#8221;.</p>
<p>So I moved to Berlin.</p>
<p>When I booked my flight to Germany in fall 2011, &#8220;two years&#8221; was my default timeline. &#8220;A couple years,&#8221; I responded confidently when someone asked how long I planned to be gone. &#8220;I should give the job a good two years,&#8221; I thought when I got hired six months in. &#8220;We&#8217;ll all still be here at least two more years,&#8221; I reassured myself about my circle of expat* friends another six months after that.</p>
<p>How foolish I was, to believe that two years would ever be enough. How <span class="st">naïve</span>,<em> </em>to assume there would be a clear demarcation between this chapter and the next.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3885 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-650x487.jpg" alt="2015-01-31 14.28.03-1" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Now almost three and a half years in, I feel firmly entrenched in my world of bilingual conversations, narrow streets, weekend jaunts around the continent, ubiquitous public transport, social welfare nets, and crusty bread. But these roots of mine are flighty. They wiggle at something as simple as a chat with a friend back home, when she catches me up on her life and I realize how much I&#8217;ve missed. When my sister or father leaves for the airport after a visit, they are pulled halfway out of the earth and end up lodged in the middle of my throat. Every time I get on a plane and head back across the ocean, a part of me fears they will be ripped out entirely. Because no matter how long I stay in Europe and embrace the rights my German passport affords me, I will always also be American. No matter how incredible a life I build for myself on this side of the Atlantic, there will always be a Life Back Home.</p>
<p>I was not aware of how much I had internalized this feeling until last summer, when my mother and I visited relatives in northwestern Germany. Sipping coffee on a sunny terrace, a family friend commented, &#8220;I could never do what you&#8217;re doing, be so far away from my family&#8230; I&#8217;m too close to them.&#8221; My reaction to her declaration was nothing short of primal. Of course I missed my family! Of course I felt close to them! I was not away <em>because</em> of, but rather, <em>in spite of</em> them &#8211; an unpleasant reality I struggle with on a near daily basis.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3892 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-650x518.jpg" alt="11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n" width="650" height="518" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-650x518.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-300x239.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Modern advances in travel and technology have enabled more and more people to adopt lifestyles fueled by wanderlust and adventure. But not all of us who leave home are <a href="http://elitedaily.com/life/culture/wanderlust-like-travel-much-no-real-home/959705/">perpetual wanderers with nomadic spirits</a>. Some of us are searching for somewhere to settle. Some of us are even surprised to find ourselves making a life away from where we grew up, away from the ones we love. I know I am.</p>
<p>I consider myself, by nature, to be a sensitive homebody. I crave being close to the people I love and place great importance on maintaining my relationships, both near and far. This explains why any time I am &#8220;away&#8221;, my pack mentality kicks in and I seek out a local community almost immediately. But I concurrently possess the intrinsic need to push myself and explore. For me, this has meant travel. Whether I credit <a href="https://psychologyblogaimee.wordpress.com/2013/12/04/wanderlust-a-genetic-basis-to-a-globetrotting-fanatic/">genetics</a> for this (nope) or my international upbringing, mixed with a little courage and a lot of privilege (that&#8217;s more like it), is not the point. The ups and downs of living somewhere other than where I grew up have become an integral part of my identity and understanding of growth and independence. They just don&#8217;t make the leaving part any easier.</p>
<p>The thing is, leaving is rarely the easy choice, even with the prospect of Something Great on the other side.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3887 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-650x487.jpg" alt="2015-02-21 16.37.36-1" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>While I never expected moving to Berlin to be easy, I did anticipate a gradual ease, and more importantly, clarity, with time. Reality proved instead to be emphatically non-linear. Rough patches hit me sporadically and without warning. My homesickness became a swelling wave, pulling in and out of shore, threatening at its peak to wash me out entirely. What if this chapter never ended? What if I never left my new home and went back to my old one? And now that I live in Vienna, my current home because of work, is my &#8220;old home&#8221; Washington, DC or Berlin? In countless discussions with fellow expat friends on the topics of home and belonging, the resounding theme has been similar: one of overwhelming choice and uncertainty.</p>
<p>A couple months ago, Kelly and I were at a close friend&#8217;s 30th birthday dinner in Berlin. Huddled in the kitchen over bottles of Spanish Temperanillo and mismatched plates of pizza and crudit<span class="st">és</span>, someone proposed we guess where the birthday boy would be 30 years from now. We had plenty of ideas for the &#8220;What&#8221;: running his own cooking school, teaching his kids how to do science experiments, maintaining his impressive beard. It was on the &#8220;Where&#8221; that we got stuck. &#8220;Italy?&#8221; we posed as the obvious choice (where he&#8217;s from). He resolutely shook his head &#8220;no&#8221;. &#8220;Germany?&#8221; He shrugged his shoulders, unsure &#8211; just like the majority of us in the room about our own futures.</p>
<p>Once you&#8217;ve opened yourself up to the world and seen first-hand that you can live, and maybe even thrive, somewhere else, it becomes increasingly difficult to know when or where to stop searching. The list of potential Something Greats becomes never-ending. And with it, the accompanying list of goodbyes.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By</em> <strong><em>Sophia Burton</em></strong></p>
<p>*My choice of the term &#8220;expat&#8221; was deliberate, as it popularly denotes migrants with privilege and mobility. For more on &#8220;expat&#8221; vs. &#8220;immigrant&#8221;, check out <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/global-development-professionals-network/2015/mar/13/white-people-expats-immigrants-migration?CMP=fb_gu">this Guardian article</a>.</p>
<p><em>All photos taken by me, in Vienna and Berlin.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: &#8220;I&#8217;m not Turkish, but my husband is&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[love]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tunisia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1251</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In a capital city marked by transformation and transience, where people are perpetually coming and going, it can feel like a true rarity to meet someone actually from that city. “H” was my first Berlin friend from Berlin. We met through a language website, after she sent me a request to practice French in exchange for German. H was working on her degree to become a French teacher. I was still new to the city and could count my local friends on one hand...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_3811" style="width: 733px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://jurigottschau.com/"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3811" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3811 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz.jpg" alt="grillplatz" width="723" height="482" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz.jpg 723w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 723px) 100vw, 723px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3811" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p style="text-align: left;">In a capital city marked by transformation and transience, where people are perpetually coming and going, it can feel like a true rarity to meet someone actually <em>from</em> that city.</p>
<p>&#8220;H&#8221; was my first Berlin friend from Berlin. We met through a language website, after she sent me a request to practice French in exchange for German. H was working on her degree to become a French teacher. I was still new to the city and could count my local friends on one hand. The first time we hung out was in February 2012 at a cafe under the <em>Savignyplatz S-Bahn</em> arches. H ended up helping me with my research on teacher quality in Germany, and I gave her tips for her upcoming study abroad program in France. Soon enough our linguistic meet-ups evolved into a friendship that waved off grammar practice in favor of relaxed Sunday afternoon coffee dates.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Our relationship also became a kind of exchange of culinary cultures. I started joining her annually to break the fast during Ramadan. As the resident atheist I wouldn&#8217;t fast before these meals. Yet I&#8217;d still be the one gnawing away at my fingers until sundown, while H and her sisters waited patiently for their first sips of rose flavored water and soup drizzled with fresh lemon juice. In return, H  joined my international crew of friends for her first Thanksgiving dinner, initiated into the world of cranberry sauce, candied sweet potatoes, and general American gluttony. Her contribution &#8211; mounds of Turkish <em>Lahmacun</em> (spiced lamb pizza) &#8211; was eagerly divvied up like party favors at the end of the night.</p>
<div id="attachment_3611" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3611" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3611 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340-650x650.jpg" alt="IMG_3340" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3611" class="wp-caption-text">Ramadan dinner with H</p></div>
<p style="text-align: left;">It didn&#8217;t take long for us to discover our mutual fascination with questions of citizenship and identity. We attended several events together on the topic and often spent our cafe time discussing our hybrid families and understanding of <em>Deutschsein</em> or &#8220;Germanness&#8221;. See, while H is a true <em>Berlinerin</em> &#8211; she was born and grew up here &#8211; her parents are from Tunisia. We shared the feeling of having more than one home; while I straddled the Atlantic, H had a foot on either side of the Mediterranean. But unlike me, H had grown up with the challenge of having to persistently defend her Germanness, to the wider community and to her own parents.</p>
<p>In countries like Germany that are still embracing their multicultural identities &#8211; Germany first recognized itself as a country of immigration in 2005 &#8211; too many still have a binary understanding of native vs. foreigner that acknowledges bloodlines over birthplace and physical appearance over personal identity. There remains a habit of probing those who look &#8220;different&#8221; about their roots, otherwise known as the dreaded &#8220;But where are you <em>really</em> from?&#8221; <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/">question</a>. Those on the receiving end of this question are often referred to as the &#8220;perpetual foreigner&#8221;, ethnic minorities who will always be seen as the “other” because of how they look.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">In H&#8217;s case, it didn&#8217;t take long to notice that the vast majority of those she came across assumed she was Turkish, including other Turkish-Germans. &#8220;Oh right, the Turkish one,&#8221; a girl on her basketball team responded, when I introduced myself as H&#8217;s friend. H once told me she gets asked if she&#8217;s Turkish more than her best friend, an actual Turkish-German who happens to be blond and fair-skinned.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3697 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-650x487.jpg" alt="2014-01-19 17.26.48" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>The confusion isn&#8217;t all too surprising, considering H&#8217;s darker features, for one, and the demographics of the city, for two. Turkish-Germans are the city&#8217;s largest ethnic minority and the largest community of Turks outside of Turkey. Estimates of the number of Turks in Berlin range from 200,000-500,000 (a combination of those with Turkish passports, partial Turkish ancestry, and ethnic minorities from Turkey). A far cry from the approximately <a href="http://www.berlin.de/lb/intmig/statistik/demografie/einwohner_staatsangehoerigkeit.html">1,500 Tunisian nationals</a> in Berlin.</p>
<p>The story of H&#8217;s parents also mirrors that of many Turkish-Germans. They immigrated to the city separately as part of a guest-worker program in the 1970s and met on the job at corporate giant, Siemens. Originally, they planned to return to Tunisia together. The couple worked 2-3 jobs, sending remittances to family in Tunisia to save up to build a house there. They sent their 3 eldest daughters back for 9 years to live with relatives and go to school. But when Germany tightened family reunification laws in the 80&#8217;s, excluding those older than 16 without German citizenship, they brought the 3 girls back to Berlin to keep the family together, by then consisting of 5 daughters.</p>
<p>H is daughter number 4 and has only visited Tunisia on vacation. She admits that a distinction exists between the older and younger sisters, due to this geographic divide in upbringing, especially apparent in attitudes toward the headscarf and family planning. Her oldest sister &#8220;lives by the Qu&#8217;ran&#8221; and hopes to move back to Tunisia permanently one day. H, on the other hand, identifies as a &#8220;<em>Berlinerin</em> with Tunisian roots&#8221;; she has no intention of leaving Germany anytime soon.</p>
<div id="attachment_3791" style="width: 657px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3791" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3791 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg" alt="htunisia" width="647" height="484" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg 647w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia-300x224.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 647px) 100vw, 647px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3791" class="wp-caption-text">H on vacation in Tunisia</p></div>
<p>When it comes to questions and comments about her being Turkish, I&#8217;ve only ever seen H respond with patience and grace. It&#8217;s the difficulties with her own parents, and especially mother, that affect her most. If you ask her about her upbringing, H will tell you that her parents were &#8220;pretty modern for immigrant standards&#8221;, letting her play sports and stay out with friends until 10pm. Sleepovers and clubs weren&#8217;t allowed, but H found ways around her parents&#8217; rules, such as working at social events like the <em>Volksfest </em>and later heading west to Dortmund for university.</p>
<p>Boyfriends, on the other hand, were out of the question. Particularly those outside of the Tunisian-German community. H dated a little in secret, but didn&#8217;t get serious with anyone until she met &#8220;A&#8221; at 19. At 28, A was almost a decade older and managing a series of internet cafes. The flirtation started small with jokes at the shop, building up slowly to weekend jogs together. Finally, A asked H out on a date.</p>
<p>H managed to keep the relationship hidden from her parents for 6 years. &#8220;I was sure they&#8217;d disapprove because he&#8217;s Turkish,&#8221; she explains. Even though both Tunisians and Turks in Germany are predominantly Muslim, H says it&#8217;s not uncommon for the older immigrant generations to be prejudiced against one another. &#8220;The Tunisians here think that all Turkish boys are in gangs, are loud and have no respect, and don&#8217;t achieve anything,&#8221; H claims; &#8220;Tunisians in Tunisia think more positively about Turks than Tunisians in Germany do.&#8221;</p>
<p>When she told her parents about the relationship in 2013, her mother threatened that H was &#8220;ruining her life&#8221; and that if she continued, they would disown her. &#8220;I haven&#8217;t even told them yet that A is Shiite,&#8221; H joked (her family is Sunni).</p>
<div id="attachment_3792" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3792" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3792 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-650x202.jpg" alt="A&amp;H" width="650" height="202" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-650x202.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-300x93.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3792" class="wp-caption-text">A &amp; H</p></div>
<p>According to H, the problem is her mother&#8217;s stubbornness more than anything else. But listening to the stories one can&#8217;t help but notice an underlying theme of fear, logical or not. A fear of losing one&#8217;s child. A fear of not relating to one&#8217;s grandchildren. A fear of the dilution of one&#8217;s cultural lineage over generations. &#8220;Many in the Tunisian-German community are scared that their kids will marry Turks and end up in Turkey,&#8221; H agrees, &#8220;my mother is also afraid her grandchildren will never learn Arabic.&#8221; H and her sisters speak strictly Tunisian Arabic with their parents. When just amongst each other, a mix of Arabic and German.</p>
<p>Language is just one question of many that H and A will face as parents. They have already decided that A will primarily speak Turkish and H mostly German, which she is more comfortable with than Arabic. They have even talked about where they will <em>really</em> end up one day. H tells me that the Tunisian consulate pays for the bodies of Tunisian nationals in Germany to be sent back for burials. A, who came to Berlin at 18 as a student, gave up his Turkish passport to become German.  As an entrepreneur he&#8217;s eager to launch projects in Turkey and maybe even retire there one day, but is limited without citizenship.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">After months of not seeing each other, H and I finally find time last November for one of our Sunday coffee dates. H arrives to the Italian cafe in an uncharacteristically bulky sweater that makes me raise my eyebrows. Shortly after ordering our lattes and chocolate cake, she spills the beans: she and A have gotten married, and she&#8217;s newly pregnant. The religious ceremony was held at their apartment with an Imam presiding and a handful of their closest friends and siblings present. H&#8217;s parents chose not to return early from their vacation in Tunisia to attend. As for their upcoming grandchild, wherever he or she decides to be &#8220;<em>really</em> from&#8221;, they are still in the dark.</p>
<p><em> &#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong> </em></p>
<p><em>&#8220;A&#8221; requested that this article remain anonymous, in order to not further weaken his cause, should H&#8217;s parents somehow come across it.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: Scotland and the question of borders</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/10/28/beyond-berlin-question-borders/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/10/28/beyond-berlin-question-borders/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2014 10:30:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Scotland]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3442</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Coming off an evening with Invisible Borders that was all about transcending boundaries, it was an eye-opening juxtaposition to visit a country that had just explored creating more stagnant borders of their own. This was to be my first trip to Scotland, but as I had visited England and Ireland in the past I wasn&#8217;t expecting much in the way of culture shock. I had heard something about an exotic concoction called Haggis, anticipated equal amounts difficulty and delight navigating the Scottish accent, and was prepared for plaid. Oh, and rain. Lots and lots of rain. So during my short stint in Edinburgh and the Highlands, I was especially interested to delve into what it was the Scots themselves believed distinguished them from the rest of the UK enough to merit separating themselves off with tighter borders. Did it really have anything to do with national identity, the sentiment conjured up by media images of teenagers covered in blue and white paint? Or was it really more for economic reasons, tied to access to finite resources like North Sea Oil? Scotland&#8217;s recent independence referendum, arising from a sweeping win by the Scottish National Party in the 2011 Parliament elections, was [...]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Coming off an evening with <a href="http://invisible-borders.com/">Invisible Borders</a> that was all about transcending boundaries, it was an eye-opening juxtaposition to visit a country that had just explored creating more stagnant borders of their own.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-11.58.20-11.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3507 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-11.58.20-11-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-06 11.58.20-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-11.58.20-11.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-11.58.20-11-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>This was to be my first trip to Scotland, but as I had visited England and Ireland in the past I wasn&#8217;t expecting much in the way of culture shock. I had heard something about an exotic concoction called <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haggis">Haggis</a>, anticipated equal amounts difficulty and delight navigating the Scottish accent, and was prepared for plaid. Oh, and rain. Lots and lots of rain. So during my short stint in Edinburgh and the Highlands, I was especially interested to delve into what it was the Scots themselves believed distinguished them from the rest of the UK enough to merit separating themselves off with tighter borders. Did it really have anything to do with national identity, the sentiment conjured up by media images of teenagers covered in blue and white paint? Or was it really more for economic reasons, tied to access to finite resources like North Sea Oil?</p>
<p>Scotland&#8217;s recent independence referendum, arising from a sweeping win by the Scottish National Party in the 2011 Parliament elections, was historic but not exceptional. Separatist movements exist all over the world, including the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/">people of Kurdistan</a> who make up a region of four Middle Eastern countries, Spain&#8217;s economic powerhouse, Catalonia, and Germany&#8217;s conservative southern state, Bavaria. Some may even surprise you &#8211; for example, Venice, where an <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2014/03/europes-latest-secession-movement-venice/284562/">unofficial referendum</a> in May of this year showed the vast majority in favor of secession from Italy. Supporters of more active movements around the globe watched closely as the Scots went to the polls this past September 18th, eager to follow suit or fuel their respective campaigns. The results held weight. After 55.3% of Scotland voted &#8220;no&#8221;, Catalonia cancelled their planned referendum, originally set for November 9th of this year.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.40.09-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3451 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.40.09-1-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-05 15.40.09-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.40.09-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.40.09-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>There are over 20 active separatist movements around the world, the majority in Europe and Asia. Of these, about a third are violent*, due primarily to ethnic and religious tensions. While some fight for human rights or religious freedom, others strive for economic power, control over resources, or wealth potential. The Scotland independence debate was rife with discussions about tax distribution, North Sea Oil, currency, and jobs. &#8220;Scotland is a very wealthy country &#8211; let&#8217;s make it feel like it!&#8221; proclaimed the homepage of the official &#8220;Yes Scotland&#8221; campaign. Meanwhile, Turkey&#8217;s Kurds have been engaged in armed struggle against the Turkish government since 1984, resulting in thousands of deaths. It is therefore an impossible and reductionist task to speak of secessionist movements as a homogenous entity. Yet regardless of the nature of the struggle &#8211; political, economic, social, ethnic, violent, peaceful, or a combination of the above &#8211; when one discusses borders, one is inherently embarking on a discussion about community, belonging, and identity.</p>
<p>As links between countries become stronger through migration, technology, economic trade, and political unions, the idea of separating oneself from the &#8220;global community&#8221; can appear unmodern, backward, even futile. &#8220;I voted no,&#8221; my Airbnb host, a documentary filmmaker originally from England, revealed as we strolled to the supermarket together my first night in rainy Edinburgh, &#8220;not because I&#8217;m against independence for the Scots, but because I believe in a borderless world.&#8221;</p>
<p>At the same time, retreating into a stronger sense of place and identity, as our world becomes more globalized, can feel almost like an instinctive reaction. An exercise in protection, preservation, even control. &#8220;It may have worked in the past, but the way the centralized government in London makes decisions for us now does not reflect who we are anymore,&#8221; my Highlands tour guide explained as we stood at the foot of Stirling Castle, &#8220;I just can&#8217;t be proud of a country that isn&#8217;t its own.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>Which begs the question: how can we embrace the inevitable (and often beneficial) changes that crossing and opening borders may bring, while simultaneously protecting what makes our home(s) &#8220;our own&#8221;?</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.42.39-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3452 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.42.39-1-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-05 15.42.39-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.42.39-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.42.39-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>For starters, the concept of a world with more open borders is conceivably less radical than many perceive it to be. &#8220;Open&#8221; does not mean &#8220;none&#8221;, nor does it mean a lawless world where people come and go as they please without screens or supervision. Within the field of migration, the concept of &#8220;open borders&#8221; generally refers to a reversal from what is, by default, an exclusionary policy, e.g. countries finding a reason to <em>let someone in. </em>Instead, the policy would switch to one of de facto inclusion, e.g. countries finding a reason to <em>keep someone out</em>. Reasons for excluding potential immigrants would lie more with criminal records and health concerns than they would with economic prospects or integration potential. Open borders is also not commensurate with the idea of open citizenship: in a world with open borders, countries could still deem individual qualifications and requirements for acquiring full citizenship rights.</p>
<p>The idea of open borders has gained traction in recent years (think &#8220;No Human is Illegal&#8221;) with the rise in global migration. Many see current immigration restrictions as inconsistent with basic egalitarian principles, such as equal opportunity, human rights, and moral obligations. On the more pragmatic end of the spectrum, there are those who advocate for open borders as a catalyst for economic growth and innovation, responding to phenomena such as lower birth rates and skilled worker shortages in more developed countries.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-13.22.05.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3450 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-13.22.05-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-05 13.22.05" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-13.22.05.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-13.22.05-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>But do questions about opening borders and globalization shifts weaken the importance of nationalism and identity? For many, despite the fact that we all interact with the global community in one form or another, place still matters most. A staggering 70% of those polled who voted &#8220;yes&#8221; to an independent Scotland claimed they did so because of &#8220;<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2014/sep/20/scottish-independence-lord-ashcroft-poll">the principle that all decisions about Scotland should be taken in Scotland</a>.&#8221;</p>
<p>This thinking was reflected in the voting demographics of the Scottish independence vote &#8211; eligible voters were only those currently residing in Scotland and Commonwealth or EU citizens. So while my Airbnb host was included despite being born in England, her Scottish friends living abroad were not (there are approximately <a href="http://worldpopulationreview.com/countries/scotland-population/">2 million Scots</a> living in other parts of the UK), nor were thousands of immigrant residents without the right passport.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-14.42.18-2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3478 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-14.42.18-2-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-06 14.42.18-2" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-14.42.18-2.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-14.42.18-2-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Although the official &#8220;yes&#8221; campaign in Scotland was largely pro-migration (<a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/scottish-independence/11035389/Scottish-immigration-has-to-increase-by-14000-to-meet-Salmond-target.html">mainly for economic reasons</a>) and may have adopted a more open policy than the rest of the UK, the independence vote brought up many questions about the future of migration and refugee policy, as well as citizenship laws. Who would be considered a citizen from &#8220;day one&#8221; of independence? What would the process be like for the foreign-born who wished to become citizens? What would dual citizenship policy look like for Scots living abroad? Would those living on the border, working on one side and living on the other, still have freedom of movement? What legal hurdles would immigrant families have to endure to visit family members spread out across the region?</p>
<p>As we lay out in <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/about/a-manifesto/">our manifesto</a>, borders hold meanings both conceptual and literal. They demarcate ideas of home and kinship as much as they do political, legal, and bureaucratic spaces. They bring people together around shared systems, laws, traditions, languages, and goals, but they also divide, separate, and limit. They influence and make statements about our engagement with local and global communities. They determine how seamlessly we can navigate having more than one home, a reality for an increasing number of us around the globe. But on the most basic level, for many, they simply represent what is possible and what isn&#8217;t.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>*Figures as of 2008. For a comprehensive account of the history of separatist movements and self-determination around the world, click <a href="http://online.sfsu.edu/swilcox/Swilcox/Shelleys_webpage_files/Wilcox,%20The%20Open%20Borders%20Debate%20on%20Immigration.pdf">here</a>.</p>
<p>For a shorter round-up on active secession movements, click <a href="http://www.dnaindia.com/world/report-7-separatist-movements-that-are-closely-watching-scotland-s-independence-referendum-2019372">here</a>.</p>
<p>All photos by yours truly from her recent trip to Edinburgh.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/10/28/beyond-berlin-question-borders/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: Ali for (and from) Germany</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/09/02/interview-ali-for-and-from-germany/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2014 08:27:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3183</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the wake of Germany's World Cup victory, much has been said about a renewed sense of German patriotism and its implications. While some have feared a connection to Germany's dark past, others have welcomed the discourse as a chance to shape a new sense of belonging within the country's evolving demographics. We've already written something about it here. But what a discussion on national identity means on the personal level is another story. Or rather many stories. Here's one...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the wake of Germany&#8217;s World Cup victory, much has been said about a renewed sense of German patriotism and its implications. While some have feared a connection to Germany&#8217;s dark past, others have welcomed the discourse as a chance to shape a new sense of belonging within the country&#8217;s evolving demographics. We&#8217;ve already written something about it <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/28/world-cup-fever-how-malleable-is-german-identity/">here</a>. But what a discussion on national identity means on the personal level is another story. Or rather many stories. Here&#8217;s one.</p>
<div id="attachment_3184" style="width: 439px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3184" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3184 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/ali.jpg" alt="Ali für Deutschland " width="429" height="429" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/ali.jpg 429w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/ali-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 429px) 100vw, 429px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3184" class="wp-caption-text">Ali at the Germany-France game at Train Cocktailbar</p></div>
<p>It took Ali <span class="gD">Riza Gürbüz over 30 years to feel welcome in Germany. Originally from East Anatolia, Ali moved to Berlin at age 12 with his brother and sister. His mother had arrived 8 years prior in 1973 as part of the last wave of guest worker recruitment. She was living in <span class="st">Neukölln and working for a cleaning company</span>. His father stayed behind in Turkey.</span></p>
<p><span class="gD"><em>The beginning wasn&#8217;t easy</em>, Ali recounts. Understanding German society, learning the language, feeling at home&#8230; this all took time. But eventually he gained his footing, finished his schooling, completed an <em>Ausbildung</em> (apprenticeship), and in 1986, began a career in industrial mechanics. Today, he&#8217;s married, has a 12 year old daughter and an active social life, and makes music in his free time. He still lives in N<span class="st">eukölln. </span><br />
</span></p>
<p><span class="gD"><strong>But despite spending the majority of his life in Germany, having German citizenship, and making a home here, he&#8217;s often felt like an outsider.</strong> </span></p>
<p><em>I still don&#8217;t really have any German friends</em>, Ali tells me on the last night of Ramadan in July, after breaking the fast together. We&#8217;re sitting outside on Kreuzberg&#8217;s iconic <span class="st"><em>Oranienstraße</em></span> with his friends, also both named Ali, both German-Turks* born in Berlin. Ali and Ali nod their heads in agreement. A rollerblading demonstration passes by in front of us. <em>I don&#8217;t understand it,</em> Ali says. <em>We all have the same sources of stress &#8211; work, money, family &#8211; so why don&#8217;t we make more of an effort to be nice to one another? </em></p>
<div id="attachment_3358" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3358" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3358 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis-650x473.jpg" alt="Breaking the fast on Oranienstraße" width="650" height="473" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis-650x473.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis-300x218.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3358" class="wp-caption-text">Breaking the fast on Oranienstraße</p></div>
<p><span class="gD">Ali can cite the definitive moment in which he felt that he had finally &#8220;arrived&#8221; in Germany. <em>I was in the Bundeswehrkrankenhaus [German Armed Forces hospital] last December for a week due to a skin issue. I received such kind and affectionate treatment from the nurses and doctors. The same treatment as everyone else. I shared a room with a guy named Wolfgang, and we talked for two days straight, about everything. The atmosphere made me feel really welcome and inspired.</em></span></p>
<p>So inspired, that he started writing a song on his phone while still on his hospital bed. Two days after he was released, he finished &#8220;Ali <span class="st">für</span> Deutschland&#8221; (literally &#8220;Ali for Germany&#8221;), a World Cup song in <span class="gD">support of the </span>German national team. After recording it, Ali ran around to different departments and bureaus in the city, asking for support. Eventually he got a production company to film it for free. The song is available for purchase online (99 cents on iTunes) and half of the proceeds go to a homeless shelter in his neighborhood.<em> I really believed in the song and project, </em>Ali explains, <em>I wanted to show that someone who has my name and looks like me supports the German team. That people from all over the world with different backgrounds live here and consider it their home. </em><em><br />
</em></p>
<p><strong>Ali <span class="st">für</span> Deutschland Music Video: </strong></p>
<p><iframe width="650" height="366" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Mzqz6hCF7uI?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>Singing alongside Ali in the music video is his daughter. <em>I see that she&#8217;s growing up differently than I did, that she&#8217;s happier. I hope this song contributes to that. </em>For Ali, it all comes back to the media. <em>When Mesut Özil [German-Turkish football player] makes a good play, German-Turkish kids get patted on the back. If he does poorly, people shake their heads at us. The migration background is always emphasized. </em></p>
<p>Ali&#8217;s point is backed by research. <a href="http://www.stern.de/panorama/stern-umfrage-knappe-mehrheit-lehnt-islam-als-teil-deutschlands-ab-2128967.html">A recent Stern poll</a> shows that over half of Germans believe that Islam does not belong in German society. <a href="http://mediendienst-integration.de/artikel/der-islam-gehoert-zu-deutschland-spielhaus.html">Experts</a> argue that Islam is often conflated with Turks, the headscarf, and migration due to images perpetuated in the media. Another common image: German-Turkish or Arab youth as more violent or prone to criminal acts than their &#8220;native&#8221; counterparts, a stereotype repeatedly rebuked by <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/schulspiegel/wissen/kriminalitaet-von-migranten-laut-gutachten-nicht-hoeher-a-983536.html">studies</a>. <em>There are so many positive examples of what German-Turks have done and do for this country</em>, Ali says,<em> but news and social media continuously choose to show negative images. I want the media to show more positive images. </em><em><br />
</em></p>
<p>Ali is a positive person by nature. His face lights up when he shares stories of making connections to people at work or through his music. But he also has plenty of examples of feeling unwelcome or misunderstood on account of his background. He makes a conscious effort to speak Turkish with his daughter only at home and German out in public, in order to avoid judgment. More than once he&#8217;s been told &#8220;Du bist mein Lieblingst<span class="st">ürke</span><em>&#8221; </em>(&#8220;You&#8217;re my favorite Turk&#8221;), by a coworker or a club bouncer, for not stirring up trouble. <em>What am I supposed to do with that?</em> Ali asks, his eyes filling with emotion. Recently, a colleague joked to Ali that the reason his work contract was not renewed was because of his new hairstyle. <em>You look like a Turk now</em>, he told Ali.</p>
<p>After 6 years at the company, successfully training incoming employees, Ali had expected to keep his job. <em>After the video, they told me my music was making me slower at work, which wasn&#8217;t true,</em> Ali says, shaking his head<em>. <strong>I always felt like they were waiting for me to explode, to show my &#8220;Turkish temper&#8221;. In the end I think they just couldn&#8217;t deal with my humanness.</strong></em></p>
<div id="attachment_3359" style="width: 579px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3359" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-3359" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/alitsm.jpg" alt="Performing at a Football Academy Gala, August 2014" width="569" height="335" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/alitsm.jpg 569w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/alitsm-300x176.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 569px) 100vw, 569px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3359" class="wp-caption-text">Performing at a Football Academy Gala, August 2014</p></div>
<p>Ali is disappointed but not disheartened. He is taking this unexpected turn as a chance to reconsider career paths. <em>I have so much experience, and I want to use that to do something good</em>, he says. He&#8217;s now thinking seriously about becoming a social worker for kids with migration backgrounds. <em>I know </em><em>what they&#8217;re going through.</em> <em>I can go into their homes and talk to their parents, help them see what options they have and make sure they don&#8217;t give up. </em>More than likely, he&#8217;ll do it with music. <em>I learned early on that music allows you to reach a lot of people. Music is its own language, one that you don&#8217;t need to understand, just feel.</em></p>
<p>Ali is certainly &#8220;for&#8221; Germany, but does he consider himself from Germany? <em>Whew,</em> Ali lets out a deep breath, <em>I&#8217;m not sure. I have parts of German culture and parts of Turkish culture. But I think, most of all, I&#8217;m a Berliner.</em></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>*The term German-Turk is a hyphenation often used for people born and/or raised in Germany with 2nd or 3rd generation Turkish backgrounds. For more on language, migration, and identity, see our article <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">here</a>.</p>
<p>For German interviews with Ali, click <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/video/ali-fuer-deutschland-deutsch-tuerke-nimmt-wm-song-auf-video-1500438.html">here</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kGYNujx3RvQ">here</a>.</p>
<p><em>All of Ali&#8217;s quotes have been translated/paraphrased by Sophia Burton.<br />
</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Berlin needs you (but why?)</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/04/review-berlin-needs-you-but-why/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/04/review-berlin-needs-you-but-why/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2014 08:20:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2702</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Why is immigration important? The debate takes many angles. There's the demographic argument, that developed countries with low birth rates and aging populations need bodies to maintain the replacement rate. There's the globalization take, that the movement of people in all forms is increasingly inevitable and contributes to global competitiveness and 21st century skills. The moral or even religious spin, emphasizing human dignity, charity, an obligation for prosperous nations to help those more needy. But few arguments are as pervasive as the economic one...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_2738" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdad.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2738" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2738 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad.jpg?w=640" alt="" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad-300x199.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2738" class="wp-caption-text">©Barbara Dietl</p></div>
<p>Why is immigration important? The debate takes many angles. There&#8217;s the <a href="http://www.thelocal.de/20131126/germany-needs-more-immigration">demographic argument</a>, that developed countries with low birth rates and aging populations need bodies to maintain the replacement rate. There&#8217;s the globalization take, that the movement of people in all forms is increasingly inevitable and contributes to global competitiveness and 21st century skills. The moral or even religious spin, emphasizing human dignity, charity, and an obligation for prosperous nations to help those more needy. Yet few arguments are as pervasive as the economic one: that immigrants fill labor shortages, tend to be more innovative, start businesses and create jobs, pay taxes, and contribute to the social welfare net (yes, often more than they &#8220;take away&#8221;).</p>
<p>It is this economic argument that is often relied upon as a point of mutual agreement that immigrants are needed. Maybe not <a href="http://www.dw.de/opinion-foreigners-welcome-sort-of/a-17651819">“wanted”</a>, but at least needed.</p>
<p>This argument extends beyond newcomers to the 2nd and 3rd generations. In countries like Germany where the history of immigration has been primarily low skilled, children of migrants still face numerous linguistic, cultural, and socioeconomic challenges. These are exacerbated by a stratified education system that is associated with lower educational attainment, limited access to higher education, and fewer chances for economic mobility. Germany fares particularly poorly in this arena: it has the <a href="http://www.oecd.org/general/oecdeducationsystemsleavemanyimmigrantchildrenflounderingreportshows.htm">OECD&#8217;s largest performance disparity</a> between native and immigrant students and is one of the only countries where 2nd generation students perform worse on international assessments than the 1st generation.</p>
<p>Enter <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> (Berlin needs you!), a program that works to improve the educational and economic outcomes of students with migrant backgrounds. Launched by the state of Berlin as part of its overall integration plan in 2006, it aims to increase the number of these students entering the public sector by 25% by bridging schools with the professional world. It is coordinated by BQN, <em>das Berufliche Qualifizierungsnetzwerk für Migrantinnen und Migranten in Berlin</em> (the Vocational Qualification Network for Immigrants in Berlin) and is funded by the state of Berlin.</p>
<p><iframe title="Berlin braucht dich! - Diverse Wege in die Arbeitswelt" width="650" height="366" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fwBxQu93g3o?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>The program works in cycles: a day-long introduction to a business or organization for 7th graders, a week-long internship for 8th graders, 3-week internships for 9th graders, and training and application days for 10th graders. Participating schools help their students find training spots with an online matching tool. Spots are currently offered in Berlin&#8217;s public sector, public companies, and the metal and electrical industries, though BQN is working toward expanding the program to include small businesses. The program has also evolved from a focus on the vocational training system (<em>Duales System</em> &#8211; working and learning in a company) to more dual study opportunities <em>(Duales Studium</em> &#8211; studying and working simultaneously).</p>
<p>Mitri Sirin, a German TV reporter of Turkish-Syrian background, moderates the 5th <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> consortium meeting in June. He highlights the culture of low expectations and need for more varied training opportunities for migrant students during a panel on diversity politics.<em> The idea that any kid in the 7th grade would know what they wanted to be when they grow up is a fairy tale,</em> he scoffs. <em>Of course I was funneled into a vocational internship with other kids like me. I was still able to make something or other of myself</em>, he adds to chuckles from the audience,<em> but not all are so lucky.</em></p>
<div id="attachment_2790" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdconsortium.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2790" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2790 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium.jpg?w=640" alt="Berlin braucht dich! Consortium Meeting June 2014" width="640" height="480" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2790" class="wp-caption-text"><em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> Consortium Meeting June 2014 ©BQN Berlin</p></div>
<p>When the panel concludes, a group of giggling students race out from behind the stage to plaster black paper on the windows and switch off the lights. It&#8217;s a bit eerie to be cloaked in darkness with pop music blaring before 11am, but soon enough the black-light theater performance has the audience tapping their feet and grinning widely. While entirely up for interpretation, the images of a ball being passed around between two sets of hands and a student struggling in a white sheet before becoming a colorful butterfly suggests a story-line of transnationalism and diversity.</p>
<p><em>The theater program is</em> <em>a kind of &#8220;empowerment action&#8221;</em>, explains Robert Westermann, PR Manager of Berlin braucht dich! <em>The group comes from one of the 32 schools we cooperate with&#8230; students from this school also take part in our internships. </em></p>
<p>Later that morning, we make sure to join the small workshop where the same students share their experiences. <em>I&#8217;ve been in Germany for 2 years and can&#8217;t speak German that well,</em> <em>but black-light theater is like another language that I can speak to everyone, without having to actually say anything, </em>shares one Iranian girl.  <em>In theater you have to learn to control yourself, but you can also be free</em>, says another. <em>Theater has taught me how to be loud</em>, exclaims a third.</p>
<div id="attachment_2737" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2737" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2737 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht.jpg?w=640" alt="Schule am Schloss students post-performance. Source: Berlin braucht dich!" width="640" height="480" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2737" class="wp-caption-text"><em>Schule am Schloss</em> students take a bow post-performance ©BQN Berlin</p></div>
<p><em>In my view, the most innovative aspect of </em>Berlin braucht dich!<em> is that schools and companies are working together on a constant and sustainable level</em>, describes Robert.<em> This stable network makes it possible to operationalize key ideas around &#8220;intercultural openness&#8221;, by changing structures, processes, and mentalities. </em></p>
<p><em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> has experienced marked success in its 8 years of operation. Since 2006, the ratio of trainees in the public sector with a migration background has been steadily on the rise and by 2009 had doubled to 16.9%. By 2013, every 5th trainee (20.5%) in the public sector and public companies had a migration background.</p>
<p>Yet it is the emphasis on mutually understood and implemented &#8220;intercultural openness&#8221; that implies <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> is about more than Euro signs. In addition to securing a more intercultural workforce through sheer numbers, BQN offers free <a href="http://www.berlin-braucht-dich.de/aktivitaeten/diversity-trainings/">diversity trainings</a> for partner schools and businesses. Migration is acknowledged not only as a reality, but as a key factor that contributes both &#8220;to our quality of life now and the sustainability of our future.&#8221; While the demand for such trainings has been low on the school side, BQN has implemented many with employees from their partner companies.</p>
<div id="attachment_2800" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdstudents.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2800" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2800 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents.jpg?w=640" alt="bbdstudents" width="640" height="480" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2800" class="wp-caption-text">Moderator and TV reporter Mitri Sirin (middle) with theater group students ©BQN Berlin</p></div>
<p>The path to a truly intercultural workforce is still laden with hurdles. Recent studies on Germany show that <a href="http://www.migazin.de/2014/06/02/vorurteil-widerlegt-junge-migranten-nicht-haeufiger-kriminell-als-deutsche-jugendliche/">prejudice</a> and <a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/karriere/studie--mit-tuerkischem-namen-sinken-chancen-auf-ausbildungsmarkt,10808620,26663588.html">hiring discrimination</a> against students with migrant backgrounds is alive and well. Access to higher education and many employment opportunities is entirely off the table, as a disproportionate number &#8211; <a href="http://www.boeckler.de/35923_41774.htm">about half</a> &#8211; of these students are funneled into the lowest vocational school track. As one of the business representatives at the meeting explained to the theater group, <em>If any of you came into an interview at our offices, you would do great. But to get to the interview stage, you would still have to pass the entrance test first, which focuses on German, math, and logic. </em></p>
<p>Challenges such as these require integrated policy approaches. Approaches that distinguish the actors involved and hold them accountable for their roles in changing the structures, norms, and mentalities that fuel these challenges. Approaches that extend beyond just the economic argument and are brave enough to acknowledge everyone&#8217;s role in fostering an intercultural and inclusive society that values the potential of each individual. In short, Berlin doesn&#8217;t just need you. It needs all of us.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>Thank you to Robert Westermann, PR Manager of <em>Berlin braucht dich!, </em>for inviting us to the consortium meeting and providing information for this article.</p>
<p>For more information on <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em>, check out their German website <a href="http://www.berlin-braucht-dich.de/">here</a>. Info in English can be found <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/ewsi/en/practice/details.cfm?ID_ITEMS=13081">here. </a></p>
<p>For another article from us on Berlin based programs for students with migrant backgrounds, click <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/18/rave-education-per-square-kilometer/%20">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/04/review-berlin-needs-you-but-why/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Seeing Berlin Through The Homeless</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2014 12:22:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bureaucracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GDR-DDR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitte]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Schöneberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2398</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[They wait for the subway doors to close before they address the car with a rehearsed speech. "Excuse the interruption, I am one of Berlin's annoying homeless people"... it usually begins, as they peddle newspapers and scan the crowd for an outstretched hand holding change or food. The majority of us keep our hands tucked away or firmly gripping our phones. Some of us fall into convenient bouts of exhaustion, promptly leaning back and closing our eyes. In this moment, we are restricted to a shared space...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_2604" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2604" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2604 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-650x433.jpg" alt="hermannplatz" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2604" class="wp-caption-text">Photo by Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>In Berlin they are especially visible on the <em>Bahn</em>. They wait for the subway doors to close before they address the car with a rehearsed speech. <em>Excuse the interruption, I am one of Berlin&#8217;s annoying homeless people&#8230;</em> it usually begins, as they peddle newspapers and scan<em> </em>the crowd for an outstretched hand holding change or food. The majority of us keep our hands tucked away or firmly gripping our phones. Some of us fall into convenient bouts of exhaustion, promptly leaning back and closing our eyes. In this moment, we are restricted to a moving car, a shared space. We can&#8217;t dodge a corner or cross the street, but we still find ways to make them invisible. We don&#8217;t look up because we feel uncomfortable. We become frustrated at them for making us feel this way. We may even become angry &#8211; at them, at society, at ourselves.</p>
<p>How the simple presence of one person can incite so much emotion, judgement, and shame.</p>
<p>How it must feel, to be simultaneously so visible and invisible.</p>
<div id="attachment_2605" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2605" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2605 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-650x459.jpg" alt="eye" width="650" height="459" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-650x459.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-300x212.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2605" class="wp-caption-text">Photo by Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><em>It&#8217;s one of the worst things for homeless people, being treated as invisible. Answer them when they speak to you, make eye contact, acknowledge them!</em> our guide Carsten Voss urges us by the end of our walk. We are wrapping up a tour called &#8220;Obdachslose zeigen ihr Berlin&#8221; (The homeless present their Berlin), run by non-profit organization <em>Querstadtein. </em>The group offers tours in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Mitte that show the reality of homelessness in the city.</p>
<p>Our guide speaks from personal experience. Decked out in designer glasses and a well-fitting sweater, it&#8217;s challenging to picture this man as the subject of the powerful story he delivers in front of stately <span class="st">Viktoria-Luise-Platz</span>. Carsten worked 80+ hours a week as a manager of an international tradeshow before burning-out and falling into depression. First came the loss of his job, then his apartment. He refused help from loved ones, other than taking refuge in a friend&#8217;s shed for a few months. It would be a year before he clawed his way back out. He cites one defining moment: <em>I happened to glance into someone&#8217;s window from the street. The woman was cooking and the man was watching </em>Tagesschau<em> on TV&#8230; I realized that if I didn&#8217;t make a change then, I would never have that again.</em></p>
<p>That year Carsten counted among Berlin&#8217;s estimated 4,000 <em>Obdachslose</em> (literally translates to &#8220;without shelter&#8221;). Not to be confused with <em>Wohnungslose</em> (&#8220;house-less&#8221;), which refers to those without homes but still in the system, <em>Obdachslose</em> are no longer in the system and may or may not have a place to sleep. Berlin has Germany&#8217;s highest concentration of <em>Obdachslose, </em>both from within and outside of the country.</p>
<p><em>There are three main categories of </em>Obdachslose <em>in Berlin</em>, Carsten explains early on in the tour. <em>Former refugees from East Germany, those groups of young people who usually have dogs with them, and immigrants.<br />
</em></p>
<p><a href="http://ec.europa.eu/social/main.jsp?catId=1061&amp;langId=en">Migrant homelessness throughout the EU</a> has risen in recent years, exacerbated by the economic crisis. This may come as no great surprise, though it&#8217;s a blow to hear that many in Berlin<em> end up staying because they find the conditions of being homeless here better than their lives back home. </em>Carsten describes this group in three geographic waves: the first from Poland, second from the Baltics, and third from Bulgaria and Romania<em>. Of course they came here planning to find jobs, start families, create a life. Some make it, but many don&#8217;t. </em></p>
<div id="attachment_2586" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-23-14-33-35.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2586" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2586 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-23-14-33-35.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-23 14.33.35" width="640" height="480" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2586" class="wp-caption-text">Cold Weather Assistance for Berlin&#8217;s Homeless by District, Winter 2013/14</p></div>
<p>Berlin has a long tradition of homelessness. It&#8217;s a poor city &#8211; Germany&#8217;s poorest &#8211; but also equipped with robust social services. Berlin has a history of attracting those who are &#8220;different&#8221;, including many immigrants, due to its diversity and tolerant atmosphere. During the days of the Berlin Wall, it was also a haven for males escaping military conscription (which ended altogether in 2011). Carsten moved to Berlin for this reason, and says he and many others like him entered fields like social work and education. This, he claims, has contributed to the city&#8217;s liberal nature and strong social net.</p>
<p>Berlin&#8217;s homeless tend to cluster in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Charlottenburg, two districts in West Berlin now more associated with high rents and artisanal cafes than alternative lifestyles. Carsten guides us to Nollendorfplatz, Berlin&#8217;s LGBT hub and site of the annual pride parade, Christopher Street Day. We stand across from the colorful <em>Regenbogen-Stele, </em>a r<span class="userContent">ainbow column erected in 2000 to celebrate the area&#8217;s high concentration of homosexual residents and open-minded atmosp<span class="text_exposed_show">here. The statue itself carries two symbols: the rainbow flag for gay pride and the <em>Rosa Winkel</em>, a pink badge first used by Nazis to distinguish homosexuals in concentration camps, and what later became an international symbol for gay rights.<br />
</span></span></p>
<div id="attachment_2507" style="width: 538px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/2014-03-23-14-21-00-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2507" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2507" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/2014-03-23-14-21-00-1.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-23 14.21.00-1" width="528" height="528" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2507" class="wp-caption-text">Nollendorf Platz&#8217;s &#8220;Regenbogen-Stele&#8221; or rainbow column celebrating gay rights</p></div>
<p>As we inspect the square, Carsten points out what our untrained eyes fail to see: a 24-hour grocery store well-equipped with bottle deposit machines, a van selling the street newspaper, a well-lit intersection. <em>Homeless people are part of this neighborhood, they have a community here</em>, he says.</p>
<p>But another faction of the city&#8217;s homeless blend in so well that we don&#8217;t see them at all. <em>Most people have an image in mind of the bag lady (or guy), unkempt and dirty, pushing around a cart filled to the brim with random items, muttering crazy things to themselves.</em>.<em>. most homeless people don&#8217;t look or act like that. </em> Carsten estimates that 60% fall into this category, homeless people who look &#8220;normal&#8221; so they can use spaces and services within the city without being noticed. They schedule their day in such a way that they always have a place to be, something to eat, even a bed to sleep in. They know when the citizens&#8217; office opens and when they can grab a shower, when they can rest in the library or supermarket, who is offering a free lunch or haircut in the city. <em>It&#8217;s an exhausting life, they have to be very organized, and they are constantly in public</em>, Carsten emphasizes: <em>the only time they have to themselves is in the shower.</em></p>
<div id="attachment_2621" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-24-08-25-20.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2621" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2621 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-24-08-25-20.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-24 08.25.20" width="640" height="480" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2621" class="wp-caption-text">Assistance notice for homeless youth in Charlottenburg</p></div>
<p>Carsten&#8217;s happy ending is a welcome take-away from an otherwise harrowing topic, but he warns against the assumption that all homeless people are unhappy or need to be saved. While many do suffer from mental illness and drug and alcohol abuse, others have deliberately chosen this lifestyle. <em>Some people want to live this way, and we have to respect that. We have to recognize them as part of society.</em></p>
<p><span class="userContent"><span class="text_exposed_show">It&#8217;s easy to dodge corners and cross streets, to switch subway cars to avoid someone&#8217;s stench or words, to grip our phones and look down. </span></span></p>
<p>It&#8217;s not as easy to look up.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>The Querstadtein homeless tours (in German) take place in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Mitte, usually on Sundays and for approximately 2 hours. Tickets cost <span class="st">€</span>9,40, and <span class="st">€</span>5,40 for students, seniors, and individuals on welfare. More information can be found at <em>http://querstadtein.org/de/stadtfuehrungen/.<br />
</em></p>
<p>For more on the Querstadtein tours in English, click <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/zeitgeist/berlin-tour-gives-a-glimpse-of-berlin-as-seen-by-homeless-people-a-913758.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>For more on the increasing restrictions on public space for homeless people across Europe, <a href="http://www.surveillance-and-society.org/articles5%283%29/homelessness.pdf">click here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: The Taxi Driver</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2014 14:00:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kurdistan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2314</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Orhan was 5 when his father moved to Berlin in 1972. It was only one year before West Germany would halt guest worker recruitment from non-European countries to fill labor shortages after World War II. His mother followed 7 years later with his youngest sister and they lived in Rudow in southeastern Neukölln - where they still live over 30 years later. "They got jobs as cleaners in an office," Orhan recounts, "but they were fired!" he adds, snorting in laughter.  I look up from my notepad, surprised...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Had I hopped into Orhan&#8217;s taxi en route to the airport, I likely would&#8217;ve assumed he was Turkish and left it at that. He might have asked me where I was flying to and I might have commented on the weather. He would&#8217;ve pulled my suitcase out of the trunk and wished me a good flight, and I would&#8217;ve thanked him. But instead, thankfully, I met Orhan in a very different context &#8211; our half-marathon training group. What follows here is his story about growing up in Kurdistan and Turkey as the child of guest workers and moving to Berlin 20 years ago. The story I would&#8217;ve likely missed. </em></p>
<div id="attachment_2377" style="width: 588px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/2014-03-30-09-50-36-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2377" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2377" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/2014-03-30-09-50-36-1.jpg?w=640" alt="Orhan and Sophia pre 2014 Berlin half marathon" width="578" height="578" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/2014-03-30-09-50-36-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/2014-03-30-09-50-36-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 578px) 100vw, 578px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2377" class="wp-caption-text">Orhan and I pre-race 2014</p></div>
<p>I meet Orhan at Fehrbelliner Platz&#8217;s Park <span class="st">Café</span>. We choose a table outside amongst the masses soaking up the unusually warm March sun. It&#8217;s that strange break between afternoon and evening,  the mood equally fitting for a coffee or beer. The space is buzzing but in a state of exhalation, as the day starts to settle and everyone&#8217;s shoulders wilt a few centimeters. This is where Orhan spends every Thursday between 4:45 and 6pm, while his daughter takes a kickboxing class around the corner.</p>
<p>My first order of business is a selfish one: though I&#8217;ve asked Orhan multiple times to tell me where he grew up, I still can&#8217;t remember the name, let alone comprehend its location geographically. Orhan draws me a little diagram: he grew up in <em>Hotan</em>, a tiny village near a town called <em>Varto</em>, part of a district called <span class="st"><em>Mûş</em></span> that lies in Anatolia, in the predominantly Kurdish southeastern part of Turkey.</p>
<div id="2330" style="width: 582px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://geopoliticsrst.blogspot.de/2012/10/turkei.html"><img aria-describedby="caption-2330" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2330 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/mapkurdistan.jpg" alt="Kurdistan on a map " width="572" height="447" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/mapkurdistan.jpg 572w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/mapkurdistan-300x234.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 572px) 100vw, 572px" /></a><p id="caption-2330" class="wp-caption-text">Varto is slightly northeast of Diyarbakir, the unofficial capital of Turkish Kurdistan</p></div>
<p>Orhan was 5 when his father moved to Berlin in 1972. It was only one year before West Germany would halt guest worker recruitment from non-European countries to fill labor shortages after World War II. His mother followed 7 years later with his youngest sister and they lived in Rudow in southeastern Neukölln &#8211; where they still live over 30 years later. <em>They got jobs as cleaners in an office</em>, Orhan recounts, <em>but they were fired!</em> he adds, snorting in laughter.  I look up from my notepad, surprised. &#8220;Why is that funny?&#8221; <em>Well, they worked with friends &#8211; they&#8217;d moved to Berlin together &#8211; and one of the guys was really funny. So they were always fooling around and making noise..</em>.<em> and one day they got fired! That guy was a real comedian.<br />
</em></p>
<p>Orhan only heard that story years later. He had stayed behind in Kurdistan, in the village with his grandmother. <em>My father didn&#8217;t plan on staying that long, like most guest workers</em>, Orhan explains,<em> but my mom eventually went, too, and my Oma became my main mom. She ended up raising me. </em>After school, Orhan did an apprenticeship in wood-making<em>. It was a 6km walk to work from Oma&#8217;s every day, alone, sometimes in 1m of snow. I was always scared the wolves would get me! </em></p>
<div id="attachment_2368" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/gallery_0610222020109423828131.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2368" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-2368" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/gallery_0610222020109423828131.jpg?w=640" alt="Portrait of a Kurdish woman (Source: Renkliisler)" width="640" height="648" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2368" class="wp-caption-text">Portrait of a Kurdish woman in Varto (Source: Renkliisler)</p></div>
<p>In the 1980s, Orhan&#8217;s parents used money earned in Germany to buy land and build a house in Izmir, on Turkey&#8217;s western coast. Orhan switched from wood-making to electrician work, and got a factory job making stoves. His remaining siblings (of which there are 5 total) started to join his parents in Berlin, applying for visas and leaving one by one. Orhan applied too, but his request was denied. German family reunification policy* has a 16 year old age limit for third country (non EU) nationals to join their parents in Germany. After age 15, other factors apply for a residence permit, such as German language proficiency and the &#8220;ability to integrate&#8221;. Orhan was already in his 20s. So he stayed in Izmir, looking after the house and spending summers in the village with his grandmother and uncle. Then came 1993, when <em>Hotan </em>and many other Kurdish villages were destroyed in a war between Turkish government forces and Kurdish rebels. The war, called &#8220;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/24/world/kurds-are-finally-heard-turkey-burned-our-villages.html">one of the most violent secrets of the 1990&#8217;s</a>&#8220;, killed more than 30,000 and displaced thousands more.</p>
<p>Orhan&#8217;s chance to go to Germany came shortly thereafter. <em>My boss asked me to go to Germany to fix a faulty order we had exported there&#8230; they needed someone who spoke a little German. </em>It was Orhan&#8217;s first trip to Germany, and by the time he returned, he had decided to try moving there again. <em>Since I had gotten a visa for the work trip and come back, I had earned the Embassy&#8217;s trust</em>, Orhan chuckles, <em>it was much easier to apply for a visa the next time.</em> On December 10, 1994, Orhan left Turkey with a 3 month visa. Upon arrival in Germany he applied for asylum. He was 27.</p>
<p>He was sent to an asylum home outside Berlin in <span class="st">Eisenhüttenstadt, Brandenburg</span>. <em>We were fed three times a day and the workers were pretty nice to us, but the conditions weren&#8217;t great&#8230; 7 or 8 of us sleeping together in one room. </em>For a year, Orhan spent one night every two weeks there to comply with policy.<em> They knew my family was in Berlin&#8230; I spent the rest of the time with them. </em>Orhan&#8217;s asylum request was eventually granted, on the grounds that his hometown in Kurdistan had been destroyed. <em><br />
</em></p>
<div id="2341" style="width: 618px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article123743604/Asylbewerberheim-in-Eisenhuettenstadt.html"><img aria-describedby="caption-2341" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2341 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/asylbewerberheim-in-eisenhuettenstadt.jpg" alt="asylum home in Eisenhuettenstadt" width="608" height="405" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/asylbewerberheim-in-eisenhuettenstadt.jpg 620w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/asylbewerberheim-in-eisenhuettenstadt-300x199.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px" /></a><p id="caption-2341" class="wp-caption-text">Asylum seekers arrive to Eisenhüttenstadt (Source: Die Welt)</p></div>
<p>This was in the mid-1990s, a decade before Germany would officially recognize itself as a country of immigration and develop a <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">national integration plan that included integration courses for newcomers</a>. Orhan signed up for a language course on his own, hoping to learn enough German to study economics at university. He quit after 3 months. <em>It wasn&#8217;t fun and always after work</em><em>, when I was so tired </em>(he did construction at the time)<em>. </em><em>The grammar was really hard. It&#8217;s still hard.<br />
</em></p>
<p>A cousin&#8217;s <span class="st">fiancé</span> suggested he try being a taxi driver. <em>I failed my taxi license test 3 times because I couldn&#8217;t pronounce the street names correctly!</em> <em>Being a taxi driver is a bit boring but it&#8217;s a clean job. Not like construction. And I like the freedom.</em></p>
<p>Orhan&#8217;s been a taxi driver ever since, working 10 hour days 5-6 days a week. He has two children, a son from his first marriage to a Turkish-German woman and a daughter with his current wife, whom he met at a gym over 10 years ago &#8211; a gym they still attend together. <em>I live a good life here. I travel a lot and I have a flexible job. </em>Orhan tries to go to Kurdistan at least once or twice a year, and has taken his kids 4 times. His next visit is this May. <em><br />
</em></p>
<p><em>My kids have 59% <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">Migrationshintergrund</a>, </em>Orhan says laughing,<em> when I&#8217;m angry with my son I scold him in Turkish, but usually we speak German. He can understand Kurdish, too.</em> <em>I tried speaking Kurdish with my daughter for a year but then gave up,</em> he adds, a hint of regret in his voice.</p>
<p>&#8220;Do you think German integration policy has gotten better since you first arrived here 20 years ago? With services like the integration courses?&#8221; <em>German immigration policy isn&#8217;t very fair</em>, Orhan replies scowling, <em>If I marry someone from Turkey and want to bring them here, they have to prove they speak German before arriving! But people from <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/20/roma-in-berlin-bureaucracy-in-lichtenberg/">Bulgaria and Romania</a>** can just come here and get social benefits even if they don&#8217;t speak the language</em>.</p>
<p><em>I don&#8217;t have German citizenship and I don&#8217;t want it,</em> Orhan declares, <em>why would I need it? </em><em>My wife and I want to buy a house in Izmir and spend maybe one third of the year there. Four months in Berlin, 4 in Izmir, 4 in Kurdistan. There&#8217;s nothing special there, where I&#8217;m from in Kurdistan&#8230; only mountains, animals </em>(the wolves!)<em>, and rocks, but, </em>Orhan makes a fist and holds it close to his stomach, <em>it still feels like home.</em></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Varto">According to Wikipedia</a>, Berlin holds Europe&#8217;s largest population from Varto, Kurdistan. Germany has Europe&#8217;s largest population of Kurds, <a href="http://www.aljazeera.com/video/europe/2013/05/201358161349732897.html">approximately 800,000</a>, many of whom came as guest workers in the 1960s. For more information on the history of this immigrant community (in German), click <a href="http://www.trend.infopartisan.net/trd0299/t090299.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>*For more information on Germany&#8217;s family reunification policy, click <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/dgs/home-affairs/what-we-do/networks/european_migration_network/reports/docs/emn-studies/family-reunification/2._de_emn_ncp_small-scale_study_iv_family_reunification_final_en_version_en.pdf">here</a> and <a href="http://www.expatica.com/de/essentials_moving_to/essentials/German-permits-for-family-reunification_18892.html%20">here</a>.</p>
<p>**Despite being part of the EU since 2007, Bulgarians and Romanians have only had access to Germany&#8217;s social welfare system since 2014, when Germany lifted work policy restrictions. This was after the EU deemed Germany in violation of economic rules of engagement.</p>
<p><em>All photos linked to source. A big thank you to Orhan for his participation!<br />
</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
