<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>racism &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/racism/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Integration in Berlin: Research for a Desolate Landscape</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/11/integration-in-berlin-research-for-a-desolate-landscape/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/11/integration-in-berlin-research-for-a-desolate-landscape/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2014 09:01:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2390</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On April 2, the new <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/">Berlin Institute for Empirical Research on Integration and Migration</a> (BIM) was launched. Certainly not the first institute of its kind in Germany, Berlin's Humboldt University, the Hertie Foundation, the Federal Employment Agency, and the German Football Association held a press conference to frame this initiative as new and needed. The reason: the field  - what is really known about the integration or inclusion of diversity - is more desert than rain-forest in this country of immigration...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On April 2, the new <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/">Berlin Institute for Empirical Research on Integration and Migration</a> (BIM) was launched. Certainly not the first institute of its kind in Germany, Berlin&#8217;s Humboldt University, the Hertie Foundation, the Federal Employment Agency, and the German Football Association held a <a href="http://www.hu-berlin.de/service/veranstaltungen/veranstaltungen_neu/?stat=show&amp;vk_id=2715">press conference</a> to frame this initiative as new and needed. The reason: the field  &#8211; what is really known about the integration or inclusion of diversity &#8211; is more desert than rain-forest in this country of immigration.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-7.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2419" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-7.jpg?w=550" alt="BIM 7" width="550" height="668" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-7.jpg 535w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-7-247x300.jpg 247w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></a></p>
<p>Improving the civic and social infrastructure of a city often begins with data. Aside from &#8220;Big Data&#8221; being the buzzword of 2014, plain ol&#8217; data is worth discussing. For <a href="http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2014/04/14/huge-new-york-development-project-becomes-a-data-science-lab/?_php=true&amp;_type=blogs&amp;_r=0">data can instruct city planners, lawmakers, social workers etc. to better approach problems of urban spaces</a> and their economies, in ways which benefit residents, including the marginalized. It might just be common sense, but empirical research (the critical boots-on-the-ground kind) is an act of taking stock of what is and what isn&#8217;t, which can prove quite useful in societies undergoing (or just learning to deal with) change.</p>
<p>Data, in this sense, is information gathered to solve a problem or answer a question. According to all panelists at the press conference, whether researchers or community and/or political stakeholders, this data is desperately required to answer the question of integration. Or is integration instead a problem to be solved?</p>
<p>As one of the not-so-timid anthropologists on the stage stated during the round of questions, <em>What we are really taking about, when we talk about integration, is how to learn to deal with and approach difference in society. </em></p>
<p><strong>The data imperative</strong></p>
<p>In light of Germany&#8217;s changing demography and political landscape, regarding immigration policy, the categories and models used to understand and support local populations have become outdated, as the <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/german-coalition-talks-move-closer-to-new-dual-citizenship-law-a-933523.html">dual-citizenship debate</a> in German Parliament over the last few months has indicated. More than just the classic census is required to capture the complexity of today&#8217;s metropolis. In Germany&#8217;s capital, where policy-makers brush shoulders with constituents and neighbors alike, real data could not be more in demand and yet, ironically, easier to find. This data goes beyond numbers.</p>
<p>Given this deficit of information and the few reasons for it, the Federal Ministry for Migration and Refugees (BAMF) <a href="http://www.bundesregierung.de/Content/DE/Pressemitteilungen/BPA/2014/04/2014-04-02-integration-kuratoriumsvorsitz.html">has been actively involved in BMI&#8217;s founding</a> and is set to be involved in its future;  BAMF&#8217;s new federal integration commissioner, Aydan Özo<span style="color: #435050;">ğ</span>uz<span style="color: #435050;">,</span> is a key member of the BIM board. Her vocal presence at the press conference made one thing clear: <em>We don&#8217;t even have the numbers, quite honestly, to determine these differences</em> [between &#8216;foreigners&#8217;, &#8216;foreign-born&#8217;, citizens with migration background etc.]. <em>This makes my job quite difficult</em>, she articulated loudly to the audience of mostly journalists. <em>We just do not have the data.</em></p>
<div style="width: 659px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img loading="lazy" src="http://www.bundesregierung.de/Content/DE/Artikel/IB/Bilder-IB/2014-04-02-eroeffnung-bim2.jpg?__blob=bpaTopmeldung&amp;v=1" alt="Eröffnungsveranstaltung des Berliner Instituts für empirische Integrations- und Migrationsforschung" width="649" height="406" /><p class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: BIM HU, Dirk Enters</p></div>
<p>Wolfgang Niersbach, President of the German Football Association (DFB) &#8211; one of three sponsors of the institute and the DFB&#8217;s first sponsorship of this kind &#8211; reiterated this data-driven impetus for more research at length. In 2006, the DFB employed its very own integration commissioner to better navigate the challenging combination of passionate football fans, visible diversity, and racism. A sweeping anti-racism campaign has been the culmination of these efforts, <em>though much is still to be learned</em>, Niersbach said. <em>Our hope for this institute is to get some more solid ground under our feet, to learn more about what works and what doesn&#8217;t work. </em>It is a learning process, and it begins with better information.</p>
<p>A key research focus of the new institute is the relationship between sports and integration, e.g., the participation of youth with migration backgrounds in local football clubs. But the playing field is different in football; <em>integration happens everyday, as 40% of the players have non-German backgrounds,</em> Niersbach mentioned emphatically, looking down the table at colleagues to see their reactions. To boot, social or ethnic differences are experienced on a more intensive and yet common-place level (at least organizationally) in football, compared to German society at large.</p>
<p>Niersbach explained: <em>Two talented football players grow up in Nuremberg playing together, they both go professional, they both have Turkish backgrounds. One day, one of them calls us up and says that he has decided to play for the Turkish national team, the other for the German national team. We are completely fine with that! We let them do what they want to do! But it was not always like that. </em>Times have changed, and so should terms and categories (the dual-citizenship debate, once again case-in-point).</p>
<p><strong>A clarification of terms</strong></p>
<p>The institute&#8217;s projects, team of researchers, sponsors, as well as its leadership, are truly diverse. Inter-disciplinary and embracing of different methodologies and languages of information, the institute seeks to embody what it studies, something Dr. Sebastian Braun, Director of BIM, emphasized throughout his introduction. A football advocate seated next to a well-known political scientist and culture critic;  anthropologists gawking at the government employee over-using the word &#8216;foreigner&#8217;; clinical psychiatrists tolerating the tactics of the employment agency, in dealing with issues of health and job competency. Diversity has to begin somewhere.</p>
<p>But where it will certainly prove to get messy is in this sticky, touchy realm of language.</p>
<p>Frank J. Weiser of the Federal Employment Agency spoke from the perspective of the market-driven state, the key aim of which is full employment and a balanced checkbook: <em>We want to improve our work with </em>Ausländer (foreigners)&#8230;<em>many of these foreigners have access to entitlement programs and experience higher unemployment than their German counterparts. I just work with the numbers, </em>he said smiling, seeming pleased with his honesty. <em>Social cohesion, approaching difference &#8211; but what about jobs?!</em>, he might have said.</p>
<p>The fissure between practice, policy, and the ideals of academia is still there and not likely to go away.</p>
<div id="attachment_3410" style="width: 646px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3410" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3410 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-3.jpg" alt="Director of German Football Association, Rep. Director of Federal Employment Agency; Photo source: DFB" width="636" height="310" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-3.jpg 636w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-3-300x146.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 636px) 100vw, 636px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3410" class="wp-caption-text">Director of German Football Association, Rep. Director of Federal Employment Agency; Photo source: DFB</p></div>
<p><em>The foreigners on our football teams used to be the exotics. In 1963, when DFB was founded, we only had three players with any sort of migration background. Today, 40% of our players have some relationship to immigration, </em>Niersbach commented.</p>
<p>Hands shot up in a hurry from the rows of journalists filling the hall.</p>
<p>A free-lance reporter and coach for a local football league called the use of the word <em>&#8220;Ausländer&#8221;</em> (foreigner)<em> </em>by both men into question. How strange it was to hear a term describing kids born or raised in Germany, kids that play football in Germany as foreign: <em>There are kids that play on our teams that are different, yes, but they play together&#8230; these kids don&#8217;t need to be integrated just because they happen to have a different skin tone.</em></p>
<p>The most vocal of the anthropologists, Prof. Dr. Wolfgang Kaschuba, director of Humboldt University&#8217;s European-Anthropology Department, agreed with this critique, bringing the other oddly-applied term <em>Menschen mit Migrationshintergrund</em> (people with migration background) into the discussion. It is not just about the word &#8220;foreigner&#8221;, which connotes otherness, apart-ness; rather, the problem lies with the terms themselves, how they shift from one individual or community to the next without time for distinction &#8211; <em>that is the humorous aspect in all of it</em> and the aspect worth exploration, i.e. empirical research. <em>I don&#8217;t used the word Ausländer at all, but I do use </em>Menschen mit Migrationshintergrund<em>, though I shorten it to MMH, and I say it M-M-H just to emphasize the irony of these terms in the German debate.</em></p>
<p>To close this round of questions, the Director of Humboldt University added, <em>When we are talking about integration, we are focusing on those people who have decided to stay in Germany, to live here, to work here. </em>But what does it mean to &#8220;decide&#8221;? To stay? To live? No one at the front of the room mentioned citizenship laws, legal frameworks regarding work and residency permission, or those political ideologies that might bar any empirical work on terminology from having real impact in Parliament. Surely, data for this will be gathered, but the question is, who will listen.</p>
<p><strong>Taking stock</strong></p>
<p>In response to a question from the <em>Tagesspiegel, as to how this institute plans to transfer its knowledge to policy-makers</em>, Naika Forouton, the Representative Director of the institute, responded, <em>One of the purposes of the institute is to move away from a one-sided discourse that we have all experienced&#8230;[However], We do not see that as our job, delivering some report to policy-makers. Pure political performance is not our role.</em></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-4.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2411" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-4.jpg?w=640" alt="BIM 4" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>In 2013 Naika Forouton wrote a highly-informative report in conjunction with the <a href="http://www.migrationpolicy.org/">Migration Policy Institute</a> (MPI), based in Washington D.C., on <a href="http://www.migrationpolicy.org/research/identity-and-muslim-integration-germany">Muslim identity and citizenship in Germany</a>. In 2012, she contributed to a volume of policy analyses for MPI. Policy analysis and the effects thereof constitute a large part of her professional activities, in fact. Perhaps the difference lies in the medium.</p>
<p>In closing, federal integration commissioner, Aydan Özo<span style="color: #435050;">ğ</span>uz, described the field to be investigated by the new BIM as deserted, barren. And to that, <em>Immigrants have been here a long time, but now they are simply increasing. The current discourse is dominated by fear; it is a fear-laden process. It is important, with this in mind, to represent how things really are.</em></p>
<p>But can we amend this desolate landscape through empirical research alone and the data it yields?</p>
<p>The anthropologist, Dr. Wolfgang Kaschuba, seemed to say &#8220;no&#8221;: <em>We need a new form of group understanding, group consensus, even relationships, even in the postmodern age, even in the era of individualism. We need to come together.</em></p>
<p>If all this coming together will produce the data this city and its neighborhoods need, somehow making it to the highest echelons of power, the BIM is a needed initiative, indeed. If not, the ivory-tower-dilemma may leave the German Football Association and others in waiting.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>For more information on the fascinating convergence of football, integration, and political engagement, see projects from the following institutions: <a href="http://www.bosch-stiftung.de/content/language1/html/28056.asp">Robert-Bosch-Stiftung</a> project page, <a href="http://heimatkunde.boell.de/dossier-fussball-integration">Heinrich-Böll-Stiftung</a> project page (here <a href="http://www.nfv-www.de/downloads/s_992/dossier_fussball_integration.pdf">PDF</a> report), <a href="http://www.integration-gelingt-spielend.de/index.php/integration/fussball-integration.html">Bundesliga Stiftung</a> project page (here <a href="http://www.bundesliga.de/media/native/dokument/ebs_broschuere.pdf">PDF </a>report), <a href="http://www.dfb.de/?id=508798">DFB &#8211; German Football Association</a> project page. </em> <em>For more press (German language) on the new institute, here a selection of sources: <a href="http://www.migazin.de/2014/04/07/anpfiff-fuer-die-migrationsforschung/">Migazin</a>, <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/wissen/neues-institut-fuer-migrationsforschung-in-berlin-spielfeld-fuer-die-zuwanderung/9708232.html">Tagesspiegel</a>, <a href="http://www.dfb.de/news/de/d-nachhaltigkeit/dfb-foerdert-neues-institut-fuer-integrationsforschung-in-berlin/56752.html">DFB</a>.</em></p>
<p>All photos unless sourced otherwise were taken by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/11/integration-in-berlin-research-for-a-desolate-landscape/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; and the White Audience</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2014 14:00:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Afrodeutsch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nazi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[segregation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theater]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2248</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One attends a play about an Afro-German living in the years of Nazism and Jim Crow not because of the dramaturgy. One buys the ticket because of the topic's near absence in the German discourse. This is not a review of the play, but rather a continuation of the discussion with the cast that followed. As one of the cast-members remarked, it all comes down to audience: "Black folks probably wouldn't go to the theater to see this play in the U.S., let alone have enough money for the ticket. And here, we have a white audience. So, who are we really talking to here? Who is seeing this play?"...
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>As a student of my own history and place in this world, nothing is more difficult for me than to write about issues of privilege, white-ness, black-ness, and justice in one sitting, because there is so much that can go wrong, so many terms that can be mis-used or mis-assigned, and so many truths that cannot be conveyed in one text. I have done my best. And with all my socio-anthropological know-how, I may still miss the point or offend, for which I am sorry: so is the nature of the subject.</em></p>
<p>One attends a play about an <em>Afrodeutscher* &#8211; </em>Afro-German &#8211; living in the years of Nazism and Jim Crow not because of the dramaturgy. One buys the ticket because of the topic, i.e. its novelty and near absence in the German discourse. &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221;, &#8220;Made Black&#8221;, at the <a href="http://www.etberlin.de/">English Theatre Berlin</a> explores the rich text of race in 1930s Berlin through the experience of Klaus, an unknowing Afro-German &#8211; a word that still spikes the air with rarity, German-ness still seen by many as a monopoly of the white-skinned.</p>
<p>But Klaus&#8217;s character and his experience of targeted exclusion are not that far from the present, as a conversation with the cast will demonstrate.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_4.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_4.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht" width="640" height="1016" /></a></p>
<p>The play&#8217;s dense telling of a complicated history of race, citizenship, and post-colonialism through dialogue is impressive. Equally worthy of praise is the playwright&#8217;s collaboration with a well-versed historian.  The Afro-German actor, with a biography startlingly similar to the protagonist he portrays, is also seemingly extraordinary. The most important element, however, relates to its audience and what this means for theater as a medium of cultural critique.</p>
<p>This is not a review of the play, per se, on which the curtains closed this past Sunday. Rather, this is a review of the discussion with the cast, playwright, and director that came after, the sentiments of which will remain prominent and powerful in my mind, long after audience members have discarded their ticket stubs.</p>
<p><strong>The Conversation</strong></p>
<p>Thursday night, we, a primarily white audience, wait patiently for the cast to take their places at the foot of the stage. The protagonist of the play, the actor to play the American jazz musician, the actor to play the German politician, the playwright (Alexander Thomas), and the director file into folding chairs. <strong>&#8220;Black folks probably wouldn&#8217;t go to the theater to see this play in the U.S., let alone have enough money for the ticket. And here, we have a white audience. So, who are we really talking to here? Who is seeing this play?&#8221;</strong>, says the actor who plays the Black American musician &#8211; the play&#8217;s connective thread to Jim Crow.<strong> </strong>The scene seems to agree.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_3.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2259" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_3.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht theater cast" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>Daniel Brunet, the mustached upstate New Yorker who produces the <a href="http://www.etberlin.de/producing-series/the-lab/">LAB series</a> for the English Theatre and directed this play, chimes in about the lack of representation of certain &#8220;communities&#8221; in cultural institutions. The problem of equitable, fair representation is something sure to resound for both American and German audiences, though certainly in different ways.</p>
<p>This problem is an old one. But it rattles and recalls Berlin&#8217;s more recent debates on multiculturalism, intercultural politics, and the integration &#8211; or just plain tolerance &#8211; of difference. &#8220;The topic of being German <em>and </em>of<em> </em>being a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Person_of_color">person of color</a> (p.o.c.) continues, often with little progress&#8221;, a p.o.c. from the audience remarks, a hint of a German accent in the throat. This topic is contemporary, indeed.</p>
<p><strong>Can theater change these parameters? Can theater ask for more diversity from institutions that have no incentive to include them?</strong></p>
<p>The playwright, a Black American married to a white German woman, wrote &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; as a way to process &#8220;the complexity of these issues&#8221;. And yet, as he makes perfectly clear, representing his own stereotypes of Germans and &#8220;the lack of place in [his] mind for an Other of color in Germany&#8221; is central to the play. &#8220;Otherwise, I would have been acting dishonestly&#8221;, he says, looking into the glare, behind which fragments of the audience, of us, must appear.</p>
<p>The protagonist of the play, himself an Afro-German, speaks, his English flooded with German vowels, his mannerisms oddly similar to his character, who re-asserts his German identity proudly throughout the play in deference to the Othering looks of those around him. This Other, created by the Black American writer, is somehow a reflection of himself, he states, admitting how through rehearsals he struggled to read his lines, even bursting into tears; how the first time he read the play, he felt personally implicated and stripped bare. <strong>&#8220;I am German, my father left when I was three years old, I grew up with my mother, was born in Hamburg, that is all I have ever known”</strong>, he says. The biographies are nearly identical, minus 80 years and a certain regime.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2311.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2255" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2311.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht stage" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>The anger he enacts in the play now takes hold of his voice: the desperation and frustration. <strong>“Once I read the script I knew it had to be done, we had to make this play. Though, during intermission, when I was sprawled on the stage in a pile of paper [the stage is composed mainly of bundles and bundles of blank paper], I sometimes thought ‘what am I doing here, who am I talking to&#8217;”</strong>.</p>
<p>Despite these questions of audience and representation, the play successfully sends a message, one of critique. It weaves the complicated history of American segregation and its sub-human treatment of Blacks with the messianic framing of America&#8217;s involvement in WWII. Through the diverse arrangement of its characters, the play scrutinizes American moral authority in the fight against Nazi ideology and fascism, drawing dramatic attention to Jim Crow and the commonalities between racist ideologies.</p>
<p><strong>The parallels between American oppression and Nazi tyranny become painfully clear, eliciting the following question from the audience: &#8220;Would you show this play in America? And under what conditions?&#8221;</strong></p>
<p>&#8220;We would just need a theater to show it&#8221;, the playwright says with a smile, confidently speaking for the work alone. &#8220;The play was actually meant for an American audience&#8221;, he adds, hence the translation of German passages and numerous references to American &#8216;race sciences&#8217;, details often omitted from textbooks. &#8220;This is a history of not only segregation but of a science [eugenics and race-based Social Darwinism] that many Americans do not know about&#8221;.</p>
<p>Such a truth of ignorance is reflected in the young woman in the play, who claims that the protagonist, Klaus, is not like &#8220;the other Negroes back home!&#8221;, though she has &#8220;never met one&#8221;.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2258" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_2.jpg?w=640" alt="colonialism Jim Crow" width="640" height="411" /></a></p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Theater approaches many controversial political topics in the United States, because it can. A very particular demographic is going to the theater; and that is where such issues can be discussed&#8221;</strong>, Brunet adds.</p>
<p>The playwright explains that he is willing to relinquish artistic license and allow others to define the scope and boundaries of the play&#8217;s possible interpretations. Some scenes are based on his own childhood, others on historical research and collaboration with the author of <em><a href="https://www.press.umich.edu/174272/other_germans">Other Germans</a>, </em>Tina M. Campt<em>, </em>about being a person of African heritage in Germany.</p>
<p>&#8220;But what is the point of the play?&#8221;, the jazz musician asks, perhaps to the audience, perhaps to no one present in this room. It is not about carving out identity from the crowd, asserting the value of the image in the attic mirror, but rather &#8220;about convincing society – the powerful – that exclusion is harmful and degrading to human beings. Now, and back then!&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;The point is, speaking truth to power&#8221;</strong>, he says, referencing, most notably, <a href="http://www.cornelwest.com/">Dr. Cornel West</a>, a giant in the continued civil rights movement for people of color, for the exploited lower classes.</p>
<p>Theater is not a dialogue with the masses, nor a dialogue with society in general, however. &#8220;Like cultural media and cultural politics, it is a dialogue with the powerful and their ideas&#8221;, says Brunet. The rest is some trickle down effect or, as the p.o.c. from the audience adds, &#8220;a change in consciousness&#8221;.</p>
<p>The camera man, a towering Black man with an equally large voice, speaks to the political or &#8220;transformative nature of the play&#8221;: <strong>“Most people ask themselves the question, are things really that different now? That is what this play does, it asks that question again of the powerful&#8221;.</strong></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5em;">With these words, I instantly feel implicated by my privilege, the things afforded to me on the basis of the position and body I was born into. The room shrinks. I shift in my seat.</span></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5em;">We are the audience. We are the ones who should see this play. We shape the discourse, often to the detriment of those who do not fit the desired mold. Theater might be a chance to reflect on <a href="http://www.taz.de/!116745/">critical whiteness</a>, even on its limitations.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2296.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2250" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2296.jpg?w=640" alt="English Theatre Berlin" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>One of the members of the cast remarks, perhaps to break a long 15 seconds of silence, <strong>&#8220;Can we imagine a black actor playing Romeo? A white actor playing Othello? Is it bad that we can&#8217;t?&#8221;</strong> For the sake of this question, &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; should be produced in another season, maybe in another city, as a voice in a room with too few listeners.</p>
<p>I sincerely hope that it might be staged in the United States, a country, where diversity often means tolerating the one that is different but disrespecting him or her just the same. As <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/ta-nehisi-coates/">Ta-Nehisi-Coates</a> wrote in <em>The Atlantic</em> this Tuesday, <strong>&#8220;We are in America, where our absence of virtue is presumed, and we must eat disrespect in sight of our sons.<em> </em>And who can be mad in America? Racism is just the wind, here. Racism is but the rain.&#8221; </strong></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*After the Nazi dust had cleared the German capital and West German society had taken root, the Black American poet and activist Audrey Lorde began to popularize the term <em>Afrodeutsche(r) </em>or Afro-German,<em> </em>during <a href="http://www.audrelorde-theberlinyears.com/">her years in the city</a>, effectively building a movement that at least gave a name to an almost invisible population.</p>
<p><em>For more information on Afro-German history in English, click <a href="http://german.about.com/od/culture/a/blackhistger.htm">here</a>. For more information on Afro-German organizations in Berlin and in all of Germany: <a href="http://isdonline.de/">Initiative schwarze Menschen in Deutschland</a>, <a href="http://www.afro-deutsche.de/">Afrodeutsche e.V</a>, <a href="http://www.adefra.com/">Schwarze deutsche Frauen und schwarze Frauen in Deutschland</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>For an interesting twist, check out our <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/">article on Black Germans</a> (the change of language here was intentional) growing up in the United States to adoptive parents, often in the segregated South. </em></p>
<p>Photo source: Kelly Miller and <a href="http://jurigottschau.com/">Juri Gottschau</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Roma in Berlin: Bureaucracy in Lichtenberg</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/20/roma-in-berlin-bureaucracy-in-lichtenberg/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/20/roma-in-berlin-bureaucracy-in-lichtenberg/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2013 14:39:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bureaucracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[discrimination]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lichtenberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1736</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On the first Tuesday of every month, the <em><a href="http://www.migrantenrat.de/">Migrantenrat Lichtenberg</a> </em>(immigrants' plenary) meets to address issues of migration affecting the district and its neighborhoods. The gospel of November's session: The Roma are coming! 2014 will be a year of change for Roma in Berlin, primarily for those who have come from Bulgaria and Romania. They will have access to the social welfare system, the situation will change dramatically. But this is about families, not simply numbers...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;<a href="http://www.bild.de/geld/wirtschaft/zuwanderung/droht-uns-eine-roma-welle-29296194.bild.htmlhttp://www.bild.de/geld/wirtschaft/zuwanderung/droht-uns-eine-roma-welle-29296194.bild.html">Is a wave of Roma threatening Germany?</a>&#8221; was the recent headline of a popular paper, known for its tabloid-esque reporting. In the Eastern district of Lichtenberg, this headline becomes bureaucracy. In reality, it is about parents, children, and families, who happen to be Roma.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/roma-familie_dokumentationszentrum.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/roma-familie_dokumentationszentrum.jpg?w=640" alt="Roma Familie_Dokumentationszentrum" width="512" height="392" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.sintiundroma.de/start.html">Source</a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">For my fieldwork in sociocultural anthropology, I run from one site of so-called immigrant integration to the next in the Berlin districts of Lichtenberg and Marzahn, doing my best to put together a structure that informs a system of practice. Within the waiting rooms and narrow offices of institutions serving immigrants, Roma are present and obvious, sticking out like a sore thumb without the opportunity for dialogue; they are talked about or talked around. <strong>And so one cannot talk about migration, diversity, and multicultural inclusion in Berlin without talking about how Lichtenberg talks about Roma.</strong></p>
<p>On the first Tuesday of every month, the <em><a href="http://www.migrantenrat.de/">Migrantenrat Lichtenberg</a> </em>(immigrants&#8217; plenary) meets to address issues of migration affecting the district and its neighborhoods. Tables are pushed together to frame a discussion, and the renovated walls of the Lichtenberg city hall fill with urgent  deliberation. The gospel of November&#8217;s session: <strong>The Roma are coming!</strong></p>
<p>At this month&#8217;s plenary, approx. 20 Berliners were in attendance. Based on attire and commentary, bureaucrats from the district employment office (Job Center) and volunteer representatives of  ethnic-cultural organizations of immigrant populations mingled with local political officers. The new district <a href="http://www.berlin.de/ba-lichtenberg/politik/integrationsbeauftragte01.html">commissioner for integration</a>, Bärbel Olhagaray, was presiding &#8211; speaking perfect <em>hochdeutsch, </em>pursing her lips after every third word. But <em>I am married to a Chilean</em>, she remarked in her introduction, one among many reasons why she is an advocate for immigrant integration.</p>
<div id="attachment_1761" style="width: 425px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/baerbel.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1761" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1761 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/baerbel.jpg" alt="baerbel" width="415" height="620" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/baerbel.jpg 415w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/baerbel-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 415px) 100vw, 415px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1761" class="wp-caption-text">Frau Bärbel Olhagaray, Integration Commissioner of Lichtenberg</p></div>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.berliner-woche.de/nachrichten/bezirk-lichtenberg/artikel/29620-baerbel-olhagaray-ist-die-neue-beauftragte-fuer-integration-in-lichtenberg/">Source</a></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5;">She offered the opening address, the title of which was &#8216;Roma in Lichtenberg&#8217;. </span><span style="line-height: 1.5;">The speech began with numbers.</span></p>
<p><em><span style="line-height: 1.5;">Roma number about 800 to 900 in Lichtenberg, though many, many more are to be expected. There are three apartment complexes known to house predominately Roma families in our district, characterized by negligent landlords and overpriced rent. We approached these residences as a reaction to complaints in the area. <strong>Families of 6 occupy 30 square meters for a price of 600 Euros, sleeping nearly shoulder-to-shoulder.</strong> The houses lack consistent ways to dispose of waste. Our priorities are to reinstate order and cleanliness and to visit the families regularly to see what is needed.</span></em></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/fennpfuhl.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1758" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/fennpfuhl.jpg?w=640" alt="Fennpfuhl" width="640" height="382" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/fennpfuhl.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/fennpfuhl-300x179.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/fennpfuhl-650x388.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.jeder-qm-du.de/platten-doku/platten-wissen/detail/wbsqp-71-r/">Source</a></p>
<p>But figures and living situations do not matter as much as Euros, at least as policy demonstrates. The economic element of Roma immigration is the primary reason the &#8216;Roma problem&#8217; has gained attention and notoriety, particularly in districts overwhelmed by rumors that may prove to be true.</p>
<p>Since Bulgaria and Romania&#8217;s entrance into the European Union&#8217;s economic area, which allows for the transference of work permission and skills from one member state to the next, only partial admission into the German job market has been granted for citizens from these countries. Citing a wave of unqualified workers, often illiterate, into a strong market-driven economy, i.e. a wave of Roma, this act of exclusion became German federal policy. According to the European Union, Germany was acting in violation of economic rules of engagement and must retract its restricted work policy for immigrants from Bulgaria and Romania at the start of 2014. This affects Roma.</p>
<p><strong><em>Most of the families are registered as self-employed</em>, Mrs. Olhagaray continued, <em>since they do not yet have the full benefits of EU citizenship, which grants them state assistance in many cases of difficulty. </em></strong>They wash windshields at traffic lights, peddle on the U-Bahn, play music in front of the mall entrance and somehow make ends meet.<em> They send most of their kids to school, as far as we are aware, and ensure that they learn German while they are there.</em></p>
<p>When she and her colleagues go by for a visit, she added, they are greeted with open arms, tea, and cake. <em>They know we are there to help them&#8230;and they need our help.</em></p>
<p>The room became silent, waiting for the evident problem to become clear.</p>
<p><strong><em>2014 will be a year of change for Roma in Berlin, primarily for those who have come from Bulgaria and Romania.</em> </strong><em><strong>They will have access to the social welfare system, the situation will change dramatically</strong>, </em>full stop.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/zigeuner.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1762" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/zigeuner.jpg" alt="zigeuner" width="312" height="412" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/zigeuner.jpg 312w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/zigeuner-227x300.jpg 227w" sizes="(max-width: 312px) 100vw, 312px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.pi-news.net/2013/01/einbrecher-asyl-antrage-von-zigeunern/">Source</a></p>
<p>Legal change may not change bureaucracy over night. In fact, it may take years until needy families receive any sort of visibility or assistance in the political arena. The <em>Migrantenrat</em> may set the agenda in the community and have an influence on local government, but laws are passed elsewhere.</p>
<p>Part of the problem with assisting Roma in Lichtenberg is the presence of stereotypes, seldom confirmed and often well-spread, evidenced by the contribution of one bureaucrat in employment services. Mrs. Olhagaray listened intently, as the woman &#8211; originally from Bulgaria &#8211; began to describe the situation of &#8216;<em>Zigeuner</em>&#8216; (gypsies), a <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/panorama/gesellschaft/zigeunersossen-streit-interview-mit-silvio-peritore-a-916760.html">word that has since become derogatory</a>, particularly in the culinary world. In a slight Slavic accent, she told of <strong><em>these people: stripping their living quarters of metal and valuable materials for money, over populating neighborhoods, lacking hygiene and order.</em></strong> With one finger pointed out the window at the end of the room:<em> the Pentecostal church, poverty, and illiteracy have led to too many children and no way to care for them!</em></p>
<p>But the cycle is slowly being broken. Many Roma children in Berlin are indeed going to school, and Berlin boasts <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/18/rave-education-per-square-kilometer/">initiatives which help them excel, as Sophia profiled back in June.</a> In many countries where Roma have lived before immigrating to Germany, school was not compulsory and in many cases was informally forbidden to them.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/roma-kids-in-school.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1759" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/roma-kids-in-school.jpg" alt="Roma kids in school" width="300" height="200" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://kubus-berlin.de/de/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/opener.jpg">Source</a></p>
<p>It seemed that our task in the <em>Migrantenrat </em>was simply to absorb the fragments of a crisis: the Roma problem unfolding like a heavy, scarlet rug out onto the plenary floor. <strong>Bureaucracy is often about working within the rules set by others, not about solving problems.</strong></p>
<p><em>But why do they come here? Why do the countries where they come from not intervene?</em>, asked a literacy volunteer in Lichtenberg schools, now working to absorb the newly-arrived children of Roma families, who may have never seen a book in their home but <em>come eagerly to learn, nonetheless, </em>she shared.</p>
<p>Without <a href="http://fra.europa.eu/sites/default/files/fra_uploads/413-EU-MIDIS_ROMA_EN.pdf">the story of systemic segregation and discrimination</a> behind the Roma (and Sinti) experience in Europe, answering this question is a difficult task. The situation becomes one of economics and not of humanism or even moral action &#8211; something enshrined in Germany&#8217;s constitution under its provisions for asylum and human rights.</p>
<p><em>So, if they can now access social services like any other EU-citizen, how many are expected to come?</em>, asked a representative from the Russian community, his voice lightened by compassion, though cut with a hint of anxiety.</p>
<p><em>Many</em>, was the message, <em>simply thousands</em>. With some other countries <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/02/opinion/02garcia.html?_r=2&amp;ref=romanipeople&amp;">forcefully rejecting Roma and clearing settlements, as in France</a>, Germany, especially Berlin, will become key destinations in the future.</p>
<p>Fortunately, social work agencies for immigrant populations have developed many projects for Roma-related challenges in Berlin, long before the problem was as acute as it is now. Talking to a <a href="http://www.dicvberlin.caritas.de/">Caritas </a>social worker from my fieldwork, I was told that it was the NGOs and not the government who pushed for <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">integration courses</a> to contain a path to literacy. <strong><em>How are they meant to learn German and get a job if they do not know the alphabet, we thought, so we asked for 900 hours of instruction instead of just 600, where they at least have a chance</em>,</strong> she said, exasperated.  <em><br />
</em></p>
<p>Another Caritas colleague was present at the <em>Migrantenrat </em>on this November day.  She sat quietly next to me, taking few notes, her arms crossed. As a social worker with more knowledge of German immigration and employment laws than any bureaucrat I have ever met, she looked a bit frustrated at the shock and awe that surrounding the discussion of a so-called impending crisis.</p>
<p>At the end of the plenary, she turned to me: <strong><em>This problem has been here a long time, we have been telling them&#8230;they didn&#8217;t listen.</em></strong></p>
<p>I turned off my recorder. After reviewing the sound bites from the evening, one thing was clear: Of course, the Roma are coming. Why wouldn&#8217;t they? <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Yrgnkd-Lsl8">Everyone is coming to Berlin.</a> This time, however, these people are not starving artists but rather a persecuted minority, seeking everything they have been denied. Even bureaucrats know that.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>There is no single <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/01/happy-weekend-a-roma-reimage/">Roma identity</a> or one Roma community, but for starters, some further resources are in order. Roma in Berlin: <a href="http://www.sinti-roma-berlin.de/">Landesverband Deutscher Sinti und Roma Berlin-Brandenburg e.V</a>., the German Roma and Sinti <a href="http://www.sintiundroma.de/start.html">documentation and educational center </a>for current debates and cultural awareness in Heidelberg, the European Union&#8217;s <a href="http://fra.europa.eu/sites/default/files/fra_uploads/413-EU-MIDIS_ROMA_EN.pdf">report on discrimination against Roma</a>. Finally, the <a href="http://www.migrantenrat.de/"><em>Migrantenrat Lichtenberg</em></a> is open to the public, if further discussions involving Roma and district politics happen to be of interest.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/20/roma-in-berlin-bureaucracy-in-lichtenberg/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rave: Why Remembering the Holocaust is Good for Immigrants</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2013 08:43:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GDR-DDR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Holocaust]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jewish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[museums]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nazi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1353</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In 2005, Germany officially became an immigration country with the establishment of its federal office for migration. The question - who are the Germans anyway? - has become increasingly important in deciding what to impart to these newcomers set to stay. Expats are good at constructing Germanness for the Germans themselves, often leaving out the Holocaust in such a description of 'German identity', however. Today's Germany - an immigration country - is a republic built on tragic events like the Holocaust, just as France is a country built on colonialism. Everything has a context, and it is this context that immigrants to Germany should learn to understand for the sake of a more complete country - a civic society which respects differences and celebrates them...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p dir="ltr">In 2005, Germany officially became an immigration country with the establishment of its federal office for migration (<a href="http://www.bamf.de/EN/Startseite/startseite-node.html">BAMF</a>). A wave of new laws and institutions were to follow, set to absorb those meant to stay &#8211; not just <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gastarbeiter">guest-workers</a>, not temporary migrants, not <a href="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vertragsarbeiter">comrades</a> (so-called <em>Vertragsarbeiter</em> from communist countries), but immigrants. In turn, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">German identity </a>has been shoved into the limelight. This country and its residents have witnessed plenty of change and adjustment, but redefining self and country after the fall of the Berlin Wall (even during the student <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protests_of_1968">protests of 1968</a>) had little to do with defining oneself in opposition to a foreign but stationary Other. Although individuals and families with non-German origins have been coming for centuries, confronting what will be an official change in what it means to be German is rather new, rather fresh.</p>
<div style="width: 600px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b038669g"><img loading="lazy" class=" " title="Justin Rowlatt and his wife Bee set out to live like a typical German family" src="http://images.dailyexpress.co.uk/img/dynamic/20/590x/make-me-a-german-420020.jpg" alt="Justin-Rowlatt-and-his-wife-Bee-set-out-to-live-like-a-typical-German-family" width="590" height="350" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Who are the Germans anyway? A BBC series answers this question by-doing</p></div>
<p dir="ltr">The question &#8211; who are the Germans anyway? &#8211; becomes increasingly important when deciding what to impart to newcomers. Which traditions deserve saving? What is important? The answers to these questions are not as simple as good bread or Hefeweizen. Expats with an outsider perspective are not shy in constructing simple &#8216;Germanness&#8217; for the Germans themselves. The BBC reality TV series &#8220;<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/tv-and-radio/2013/aug/07/make-me-german-tv-review">Make Me a German</a>&#8221; plays with stereotypes and assumptions about what is <em>typisch deutsch</em> (typically German); the viral blog post <a href="http://www.uberlin.co.uk/what-i-know-about-germans/"><em>What I know about Germans </em></a>is just one example of trendy list-making of all things &#8216;German&#8217; by temporary residents; Berlin-based comedy writer <a href="http://adam-fletcher.co.uk/">Adam Fletcher</a> has created an entire <a href="http://store.hipstery.com/">brand</a> just based on the funny categorization of ‘Germanness’. On a tote bag in Fletcher’s line of nifty and hilarious merchandise: an engineer’s instruments, a watch, whole wheat, nude culture, asparagus. But where is the concentration camp in these lists, this series, or this fashion line? Where is the Holocaust?</p>
<div id="attachment_1362" style="width: 522px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218225820494823.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1362" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-1362" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218225820494823.png?w=640" alt="Aviary Photo_130218225820494823" width="512" height="682" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1362" class="wp-caption-text">Entrance to Sachsenhausen concentration camp, Oranienburg, DE</p></div>
<p dir="ltr">This past weekend, I embarked on a day-long tour of the former <a href="http://www.stiftung-bg.de/gums/en/index.htm">Sachsenhausen concentration camp</a> with a good friend here in Berlin &#8211; a friend, who just happens to be Jewish and originally from Ukraine.  We were a small group for an English speaking tour, minuscule in comparison to the masses of Italian and Spanish tour groups all heading to the same location. Two Taiwanese students, an American-Spanish couple on vacation from their residence in Saudi Arabia, a Brazilian student traveling Europe for the first time, a Bulgarian engineer, and Max and I (both Americans). We met our guide Alex, exchanged small talk, in part to find out why we all were willing to commit seven hours on a Sunday to hearing about tragedy, visiting the haunted, vast expanses of Sachsenhausen &#8211; a concentration camp just right on the edge of Berlin, reachable with the S-Bahn (public transit).</p>
<p dir="ltr">In contemporary political discussions about integration of immigrants into ‘German society’, no one claims that integration requires learning the lessons of the Holocaust. And yet, federal integration programs combined with international perception of Germanness say just that. The public concept of historical memorialization and its application, called <em>Vergangenheitsbewältigung, </em>is just as important to living in German society as <em>v</em><em>ollkorn Brötchen </em>or <em>Oktoberfest. </em></p>
<p dir="ltr">On our tour&#8217;s long walk from <a href="http://www.oranienburg.de/texte/seite.php?id=91511">Oranienburg</a> station to the gates of the camp, passing average-looking &#8216;German&#8217; homes with gardens neatly segregated from the street by high fences, I spoke with Natalia (the student from São Paulo) about Germany, the Germans, and the Holocaust. She brought up an interesting point: “How do the Germans feel about it &#8211; that people go to Venice to see the canals and to Berlin to see the Holocaust? I can imagine they don’t like it”. A man jogged past us in bright running-gear, his dog trotting behind him, just passing the entrance to the camp. This is part of being German &#8211; accepting that this is how you are seen in the world, that this history is an indivisible part of any sense of being German, it seemed.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218225935786183.png"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1363" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218225935786183.png?w=640" alt="Aviary Photo_130218225935786183" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p dir="ltr">For new residents of Berlin, the past still matters and maybe even more than integration programs can provide for. My Ukrainian-American-Jewish friend Max (gotta love them hyphens) and his family left Kiev when he was five, in part due to Antisemitism. His great-great-grandparents were killed in the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Babi_Yar">Babi Yar massacre</a> of 1941. The precarious relationship of the German government to its new status as an immigration country, let alone the way it classifies its non-German residents, is very much familiar to Max. &#8220;So, how does that make you feel as a Jew in Germany?&#8221;, I asked a bit sheepishly, recognizing the change of context from friendly chatter we usually entertain to rrrrrreal real fast. Many Jewish immigrants to Germany have likely heard this question before. “Antisemitism is more the exception than the rule. I don’t feel confronted by it in daily life&#8230;but I know it’s there”, he concluded. He is supportive of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-Fascist_Action">Antifa</a> movements, aware that being Jewish in Germany is complicated but totally do-able, requiring a little finesse. Berlin, of course, has all kinds of finesse.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Our tour entered Sachsenhausen through the renovated watchtower and its metal gates, a construction bearing the architectural legacy of the post-war custodians of the camp and many others &#8211; the (East) German Democratic Republic. A stream of other visitors followed our trail, audio devices pressed to their ears. I felt strange, almost supportive of an odd form of tourism, securing Natalia&#8217;s comment about the connection of Holocaust tourism to German identity in reality.</p>
<p dir="ltr" style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3419" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_1302182256975699431.png" alt="aviary-photo_130218225697569943" width="606" height="606" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_1302182256975699431.png 606w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_1302182256975699431-300x300.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 606px) 100vw, 606px" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">A cacophony of languages could be heard as we moved from one monument within the camp to another &#8211; Swedish, Japanese, British English, French &#8211; all reading the same saddening information on plaques or biographical exhibition panels, all bearing witness to tragedy and an integral part (if not the deciding event) of this country&#8217;s history and present.</p>
<p dir="ltr">We moved to the far edge of the camp, heading toward the restored Barrack 38: the Jewish barrack turned memorial documentation center. As we entered the small structure, the smell of charred wood was unmistakable, paint peeling from the siding of the latrine and sleeping porch. Arson. In 1992, German identity was thrust under international limelight after reunification and the growing pains that followed, further exacerbated by the rise of Neonazism in the former East. Arson was a key expression of this tension. This same year of the attack on Barrack 38, Neonazis set fire to a refugee housing facility not too far from Berlin, terrorizing residents in the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Riot_of_Rostock-Lichtenhagen">riot of Rostock-Lichtenhagen</a>. The political activities of parties and movements, such as the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Democratic_Party_of_Germany">NPD</a> (German Nationalist Party with strong Neonazi ties), as well as the recent <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/topic/national_socialist_underground/">Neonazi terror-cell</a> and its string of xenophobic murders across Germany, point to a  contemporary relevance of the Nazi past to Germany’s future as a country of immigration. The Holocaust and its constitutive role in Germany identity has been part of the country&#8217;s historical development ever since. What to teach immigrants &#8211; remember the Holocaust.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3420" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226423822983-650x487.png" alt="aviary-photo_130218226423822983" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226423822983-650x487.png 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226423822983-300x225.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226423822983-80x60.png 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226423822983.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">We left the camp in a drizzle of rain, boarding the S-Bahn back to Berlin. As our guide Alex (speaking a high variety of the King&#8217;s English) began to share an illustrative vignette about the end of the war and deterioration of Nazi moral power in Germany, passengers in the train appeared perturbed. A woman with fiery hair shook her head in disgust; she furled insults in German in our guide&#8217;s direction (understood only by me at the time). Another stern-faced German woman entered shortly after, raising her voice to replace that of the recently exited red-haired woman. Her lips quivering, she looked to be my mother’s age, the veins in her neck traumatically flinching, exposed. “Why don’t you just stop talking. It is rude what you are doing. It is not right what you are doing. We don’t need to be lectured to! You must stop&#8221;, she said abruptly in English.</p>
<p dir="ltr">German trains and buses are anything but loud, each keeping to his or herself in a very strong show of privacy. This may be a stereotype, but it illuminates the particular conflict that ensued quite well.</p>
<p dir="ltr">With eyes closed in shock, our guide explained that we were on an educational tour of the concentration camp, that he had been doing this for years and had never had such a negative reaction. He kept calm and showed no sign of anger or distress. The female companion of the pulsing-veined woman responded loudly with perhaps the only words she knew: &#8220;shut uppp!&#8221;, popping the &#8216;p&#8217; just at the end.</p>
<p dir="ltr">My friend Max intervened &#8211; asked our guide to have a seat, standing to allow him to do so. With hands shaking and eyes kept closed, Alex continued his narrative: the time after the war, the protests of 1968, de-Nazification in educational and political institutions, current movements of young people, general skepticism toward patriotism in Germany ever since &#8211; all forming parts of a whole history that has never really come to a close.</p>
<p dir="ltr">As we exited the train, the pulsing-veined woman ran to Alex, extending her hand to graze his: &#8220;I agree with everything you said!&#8221;, she said, &#8220;but you were just speaking so loud for a public place! It is a train, not a classroom. Your voice was really just too loud for all of us, so for next time, just speak quieter.&#8221; She paused, Alex thanked her. And then with one last quiver of the lip: &#8220;I was one of those Germans you talked about, one of those students with guilt for something I wasn&#8217;t even old enough to have participated in. So thank you for what you said&#8230;&#8221;</p>
<p dir="ltr">&#8220;I don’t want anyone thinking ‘oh these horrible Germans’. I don’t want you all leaving thinking that,&#8221; the woman added as we had nearly let the train doors shut behind us, her eyes directed at all of us in a show of penetrating honesty. Education about the past does more than just memorialize or prevent reoccurrence: it avoids essentialization of historical events and preserves the complexity of it all.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3421" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226704073063-650x487.png" alt="aviary-photo_130218226704073063" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226704073063-650x487.png 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226704073063-300x225.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226704073063-80x60.png 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226704073063.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">With the new immigration status of 2005 and the integration programs that followed, came the creation of an <a href="http://www.bamf.de/EN/Willkommen/DeutschLernen/Integrationskurse/InhaltAblauf/inhaltablauf-node.html">&#8216;integration curriculum&#8217;</a>, including cultural orientation that included this very facet of Germanness: the Holocaust. Immigrants participating in the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">integration courses </a>visit historical institutions designed to communicate the significance of the Nazi period for Germany as both a modern state and as a group of transnational or transethnic individuals.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Official curriculum including Holocaust field-trips doesn&#8217;t answer all questions, however. Politicians are still scratching their heads at the &#8216;German question&#8217; &#8211; each party choosing which elements it wants to claim for the imagined &#8216;nation&#8217;, some famously campaigning for a <em>Leitkultur (</em>one central guiding culture for Germany by Germans). Such a sentiment has been heavily criticized by most politicians outside of the leading conservative party (CDU), including the head of the Jewish Council of Germany, Paul Spiegel. In a speech to Parliament, Spiegel said <em><a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/archiv/leitkultur---die-scharfe-kritik-von-paul-spiegel-am--verbalen-zuendeln-der-politiker--hat-die-union-aufgeschreckt--der-bundesrat-stimmte-dem-antrag-auf-ein-verbot-der-rechtsextremen-npd-zu--merz-versuchte-zu-intervenieren,10810590,9851008.html">&#8220;Ist es etwa deutsche Leitkultur, Fremde zu jagen, Synagogen anzuzünden, Obdachlose zu töten?&#8221;</a>, &#8220;is it &#8216;German culture&#8217; to hunt down foreigners, to light synagogues on fire, to kill the homeless</em>?&#8221; The Holocaust is not far from these debates about Germanness, thus it is no wonder that it is included at least in educational programs to include newcomers in German society.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Today&#8217;s Germany &#8211; an immigration country &#8211; is a republic built on tragic events like the Holocaust, just as France is a country built on colonialism. This is not to say that countries and their residents are reducible to history. Rather it is to say that institutions and individuals are still intimately connected to what came before. It is about understanding how one can relate to such a history in its contemporary place, shaping either collective guilt or political activism (in the likes of Antifa) just the same. Everything has a context, and it is this context that immigrants to Germany should learn to understand for the sake of a more complete country &#8211; a civic society which respects differences and celebrates them. For Germany is not just for those who were once classified as &#8216;ethnically German&#8217;, it is for anyone that chooses to reside in Germany. Becoming German* is understanding history and what it might mean for the present, regardless of ethnicity.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><em>-By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>*Not sure, if you are German? Take this funny quiz from none other than Adam Fletcher <a href="http://www.thegermanquiz.com/">here</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>Our free tour to Sachsenhausen concentration camp was provided by <a href="http://www.viveberlintours.de/en/tours/sachsenhausen">Vive Berlin Tours</a></em>, <em>meeting Tuesdays, Fridays, and Sundays at 10am at Balzac Coffee on Potsdamer Platz year-round. Our guide, <a href="http://www.viveberlintours.de/en/guides">Alex</a>, comes highly recommended, as does this cooperative-style tour company which prides itself on expertise and narrative, as well as fairness for its employees. </em></p>
<p>Photo source: first image linked to source, otherwise taken by Kelly Miller</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Weekend Review: Germany&#8217;s &#8216;Brown Babies&#8217; (how America&#8217;s good-guy image might get a run for its money)</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2013 16:38:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Afrodeutsch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[segregation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=724</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Berlin can be a historical mine field. Escaping the fact that genocide, division, tyranny, even the colonial division of Africa began on this ground is an impossible feat. As American tourists wander through the many memorials to the lost, murdered, and persecuted that saturate the city with this remembrance of tragedy, I have to ask myself: Do we Americans think that we were always the “good guys” in this mess?]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Berlin can be a historical mine field. Escaping the fact that genocide, division, tyranny, even the colonial division of Africa began on this ground is an impossible feat. As American tourists wander through the many memorials to the lost, murdered, and persecuted that saturate the city with this remembrance of tragedy, I have to ask myself: Do we Americans think that we were always the “good guys” in this mess?</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter" src="http://www.kinocast.net/wp-content/uploads/Kinocast/Inglorious_Basterds2.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>Germany may have a particularly difficult past, but the catastrophes of the 21<sup>st</sup> century &#8211; and the ill which permeate them &#8211; were in no form a European phenomenon, let alone a product of everyone’s favorite enemy: Adolf Hitler and the Third Reich. American mythos about WWII would like to position a liberating force of Justice against a tyrannical force of Evil (usually inaccurately embodied by one Charlie Chaplin-mustache-wearing leader doing a special kind of rigid salute). Villains of this type, the kind meant for blockbuster films and theatrical reenactments, often detract from the other kind of villain &#8211; our own. Demonizing Germany as the dramatically viscous perpetrator can detract from the other transatlantic evil-dooers, namely, those who held other human beings of darker skin in socioeconomic captivity for centuries (see the <a href="http://newjimcrow.com/">New Jim Crow</a> for its present manifestations). No other history of slavery, segregation, and integration is as dynamic and disgusting as the American story. And yet, Nazi Germany steals the show; the Americans arrive with massive tanks and candy for children; evil is blighted out with a swift hand of justice and freedom&#8230;so goes the myth of the &#8220;good guys&#8221;. And so this myth must be, once again, popped.</p>
<p>I know just the documentary to do it &#8211; <em>Arte&#8217;s </em>&#8220;<a href="http://videos.arte.tv/de/videos/brown-babies--7526612.html">Brown Babies</a>&#8221; in German or its English counterpart &#8220;<a href="http://brownbabiesproject.com/">The Mischlingskinder Story</a>&#8220;. I watched &#8220;Brown Babies&#8221; on <em>Arte </em>this past Thursday. Here are some scenes, impressions, maybe even a splash of critique. Most importantly, here is a snapshot of an oft-forgotten part of history, giving America&#8217;s good-guy image a run for its money.</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p><em>A 50-something black man with slight European features,  hair combed back into waves, drives a tractor through the wheat fields of a farm just outside Washington D.C. He uses the back of his hand to wipe sweat from his eyes. In those eyes is nothing but wandering, the search for self and whatever comfort the solidification of one’s biography might provide.</em></p>
<p>He is one of more than 100,000 so-called <em>Besatzungskinder</em>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_children">War children</a>, born shortly after WWII to a German mother and an American father, a soldier, stationed on temporary duty in post-war Germany, when the country, especially Berlin, was divided into strict military zones. Dan belongs to smaller sub-set within this statistic, a sub-set not so often discussed. Dan is black, well mulatto…well he isn’t sure, and in the 1950s, neither Germany nor the United States saw him as ‘integratable’, rather as “racially problematic”. Germany suggested the return of such children to their &#8216;origins&#8217;, that is, to families with similar &#8216;racial&#8217; composition. America accepted such children under the pretense of segregation &#8211; they would be kept out of white public places, situated in families of their own kind. And all this <em>after </em>the Holocaust, after the scandal of rejected Jewish refugees from American shores leading up to the genocide, all this after moral imperatives were touted as reasons to enter to the war.</p>
<p>And so in 1951, shipments of darker-skinned children began, sent to strangers in a land which forbid them most basic rights. 7,000 of these so-called brown babies were adopted by families in the United States, almost exclusively into African-American families, as Jim Crow and general trends within the Union would dictate. Their German mothers gave them up for many reasons, often rooted in a combination of state and community pressure to rid society of un-integratable elements. The United States took them in officially, but did little to ensure their well-being, ensuring rather their subjection to segregation.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/wanda-lynn.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-725 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/wanda-lynn.jpg" alt="Rosemarie Pena" width="640" height="459" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/wanda-lynn.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/wanda-lynn-300x215.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/wanda-lynn-650x466.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>In the 1950s, shipping half-white, half-black children to African-American families was a political act and often a dangerous one. Civil Rights protests were just beginning to take root in student communities, church congregations, workers’ strikes; the pavement of Montgomery and even Chicago were already tainted with the blood of black Americans and the rubber bullets of an oppressive state. Many of these children were put into the American South, but even in the North, racial discrimination was social custom even if it wasn&#8217;t outright law. It was in 1955 that Rosa Parks refused to give up her seat on a bus, unleashing lynchings and riots across the South. In this same year the corpse of young <a href="http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/amex/till/">Emmit Till</a> was found flogged and bloated in a river of impunity. Into this oppression and brewing revolution young children speaking only German, the language of the former enemy, arrived, hearing the term <em>Kraut </em>for the very first time, often followed by N***** or Negro. Quite confusing nomenclature for a confusing situation!</p>
<p><em>“We did not choose to be a part of a movement. But living in the black family I was in, I had to participate”, Dan describes. His parents took in many other “brown babies”. But not as an act of charity, rather as an economic calculation with a full farm to run, he tells the camera. European-black children did not share the history of the ‘freed’ slaves. The movement felt foreign to him; his family estranged.</em></p>
<p><em>Peggy, also in her late 50s, decides to track down her biological mother in Germany. She flies to Karlsruhe, finds herself wandering among clean cobble-stone streets, searching for the small graveyard where her mother is buried. She pulls weeds away from the headstone, planted in an untended cemetery in 1992 &#8211; she waited too long. </em></p>
<p><em>Peggy seeks relatives, rings the apartment building of her biological sister, clutching papers with information of living and deceased family members. It is amazing what the internet can provide. A small blonde-haired woman opens the door, shocked as Peggy explains their relation. The encounter in the apartment is quaint, even restrained. Peggy sits with a Lakers baseball cap and a &#8220;USA&#8221; T-shirt, her hands nervously folded in her hap. She asks for photos. </em><em>“You look like her”; “your father is Peurto Rican”; “she just didn’t want kids; she would rather go dancing than stay home with the children”. A niece visiting from American conveniently interprets. </em></p>
<p>The other 4 stories of unwanted birth, migration, adoption, black or multiracial identity in the United States dash across the screen. Stories of the falsified Afro in a time in which hair was political, vignettes  of a childhood growing up in families struggling to identify themselves as revolutionaries, subservient, fighters, blacks, or former slaves, Afro-German-American children asking too many questions about their own lighter skin color, getting often in the middle of fights, hearing the repeated “you are lucky I took you in”.</p>
<p>Germany and the United States are two very different countries compared to their pasts – both dealing with racism publicly and productive, though there is much to be done. The project is just beginning. Part of a complete <em>Vergangenheitsbewältigung </em>(German for confronting or even overcoming the past) is recognizing times of complicity and complacency, integrating these moments of ethical weakness within our teaching and reproduction of historical narratives. For the stories we tell of ourselves are only as true as the breadth of their inclusion. Until this point, WWII narratives have heroized Americans as Liberators and Germans as evil-dooers. Within the greater spectrum of historical experience, America continued to inhumanely repress its ethnic minorities, long after the tragedy of Auschwitz was unleashed. What does this say about America? And what does this say about the good guys?</p>
<p>What cannot be explained in a documentary is the complexity and variation in experience between regions of the United States, family dynamics, configurations of urban versus rural upbringing, and even color-based hierarchies within American black communities. The German documentary could have spent a few more minutes devoted to these differences and what cannot be examined, even made sense of within the pictured narratives. &#8220;Brown Babies&#8221; comes highly recommended, despite its inability to make all complexity of a generation and a movement accessible. It can be moved anytime from <a href="http://videos.arte.tv/de/videos#/tv/coverflow///1/120/"><em>Arte</em></a>&#8216;s Mediathek.</p>
<p><em>-By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em> </em>For more information on Afro-German children born directly after the war, including those not necessarily shipped out to black American families, check out the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brown_Babies">Wikipedia</a> page as a starting ground, this interesting <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/germany-s-brown-babies-the-difficult-identities-of-post-war-black-children-of-gis-a-651989.html">article</a> (in English) from <em>Der Spiegel, </em>and the website <a href="http://blackgermans.us/new/">Black Germans US</a> &#8211; a networking, research, and media project by Afro-German-Americans living either in the United States or in Germany.</p>
<p>Photo source &#8211; <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/germany-s-brown-babies-the-difficult-identities-of-post-war-black-children-of-gis-a-651989.html">Spiegel Online</a>, IMDB</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
