<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Islam &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/islam/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Why Feminism and Hijab Go Together</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/12/04/feminism-hijab-go-together/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2016 09:30:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[feminism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hijab]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4704</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As Muslim refugees who choose to wear hijab become a lasting part of the societies of those European states that have taken them in, their right to be different must be defended. Most importantly, we must defend the right of women to choose. It is this choice that makes women free. This is why feminism and hijab go together.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Donald Trump will soon take over the most (seemingly) powerful office in the United States. In just one month,&nbsp;<em>Vogue</em> will launch&nbsp;its <a href="http://en.vogue.fr/fashion/fashion-news/articles/conde-nast-international-launches-vogue-arabia/43938">first ever Arabia edition</a>. These two events are related &#8211; by hijab.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Only hours after Trump was proclaimed victor by electoral vote, a certain fear took hold in minority populations in the United States. Fear of deportation, of political oppression, of social persecution. This fear has proven itself well-founded. The Southern Poverty Law Center recently reported </span><a href="http://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/hate-on-the-rise-after-trumps-election">a dramatic increase in hate crimes and xenophobic harassment</a>, since Trump’s victory.</p>
<div id="attachment_4711" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4711" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4711 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341-650x433.jpg" alt="reise_usa-2015-bearbeitet-341" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4711" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Given the President-elect’s verbal attacks on Islam and Muslims in (or coming to) America, this fear of emboldened hostility in the general populace is felt <a href="http://people.com/bodies/muslim-women-scared-wear-hijab-trump-win/">ever so acutely</a> by America’s diverse Muslim community. Muslim women, in particular, have expressed a new hesitation to wear hijab in public &#8211; the traditional headscarf &#8211; following the election. As </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">New York Magazine</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> reports, many young Muslima <a href="http://nymag.com/thecut/2016/11/after-trumps-win-muslim-women-are-afraid-to-wear-the-hijab.html">took this fear to twitter</a>. One young woman tweeted her devout mother’s words of caution, &#8220;Please don’t wear your hijab today,&#8221; only to be attacked by right-wing trolls, twitter’s escalating problem in this age of free speech and anti-democratic vitriol. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Whether or not a Trump presidency and its fallout will actually lead to physical harm of Muslim women is not something we can know, right now. But we can juxtapose this fear&nbsp;with hijab as an object of both identity and ridicule&nbsp;&#8211; an object that conservative movements and some European governments have taken outright offense to.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Editor-in-chief of Vogue<em> Arabia</em> is a Saudi princess, a self-professed queen of elegant women in any silhouette. She, </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Deena Aljuhani Abdulaziz, </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">is also a champion of the down-to-earth cat-walk. And she does not (perhaps no surprise here) actually live in the Kingdom</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Although D. Aljuhani Abdulaziz&nbsp;does not herself wear hijab, she supports women who do. According to her interview with </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The New York Times</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, the consumer preferences of Muslim women are <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/11/03/fashion/islamic-fashion-vogue-arabia.html">at the core of this <em>Vogue</em></a>. The magazine’s mission for women in the Muslim world, she explained, is to highlight dress in its femininity, its creativity, and its usage by everyday women across the Arab world, hijab or no hijab. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is not only Arab women living in Doha or Beirut who ascribe to the beauty norms of hijab-wearing models and hijab-based marketing, thus <em>Vogue Arabia</em>’s readership will surely not stay confined to the Arab world. It is published online in both English and Arabic and maintains an international aesthetic (both in branding and in the women who gloss its pages). The princess and Conde Nast seem cognizant of the status of women in hijab: they represent an established style and lifestyle, on a global scale. </span></p>
<div id="attachment_4712" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4712" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4712 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2-650x433.jpg" alt="reise_london-2014-bearbeitet-2" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4712" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This recognition is not limited to Big Money in the Arab world. Women in hijab have begun to take their place among trendsetting brands in countries in which they are decidedly the minority. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Even in Trump’s America, CoverGirl recently <a href="http://firsttoknow.com/meet-the-new-face-of-covergirl-hijab-wearing-beauty-blogger-nura-afia/?utm_source=contentad_backfill&amp;utm_campaign=meet-the-new-face-of-cov-211246&amp;pp=1&amp;utm_medium=180533">added a Muslima in hijab</a> to its blogosphere and promotional sites, a hijab-friendly designer <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-37381770">stole the show at this year’s New York Fashion Week</a>, a U.S. beauty pageant contestant&nbsp;did <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/goatsandsoda/2016/11/29/503729951/the-beauty-pageant-contestant-wore-a-burkini">the whole thing in burkini and hijab</a>, and (if you haven’t heard) Marvel released <a href="http://marvel.wikia.com/wiki/Kamala_Khan_(Earth-616)">its first Muslima superhero</a>. Yes, even superheroes can wear scarves, and <a href="https://mic.com/articles/125199/badass-muslim-superheroes-comics-tv">it doesn&#8217;t stop at Marvel</a>.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><em>Vogue</em> and these other agents of popular culture bring the hijab into a different type of mainstream &#8211; of fashion and femininity. In asserting that &#8220;Yes, this too is a woman,&#8221; a woman’s choice of what to wear is expanded. Bikinis were first <a href="http://content.time.com/time/photogallery/0,29307,1908353_1905442,00.html">popularized and freed from social taboo</a> by aggressive marketing campaigns and photo-shoots. So, why not hijab? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Perhaps the most important point, however, is not whether or not hijab can be normalized; it is whether or not such mainstreaming actually leads to more freedom. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the case of Muslima in increasingly hostile environments, such as the United States or any European state as of late, this freedom is being put to the test. Hijab or body-covering of any sort is increasingly becoming a marker of difference. With the rise of the populist Right, our societies are becoming more and more opposed to such difference. And the power of the masses has, historically, had something to say about women’s dress, women’s bodies, and, ultimately, women’s rights. For better or for worse.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Women’s heads have been the subject of political struggle for centuries. In this century, the forcible removal of hijab has corresponded with two trends, in particular: with Western influence in majority-Muslim countries or, as this summer’s burkini controversy demonstrated, with Western societies asserting nationalistic values and (patriarchal) identity. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;Freedom from&#8221; or &#8220;freedom to&#8221; are phrases associated with women’s behaviors, from dress to sexual activity to reproductive health, from France to Saudi Arabia. And we are often told to take a side: &#8220;Do you want women to be free from patriarchal oppression?&#8221; or &#8220;Do you want women to be free to wear whatever they choose?&#8221; </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But how does one think about the fight to wear hijab and the fight to be freed from hijab in one, unified thought? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Iran is a near perfect testament to such a thought. The country&#8217;s transition from Reza Shah Pahlavi to Ayatollah Khomeini provides an example of an apparent (and near perfect) paradox in practice.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the late 1920s in a still monarchical Iran, the Shah instituted what he called &#8220;a gradual process of hijab removal&#8221; from public institutions. The Shah’s friend and mentor, Turkey’s Mustafa Kemal Attatürk, espoused the view that head-covering reflected not only non-Western dress but non-Western thought. &#8220;Backwards women&#8221; stood for an undesirable social system, which extended into the confines of the home. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hijab was thus a stand-in or a symbol for the greater societal transformation each autocratic leader desired for the value system of his society. If Turkey and Iran were to join the rational, &#8220;enlightened&#8221; throngs of European history, in body and in mind, women had to remove their scarves.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Iran, in the period between these so-called modernization reforms and the Revolution, looked much like any other European country, with tanned youth in swimsuits smoking cigarettes on the beach, and Beatles records flying off the shelves. But in the late 1970s, frustration with the corrupt dictatorship of the Shah and the monarchy as a system of undemocratic government brought thousands of Iranian men and women out onto the streets. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the early days of 1979, secular and religious women alike protested for the right to ascribe to the value system of their choice. Whether Western or not, it was up to women to decide, not the Shah. </span></p>
<div id="attachment_4714" style="width: 510px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4714" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4714 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Iranian_Revolution_1979_marching_young_people.jpeg" alt="iranian_revolution_1979_marching_young_people" width="500" height="339" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Iranian_Revolution_1979_marching_young_people.jpeg 500w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Iranian_Revolution_1979_marching_young_people-300x203.jpeg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4714" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Wikimedia Commons</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As the revolution took a strident Islamic turn, women who did not wear hijab began to see the institution of the new state as a threat to their freedom of choice. Indeed, the &#8220;Islamic&#8221; in &#8220;Islamic Republic&#8221; now meant hijab, for all women. Iranian women were thus divided along ideological lines, and the new Islamic state was thus effective in reducing the voice and power of its most educated and mobile constituency: women.</span></p>
<p><iframe title="March 8, 1979 Iranian Women March Against Hijab and Islamic Laws" width="650" height="488" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/pxGYLk92edY?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With religious rule by Ayatollah Khomeini came moral rule in the homes and upon the bodies of women. Laws protecting women against the men of their family were eliminated. But as long as women were covered, they were able to obtain political office, attend university, and build a career. The hijab acted as a pass into the greater halls of society. It continues to act as the safeguard of a theocratic order, which exercises control while permitting necessary freedoms.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Iranian case is not so different from the European burkini fiasco last summer. The burkini &#8211; a full-body covering made of swimwear material, with an attached head covering like a swim cap &#8211; was banned in many French towns and cities for its subversion of secularist values. Women were to uphold the state’s belief in its own ideological abstention from religious practice in public life. Even while swimming. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The ban has since been <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-37198479">overturned at a federal level</a>, though some French municipalities claim that they will continue to enforce it. The mayor in the town where the ban made headlines, with police officers requiring a woman to remove her <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/08/28/world/europe/france-burkini-bikini-ban.html?_r=0">burkini on the beach</a>, called the ban an attempt to require &#8220;<a href="http://edition.cnn.com/2016/08/30/europe/french-mayor-cogolin-burkini-ban/">them to adopt our way of life.&#8221;</a> The &#8220;them&#8221; in this sentiment could be none other than Muslims, Europe&#8217;s favorite Other.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Liberal democracies, which respect the rights of minorities, demand pluralism &#8211; in lifestyle, in religious practice, in appearance, in ideology. Why does this pluralism extend only partially to women?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In France, the beach was briefly a battlefield. Muslim women were caught at the cross hairs of a power play between establishment norms and the liberty of choice that defines many arguments of cultural expression in other countries. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But the battlefield is an ideological one, surpassing the boundaries of nation and norms. It all comes down to the right to choose.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This is something women have been fighting for for centuries, from the ability to choose political leadership to the ability to choose a marital partner. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We can debate the merits behind the practice of the headscarf, its history in the Islamic world or even in the life of the prophet Muhammad, but what we should not debate is the ability of a woman to choose a practice, if it does no harm to her. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">France, in particular, makes the argument that the mere act of covering the body does harm to &#8220;the dignity and liberty&#8221; of said body. The issue of hijab is thus framed as one of protection, i.e. paternalism. A closer look at France’s relationship to identity politics and its systematic attempts to eliminate differences for the sake of the secular, homogeneous French state suggests that the protection enacted here is a fairly one-way street: There is &#8220;freedom from&#8221; but rarely &#8220;freedom to.&#8221;<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In Germany, a similar ban on head coverings for women exists. This ban is <a href="http://www.dw.com/en/can-muslim-women-wear-a-headscarf-at-work-in-germany/a-17953746">often a private and religious matter</a>, with church-based organizations or certain institutions able to decide when and if they will tolerate hijab. The attempts by school districts to ban headscarves in their teaching staff have been only partially successful, as German courts usually have the last word, overturning discriminatory practices, unless a specific legal conflict can be identified.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">German politicians have <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/08/19/germanys-potential-burqa-ban-has-a-problem-where-are-the-burqas/?utm_term=.947e281fb60a">also proposed a burqa ban</a>. The only problem is: hardly any women in Germany wear a burqa. Here, a moral stance is taken in preventing supposed harm before this harm could be said to occur. Ideology much? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Of course, the burqa is far from the burkini or the hijab. But it is no coincidence that the burqa ban discussion resurfaced and gained political momentum around the time of the burkini fiasco in France. Some European leaders may oppose France&#8217;s handling of the burkini on its beaches, but many have verbally and practically expressed their approval of policing Muslim women&#8217;s dress.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If one were to apply this&nbsp;logic of&nbsp;infringement of personal liberty to other arenas affecting the female body, one would end up with a long list of potential offenders, from beauty salons to botox offices to lingerie stores, where certain body parts are literally strapped down and constrained for the sake of smooth curvature. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;But these things make us feel good, make us feel pretty,&#8221; a French woman would likely respond. &#8220;And this is my right!&#8221;</span></p>
<div id="attachment_4715" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4715" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4715 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420-650x433.jpg" alt="berlin-bearbeitet-2014-420" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4715" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Type &#8220;hijab&#8221; into Pinterest and a fashion show will appear &#8211; women who use hijab as a way to present themselves in their way to the world. Stroll down the Turkish market at Berlin&#8217;s Maybachufer and you will encounter smiling groups of Muslima holding silk scarves up to their faces, matching patterns with dresses and jackets in mind, practicing new and different folds, depending on the material.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are wedding hijabs, hijabs for supermarket trips, and hijabs for dates, just as there are shoes for weddings, for nights out, or for lazy Saturdays.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hijab, like shoes, can make women feel good, because they make women feel pretty in a way that is also comfortable. It is both a lifestyle with religious and cultural roots and an identity mixed up with the many different conceptions humans have of beauty. Beauty: with all its socio-cultural baggage, the construct of forces beyond our individual minds and mirrors, forces that will always be a little bit oppressive but also a little bit fun, because they are familiar and somehow the product of our daily life within them. And this is their, our right.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As Trump ascends his throne to rule over the many who do not approve of or give license to his authoritarianism or assimilationist view of cultural differences, the hijab becomes one of those things that needs protection.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As Muslim refugees who choose to wear hijab become a lasting part of the societies of those European states that have taken them in, their right to be different must be defended. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Most importantly, we must defend the right of women to choose.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is this choice that makes women free. This is why feminism and hijab go together.</span></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>For more on the history of women in Iran, from hairstyles to political movements, see these sources: U.S. Institute of Peace&#8217;s <a href="http://iranprimer.usip.org/resource/womens-movement">Iran Primer: the Women&#8217;s Movement;</a> these pieces from a </em>New York Times<em>&nbsp;series &#8220;<a href="http://nytlive.nytimes.com/womenintheworld/2015/06/02/6-pervasive-misconceptions-about-iranian-women/">6 Pervasive Misconceptions about Iranian Women</a>&#8221; and &#8220;<a href="http://nytlive.nytimes.com/womenintheworld/2015/09/15/the-day-100000-iranian-women-protested-the-head-scarf/">The Day 100,000 Women Protested the Headscarf</a>&#8220;; this acclaimed book on the complexity of the Revolution: </em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Islamic-Utopian-Political-Biography-2000-06-03/dp/B019NRY9QG/ref=sr_1_3?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1480842551&amp;sr=1-3&amp;keywords=an+islamic+utopian+ali+shari%27ati">An Islamic Utopian: A Political Biography of Ali Shari&#8217;ati;</a><em> and the memoir, </em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/1400064708/?tag=thneyo0f-20">Iran Awakening</a><em>, by the Nobel-prize-winning activist Shirin Ebadi.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>And if you&#8217;re curious about women in hijab on the internet and in the fashion world, here are some people to watch: <a href="https://www.hautehijab.com/blogs/hijab-fashion">Haute Hijab</a> (U.S. fashion blogger with an entry titled &#8220;Embracing Our Identity in a Post 2016 Election World&#8221;), <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC_KQKeg7kNrlvrIXPnpwgEA">Dina Tokio</a> (U.K. vlogger and fashion designer), <a href="http://ww38.hipsterhijabis.com/about.html">Hipster Hijabis</a> (just what it sounds like), <a href="http://hanatajima.com/">Hana Tajima</a> (up-and-coming U.K. fashion designer), and <a href="http://hijablicious.com/">Hijablicious</a> (a site for &#8220;hijab with soul&#8221;).</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Circumcision at the Jewish Museum Berlin</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/12/05/review-circumcision-jewish-museum-berlin/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2014 13:14:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Judaism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3532</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Circumcision has a history of being used to make distinctions between 'us' and 'them', particularly in Germany. In the United States the debate on foreskin or no-foreskin looks much different, citing hygiene rather than religious freedom. This begs the question if arguments against a religious practice, such as the one raised in the German context, can ever be purely about legal arguments - for the rights of children, as German courts have decreed - when strong divisions between those of Christian heritage and those of Muslim and/or Jewish heritage remain. This question was the inspiration for the newest exhibition at the Jewish Museum Berlin, a timely one, at that...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Circumcision has a long history of enabling Othering processes, i.e. society defining itself on the basis of what it is not. According the Duke anthropologist <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/william-m-obarr/celebrating-circumcision_1_b_1902275.html">William O’Barr</a>, the absence of circumcision in Michelangelo’s famous <em>David</em> exemplifies this bit: Despite David’s well-known Jewish roots, let alone his place as a key protagonist in the Jewish scriptural tradition, his foreskin remains seemingly intact; this David seems more Florentine, more like the dominant Europeans at the time, than Jewish.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/books/2011/jul/29/david-mary-hoffman-review"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3537" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/David-Michelangelo-007.jpg" alt="David Michelangelo" width="487" height="293" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/David-Michelangelo-007.jpg 459w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/David-Michelangelo-007-300x180.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 487px) 100vw, 487px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Michelangelo likely had little experience with circumcision, given that this practice was historically reserved for the Jewish minority. The lack of foreskin thus served as a point from which the fringe of majority culture could be measured. Most Europeans at the time were simply <em>not </em>circumcised.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">In Germany, circumcision is still a practice attributed to members of the Jewish and Islamic traditions. Given Germany&#8217;s immigration history, the practice also serves largely to distinguish more recent immigrants from your German with either Catholic or Protestant roots. In kind, the debate as to the legality and humanity of the removal of a child&#8217;s foreskin has taken on an us vs. them quality. The discussion has also tended to position &#8216;reason and modernity&#8217; against &#8216;antiquated tradition&#8217;, as this<a href="http://www.taz.de/!98008/"> interview</a> with a German Green Party member indicates (a party, which gave strong support to legislation banning the practice among infants and young children). Just two years ago, a Cologne court ruled against the circumcision of youngsters. The decision was presented as an act in favor of the human rights of children &#8211; this logic continues to dominate.</p>
<p>In the United States, approx. 79% of men are circumcised, <a href="http://www.cdc.gov/hiv/pdf/prevention_research_malecircumcision.pdf">according to the Center for Disease Control</a>. Many of these men do not belong to religious traditions that prescribe the practice; I doubt many parents would cite compliance with God&#8217;s covenant as the reason for their son’s procedure. Since its introduction during WWII as a matter of (presumed) <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2788411/">hygiene</a>, it never had time to become a pronounced public marker of difference.</p>
<div id="attachment_3565" style="width: 541px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://www.guggenheim.org/new-york/collections/collection-online/artwork/3478"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3565" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3565 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/circumcision-january1.jpg" alt="circumcision-january pollock" width="531" height="450" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/circumcision-january1.jpg 531w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/circumcision-january1-300x254.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 531px) 100vw, 531px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3565" class="wp-caption-text">Jackson Pollock 1946, &#8220;Circumcision&#8221;</p></div>
<p>But even in the United States, the practice has more recently come under a critical knife, though more medical than cultural, as a recent <em>Atlantic </em><a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2014/12/foreskin-keep-or-cut/383362/">article</a> on the subject illustrates. The more contemporary critique in the United States seems to be little more than an attempt to re-evaluate the merits of bodily modification, without going so far as to refer to this practice as &#8216;mutilation&#8217; on the part of fundamentalist religions.</p>
<p>Given this background, the importance of context is undeniable in evaluating the discourse on circumcision from one place to another. In other words, the &#8216;who&#8217;s who&#8217; in <em>beschnitten</em> vs. <em>unbeschnitten</em> may say much more about the state of society (and its latent tensions) than medical-ethical arguments against the practice immediately reveal. This begs the question if arguments against a religious practice, such as this one, can ever be purely about the rights of children, as German courts have decreed and German politicians argued. This question and the delicate history from which it emerges were the inspiration for the newest exhibition at the <a href="http://www.jmberlin.de/main/EN/homepage-EN.php">Jewish Museum Berlin</a> – an institution known for <a href="http://www.jmberlin.de/main/EN/03b-Academy/04-Academy-Programs/00-academy-programs.php">programming</a> on inclusion/diversity topics that extends beyond the docket of Jewish history and culture.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Haut-Ab.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-3569 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Haut-Ab.jpg" alt="Haut Ab" width="330" height="374" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Haut-Ab.jpg 330w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Haut-Ab-264x300.jpg 264w" sizes="(max-width: 330px) 100vw, 330px" /></a></p>
<p>The exhibit, &#8220;<a href="http://www.jmberlin.de/main/DE/01-Ausstellungen/02-Sonderaustellungen/2014/brit-mila.php">Haut ab!</a>&#8221; or &#8220;<a href="http://www.jmberlin.de/main/EN/01-Exhibitions/02-Special-Exhibitions/2014/brit-milah.php">Snip it!</a>&#8220;, opened a little more than one month ago. Days before the exhibit’s scheduled reveal, I had the opportunity to take part in a preview for bloggers and tweeters. Our tour guide was the exhibition’s co-curator, an expert in Judaica. In addition to the objects&#8217; historical significance, her comments revealed a recognition of the tightly-stretched contemporary fabric upon which the exhibit rests. The careful placement of artifacts, soundbites, and images transmits a similar message of a need to explain and take stock of a (perhaps unnecessarily) tension-filled topic, in light and because of history.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3539 size-large aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004-650x365.jpg" alt="WP_20141022_004" width="650" height="365" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004-650x365.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Entering through the exhibit&#8217;s initial darkened spaces &#8211; final preparations being made, lighting not quite right &#8211; a historical narrative of a religion&#8217;s genesis and later adaptations in diaspora forms a quilt of impressions. The next rooms give way to the ritual&#8217;s place in Islam and the stark move from Christianity&#8217;s embrace of old Jewish tradition &#8211; as being sacredly tied to the life and times of Jesus &#8211; to artists&#8217; depictions of Othered violence, even savagery, against children. Juxtaposed with a historical development are artifacts from the Islamic ceremony in which a young boy is inducted into a long Muslim lineage. For all Berliners, the following image is a familiar one: costumes for a &#8216;little prince&#8217;, complete with scepter and golden cap. But how many recognize this as part of a fundamental <em>rite de passage, </em>the commanded removal of foreskin? Images of the sons of German guest workers in the 1970s, little princes in-waiting, place the practice further back in German heritage than the media tends to convey. As Germany&#8217;s immigration history indicates, circumcision is nothing new. But this photograph of an eager little boy could have been taken last week, swimming in a hat much too big among a happy mass of friends and family.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3558 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016-650x365.jpg" alt="WP_20141022_016" width="650" height="365" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016-650x365.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>The final room of the exhibit greets visitors with an interactive arrangement of outside discourses on circumcision, clips taken primarily from American television. Images and audio insert diverse perspectives into what our guide calls &#8216;the polemical German frame&#8217;. Familiar cartoons and sitcoms cast blue light onto the carpeted floor. Scenes from South Park, Judge Judy. As we exit, a final work, the oeuvre of commentary, salutes its visitors: three figures, bodies identical, if not for the flags draped over three sets of genitalia.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-3557 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021-365x650.jpg" alt="WP_20141022_021" width="350" height="623" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021-365x650.jpg 365w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021-168x300.jpg 168w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021.jpg 366w" sizes="(max-width: 350px) 100vw, 350px" /></a></p>
<p>One could make the case that circumcision in Germany is more a stand-in for society&#8217;s difficult grappling with religious difference and demographic change. Perhaps more background is needed to do so, however. So to be more specific, as a <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/politik/deutschland/studie-belegt-grosse-vorbehalte-gegenueber-muslimen-a-1006332.html">recent study</a> by the <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/en/welcome/">Berlin Institute for Empirical Migration and Integration Research</a> indicates, a majority of Germans polled continue to see Islam as un-German &#8211; this despite the approx. 5+ million Muslims who have made Germany their home. To complicate things, Germany is one of the most secular countries in Europe, with most of its residents of so-called Christian heritage bearing little association to either church or faith in their daily lives. There is also a history of a certain institutional religiosity despite public secularism: for example, the prominence of the CDU Party (Christian Democratic Union) and the obligatory church-tax to Protestant or Catholic churches, even synagogues, while blatantly excluding Muslim houses of prayer.</p>
<p>As this new exhibit at the Jewish Museum Berlin demonstrates, circumcision in Germany is complicated, deeply embedded in <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/28/world-cup-fever-how-malleable-is-german-identity/">the question of German identity</a> and the norms that demarcate such a thing. I wonder, though, if the constant discussion serves only to create scandal out of culture. For where is Othered difference, when there is no longer spectacle?</p>
<p>&#8220;Snip it&#8221;/&#8221;Haut ab&#8221; at the Jewish Museum Berlin runs until March 1. It&#8217;s worth a visit.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>All images are linked to original source or were otherwise taken by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Ramadan with Neighbors: It&#8217;s About Showing Up</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2013 14:17:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kreuzberg]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1203</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For those non-Muslims among us, Ramadan is an almost hidden spectacle with mysterious allure: the hot tea, the music, and the platters of food only come out when the sun has turned in for the day or before it has even appeared. We hear the clatter of dishes from our neighbors’ windows late into the night or watch children unpack colorful sweets on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eid_ul-Fitr"><i>Eid al-Fitr</i></a>, all without necessarily being able to place these traditions in our own line of experience. In honor of the last night of Ramadan, here is a reflection on an event Sophia and I attended last Friday as part of Berlin's festival <a href="http://www.piranhakultur.de/event/events_2013/naechte_des_ramadan"><i>die </i></a><i><a href="http://www.piranhakultur.de/event/events_2013/naechte_des_ramadan">Nächte des Ramadan</a>, </i>the Nights of Ramadan...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Many of the world&#8217;s cities teem with fasting bodies during the c. 30 days of the Muslim holiday of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramadan_(calendar_month)">Ramadan</a>. About <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/berlin/berlinerstatistik/1670484.html">300,000 Muslims</a> live in Berlin: that makes for a lot of hungry individuals during the holy month. Of course, not every Muslim fasts, not every faster is Muslim, and not all Muslims celebrate Ramadan the same (or even at all). But for those non-Muslims among us, Ramadan is an almost hidden spectacle with mysterious allure: the hot tea, the music, and the platters of food that only come out when the sun has turned in for the day or before it has even appeared. We hear the clatter of dishes from our neighbors’ windows late into the night or watch children unpack colorful sweets on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eid_ul-Fitr"><i>Eid al-Fitr</i></a>, all without necessarily being able to place these traditions in our own line of experience. So, what is it actually like to break the fast at the end of the day among friends and family? Among neighbors?</p>
<p>Today is the last day of Ramadan, so it is high time for some reflection on an event Sophia and I attended last Friday as part of Berlin&#8217;s festival <a href="http://www.piranhakultur.de/event/events_2013/naechte_des_ramadan"><i>die </i></a><i><a href="http://www.piranhakultur.de/event/events_2013/naechte_des_ramadan">Nächte des Ramadan</a>, </i>the Nights of Ramadan. Organized by the <a href="http://kreuzbergmuseum.de/index.php?id=1">Kreuzberg Museum</a>, the whole community was invited to an <a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/berlin/muslime-in-berlin-reim-den-ramadan,10809148,23930332.html"><i>Iftar </i></a>celebration, the nightly breaking of the fast, in the museum&#8217;s garden right near <i>Kottbusser Tor</i>. Of course the breaking of bread in the privacy of one’s home is different from the organization of an intentional <em><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/10/whose-multikulti-is-it-the-elusive-definition-of-multiculturalism/">Multikulti</a></em> program. This event was not just about eating and drinking in public after another day doing without: it was about bringing fasting bodies together with the curious non-Muslims or non-fasters among us.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/photo.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1208" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/photo.jpg?w=640" alt="photo" width="640" height="640" /></a></p>
<p><i>The gates to the Kreuzberg Museum open to long tables and benches decked with white cloth and table settings. Plates of bloated dates run down the center, stuffed with walnuts, dark chocolate, and coconut.  </i>&#8220;They just put everything in them our bodies might want”,<i> says the small-framed woman across from me with a laugh &#8211; an instructor of </i><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">Integrationskurse</a><i>* in Berlin, she tells me. Having fasted and even worked all day, she doesn&#8217;t seem one bit tired, rather concentrated and composed. I am boiling in the midst of what I consider extreme humidity; not a bead of sweat is to be seen on her face which sits surrounded by heavy, sage-green cloth. </i>“You just get used to it, to not eating”,<i> she responds, when I ask if it is difficult, my flashbacks of Lent-related chocolate withdrawal ever-present. </i>“And I can lay down once and a while at work to rest”,<i> she adds. She has been fasting for years, even before she was a practicing Muslim. </i>“I used to fast with my brother, though my parents never participated”.<i> She is originally from Azerbaijan, six years in Germany and still not sure if it’s home. “</i>They are German”,<i> she says pointing to her three friends, “</i>I just live here”<i>. A laugh erupts into the sticky night. She rests her palm on her cheek. </i></p>
<p><i>I find the buffet prepared by (the speaker’s words not mine) </i>die Arabische Frauen<i> (Arab women) and try to take a picture of the overwhelming spread. Ladies in bright colors scurry to assemble more heaps of greasy drumsticks, mounds of semolina and rice with toasted almonds, deep-fried spinach and clumps of rose-colored meat in a breaded dress. </i></p>
<p><i>A small man brings the microphone to his lips  &#8211; not on the stage, but beneath it &#8211; and the prayer begins. It is exactly 9:02pm, and the sun has sunken beneath the city lights. No one dares to nibble on the dates, which is the signal that the fast has been broken. It is silent except for the melodic call to prayer. The teacher from Azerbaijan mouths the words without making a sound, her cheekbones concealed now by the edges of her headscarf</i>. <i>Her head turns downward to fall into her hands forming an invisible Koran in her lap, her palms and their scriptures seeming to capture all sound.</i></p>
<p><i>The three friends of our new teacher-friend return to the table with piles of food, offering us as much as we like, since we will not be getting in line until after those who have fasted. When we protest, the teacher remarks in between slow and measured bites off the chicken bone in her hand,</i> “Your stomach shrinks throughout the day, so your eyes are much bigger than your capacity”. <i>She smiles and points to the mound of food in the middle of our table. Köfte is rolled onto our plates as we politely probe with questions. The three friends are just beginning their 20s, studying at university, active in the </i>organization <a href="http://www.muslimische-jugend.de/">Muslimische Jugend in Deutschland e.V</a><i>. Their involvement in this organization brought them and the teacher together, who seems to smile adoringly but wisely at her younger companions as they speak. None of the three wear </i>hijab; <i>one is engaged to her high school sweetheart and studying to earn her PhD in forensic science. </i></p>
<p style="text-align: center;" align="center"> <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/photo-2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter  wp-image-1207" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/photo-2.jpg?w=640" alt="photo (2)" width="448" height="448" /></a></p>
<p><i>The director of the Kreuzberg Museum addresses the public – families finished eating though chattering loudly as ever, interested passers-by with backpacks watching the stage, the Kreuzberg Fire Dept. laughing with friends and looking dapper in suits. A small German man in a somber white button-down and black pant, he thanks the neighbors for their patience in tolerating the noise and those neighbors who came to take part, then introduces the musical performance of the night. The Iraqi-German musician <a href="http://www.saif-karomi.com/music.htm">Saif Karomi</a> enters the stage with a beautiful Oud gripped in his right hand. His music, with the accompaniment of a slender wooden flute and a steady Djembe, seeps out into the night. Most of the windows from Kotti’s high-rise apartments are glowing, many left open to let the sounds and the light stream in. </i></p>
<p style="text-align: center;" align="center"><a href="http://www.piranhakultur.de/gallery/ramadan_2013/saif_karomi_02_08"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1231" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/music.jpg" alt="Music" width="400" height="333" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/music.jpg 400w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/music-300x249.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a></p>
<p><i>Trays of dessert circulate the courtyard: pistachio cream with rose water in a honey-soaked pancake </i>(Qatayef);<i> walnuts bathed in honey, chopped, and folded delicately into sweet bread; pistachio and nougat doused in dark chocolate and coconut. Hot tea is served in elegant glasses fit to the palm. Clapping begins in rhythmic compliment to the weeping lull of the Oud. At 11pm the lanterns are extinguished. We head out the gates of the Kreuzberg museum, passing a line of young people smoking on the steps near the sheet of Kebap shops and neon-lit bars. We move on and outward into the other neighborhoods we know well, my body in anything but a state of want.</i></p>
<p align="center"> <a href="http://www.recettes-cuisine-afrique.info/IMG/jpg/Qatayef.jpg"><img loading="lazy" src="http://www.recettes-cuisine-afrique.info/IMG/jpg/Qatayef.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="300" /></a></p>
<p>At this event, I kept asking myself what the words &#8220;integration&#8221; and &#8220;diversity&#8221; really mean to the politicians who speak them. To me, it is not about &#8220;to each his or her own&#8221; or just about learning the majority language, rather it is about taking part in a two-way process. It is about getting to know one another and forging new spaces of neighborhood between these ways of knowing. It is often just about showing up to our neighbor’s barbecue, about inviting the friendly guy from the <i>Späti</i> to a party, about delivering mail to the lady upstairs (even if she never looks friendly) and staying in a slightly damp hallway to chit-chat (and not because you want to). I have learned from these experiences that it really is just about going to places, interacting with others, and maybe asking questions. Taking an interest in the life and interests of one’s neighbor is an integral part of what it means to live in a metropolis. Any other way forward and things might just fall apart.</p>
<p>Ramadan is one way of holding everything together, keeping us honest in whether or not we really value difference – just like I really value pistachio cream and the Oud, maybe just as much as I value mayo on my fries or the American Diner. Such meet-your-neighbor events also give us reason to congregate and converse about all the things we do not know but might just assume about one another. Not everyone at this event wore <em>hijab</em> or prayed with beads, not everyone fasted, not everyone was Muslim or even the same type of Muslim, for that matter.</p>
<p>It should be of interest to all of us that nearly 7% of Berlin&#8217;s population may be abstaining from food and water in 90 degree heat and 50% humidity, still going to work, driving cars, pushing strollers, running errands, participating in daily life during the holiest days in the Muslim religion. This phenomenon is happening all over the world, times ten, in many different shapes and flavors.</p>
<p>The Kreuzberg Museum holds this event every year. We hope events like it will show up in places less expected than Kreuzberg, maybe even more situated in the everyday. We just have to show up and be a part of it.</p>
<p><i>&#8211; By <b>Kelly Miller</b></i></p>
<p>*<i>Integrationskurse</i> are federally mandated integration courses for immigrants and refugees within their first three years of residence in Germany. However, these courses have only been in existence since 2005, allowing many earlier waves of immigrants the chance to participate in a combination of language-learning and cultural orientation after the three year period has passed.</p>
<p>Photos by Sophia Burton or otherwise sourced with link to image.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
