<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>design &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/design/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Reviewing the Rave: &#8220;We are the We&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/13/reviewing-the-rave-we-are-the-we/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 21:04:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1269</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We're so used to talking all the time that words tend to lose their effect. Especially when the talking is predominantly happening in one direction, as it so often does in immigration discourse. The <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/02/rave-i-am-not-a-terrorist/">Migrantas</a> organization is unleashing an alternate voice within immigrant women in Germany that is arguably just as powerful: their artistic creativity...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/1085152_547637008637523_1494864328_o.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-1277 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/1085152_547637008637523_1494864328_o.jpg?w=640" alt="1085152_547637008637523_1494864328_o" width="640" height="426" /></a></p>
<p>We&#8217;re so used to talking all the time that words tend to lose their effect. Especially when the talking is predominantly happening in one direction, as it so often does in immigration discourse. The <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/02/rave-i-am-not-a-terrorist/">Migrantas</a> organization is unleashing an alternate voice within immigrant women in Germany that is arguably just as powerful: their artistic creativity. Simple pencil and paper sketches are transformed into pictograms by the Migrantas artists, then shared with the city on billboards, postcards, and public transit. The finished products don&#8217;t utter a sound but are easily worth more than a thousand words.</p>
<p>This past April, Kelly and I participated in one of a series of <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/02/rave-i-am-not-a-terrorist/">Migrantas workshops</a> in Berlin. Though the two of us pretty much <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/about/">live and breathe immigration</a>, we were surprised how much there was left to reflect upon, namely our own migration experiences. For over two hours, we scribbled alongside five other participants in the very fitting <em>Haus der Kulturen der Welt</em> (House of World Cultures), producing a total of 28 sketches for the artists to work with. Our workshop group was younger than average and also more mobile and privileged: we were all well-educated and, except for Kelly, in possession of the highly-coveted EU passport. But the dynamics of integration go far beyond the legal and political. Economically, linguistically, professionally, socially, personally, even romantically&#8230; in one way or another we were all struggling to feel like insiders.  At the same time, we recognized and celebrated the excitement, enrichment, and fulfillment that accompanies the process.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/img_3348.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/img_3348.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_3348" width="640" height="368" /></a><strong>&#8220;Migration = Enrichment&#8221;/&#8221;&#8216;<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">Migrants&#8217; anyway</a>&#8221; <strong>(despite having a German passport)</strong><br />
</strong></p>
<p>This past Friday came the big reveal: we gathered with members of other workshops and the interested public at Berlin&#8217;s <em>Rotes Rathaus</em> for the opening of the exhibit showcasing our work. The exhibit was simple and straightforward, just like the Migrantas concept. A singular stretch of sketches grouped into common themes around accompanying pictograms. No curators, no conjectures, no conclusions. Only an opportunity to see the world through someone else&#8217;s lens and pencil strokes.</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-09-47-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3423" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-09-47-1-650x650.jpg" alt="2013-08-09-20-09-47-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-09-47-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-09-47-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></strong></p>
<p>The biggest take-away for Kelly and me came in how much in common we seemed to have with children of Turkish guest workers, students from Brazil, and grandmothers from Kurdistan. While our migration contexts, freedom of mobility, and future plans certainly vary drastically, our feelings about the integration process were at times strikingly similar. One group of images showed X&#8217;s over a mouth, a knot in a tongue, a speech bubble filled with jibber-jabber, and the phrase &#8220;I&#8217;m not stupid, I&#8217;m just starting to learn German!&#8221;. Where words may have only shown difference, our sketches revealed connection and commonality, finding themselves side-by-side on the board.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-25-01-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3424" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-25-01-1-650x650.jpg" alt="2013-08-09-20-25-01-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-25-01-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-25-01-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><strong>&#8220;Authorities&#8221;. Sketches underneath and to the right of the main pictogram by Kelly.</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/img_3390.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/img_3390.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_3390" width="518" height="518" /></a><strong>&#8220;Job, Effort, Luck, Rejection, Trainee, Intern, Degree, Training&#8221;. Sketch on upper right by Sophia.</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-28-36.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-28-36.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-08-09 20.28.36" width="640" height="480" /></a><strong>&#8220;Language, Communication, Friendship, Feelings, Smile&#8221;</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-24-00-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3426" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-24-00-1-650x650.jpg" alt="2013-08-09-20-24-00-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-24-00-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-24-00-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><strong>&#8220;Heimweh&#8221;/&#8221;Homesickness&#8221;</strong></p>
<p>The points of commonality extended beyond those with migration backgrounds, perhaps one of the most valuable but under-appreciated aspects of the work Migrantas does. As one German presenter shared during her welcome speech, images of twisted tongues and closed mouths transported her back to her first experience abroad in Spain with her family and the frustration and fear she felt about not being able to communicate. &#8220;My mother taught me the term <em>no hablo español</em>, and I noticed that the pronoun was missing. I thought she did it on purpose so that it&#8217;d be really clear I couldn&#8217;t speak the language.&#8221; Immigrants or not, these images deliver the compelling message that we are all individuals, we all have multi-faceted identities, and we have all at some point or another felt different. <em>Wir sind das Wir</em>. We are the we.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3427" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27-650x487.jpg" alt="2013-08-09-20-14-27" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2migrantas_piktogramm_wir_sind_das_wir_300dpi.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1337" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2migrantas_piktogramm_wir_sind_das_wir_300dpi.jpg?w=640" alt="migrantas_piktogram_wir_sind_das_wir_300dpi" width="589" height="589" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton </strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>Don&#8217;t forget to check out the Migrantas exhibit for yourself at Berlin&#8217;s </em>Rotes Rathaus at <em>Alexanderplatz. Free to the public and open until August 27th. Keep an eye out for upcoming Migrantas workshops and exhibitions around Germany by liking them on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/migrantas/144071052327456">Facebook</a>. Registration is free and open to all with a migration story to the city where they now reside.<br />
</em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">First and last photos by Ruben Gonzalez Escudero/Migrantas; all other photos by Sophia Burton</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rave: &#8220;I am not a Terrorist&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/02/rave-i-am-not-a-terrorist/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2013 12:00:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[design]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.wordpress.com/?p=69</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In Berlin, the dimensions of migration and diversity may sometimes be over-simplified, but groups like Migrantas are changing that, and doing so creatively. The best part: the voice and agency of the "immigrants", so often talked-about and so seldom talking-back, take center stage...
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>Migrantas &#8211; Visual Language of Migration</h3>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://www.grassrootsfeminism.net/cms/sites/default/files/logotype_migrantas.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="200" /></p>
<p><em>Occasionally, we will share either a little rant (something we dare to criticize) or a little rave (something we love)&#8230;maybe even both depending on the kind of juices we have flowing in response to this magnificent concrete jungle of ours. I wrote this particular Rave before having contacted the artistic heroes of <a href="http://www.migrantas.org/">Migrantas</a>, before having taken part in the process of telling my migration story and finding myself nearly in tears, not quite knowing what it was I had to share. Storytelling is like that, full of surprises and revelations. Sophia and I were two of the seven participants in the Berlin Migrantas workshop this past week. We are proud to announce that impressions and sketches will be exhibited in the </em>Rotes Rathaus<em> this coming August, three graphic designs resulting from the workshop to be seen on street corners around Berlin, as well. Until then, enjoy this little pat-on-the-back for some locally-based activists&#8230;</em></p>
<p>Recognizing difference in daily life is good for everyone &#8211; different conceptions of beauty, different beliefs in the cosmos, different  ideas of home and the familiar, even different interpretations of the classic sandwich. The more we realize that the uniqueness of our own culture(s) is only part and parcel to the city&#8217;s greater beat, the richer our lives, even if <i>Käsebrot</i> (a cheese and butter sandwich) will never know the joys of aioli and thinly-sliced tomato.</p>
<p>Today&#8217;s applause for doing the good work of &#8220;telling&#8221; such difference goes to the <a href="http://www.migrantas.blogspot.de/">Migrantas</a> project, whose particular bent on migration-focused creative activism came into my life by happenstance: passing an exhibition of their work in the halls of one of my university&#8217;s hideously functionalist buildings.</p>
<p>In Berlin, the dimensions of migration and diversity may sometimes be over-simplified, but groups like Migrantas are changing that, and doing so creatively. The best part: the voice and agency of the &#8220;immigrants&#8221;, so often talked-about and so seldom talking-back, take center stage.</p>
<p>The child of visual arts, graphic design, and social sciences, the workshop teams of Migrantas transform questions of movement, displacement, adjustment, and integration into opportunities for intercultural visual dialogue. At workshops organized between artists and (im)migrants, participants are asked to draw their multicultural, multi-layered experiences quickly with pencils. Little guidance is provided &#8211; call it a stream-of-consciousness meets ink blot approach to finding voice and using it. And then the sharing begins; a narrative catharsis, of sorts, ensues.</p>
<p>In the months following, the graphic designers work to transform these pieces of &#8220;voice&#8221; into simple but effective designs for the city, essentially designs meant to fit flexibly within the many nooks and crannies of public understanding. Posted like advertisements at bus stops or on prominent corners, public space is transformed. The city itself becomes a  &#8220;platform aimed to make visible the thoughts and feelings of those who have left their own country and now live in a new one&#8221; (Migrantas.org).</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://www.atissuejournal.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/Imigration_05.jpg" alt="" width="615" height="301" /></p>
<p>In 2006, Berlin played host to Migrantas exhibitions, seen from the anonymous seats of the U-Bahn to postcard-sized images found in smoky corners of the bar scene. Expect much more to come from this little army of activists in August 2013.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Keep an eye out for upcoming Migrantas workshops and exhibitions, by liking them on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/migrantas/144071052327456">facebook </a>. Registration is free and open to all with a migration story to the city where they now reside. ***And be </em><em>sure to send us suggestions for rants or raves in the future! We can&#8217;t always be so passionately opinionated <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.0.1/72x72/1f642.png" alt="🙂" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /> ***</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
