<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Afrodeutsch &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/afrodeutsch/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Review: &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; and the White Audience</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2014 14:00:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Afrodeutsch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nazi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[segregation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theater]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2248</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One attends a play about an Afro-German living in the years of Nazism and Jim Crow not because of the dramaturgy. One buys the ticket because of the topic's near absence in the German discourse. This is not a review of the play, but rather a continuation of the discussion with the cast that followed. As one of the cast-members remarked, it all comes down to audience: "Black folks probably wouldn't go to the theater to see this play in the U.S., let alone have enough money for the ticket. And here, we have a white audience. So, who are we really talking to here? Who is seeing this play?"...
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>As a student of my own history and place in this world, nothing is more difficult for me than to write about issues of privilege, white-ness, black-ness, and justice in one sitting, because there is so much that can go wrong, so many terms that can be mis-used or mis-assigned, and so many truths that cannot be conveyed in one text. I have done my best. And with all my socio-anthropological know-how, I may still miss the point or offend, for which I am sorry: so is the nature of the subject.</em></p>
<p>One attends a play about an <em>Afrodeutscher* &#8211; </em>Afro-German &#8211; living in the years of Nazism and Jim Crow not because of the dramaturgy. One buys the ticket because of the topic, i.e. its novelty and near absence in the German discourse. &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221;, &#8220;Made Black&#8221;, at the <a href="http://www.etberlin.de/">English Theatre Berlin</a> explores the rich text of race in 1930s Berlin through the experience of Klaus, an unknowing Afro-German &#8211; a word that still spikes the air with rarity, German-ness still seen by many as a monopoly of the white-skinned.</p>
<p>But Klaus&#8217;s character and his experience of targeted exclusion are not that far from the present, as a conversation with the cast will demonstrate.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_4.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_4.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht" width="640" height="1016" /></a></p>
<p>The play&#8217;s dense telling of a complicated history of race, citizenship, and post-colonialism through dialogue is impressive. Equally worthy of praise is the playwright&#8217;s collaboration with a well-versed historian.  The Afro-German actor, with a biography startlingly similar to the protagonist he portrays, is also seemingly extraordinary. The most important element, however, relates to its audience and what this means for theater as a medium of cultural critique.</p>
<p>This is not a review of the play, per se, on which the curtains closed this past Sunday. Rather, this is a review of the discussion with the cast, playwright, and director that came after, the sentiments of which will remain prominent and powerful in my mind, long after audience members have discarded their ticket stubs.</p>
<p><strong>The Conversation</strong></p>
<p>Thursday night, we, a primarily white audience, wait patiently for the cast to take their places at the foot of the stage. The protagonist of the play, the actor to play the American jazz musician, the actor to play the German politician, the playwright (Alexander Thomas), and the director file into folding chairs. <strong>&#8220;Black folks probably wouldn&#8217;t go to the theater to see this play in the U.S., let alone have enough money for the ticket. And here, we have a white audience. So, who are we really talking to here? Who is seeing this play?&#8221;</strong>, says the actor who plays the Black American musician &#8211; the play&#8217;s connective thread to Jim Crow.<strong> </strong>The scene seems to agree.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_3.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2259" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_3.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht theater cast" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>Daniel Brunet, the mustached upstate New Yorker who produces the <a href="http://www.etberlin.de/producing-series/the-lab/">LAB series</a> for the English Theatre and directed this play, chimes in about the lack of representation of certain &#8220;communities&#8221; in cultural institutions. The problem of equitable, fair representation is something sure to resound for both American and German audiences, though certainly in different ways.</p>
<p>This problem is an old one. But it rattles and recalls Berlin&#8217;s more recent debates on multiculturalism, intercultural politics, and the integration &#8211; or just plain tolerance &#8211; of difference. &#8220;The topic of being German <em>and </em>of<em> </em>being a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Person_of_color">person of color</a> (p.o.c.) continues, often with little progress&#8221;, a p.o.c. from the audience remarks, a hint of a German accent in the throat. This topic is contemporary, indeed.</p>
<p><strong>Can theater change these parameters? Can theater ask for more diversity from institutions that have no incentive to include them?</strong></p>
<p>The playwright, a Black American married to a white German woman, wrote &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; as a way to process &#8220;the complexity of these issues&#8221;. And yet, as he makes perfectly clear, representing his own stereotypes of Germans and &#8220;the lack of place in [his] mind for an Other of color in Germany&#8221; is central to the play. &#8220;Otherwise, I would have been acting dishonestly&#8221;, he says, looking into the glare, behind which fragments of the audience, of us, must appear.</p>
<p>The protagonist of the play, himself an Afro-German, speaks, his English flooded with German vowels, his mannerisms oddly similar to his character, who re-asserts his German identity proudly throughout the play in deference to the Othering looks of those around him. This Other, created by the Black American writer, is somehow a reflection of himself, he states, admitting how through rehearsals he struggled to read his lines, even bursting into tears; how the first time he read the play, he felt personally implicated and stripped bare. <strong>&#8220;I am German, my father left when I was three years old, I grew up with my mother, was born in Hamburg, that is all I have ever known”</strong>, he says. The biographies are nearly identical, minus 80 years and a certain regime.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2311.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2255" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2311.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht stage" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>The anger he enacts in the play now takes hold of his voice: the desperation and frustration. <strong>“Once I read the script I knew it had to be done, we had to make this play. Though, during intermission, when I was sprawled on the stage in a pile of paper [the stage is composed mainly of bundles and bundles of blank paper], I sometimes thought ‘what am I doing here, who am I talking to&#8217;”</strong>.</p>
<p>Despite these questions of audience and representation, the play successfully sends a message, one of critique. It weaves the complicated history of American segregation and its sub-human treatment of Blacks with the messianic framing of America&#8217;s involvement in WWII. Through the diverse arrangement of its characters, the play scrutinizes American moral authority in the fight against Nazi ideology and fascism, drawing dramatic attention to Jim Crow and the commonalities between racist ideologies.</p>
<p><strong>The parallels between American oppression and Nazi tyranny become painfully clear, eliciting the following question from the audience: &#8220;Would you show this play in America? And under what conditions?&#8221;</strong></p>
<p>&#8220;We would just need a theater to show it&#8221;, the playwright says with a smile, confidently speaking for the work alone. &#8220;The play was actually meant for an American audience&#8221;, he adds, hence the translation of German passages and numerous references to American &#8216;race sciences&#8217;, details often omitted from textbooks. &#8220;This is a history of not only segregation but of a science [eugenics and race-based Social Darwinism] that many Americans do not know about&#8221;.</p>
<p>Such a truth of ignorance is reflected in the young woman in the play, who claims that the protagonist, Klaus, is not like &#8220;the other Negroes back home!&#8221;, though she has &#8220;never met one&#8221;.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2258" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_2.jpg?w=640" alt="colonialism Jim Crow" width="640" height="411" /></a></p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Theater approaches many controversial political topics in the United States, because it can. A very particular demographic is going to the theater; and that is where such issues can be discussed&#8221;</strong>, Brunet adds.</p>
<p>The playwright explains that he is willing to relinquish artistic license and allow others to define the scope and boundaries of the play&#8217;s possible interpretations. Some scenes are based on his own childhood, others on historical research and collaboration with the author of <em><a href="https://www.press.umich.edu/174272/other_germans">Other Germans</a>, </em>Tina M. Campt<em>, </em>about being a person of African heritage in Germany.</p>
<p>&#8220;But what is the point of the play?&#8221;, the jazz musician asks, perhaps to the audience, perhaps to no one present in this room. It is not about carving out identity from the crowd, asserting the value of the image in the attic mirror, but rather &#8220;about convincing society – the powerful – that exclusion is harmful and degrading to human beings. Now, and back then!&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;The point is, speaking truth to power&#8221;</strong>, he says, referencing, most notably, <a href="http://www.cornelwest.com/">Dr. Cornel West</a>, a giant in the continued civil rights movement for people of color, for the exploited lower classes.</p>
<p>Theater is not a dialogue with the masses, nor a dialogue with society in general, however. &#8220;Like cultural media and cultural politics, it is a dialogue with the powerful and their ideas&#8221;, says Brunet. The rest is some trickle down effect or, as the p.o.c. from the audience adds, &#8220;a change in consciousness&#8221;.</p>
<p>The camera man, a towering Black man with an equally large voice, speaks to the political or &#8220;transformative nature of the play&#8221;: <strong>“Most people ask themselves the question, are things really that different now? That is what this play does, it asks that question again of the powerful&#8221;.</strong></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5em;">With these words, I instantly feel implicated by my privilege, the things afforded to me on the basis of the position and body I was born into. The room shrinks. I shift in my seat.</span></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5em;">We are the audience. We are the ones who should see this play. We shape the discourse, often to the detriment of those who do not fit the desired mold. Theater might be a chance to reflect on <a href="http://www.taz.de/!116745/">critical whiteness</a>, even on its limitations.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2296.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2250" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2296.jpg?w=640" alt="English Theatre Berlin" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>One of the members of the cast remarks, perhaps to break a long 15 seconds of silence, <strong>&#8220;Can we imagine a black actor playing Romeo? A white actor playing Othello? Is it bad that we can&#8217;t?&#8221;</strong> For the sake of this question, &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; should be produced in another season, maybe in another city, as a voice in a room with too few listeners.</p>
<p>I sincerely hope that it might be staged in the United States, a country, where diversity often means tolerating the one that is different but disrespecting him or her just the same. As <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/ta-nehisi-coates/">Ta-Nehisi-Coates</a> wrote in <em>The Atlantic</em> this Tuesday, <strong>&#8220;We are in America, where our absence of virtue is presumed, and we must eat disrespect in sight of our sons.<em> </em>And who can be mad in America? Racism is just the wind, here. Racism is but the rain.&#8221; </strong></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*After the Nazi dust had cleared the German capital and West German society had taken root, the Black American poet and activist Audrey Lorde began to popularize the term <em>Afrodeutsche(r) </em>or Afro-German,<em> </em>during <a href="http://www.audrelorde-theberlinyears.com/">her years in the city</a>, effectively building a movement that at least gave a name to an almost invisible population.</p>
<p><em>For more information on Afro-German history in English, click <a href="http://german.about.com/od/culture/a/blackhistger.htm">here</a>. For more information on Afro-German organizations in Berlin and in all of Germany: <a href="http://isdonline.de/">Initiative schwarze Menschen in Deutschland</a>, <a href="http://www.afro-deutsche.de/">Afrodeutsche e.V</a>, <a href="http://www.adefra.com/">Schwarze deutsche Frauen und schwarze Frauen in Deutschland</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>For an interesting twist, check out our <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/">article on Black Germans</a> (the change of language here was intentional) growing up in the United States to adoptive parents, often in the segregated South. </em></p>
<p>Photo source: Kelly Miller and <a href="http://jurigottschau.com/">Juri Gottschau</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Weekend Review: Germany&#8217;s &#8216;Brown Babies&#8217; (how America&#8217;s good-guy image might get a run for its money)</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2013 16:38:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Afrodeutsch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[segregation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=724</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Berlin can be a historical mine field. Escaping the fact that genocide, division, tyranny, even the colonial division of Africa began on this ground is an impossible feat. As American tourists wander through the many memorials to the lost, murdered, and persecuted that saturate the city with this remembrance of tragedy, I have to ask myself: Do we Americans think that we were always the “good guys” in this mess?]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Berlin can be a historical mine field. Escaping the fact that genocide, division, tyranny, even the colonial division of Africa began on this ground is an impossible feat. As American tourists wander through the many memorials to the lost, murdered, and persecuted that saturate the city with this remembrance of tragedy, I have to ask myself: Do we Americans think that we were always the “good guys” in this mess?</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter" src="http://www.kinocast.net/wp-content/uploads/Kinocast/Inglorious_Basterds2.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>Germany may have a particularly difficult past, but the catastrophes of the 21<sup>st</sup> century &#8211; and the ill which permeate them &#8211; were in no form a European phenomenon, let alone a product of everyone’s favorite enemy: Adolf Hitler and the Third Reich. American mythos about WWII would like to position a liberating force of Justice against a tyrannical force of Evil (usually inaccurately embodied by one Charlie Chaplin-mustache-wearing leader doing a special kind of rigid salute). Villains of this type, the kind meant for blockbuster films and theatrical reenactments, often detract from the other kind of villain &#8211; our own. Demonizing Germany as the dramatically viscous perpetrator can detract from the other transatlantic evil-dooers, namely, those who held other human beings of darker skin in socioeconomic captivity for centuries (see the <a href="http://newjimcrow.com/">New Jim Crow</a> for its present manifestations). No other history of slavery, segregation, and integration is as dynamic and disgusting as the American story. And yet, Nazi Germany steals the show; the Americans arrive with massive tanks and candy for children; evil is blighted out with a swift hand of justice and freedom&#8230;so goes the myth of the &#8220;good guys&#8221;. And so this myth must be, once again, popped.</p>
<p>I know just the documentary to do it &#8211; <em>Arte&#8217;s </em>&#8220;<a href="http://videos.arte.tv/de/videos/brown-babies--7526612.html">Brown Babies</a>&#8221; in German or its English counterpart &#8220;<a href="http://brownbabiesproject.com/">The Mischlingskinder Story</a>&#8220;. I watched &#8220;Brown Babies&#8221; on <em>Arte </em>this past Thursday. Here are some scenes, impressions, maybe even a splash of critique. Most importantly, here is a snapshot of an oft-forgotten part of history, giving America&#8217;s good-guy image a run for its money.</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p><em>A 50-something black man with slight European features,  hair combed back into waves, drives a tractor through the wheat fields of a farm just outside Washington D.C. He uses the back of his hand to wipe sweat from his eyes. In those eyes is nothing but wandering, the search for self and whatever comfort the solidification of one’s biography might provide.</em></p>
<p>He is one of more than 100,000 so-called <em>Besatzungskinder</em>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_children">War children</a>, born shortly after WWII to a German mother and an American father, a soldier, stationed on temporary duty in post-war Germany, when the country, especially Berlin, was divided into strict military zones. Dan belongs to smaller sub-set within this statistic, a sub-set not so often discussed. Dan is black, well mulatto…well he isn’t sure, and in the 1950s, neither Germany nor the United States saw him as ‘integratable’, rather as “racially problematic”. Germany suggested the return of such children to their &#8216;origins&#8217;, that is, to families with similar &#8216;racial&#8217; composition. America accepted such children under the pretense of segregation &#8211; they would be kept out of white public places, situated in families of their own kind. And all this <em>after </em>the Holocaust, after the scandal of rejected Jewish refugees from American shores leading up to the genocide, all this after moral imperatives were touted as reasons to enter to the war.</p>
<p>And so in 1951, shipments of darker-skinned children began, sent to strangers in a land which forbid them most basic rights. 7,000 of these so-called brown babies were adopted by families in the United States, almost exclusively into African-American families, as Jim Crow and general trends within the Union would dictate. Their German mothers gave them up for many reasons, often rooted in a combination of state and community pressure to rid society of un-integratable elements. The United States took them in officially, but did little to ensure their well-being, ensuring rather their subjection to segregation.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/wanda-lynn.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-725 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/wanda-lynn.jpg" alt="Rosemarie Pena" width="640" height="459" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/wanda-lynn.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/wanda-lynn-300x215.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/wanda-lynn-650x466.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>In the 1950s, shipping half-white, half-black children to African-American families was a political act and often a dangerous one. Civil Rights protests were just beginning to take root in student communities, church congregations, workers’ strikes; the pavement of Montgomery and even Chicago were already tainted with the blood of black Americans and the rubber bullets of an oppressive state. Many of these children were put into the American South, but even in the North, racial discrimination was social custom even if it wasn&#8217;t outright law. It was in 1955 that Rosa Parks refused to give up her seat on a bus, unleashing lynchings and riots across the South. In this same year the corpse of young <a href="http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/amex/till/">Emmit Till</a> was found flogged and bloated in a river of impunity. Into this oppression and brewing revolution young children speaking only German, the language of the former enemy, arrived, hearing the term <em>Kraut </em>for the very first time, often followed by N***** or Negro. Quite confusing nomenclature for a confusing situation!</p>
<p><em>“We did not choose to be a part of a movement. But living in the black family I was in, I had to participate”, Dan describes. His parents took in many other “brown babies”. But not as an act of charity, rather as an economic calculation with a full farm to run, he tells the camera. European-black children did not share the history of the ‘freed’ slaves. The movement felt foreign to him; his family estranged.</em></p>
<p><em>Peggy, also in her late 50s, decides to track down her biological mother in Germany. She flies to Karlsruhe, finds herself wandering among clean cobble-stone streets, searching for the small graveyard where her mother is buried. She pulls weeds away from the headstone, planted in an untended cemetery in 1992 &#8211; she waited too long. </em></p>
<p><em>Peggy seeks relatives, rings the apartment building of her biological sister, clutching papers with information of living and deceased family members. It is amazing what the internet can provide. A small blonde-haired woman opens the door, shocked as Peggy explains their relation. The encounter in the apartment is quaint, even restrained. Peggy sits with a Lakers baseball cap and a &#8220;USA&#8221; T-shirt, her hands nervously folded in her hap. She asks for photos. </em><em>“You look like her”; “your father is Peurto Rican”; “she just didn’t want kids; she would rather go dancing than stay home with the children”. A niece visiting from American conveniently interprets. </em></p>
<p>The other 4 stories of unwanted birth, migration, adoption, black or multiracial identity in the United States dash across the screen. Stories of the falsified Afro in a time in which hair was political, vignettes  of a childhood growing up in families struggling to identify themselves as revolutionaries, subservient, fighters, blacks, or former slaves, Afro-German-American children asking too many questions about their own lighter skin color, getting often in the middle of fights, hearing the repeated “you are lucky I took you in”.</p>
<p>Germany and the United States are two very different countries compared to their pasts – both dealing with racism publicly and productive, though there is much to be done. The project is just beginning. Part of a complete <em>Vergangenheitsbewältigung </em>(German for confronting or even overcoming the past) is recognizing times of complicity and complacency, integrating these moments of ethical weakness within our teaching and reproduction of historical narratives. For the stories we tell of ourselves are only as true as the breadth of their inclusion. Until this point, WWII narratives have heroized Americans as Liberators and Germans as evil-dooers. Within the greater spectrum of historical experience, America continued to inhumanely repress its ethnic minorities, long after the tragedy of Auschwitz was unleashed. What does this say about America? And what does this say about the good guys?</p>
<p>What cannot be explained in a documentary is the complexity and variation in experience between regions of the United States, family dynamics, configurations of urban versus rural upbringing, and even color-based hierarchies within American black communities. The German documentary could have spent a few more minutes devoted to these differences and what cannot be examined, even made sense of within the pictured narratives. &#8220;Brown Babies&#8221; comes highly recommended, despite its inability to make all complexity of a generation and a movement accessible. It can be moved anytime from <a href="http://videos.arte.tv/de/videos#/tv/coverflow///1/120/"><em>Arte</em></a>&#8216;s Mediathek.</p>
<p><em>-By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em> </em>For more information on Afro-German children born directly after the war, including those not necessarily shipped out to black American families, check out the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brown_Babies">Wikipedia</a> page as a starting ground, this interesting <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/germany-s-brown-babies-the-difficult-identities-of-post-war-black-children-of-gis-a-651989.html">article</a> (in English) from <em>Der Spiegel, </em>and the website <a href="http://blackgermans.us/new/">Black Germans US</a> &#8211; a networking, research, and media project by Afro-German-Americans living either in the United States or in Germany.</p>
<p>Photo source &#8211; <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/germany-s-brown-babies-the-difficult-identities-of-post-war-black-children-of-gis-a-651989.html">Spiegel Online</a>, IMDB</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rant: Who&#8217;s/Whose Normal?</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2013 09:06:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Afrodeutsch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[consumerism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=514</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It's these little images, phrases, and jokes that become so deeply engrained within our mindsets and pervasive within our culture that they are considered "normal". But in a city as diverse as Berlin - where 1 in every 7 inhabitants is non-German, over 138 countries are represented, and the LGBT population is one of Europe's largest - what or who the hell is "normal" anyway? And whose definition are we even using?...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/2013-04-23-09-36-18.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/2013-04-23-09-36-18.jpg" alt="2013-04-23 09.36.18" width="459" height="344" /></a></p>
<p>It&#8217;s the little things that count, right? Unfortunately more than we give them credit for.</p>
<p>The fuel that perpetuates group divisions comes in all shapes and sizes. Prejudice and fear of the other is not innate in us, it is taught. And many of the &#8220;lessons&#8221; we receive are so subliminal and seemingly minor that they are dismissed as not warranting attention, let alone action. That or they go unnoticed altogether.</p>
<p>Like when my German relatives and colleagues jokingly use the term <em>Negerküsse</em> (N***** kisses) to describe marshmallow filled chocolates that went by this name in a former era. While younger Germans have been taught that the word <em>Neger*</em> is highly offensive, the term <em>Negerküsse</em> has persevered and is still considered by many to be cute and funny. What&#8217;s not so cute and funny but happening in the current era?<em> Afrodeutsche</em> children <a href="http://www.bildungswald-welper.de/seminar_negerkuesse.html">being called <em>Negerküsse</em></a> because they have darker skin and feeling ostracized for looking &#8220;different&#8221;.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/negerkuss_collage.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-523 aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/negerkuss_collage.jpg" alt="negerkuss_collage" width="411" height="287" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/negerkuss_collage.jpg 400w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/negerkuss_collage-300x210.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 411px) 100vw, 411px" /></a><strong>&#8220;Negerküsse&#8221; sind wir nicht/We&#8217;re not &#8220;N***** kisses&#8221; (A project for Afro-German youth and their parents)</strong></p>
<p>It&#8217;s these little images, phrases, and jokes that become so deeply engrained within our mindsets and pervasive within our culture that they are considered &#8220;normal&#8221;. But in a city as diverse as Berlin &#8211; where 1 in every 7 inhabitants is non-German, over 138 countries are represented, and the LGBT population is one of Europe&#8217;s largest &#8211; what or who the hell is &#8220;normal&#8221; anyway? And whose definition are we even using?</p>
<p>I&#8217;m not sure which definition the folks at the Leiser shoe store chain are using, but it seems pretty antiquated to me. Their new marketing campaign, <em>Traumpaare</em> (dream pairs), packages pairs of shoes alongside &#8220;dreamy&#8221; couples, all of which are heterosexual and Aryan with &#8211; surprise! &#8211; blond, blue-eyed children.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/2013-04-11-09-35-05.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/2013-04-11-09-35-05.jpg" alt="2013-04-11 09.35.05" width="535" height="402" /></a></p>
<p>For kicks, I gave their <a href="http://www.leiser.de">website</a> a quick look to see if I was missing anything, but only found more of the same. It seems Leiser&#8217;s idea of diversity is a brunette. As far as skin pigment, facial features, and sexual orientation go, these advertisements do not stray very far from Nazi propaganda:</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/aryan-family-neues-volk-1a8ezjw.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-521 aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/aryan-family-neues-volk-1a8ezjw.jpg" alt="aryan-family-neues-volk-1a8ezjw" width="297" height="414" /></a>Now, I&#8217;m not calling anyone at Leiser a Nazi any more than I&#8217;m saying that plastering a Turkish or Thai face on these posters will fix race relations. I&#8217;m sure Leiser wasn&#8217;t trying to be divisive with their poster campaign; in fact, I&#8217;m sure they didn&#8217;t think about it at all. And just like their creative process, the effect of these images will go largely unnoticed because they&#8217;re just storefront posters. They&#8217;re not a man screaming from a podium; they&#8217;re not even a racist comment muttered under someone&#8217;s breath on the subway. But they exist and they perpetuate a societal idea(l) of beauty and belonging that is outdated at best and exclusionary at worst.</p>
<p>In the Berlin I know, &#8220;normal&#8221; is my apartment building filled half with German seniors and half with young families from Spain, Greece, and Poland. It&#8217;s a park full of Vietnamese- and Thai-German families selling <em>pad thai</em> and drinking Beck&#8217;s. It&#8217;s a subway ride at 4am after a friend&#8217;s party, sitting next to a couple Turks and across from a pair of transvestites.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Rather than be discriminatory, let&#8217;s become more discerning and increase our awareness of hurtful language and misrepresentative images. We could all stand to pay more attention to these (not so) little things in life.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>*The term Neger is tricky to translate into English because of the socio-historical differences between Germany and the US that affect language around race. Officially, Neger translates to &#8220;nigger,&#8221; but the term has historically been used much more neutrally in Germany and is sometimes translated to &#8220;negro&#8221;. Today, the term Neger is widely regarded as offensive and campaigns exist to eradicate its use altogether. Accepted German terms for describing darker skinned individuals are &#8220;Afrodeutsch&#8221; (Afro-German) or &#8220;Schwarze(r)&#8221; (black). </em></p>
<p><!-- [if gte mso 9]&gt;--></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
