<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>immigration &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/immigration/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Moralpolitik and the Ressentiments of Change</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 15:35:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4120</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[According to headlines, the German government has pledged haven – albeit temporary in many cases – to up to 800,000 refugees or migrants applying for asylum in the country. The U.S., despite initial wavering, has signaled that it will work to raise its refugee quota yearly, with the goal of a 100,000 cap by 2017. Yet within and around this historical moment of humanitarian crisis and measured political response are the inflammatory words of Donald Trump. He recently roared to a crowd in Iowa that, if elected, he “will deport all of the 11 million illegal migrants in this country.”]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As German and U.S. refugee policies inevitably collide in light of current events, this writer finds herself in the United States. The other writer of this blog will soon be in Germany, taking stock of the so-called “refugee crisis” on the ground. On my side of the Atlantic, a crisis is not yet to be felt… at least not so acutely. This has as much to do with media semantics as it does with history.</p>
<p>According to headlines, the German government has pledged haven – albeit temporary in many cases – <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/aug/20/germany-raises-estimate-refugee-arrivals-800000">to up to 800,000 refugees or migrants applying for asylum in the country</a>. The U.S., despite initial wavering, <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/news/nation/2015/09/20/increase-admission-refugees-kerry-says/fnCweeIlCS8g47VF7VAkBP/story.html">has signaled that it will work to raise its refugee quota</a> yearly, with the goal of a 100,000 cap by 2017. The Pope, as leader of the spiritual state of Catholicism, <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">has planned to make migrants and refugees one of the few central issues of his travels around the Western Hemisphere this week</a>.</p>
<p>All at once, it seems that moral duty, a college ethics course, and politics have fused into one mandate to assist.</p>
<p>Yet within and around this historical moment of humanitarian crisis and measured political response are the inflammatory words of Donald Trump. He recently roared to a crowd in Iowa that, if elected, he “<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">will deport all of the 11 million illegal migrants in this country.</a>” When asked by Univision’s anchor Jorge Ramos how he would accomplish such a feat, he coolly responded, “I’m a great manager.”</p>
<div id="attachment_4127" style="width: 630px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4127" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-4127" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg" alt="Donald Trump immigration" width="620" height="372" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg 620w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP-300x180.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4127" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Charlie Neibergall/AP via <em><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">The Guardian</a></em></p></div>
<p>One can easily get caught up in the absurdity that is the American campaign season, enjoying its theatrics as a harmless part of the celebrity process. But Trump’s words should hold weight, and they should be cause for alarm.</p>
<p>Trump’s message is not as obtuse, as unnecessarily harsh as it might seem; it reflects not only present sentiment but historical precedent… for both the United States and Germany. With the current refugee and migrant crisis, old tensions are slowly and loudly being unearthed. And the mobility of many of the world&#8217;s displaced, traumatized, and poor is not likely to change any time soon.</p>
<p>National Public Radio’s <em>Fresh Air</em> <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/10/439114563/americas-forgotten-history-of-mexican-american-repatriation">recently interviewed</a> one of the scholars behind the book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Decade-Betrayal-Mexican-Repatriation-1930s/dp/0826339735">Decade of Betrayal: Mexican Repatriation in the 1930s</a>”. The volume documents a massive and relentless deportation program at a time when xenophobia and economic distress were rampant. Historians Raymond Rodriguez and Francisco Balderrama document what is nothing short of a terrifying episode in American history – frightening for what right-wing reactionaries in a new age of migration might be capable of.</p>
<p>As Rodriguez shared with <em>Fresh Air</em>’s host, Terry Gross, the 1930s treated Mexican Americans with great malice and abuse. For reason only of their heritage, they were targeted by government programs and private citizens alike. This abuse culminated in the federal government&#8217;s campaign to strip millions of Americans of their citizenship. Not all those rounded up in deportation raids were naturalized citizens, though <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">estimates suggest than ½ of those expelled were</a>. Most were visa-holders of some sort, their only crime having been born a member of a demonized ethnic group.</p>
<p>Governmental programs to round up and expel society’s undesirables often begin in cities, according to history (see the American strategy of Japanese internment or Nazi Germany&#8217;s institution of the urban ghetto). And so Los Angeles was the primary target of the government’s Mexican American deportation program. Largely as a response to the despair the Great Depression had unleashed across the country, officials systematically sent entire families from the L.A. area back to Mexico, with no infrastructure in place to receive them. <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">From 1929 to 1944, 1/3 of L.A.’s Mexican American population was deported</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4128" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4128" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4128" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-650x487.jpg" alt="Los Angeles Mexican Americans 1932" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4128" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Los Angeles Public Library/Herald Examiner Collection via <em><a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">National Public Radio</a></em></p></div>
<p><em>Ressentiments</em> – projection of resentment or fear onto often vulnerable groups in society – were widespread both in the U.S. and in Germany throughout the Great Depression. Xenophobia in the face of severe economic collapse paved the way for Germany’s organized extermination machinery. The U.S.’s internment of Japanese and German citizens, its continued subordination of Black Americans, and its systematic deportation of Mexican Americans demonstrate that this country was in no way spared such a nasty past.</p>
<p>Slowly but surely, such <em>ressentiments</em> have now begun to return. This time, Germany may be more in the right, even despite a few documented attacks on refugee facilities, while America edges closer toward the precipice of wrong.</p>
<p>…</p>
<p>On my side of the ocean, I have arrived into a complicated sector of the nexus of natural diversity and these increasing <em>ressentiments. </em>Vancouver, Washington, where both my parents now live, <a href="http://www.thenation.com/article/browning-america/">is becoming increasingly &#8220;Brown&#8221;</a>. Separated only by a short bridge across the Columbia River, Southwest Washington has become Portland&#8217;s semi-urban/semi-rural extension. Because the northern bank of the river offers families more space for cheaper, better funded schools for fewer private tax dollars, and income tax exemption, immigrants who may have otherwise moved to the Portland, Oregon metro area are now planting themselves on the side of its less expensive neighbor. Portland, as a result, <a href="http://www.oregonlive.com/news/index.ssf/2009/01/in_a_changing_world_portland_r.html">has become increasingly White</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4129" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4129" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4129" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-650x366.jpg" alt="Interstate bridge over the Columbia River, connecting Portland, Oregon and Vancouver, Washington" width="650" height="366" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-650x366.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-300x169.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4129" class="wp-caption-text">Interstate bridge over the Columbia River, connecting Portland, Oregon and Vancouver, Washington</p></div>
<p>According to most recent U.S. census data, Vancouver is now 11% Hispanic, inching closer to the national average. We can expect this number to be much higher in reality, as immigrants will often opt out of participation in the census. There are other ethnic groups represented in Vancouver’s demographic development: For example, 18% of families speak a language other than English at home, and the traditional taco truck has recently seen competition in North African, Japanese, and Thai flavors.</p>
<p>None of this would seem all that significant, if I were not writing about a traditionally conservative county, with once sprawling farm land and a historical military base; a county that has now been converted into a rare blend of suburban developments, strip malls, urbane boutiques, and miles and miles of regional road. The nickname of &#8220;Van-tucky&#8221;* &#8211; something I have only heard used on the other side of the water, mind you &#8211; might tell you all you need to know.</p>
<p>The rate of poverty in Vancouver is also higher than the national average. Vancouver&#8217;s mayor recently <a href="http://www.cityofvancouver.us/ced/page/affordable-housing-task-force">launched a task force</a> to investigate the cause of growing homelessness, rising rents, and increased demand for housing in the city’s most accessible and commercially viable areas. Serving as Portland’s &#8220;bedroom community&#8221; brings with it numerous tax and transportation disadvantages, as well, such as costly inter-city transit for a significant commuter population and bridges nationally notorious for being structurally unsound.</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p>In a brand-new cocktail bar in downtown Vancouver, which serves only locally-distilled (read artisanal) spirits, I sip my smoky-cucumber-tequila mixture and listen in on the interaction between the unlikely combination of guests who have just joined me on the patio. Three White bikers &#8211; two older women with smokers&#8217; cough and one machismo with a mustache &#8211; scoff at the price of their beer. Across from them at a nearby table, two women in their mid-20s, both with long black hair, one who speaks English with an accent.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-4130" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-650x366.jpg" alt="cocktail Vancouver, Washington" width="650" height="366" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-650x366.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-300x169.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Older veterans and cowboy-like characters are scattered across Vancouver’s downtown like curated remains of what was once here. They drink Rainier out of cans &#8211; Washington State’s Pabst Blue Ribbon with more local charm &#8211; and chain smoke in the park. They inhabit the dive bars with names like &#8220;Lounge&#8221; and antique neon advertisements. It seems that establishments like this new artisanal cocktail bar threaten to upset a tender balance between familiarity, comfort, and growth.</p>
<p>“$4! Bullshit”, one of the women hollers. The two younger ladies nudge their shoulders closer together, in order to continue a conversation disrupted by the boom of our three new patio companions.</p>
<p>The machismo turns toward the young women’s table, putting his hand on one of their legs. “Where you from, honey?&#8221;, he begins his monologue, &#8220;I’m a native, been here for more than 20 years, Detroit before that. You know how much this place has changed?”</p>
<p>Neither responds; however, the one whose leg is playing host to the man’s hand begins to shift uncomfortably.</p>
<p>&#8220;Where you from honey? You aren&#8217;t from around here, I can tell you that!&#8221;, one of the older women yells between sips from her can. “When did Rainier get this damn expensive? It’s bullshit, $4! I’ll tell you something…”</p>
<p>One of the young, dark-haired women flashes machismo a smile. &#8220;I&#8217;m from Panama!&#8221;, she says, and extends her hand for a shake. He takes it and squeezes it, returning both their hands to the table.</p>
<p>“I’m American, from here&#8221;, the other woman says, her leg now turned as far away from his body as the chair allows.</p>
<p>&#8220;But where are your parents from then?&#8221;, machismo asks with a chuckle. &#8220;That&#8217;s what I&#8217;m asking, ain&#8217;t it?&#8221;</p>
<p>She concedes, but stands to use the restroom (or simply disappear into the building) as she does: &#8220;Well, I&#8217;m Filipino.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p><em>Ressentiments</em> toward the Other can begin and fester in spaces of socioeconomic change. With President Obama’s pledge to take in 100,000 refugees, the question becomes “How will this country prepare its citizens to engage respectfully and kindly with members of a majority Muslim country?” The first step in this process is realizing that we have a lot of work to do, and we need politicians who will help us get there.</p>
<p>Germany has seen a fair share of reporting on the readiness of its population to open its arms to newcomers. It is easy to draw parallels to the past, particularly to Germany’s track record in <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/20/441732811/in-germany-migrants-find-footing-but-also-some-resistance">failing to integrate its guest-worker population and in promoting ethnic-based citizenship until it was almost too late</a>. However, it is Germany the rest of the world now looks to in awe &#8211; for choosing a kind of <em>moralpolitik</em> over patterns of the past.</p>
<p>Being so far away from a society I sometimes feel I know more about than my own (society of origin), I can’t help but beam with pride in watching small towns across Germany distribute clean clothes, socks, new toys, children’s books, and warm meals to the thousands of human beings in need who have crossed their borders. Nevertheless, Germany has since issued temporary border controls. Order still wins out over populist charity.</p>
<p>But aiming for a collective solution to the continuous stream of migrants and refugees into Europe, German leaders have worked to reach agreement upon a refugee quota for EU member states. Just this Tuesday this quota became a provisional reality.</p>
<p>Time will tell if all members comply, and if a sense of moral duty is really as strong as images of kind citizens touting bags of donations suggest. Yet I do have the sense that with each step toward welcoming the Other, <em>ressentiments</em> have fewer chances of surviving. When demonstrations of kindness are just so strong, so publicly undeniable, that Trump-esque hate can find no oxygen for its fire.</p>
<p>That is what I hope for America.</p>
<p>At the moment, the U.S. remains crippled and complicated by its multi-layered fears of all the regions of the world it has wronged. As UN Ambassador <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/23/442761552/10-000-syrian-refugees-just-the-floor-of-u-s-effort-says-ambassador-power">Samantha Power made clear in an NPR interview recently</a>, the country is not ready to simply do the right thing; it has to be a calculated response, taking security into account.</p>
<p>Overcoming fear is America&#8217;s consistent and stubborn challenge. I just hope the mistakes of the 1930s can mean something.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*Van-tucky is a reference to the southern state of Kentucky, the unofficial home of fried-chicken and horse races.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Refugees Welcome: Local Interventions for an EU Dilemma</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/04/30/refugees-welcome-local-interventions-for-an-eu-dilemma/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/04/30/refugees-welcome-local-interventions-for-an-eu-dilemma/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 13:04:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[European Union]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3965</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This article is intended to inform, as well as to encourage advocacy and action. As any seasoned volunteer or activist knows, engagement relies heavily on context, identifying not only how to get involved but why and in which capacity, based on the complex landscape of need one encounters.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Saturday, the 18th of April, a small fishing vessel capsized off the coast of Libya on its way to one of the European Union’s coastal states. On its way, it passed through waters patrolled by the European Union&#8217;s security agency, Frontex. Its demise was quick, only 28 passengers were rescued; an estimated 900 are said to have perished. Of the dead, roughly 200 had had little chance of escape, locked securely in the ship&#8217;s hull by the smugglers commissioned with their passage. A similar event had made headlines just the Sunday before: 400 dead in the water. Yet even more sobering is the UN&#8217;s projected number of migrant deaths by the end of 2015: <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/italy/11548995/Mediterranean-migrant-crisis-hits-Italy-as-EU-ministers-meet-live.html">approximately 30,000</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_3993" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3993" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3993 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-650x488.jpg" alt="Essen_ProAsyl" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3993" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Pro Asyl</p></div>
<p>Although this tally of the dead got its start long ago, both the number and its surrounding political situation seem to be escalating at an alarming rate. It is possible that this escalation is, in part, due to the quick reporting the digital-age affords a global readership. But, given the current death toll and its greater context of inter-regional instability, one thing seems fairly certain: If safer pathways for migration to the European Union continue to remain restricted or inaccessible to many, the intersecting lines of risk and desperation will continue to make safety subordinate to a chance at what is (presented as) a better life.</p>
<p>Yet the most immediate and real consequence of these reports of danger leading to disaster may not be deterrence but desensitization: The drowned and discarded may begin to shock a little less with each headline, and, worse yet, public support for the displaced &#8211; in our communities, off our shores, and even in those far-off lands to which our governments sell arms in exchange for cheap manufactured goods (an oversimplification of the global balance of trade, of course, but the point remains a valid one) &#8211; may wane.</p>
<p>But this doesn&#8217;t have to be the case. This article is intended to inform, as well as to encourage advocacy and action. As any seasoned volunteer or activist knows, engagement relies heavily on context, identifying not only how to get involved but why and in which capacity, based on the complex landscape of need one encounters. And so, I will first offer a summary of information I find important in creating this context, beginning with an understanding of Germany&#8217;s position in the asylum system of the European Union and followed by an unpacking of certain terms and categories. The latter is not meant to distinguish between and thus arrange various grades of human value based on one&#8217;s reasons for migration; rather, examining these categories is an attempt to identify and elucidate the different contours and sites of vulnerability to be found in refugee and immigrant advocacy, with navigating such categories being crucial to successful support. The most important bit follows these term-laden sections &#8211; namely, a list of ways to get involved in Berlin housing facilities and neighborhood support centers for asylum-applicants. Some options for digital activism and direct actions around Germany will also be included for our readers further afield.</p>
<p>In the end, my hope is to transform this article into a helpful resource page for the <em>Collidoscope</em> webpage. Thus feedback on ways to improve its information and add to or amend its list of opportunities for involvement is greatly appreciated!</p>
<p><strong>Asylum in the EU and refugee status in Germany: an overview</strong></p>
<p>It is helpful to continue with numbers as a means of illustrating the magnitude of the situation (despite my preference for qualitative vs. purely quantitative data &#8211; for which this blog tends to be a perfect example). In 2014, Germany housed approximately 173,000 applicants for asylum, an increase of 192% from the previous year. By the end of 2015, upwards of 300,000 applicants for asylum are projected to enter and remain temporarily in the country [source: <a href="http://www.bamf.de/DE/Infothek/Statistiken/Asylzahlen/asylzahlen-node.html">BAMF</a>]. Despite its shock-value, this remains a small number in the grand scheme of immigration flows. Relative to the asylum policies of the other G-20 countries, however, this is a significant number. The United States, for example, processed 121,000 asylum claims in 2014, a country with four times the population of Germany [source: <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/europe/new-migration-crisis-overwhelms-european-refugee-system/2015/04/21/3ab83470-e45c-11e4-ae0f-f8c46aa8c3a4_story.html">Washington Post</a>].</p>
<p>This does not mean that all claims and their applicants are granted residency in Germany. In fact, most are rejected, resulting in deportation either once a decision has been reached or in a temporary stay of inevitable deportation. Only 24% were granted refugee status in 2014, which excludes a guarantee of permanent status, i.e. returning &#8220;status-refugees&#8221; to their countries of origin once conflicts can be said to be resolved. Last year, only 1.8% received the coveted gift of permanent asylum [source: <a href="http://www.bamf.de/SharedDocs/Anlagen/DE/Publikationen/Broschueren/broschuere-bundesamt-in-zahlen-2014-asyl.pdf?__blob=publicationFile">BAMF</a>].</p>
<p>Nevertheless, 2014&#8217;s final tally of approximately 34,000 accepted refugees indicates a lag in the participation of other EU member states, such as the Netherlands, Poland, or Ireland, not to mention the strange and ineffective logic behind the so-called Dublin III convention*. As the commissioner for the German federal agency for migration and refugees, Aydan Özoguz, commented just last week: “The European asylum system doesn’t work. Some countries are doing very little. We are one of the richest countries and we want to help, but it’s not okay that Germany, Sweden and France are taking 50 percent of the refugees, while other countries do nothing” [source: <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/europe/new-migration-crisis-overwhelms-european-refugee-system/2015/04/21/3ab83470-e45c-11e4-ae0f-f8c46aa8c3a4_story.html">Washington Post</a>].</p>
<p>EU leaders met just last week in an emergency summit to discuss changes to this increasingly dysfunctional system. Given Germany&#8217;s position as home to the greatest number of asylum-applicants, decisions made here set both the moral and practical tone for the other states in the European Union&#8217;s common asylum system &#8211; an infrastructure guided less by comprehensive agreements and more by a few select rules. At the summit&#8217;s conclusion, leaders agreed to invest more money in rescue efforts: more boats and life-vests for the Mediterranean. But what of more legal, safe pathways into the European Union?</p>
<p>Over the last few days, arguments have been made for a reform to the immigration policies that prevent potential workers from entering the country by legal means, unrelated to the conditions for asylum but also free from the ardor of submitting a claim and waiting years for a decision. <a href="http://www.iwkoeln.de/presse/interviews/beitrag/michael-huether-in-der-welt-iw-fordert-mehr-fluechtlinge-fuer-deutschen-arbeitsmarkt-223062">According to the Institut für deutsche Wirtschaft</a> (IW), one in five asylum-applicants has a college degree and one in three are skilled in some trade or another. With German industry&#8217;s sustained calls for increased immigration (to compensate for an aging or less technically-skilled population), providing a more accelerated pathway to a safe life in Germany for those migrants who qualify, while meeting the utilitarian imperative of the political establishment, seems like a win-win. Traditional asylum and provisions for refugees would not be eliminated, by any means, but the number of migrants from poor or conflict-ridden countries would be allowed to increase, saving many the eventual rejection most asylum-applicants face once they arrive in Europe, if they are lucky enough to survive the journey (see the <a href="http://heindehaas.blogspot.de/2015/04/let-their-people-drown-how-eu.html">recent appeal from social scientist Hein de Haas</a> for more on this argument).</p>
<p>However, as is often the case in coordinated responses to humanitarian need, calculations of domestic burden vs. benefit will dominate. And an end to these calculations is nowhere in sight. That is to say, if we wait for political change, we may be waiting at a high opportunity cost &#8211; that of everyday advocacy for and support of the displaced. But first, categories&#8230;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Refugee&#8221; or &#8220;asylum-seeker&#8221;?</strong></p>
<p>The distinction between those with refugee status and those who have submitted an application for asylum (referred to as &#8220;asylum-applicant&#8221; thus far) is an important one, as it helps to explain the origins and role of the <em>Flüchtlingsheim</em> (state-sponsored but privately-run housing facility for asylum-applicants) in the everyday landscape of German towns and cities, including Berlin. Of course, the implementation of national asylum law can vary state by state, given Germany&#8217;s federal balance of power; Saxony, Bavaria, and Berlin may differ in the scope and quantity of services provided to asylum-applicants residing in each state&#8217;s respected <em>Flüchtlingsheime,</em> for example,<em> </em>as this <a href="http://www.proasyl.de/de/news/detail/news/pro_asyl_studie_zur_unterbringung_von_fluechtlingen_in_deutschland/">study</a> demonstrates. But, in all cases, the foundation of German asylum law is built on a differentation between those whose claims have been adjudicated (decided by a judge in German administrative court) and those who have filed claims but are awaiting a decision, assigning different rights and restrictions to these different groups, accordingly. The most important rights and restrictions are those affecting the freedom of movement and activity for those migrants to fall in the &#8220;asylum-applicant&#8221; category. They are as follows:</p>
<p>&#8211; Asylum-applicants are generally not allowed to work until they receive formal status: either as a &#8220;refugee&#8221; (a temporary status, in most cases), as an &#8220;asylee&#8221; (long-term or permanent status), or as a &#8220;tolerated person&#8221; (<em>Geduldete</em>). There are, of course, some exceptions to this rule; for example, asylum-applicants in Berlin and Brandenburg are allowed to pursue employment one year after their application has been submitted, though this work allowance remains heavily restricted and qualified. This means that, in general, asylum-applicants are not able to provide for themselves, thereby becoming fully dependent on the services financed by the federal government, the respective state, and third-parties responsible for service provision. The housing facility system of the <em>Flüchtlingsheim</em> was established both to meet the need for accommodation and to enforce this ban on employment.</p>
<p>&#8211; Up until January of this year, all asylum-applicants were to remain in the state and district either in which they had applied for asylum or to which they had been assigned. They were not able to determine this geographical location or the particular facility in which they would live, even in the case of friends or relatives already in the country. These rules for residency and domicile make up the German system of <em>Residenzpflicht.</em> According to the organization Pro Asyl, <a href="http://www.proasyl.de/de/themen/basics/basiswissen/rechte-der-fluechtlinge/bewegungsfreiheit/residenzpflicht/">these restrictions have been partially lifted</a>. It is unclear, however, to what extent the residency requirement will be relaxed. And as with any policy reform, there will certainly be a lag in public officials and bureaucrats implementing changes. In other words, asylum-applicants may still be prohibited (by staff and local enforcement personnel) from leaving their assigned district, and limits to mobility may still be decided on a state-by-state and case-by-case basis.</p>
<p>&#8211; Residents of <em>Flüchtlingsheime</em> are frequently re-distributed to prevent over-crowding and to maintain an equitable distribution of the financial burden, relative to each state&#8217;s population and economic situation. The freedom of movement, which the abolition of <em>Residenzpflicht </em>may have provided, is overruled and/or overshadowed by this re-distribution mandate.</p>
<p>&#8211; Once asylum-applicants have received a decision from the judge &#8211; the time between the initial filing of the application, the hearing, and the eventual decision often proving to be a year-long ordeal -, those without status granted are either returned to their country of origin (often within a few months of the decision) or are given a <i>Duldung</i>, becoming a &#8220;tolerated person&#8221; for as long as the state deems their return difficult (e.g. in the case of illness, psychological distress, age, family relations, financial situation in the country of origin). <em>Geduldete</em> are free to seek employment and live among the general population, securing their own housing, albeit within the town/city of their asylum-application. But, in most cases, they are not entitled to the same social services as those with refugee status and can be deported at any time, particularly in the case of a minor infraction.</p>
<p>These terms serve to complicate the issue of refugees and the work of refugee advocacy, as various levels of status and treatment before the law are at play. In my opinion, when the media and public discourse fail to make these distinctions, the complexity of the issue and its effect on the experience of real human beings is side-lined to a language that prefers the simplicity of pure humanitarianism &#8211; a moral outlook recognized neither by German law-makers nor by the structures of the European Union. In simple terms, those crossing the Mediterranean and those living in close quarters in Berlin&#8217;s many <em>Flüchtlingsheime </em>are not all &#8220;refugees&#8221;. If they were, they would receive the humane treatment popular opinion affords them.</p>
<div id="attachment_3994" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3994" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3994 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind-650x650.jpg" alt="Deichkind" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3994" class="wp-caption-text">German pop group Deichkind; Source: <a href="https://instagram.com/p/0tB_FivQxn/">Instagram</a></p></div>
<p>Yet, when we acknowledge that it is precisely because of the precarity of their status that they need our help, the situation looks much different. And local interventions in the experience of this precarity become most important, beyond #refugeeswelcome.</p>
<p><strong>How to help</strong></p>
<p>A few weeks ago I visited a new housing facility for asylum-applicants in Reinickendorf, one of the northernmost districts of Berlin. In an idyllic setting, surrounded by pine and quiet residential streets, a former High School has been converted into a 300 bed hostel for migrants awaiting status. The space is rudimentary but well-organized, staff making do with donated toys and German courses, among other diverse activities, as a means to entertain the many children &#8211; many of whom have been waiting for more than two months to enroll in the local school. The staff &#8211; about 10 in number &#8211; communicate with residents in what seems to be a mix of German, English, French, and enthusiastic signage. There is an artist working on the aesthetic revitalization of the place &#8211; literally making the dark halls of a High School a place that feels like home for its residents. There are social workers and psychologists who visit on occasion. Basic meals are catered three times a day on a set schedule. &#8220;House Rules&#8221; are posted in various languages in the foyer. And security guards patrol the grounds, which are clearly the remains of a once vibrant schoolyard, complete with a basketball court (nets partially intact) and a covered concrete playground for jumping rope and hopscotch. We chat about setting up in-house cooking activities, to bring residents and staff closer together, and about using the open space to start a garden, giving the families an opportunity to build and realize a strenuous but rewarding project, even harvest its fruits. The plans are piece-meal and heavily reliant on donations and organizational finesse. In many ways, it is simply about showing up (a familiar mantra), trying to be of help, and deferring to the staff who are there throughout the week trying to make the facility a better place for all who live there.</p>
<p>There are more than 40 facilities just like this one across Berlin, housing upwards of 11,000 asylum-applicants. <a href="http://www.morgenpost.de/berlin/article139453814/Senat-baut-36-neue-Fluechtlingsheime-in-Berlin.html">36 more facilities just like them are planned</a> for the end of 2015. The need is great, but so is this city. Here is a list of established groups across Berlin who work directly with <em>Flüchtlingsheime </em>like the one mentioned above; all of these organizations are certainly eager for new volunteers:</p>
<p>Flüchtlingsinitiative Klausener Platz [evagoemuesay(at)gmail.com]</p>
<p><a href="https://hellersdorfhilft.wordpress.com/">Hellersdorf hilft e.V.</a></p>
<p>Initiative Grenzen weg Hellersdorf [grenzenweg(at)gmx.de]</p>
<p><a href="http://www.wir-netzwerk.de/">Willkommen in Reinickendorf</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.willkommensbuendnis-steglitz-zehlendorf.de/">Willkommensbündnis für Flüchtlinge Steglitz-Zehlendorf</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.lichtenbergerbuendnis.de/">Lichtenberger Bündnis für Demokratie und Toleranz</a></p>
<p><a href="https://bunterwind.wordpress.com/">Bunter Wind für Lichtenberg</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.willkommen-im-westend.de/">Willkommen im Westend &#8211; Refugees Welcome</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.zentrum-für-demokratie.de/">Netzwerk für Flüchtlinge in Treptow-Köpenick</a></p>
<p><a href="http://multitude_tk@riseup.net">Multitude Gruppe Köpenick</a> (for German speakers only &#8211; German language instruction)</p>
<p><a href="https://arbeitsgruppefluchtundmenschenrechte.wordpress.com/">Arbeitsgruppe Flucht und Menschenrechte Treptow-Köpenick</a></p>
<p><a href="http://uffmucken-schoeneweide.de/">Initiative &#8220;Uffmucken Schöneweide&#8221;</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.buendnis-neukoelln.de/">Bündnis Neukölln</a></p>
<p><a href="http://fluechtlingshilfe@britzerinitiative.de">Aktionsbündnis Flüchtlingshilfe Britz</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.multitude-berlin.de/">Initiative Multitude e.V.</a> (for German speakers only &#8211; German language instruction in Spandau, Westend, Lichtenberg, Marzahn, Prenzlauer Berg)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.pankow-hilft.de/">Willkommensnetzwerk &#8220;Pankow Hilft!&#8221;</a> (Pankow, Prenzlauer Berg, Weissensee, Buch)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Fl%C3%BCchtlinge-willkommen-in-Buch-und-Karow/1481160482158156">Flüchtlinge willkommen in Buch und Karow</a></p>
<p><a href="http://u_strassburger@posteo.de">Unterstützer_innenkreis Flüchtlingsunterkunft Prenzlauer Berg</a></p>
<p>Initiative &#8220;Wedding Hilft&#8221; [wedding.hilft(at)gmail.com]</p>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/moabithilft">Initiative &#8220;Moabit Hilft&#8221;</a></p>
<p><a href="http://neuenachbarschaft.wordpress.com/">Initiative &#8220;Neue Nachbarschaft Moabit&#8221;</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.willkommensbuendnis-steglitz-zehlendorf.de/">Willkommensbündnis für Flüchtlinge in Steglitz-Zehlendorf</a></p>
<p><a href="http://bglbb.blogsport.de/">Bündnis gegen Lager Berlin-Brandenburg</a></p>
<p><a href="http://asylstrikeberlin.wordpress.com/">Oranienplatz</a></p>
<p>For those without immediate time to spare but keen on staying informed on actions and opportunities as they develop, track the activities of  the <a href="http://www.fluechtlingsrat-berlin.de/">Flüchtlingsrat-Berlin</a> (the local office of the nation-wide &#8220;refugee council&#8221; model) and <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">GiveSomethingBacktoBerlin</a> (a community platform for volunteer engagement, including frequent posts from groups seeking participants in visits to and on-going projects within <em>Flüchtlingsheime</em>).</p>
<p>Of course, this type of on-site involvement is not for everyone. The type of validation that often comes with structured community engagement projects is not likely to be found here. And, although I am a fan of &#8220;showing up&#8221; and getting one&#8217;s hands dirty, applying pressure on policy-makers and raising awareness to the need for asylum and immigration reform remain incredibly important contributions. Here are a few resources on direct actions and politics-oriented digital activism; these options are great for those further afield who would like to participate in some way, even if just with a click:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/367018126842745,%20http://www.amnesty.de/2015/4/20/massensterben-im-mittelmeer-stoppen-seenotrettung-jetzt">Amnesty International Germany&#8217;s campaign against </a><em><a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/367018126842745,%20http://www.amnesty.de/2015/4/20/massensterben-im-mittelmeer-stoppen-seenotrettung-jetzt">Massensterben im Mittelmeer</a> (</em>flash-mobs and rallies around the offices of Parliament and Executive Government)</p>
<p><a href="http://action.amnesty.de/l/ger/p/dia/action3/common/public/?action_KEY=9703&amp;d=1">#SOSEurope Amnesty International petition</a> (calling upon Merkel&#8217;s government to reform immigration and asylum policy)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.proasyl.de/de/home/seenotrettung-jetzt/">ProAsyl petition</a> (for more EU member-state support of rescue efforts in the Mediterranean)</p>
<p>Donate to the organization <a href="http://www.proasyl.de/de/">Pro Asyl:</a> perhaps the best way to assist the many asylum-applicants residing in Germany and other EU member states by way of a great and highly-effective organization. Pro Asyl coordinates volunteer activities, contributes to accurate reporting and research on asylum in the EU, and offers legal counsel to asylum-applicants, among many other great services.</p>
<p><strong>Why local interventions matter</strong></p>
<p>A <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/media/2015-05-16_EFA-Forschungsbericht_Endfassung.pdf">study</a> was just released by the new <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/">Berlin Institute for Empirical Migration and Integration Research</a>* (BIM) on Berlin-based volunteer engagement  in support of asylum-applicants and resettled refugees. It points to severe deficits in state services for which the unpaid contributions of volunteers strive to remedy. In particular, without the engagement of what the study deems predominately secular, middle-class females, many asylum-applicants would have great difficulty communicating with those agencies charged with the processing and, ultimately, the acceptance or rejection of their claim to refugee status. Additionally, despite the <em>Trägerschaft </em>structure, in which third-party organizations assume partial financial responsibility and full operational responsibility for these housing facilities, many goods and services would otherwise be sorely lacking without the donation-drives and supply deliveries of volunteers. The study describes the especially integral role of volunteers in assisting in the navigation of Germany&#8217;s complex bureaucratic structures: something necessary for immigrants of any sort to successfully remain in the country.</p>
<div id="attachment_3995" style="width: 498px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3995" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3995" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider-488x650.jpg" alt="Source: Pro Asyl" width="488" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider.jpg 488w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider-225x300.jpg 225w" sizes="(max-width: 488px) 100vw, 488px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3995" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Pro Asyl</p></div>
<p>And even the simple opportunity for social interaction, which comes with visits from the outside, can have a great effect on an asylum-applicant&#8217;s success, encouraging language and intercultural skills through everyday relationships that will serve them well in the future. From building the capacity to make one&#8217;s case successfully to a judge to preparing for integration into the local job-market once status, whether temporary or permanent, has been granted, seeing to the wellness of a <em>Flüchtlingsheim&#8217;s </em>residents is a powerful intervention in an often bleak process. In the end, it is the state that decides who may be called a &#8220;refugee&#8221; and who might have a chance at a better life, but volunteers may prove to be one of the deciding factors in who will be welcomed.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>As already mentioned, please submit your comments or write us an email with suggestions or changes, so that this can become a helpful and accurate resource for months to come. And please share with your various networks. The more informed our communities, the better activists we can be!</em></p>
<p>*Technically, certain conventions of the European Union (such as the oft-cited Dublin III agreement) requires that migrants seeking asylum, i.e. refugee status, apply for and receive asylum for the first EU country on which they are said to have set foot. In practice, however, Dublin III is inconsistently enforced, thus allowing asylum-applicants to submit a claim in an economically prosperous country like Germany.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/04/30/refugees-welcome-local-interventions-for-an-eu-dilemma/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: On Leaving Home(s)</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/03/23/lens-on-leaving-homes/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 15:32:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[family]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vienna]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3869</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Last month, Kelly wrote about the implications of "collecting ourselves" to make a move back home. While wrought with complications in its own right, returning to where one grew up, has family, or holds full political and legal rights is a move that Makes Sense. One chapter closes, and however painful or messy, the next begins...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3881 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-650x487.jpg" alt="2014-11-16 13.46.44" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Last month, Kelly wrote about the implications of &#8220;<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/02/13/lens-leaving-berlin/">collecting ourselves</a>&#8221; to make a move back home. While wrought with complications in its own right, returning to where one grew up, has family, or holds full political and legal rights is a move that Makes Sense. One chapter closes, and however painful or messy, the next begins.</p>
<p>After graduate school, I started losing the ability to picture my life in chapters. My decisions were no longer dictated by a series of steps culminating in clear milestones. I suddenly felt accosted by the need to figure out what I wanted to Do and Be&#8230; this time for the long run. And, given my international experiences and dual citizenship, the question of &#8220;What&#8221; promptly extended to one of &#8220;Where&#8221;.</p>
<p>So I moved to Berlin.</p>
<p>When I booked my flight to Germany in fall 2011, &#8220;two years&#8221; was my default timeline. &#8220;A couple years,&#8221; I responded confidently when someone asked how long I planned to be gone. &#8220;I should give the job a good two years,&#8221; I thought when I got hired six months in. &#8220;We&#8217;ll all still be here at least two more years,&#8221; I reassured myself about my circle of expat* friends another six months after that.</p>
<p>How foolish I was, to believe that two years would ever be enough. How <span class="st">naïve</span>,<em> </em>to assume there would be a clear demarcation between this chapter and the next.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3885 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-650x487.jpg" alt="2015-01-31 14.28.03-1" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Now almost three and a half years in, I feel firmly entrenched in my world of bilingual conversations, narrow streets, weekend jaunts around the continent, ubiquitous public transport, social welfare nets, and crusty bread. But these roots of mine are flighty. They wiggle at something as simple as a chat with a friend back home, when she catches me up on her life and I realize how much I&#8217;ve missed. When my sister or father leaves for the airport after a visit, they are pulled halfway out of the earth and end up lodged in the middle of my throat. Every time I get on a plane and head back across the ocean, a part of me fears they will be ripped out entirely. Because no matter how long I stay in Europe and embrace the rights my German passport affords me, I will always also be American. No matter how incredible a life I build for myself on this side of the Atlantic, there will always be a Life Back Home.</p>
<p>I was not aware of how much I had internalized this feeling until last summer, when my mother and I visited relatives in northwestern Germany. Sipping coffee on a sunny terrace, a family friend commented, &#8220;I could never do what you&#8217;re doing, be so far away from my family&#8230; I&#8217;m too close to them.&#8221; My reaction to her declaration was nothing short of primal. Of course I missed my family! Of course I felt close to them! I was not away <em>because</em> of, but rather, <em>in spite of</em> them &#8211; an unpleasant reality I struggle with on a near daily basis.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3892 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-650x518.jpg" alt="11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n" width="650" height="518" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-650x518.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-300x239.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Modern advances in travel and technology have enabled more and more people to adopt lifestyles fueled by wanderlust and adventure. But not all of us who leave home are <a href="http://elitedaily.com/life/culture/wanderlust-like-travel-much-no-real-home/959705/">perpetual wanderers with nomadic spirits</a>. Some of us are searching for somewhere to settle. Some of us are even surprised to find ourselves making a life away from where we grew up, away from the ones we love. I know I am.</p>
<p>I consider myself, by nature, to be a sensitive homebody. I crave being close to the people I love and place great importance on maintaining my relationships, both near and far. This explains why any time I am &#8220;away&#8221;, my pack mentality kicks in and I seek out a local community almost immediately. But I concurrently possess the intrinsic need to push myself and explore. For me, this has meant travel. Whether I credit <a href="https://psychologyblogaimee.wordpress.com/2013/12/04/wanderlust-a-genetic-basis-to-a-globetrotting-fanatic/">genetics</a> for this (nope) or my international upbringing, mixed with a little courage and a lot of privilege (that&#8217;s more like it), is not the point. The ups and downs of living somewhere other than where I grew up have become an integral part of my identity and understanding of growth and independence. They just don&#8217;t make the leaving part any easier.</p>
<p>The thing is, leaving is rarely the easy choice, even with the prospect of Something Great on the other side.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3887 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-650x487.jpg" alt="2015-02-21 16.37.36-1" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>While I never expected moving to Berlin to be easy, I did anticipate a gradual ease, and more importantly, clarity, with time. Reality proved instead to be emphatically non-linear. Rough patches hit me sporadically and without warning. My homesickness became a swelling wave, pulling in and out of shore, threatening at its peak to wash me out entirely. What if this chapter never ended? What if I never left my new home and went back to my old one? And now that I live in Vienna, my current home because of work, is my &#8220;old home&#8221; Washington, DC or Berlin? In countless discussions with fellow expat friends on the topics of home and belonging, the resounding theme has been similar: one of overwhelming choice and uncertainty.</p>
<p>A couple months ago, Kelly and I were at a close friend&#8217;s 30th birthday dinner in Berlin. Huddled in the kitchen over bottles of Spanish Temperanillo and mismatched plates of pizza and crudit<span class="st">és</span>, someone proposed we guess where the birthday boy would be 30 years from now. We had plenty of ideas for the &#8220;What&#8221;: running his own cooking school, teaching his kids how to do science experiments, maintaining his impressive beard. It was on the &#8220;Where&#8221; that we got stuck. &#8220;Italy?&#8221; we posed as the obvious choice (where he&#8217;s from). He resolutely shook his head &#8220;no&#8221;. &#8220;Germany?&#8221; He shrugged his shoulders, unsure &#8211; just like the majority of us in the room about our own futures.</p>
<p>Once you&#8217;ve opened yourself up to the world and seen first-hand that you can live, and maybe even thrive, somewhere else, it becomes increasingly difficult to know when or where to stop searching. The list of potential Something Greats becomes never-ending. And with it, the accompanying list of goodbyes.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By</em> <strong><em>Sophia Burton</em></strong></p>
<p>*My choice of the term &#8220;expat&#8221; was deliberate, as it popularly denotes migrants with privilege and mobility. For more on &#8220;expat&#8221; vs. &#8220;immigrant&#8221;, check out <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/global-development-professionals-network/2015/mar/13/white-people-expats-immigrants-migration?CMP=fb_gu">this Guardian article</a>.</p>
<p><em>All photos taken by me, in Vienna and Berlin.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: Leaving Berlin, collecting ourselves</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/02/13/lens-leaving-berlin/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2015 11:23:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ex-pat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3817</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Leaving Berlin might mean losing some connection to the tangible trek between dreams, realizations, and moments of vulnerability that is our movement through years, our aging and maturation, in any sense. But it is only temporary. Indeed, collecting ourselves means leaving ourselves. But only for now...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Before coming to Berlin, I was an archivist at an educational institution in Seattle, slowly working my way through a collection of artifacts that had been donated largely from Holocaust survivors and their families. Charged with accessioning (and/or digitally cataloging) over fifteen years of diffuse and often inconsistent records, I found myself forced to establish uncomfortable hierarchies. Collections are the result of measured calculations of value, often assessing the significance of one form of memory over another.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/memory_revised.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-3827 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/memory_revised.jpg" alt="memory_revised" width="742" height="603" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/memory_revised.jpg 742w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/memory_revised-300x243.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/memory_revised-650x528.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 742px) 100vw, 742px" /></a></p>
<p>Any museum has to be painfully selective; time, space, and targeted mission result in a lot of rejection. Pure and simple, refusing to &#8216;collect&#8217; something belonging to a victim of the Holocaust or a veteran of WWII means embarking on tricky, emotional terrain.</p>
<p>Despite its challenge, I learned a lot from this experience &#8211; knowledge that has served me well in a different city, a different country. For it was not by chance that my first foot in any of Berlin&#8217;s rapidly revolving doors was in an institution that appraised, tracked, and managed large quantities of objects: an art gallery. Yet, to my relief, I was no longer responsible for the task of sorting, accepting, and rejecting. The hierarchy already existed. I simply had to regularly tighten its nuts and bolts.</p>
<p>Now, I am tasked with doing a little of both. Because, you see, I am eagerly awaiting to learn whether or not any of the PhD fellowships I applied for last year will take me. Did I mention that these programs are in the United States? So, as I chew through a new set of nails and amend an ever-lengthening scroll of plan b&#8217;s, I am mentally and physically preparing for the Great Move Back. By default, this involves packing up what will have been a four-year ride in what I can best &#8211; and momentarily, as I am sure this will change &#8211; describe as a lesson in patience, adaptation, and even &#8216;failure&#8217;.</p>
<p>This is the archivist&#8217;s ultimate challenge: collecting oneself.</p>
<p>It is easier to apply some value equation to the memories of others, a different story entirely when each beloved stage of your life is on the chopping block.</p>
<p><a href="http://faculty.georgetown.edu/irvinem/theory/Clifford-OnCollectingArtandCulture.pdf">According to the anthropologist Clifford Geertz</a>, &#8216;collecting&#8217; is an almost universal process across cultures. Some  sort of &#8220;gathering&#8221; of the objects of both the everyday and the past is an important part of what he calls &#8220;marking off a domain of self&#8221;. Just as meaning, value, and story are carefully created in museums, galleries, and other institutions of public curation and display, so our lives become careful practices in determining what is now important, what might fall away, and what is to follow us to our next (literal and figurative) destination.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3837" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon-650x487.jpg" alt="Wohnwagon" width="580" height="435" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px" /></a></p>
<p>I could not agree more with Clifford Geertz. As I plan which &#8216;artifacts&#8217; to take with me and which to disregard, I am accounting for who I once was, who I am now, and which stages of transformation are important to catalog into the future fabric of my life. Most importantly, I want to make sure I remember what this &#8220;Kelly&#8221; was like as a foreigner, as a U.S. national in the European Union, or as an &#8216;ex-pat resident&#8217; in a city like Berlin. And I want to be able to tangibly review and understand, perhaps again and again, how these stages and categories underwent change.</p>
<p>Thus, I need to &#8220;mark my domain&#8221; and &#8220;gather myself&#8221;.</p>
<p>It should be no surprise that immigrants, in particular, are constantly renegotiating hierarchies of value and meaning. Usually due to the constraints of geography and financial practicality, the contents of one&#8217;s home must be down-sized, even partly abandoned. Inevitably, pieces of childhood and/or integral moments of budding adulthood are left behind. Imagine that: deciding which family albums to send to a distant aunt for storage, which heirlooms to pass on to those who may never know what it is like to say goodbye to the literal bulk of memory, or which books to put up for sale, never-mind the story behind the inscriptions.</p>
<p>And yet, returning to the proverbial bassinet, to the place that promises comfort in familiarity, might be just as difficult for immigrants as was leaving it.</p>
<p>For me, this seems to be increasingly the case. The longer I live apart from the places where material comforts and their consumer habits formed and enveloped my surroundings, the more I recognize significance in those fewer objects I have come to possess. Less has, in this case, become truly more.</p>
<p>In the end, the way in which the self relates to &#8216;stuff&#8217; is, over time, subject to drastic change. The way in which these objects may shape who we think we are in the world does too. And this complicates the process of collection.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/IMG_66181.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3835" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/IMG_66181.jpg" alt="IMG_6618" width="580" height="435" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/IMG_66181.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/IMG_66181-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/IMG_66181-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px" /></a></p>
<p>In an <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/16/lens-going-away/">article</a> I wrote here more than a year ago (on my challenging but enriching relationship with family, friends, and self on both sides of the Atlantic), I mentioned that the two-sided sense of home one experiences living abroad indefinitely affects one&#8217;s purchasing decisions. Towels, for example, fell into this category of things somehow neglected in the everyday of my Berlin consumerism. Now, one year later, I have quite an assortment of towels (thanks, Juri), in addition to newly minted whisky glasses, books both recently bought and borrowed, certainly more dishware, and a growing pile of greeting cards and heartfelt letters I don&#8217;t think will ever land entirely in the recycling.</p>
<p>And so the collecting, the sorting, the hierarchy of value begins. And with it, the worries of abandoning something I won&#8217;t miss until it&#8217;s no longer there.</p>
<p>For who will receive my salvaged desk with its coffee stains and dents &#8211; from years of free-lance, home-bound labor; my ever-growing tropical tree of a houseplant &#8211; a gift from my dear roommates; my antiquated but charming boombox &#8211; discovered in a damp basement; my IKEA comfy-chair &#8211; hauled in two-go&#8217;s from the south of Berlin? Will their future recipients understand what they signify? What they meant, to me?</p>
<p>More recently, I have tried to reconstruct the contents of the pack I first brought with me to Berlin, its meager (if not forced) element of chosen austerity: three pairs of shoes, two copies of classic literature, two copies of hard-knock poetry, one folder of important personal documents,  toothpaste and a toothbrush, a miniature Ganesha statue, a laptop &#8211; you get the picture. Establishing some sort of a contrast is helping me, now, to re-collect.</p>
<p>To complete this act of comparison, I rummaged through boxes of the miscellaneous items one learns to hold on to after more than three years of lived life in a cosmopolitan metropolis, with all the adventures in between: ticket stubs, letters, newspaper clippings (so antiquated-adorable, I know), event flyers, various city maps. What I have found is that the &#8220;Kelly&#8221; from three years ago might have expected to uncover herself in the objects she could fit in one suitcase, while this &#8220;Kelly&#8221; &#8211; as the more recent product of the European Union, parts of the German social system, and a fragmented but very resilient city of complex diversity &#8211; would never expect such a thing.</p>
<p>I am just too different; my surroundings are just too different, too complex even. But perhaps it has always been this way. And it has just taken me three years to see it.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/foot_revised1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3836 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/foot_revised1-556x650.jpg" alt="foot_revised" width="556" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/foot_revised1.jpg 556w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/foot_revised1-256x300.jpg 256w" sizes="(max-width: 556px) 100vw, 556px" /></a></p>
<p>In this exercise of trying to curate the display of current me to future life, I have become (relatively) certain of one thing: that much of what I will take with me and much of what I will leave behind will become obsolete in the years to come. Because our hierarchies of what matters and what matters Right Now are constrained by time and its passage. Because we grow older. And so does our stuff, its significance and relationship to memory fading.</p>
<p>Leaving Berlin might mean losing some connection to the tangible trek between dreams, realizations, and moments of vulnerability that is our movement through years, our aging and maturation, in any sense. But it is only temporary. Indeed, collecting ourselves means leaving ourselves.</p>
<p>But only for now.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>All photos were taken by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: &#8220;I&#8217;m not Turkish, but my husband is&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[love]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tunisia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1251</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In a capital city marked by transformation and transience, where people are perpetually coming and going, it can feel like a true rarity to meet someone actually from that city. “H” was my first Berlin friend from Berlin. We met through a language website, after she sent me a request to practice French in exchange for German. H was working on her degree to become a French teacher. I was still new to the city and could count my local friends on one hand...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_3811" style="width: 733px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://jurigottschau.com/"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3811" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3811 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz.jpg" alt="grillplatz" width="723" height="482" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz.jpg 723w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 723px) 100vw, 723px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3811" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p style="text-align: left;">In a capital city marked by transformation and transience, where people are perpetually coming and going, it can feel like a true rarity to meet someone actually <em>from</em> that city.</p>
<p>&#8220;H&#8221; was my first Berlin friend from Berlin. We met through a language website, after she sent me a request to practice French in exchange for German. H was working on her degree to become a French teacher. I was still new to the city and could count my local friends on one hand. The first time we hung out was in February 2012 at a cafe under the <em>Savignyplatz S-Bahn</em> arches. H ended up helping me with my research on teacher quality in Germany, and I gave her tips for her upcoming study abroad program in France. Soon enough our linguistic meet-ups evolved into a friendship that waved off grammar practice in favor of relaxed Sunday afternoon coffee dates.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Our relationship also became a kind of exchange of culinary cultures. I started joining her annually to break the fast during Ramadan. As the resident atheist I wouldn&#8217;t fast before these meals. Yet I&#8217;d still be the one gnawing away at my fingers until sundown, while H and her sisters waited patiently for their first sips of rose flavored water and soup drizzled with fresh lemon juice. In return, H  joined my international crew of friends for her first Thanksgiving dinner, initiated into the world of cranberry sauce, candied sweet potatoes, and general American gluttony. Her contribution &#8211; mounds of Turkish <em>Lahmacun</em> (spiced lamb pizza) &#8211; was eagerly divvied up like party favors at the end of the night.</p>
<div id="attachment_3611" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3611" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3611 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340-650x650.jpg" alt="IMG_3340" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3611" class="wp-caption-text">Ramadan dinner with H</p></div>
<p style="text-align: left;">It didn&#8217;t take long for us to discover our mutual fascination with questions of citizenship and identity. We attended several events together on the topic and often spent our cafe time discussing our hybrid families and understanding of <em>Deutschsein</em> or &#8220;Germanness&#8221;. See, while H is a true <em>Berlinerin</em> &#8211; she was born and grew up here &#8211; her parents are from Tunisia. We shared the feeling of having more than one home; while I straddled the Atlantic, H had a foot on either side of the Mediterranean. But unlike me, H had grown up with the challenge of having to persistently defend her Germanness, to the wider community and to her own parents.</p>
<p>In countries like Germany that are still embracing their multicultural identities &#8211; Germany first recognized itself as a country of immigration in 2005 &#8211; too many still have a binary understanding of native vs. foreigner that acknowledges bloodlines over birthplace and physical appearance over personal identity. There remains a habit of probing those who look &#8220;different&#8221; about their roots, otherwise known as the dreaded &#8220;But where are you <em>really</em> from?&#8221; <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/">question</a>. Those on the receiving end of this question are often referred to as the &#8220;perpetual foreigner&#8221;, ethnic minorities who will always be seen as the “other” because of how they look.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">In H&#8217;s case, it didn&#8217;t take long to notice that the vast majority of those she came across assumed she was Turkish, including other Turkish-Germans. &#8220;Oh right, the Turkish one,&#8221; a girl on her basketball team responded, when I introduced myself as H&#8217;s friend. H once told me she gets asked if she&#8217;s Turkish more than her best friend, an actual Turkish-German who happens to be blond and fair-skinned.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3697 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-650x487.jpg" alt="2014-01-19 17.26.48" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>The confusion isn&#8217;t all too surprising, considering H&#8217;s darker features, for one, and the demographics of the city, for two. Turkish-Germans are the city&#8217;s largest ethnic minority and the largest community of Turks outside of Turkey. Estimates of the number of Turks in Berlin range from 200,000-500,000 (a combination of those with Turkish passports, partial Turkish ancestry, and ethnic minorities from Turkey). A far cry from the approximately <a href="http://www.berlin.de/lb/intmig/statistik/demografie/einwohner_staatsangehoerigkeit.html">1,500 Tunisian nationals</a> in Berlin.</p>
<p>The story of H&#8217;s parents also mirrors that of many Turkish-Germans. They immigrated to the city separately as part of a guest-worker program in the 1970s and met on the job at corporate giant, Siemens. Originally, they planned to return to Tunisia together. The couple worked 2-3 jobs, sending remittances to family in Tunisia to save up to build a house there. They sent their 3 eldest daughters back for 9 years to live with relatives and go to school. But when Germany tightened family reunification laws in the 80&#8217;s, excluding those older than 16 without German citizenship, they brought the 3 girls back to Berlin to keep the family together, by then consisting of 5 daughters.</p>
<p>H is daughter number 4 and has only visited Tunisia on vacation. She admits that a distinction exists between the older and younger sisters, due to this geographic divide in upbringing, especially apparent in attitudes toward the headscarf and family planning. Her oldest sister &#8220;lives by the Qu&#8217;ran&#8221; and hopes to move back to Tunisia permanently one day. H, on the other hand, identifies as a &#8220;<em>Berlinerin</em> with Tunisian roots&#8221;; she has no intention of leaving Germany anytime soon.</p>
<div id="attachment_3791" style="width: 657px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3791" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3791 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg" alt="htunisia" width="647" height="484" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg 647w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia-300x224.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 647px) 100vw, 647px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3791" class="wp-caption-text">H on vacation in Tunisia</p></div>
<p>When it comes to questions and comments about her being Turkish, I&#8217;ve only ever seen H respond with patience and grace. It&#8217;s the difficulties with her own parents, and especially mother, that affect her most. If you ask her about her upbringing, H will tell you that her parents were &#8220;pretty modern for immigrant standards&#8221;, letting her play sports and stay out with friends until 10pm. Sleepovers and clubs weren&#8217;t allowed, but H found ways around her parents&#8217; rules, such as working at social events like the <em>Volksfest </em>and later heading west to Dortmund for university.</p>
<p>Boyfriends, on the other hand, were out of the question. Particularly those outside of the Tunisian-German community. H dated a little in secret, but didn&#8217;t get serious with anyone until she met &#8220;A&#8221; at 19. At 28, A was almost a decade older and managing a series of internet cafes. The flirtation started small with jokes at the shop, building up slowly to weekend jogs together. Finally, A asked H out on a date.</p>
<p>H managed to keep the relationship hidden from her parents for 6 years. &#8220;I was sure they&#8217;d disapprove because he&#8217;s Turkish,&#8221; she explains. Even though both Tunisians and Turks in Germany are predominantly Muslim, H says it&#8217;s not uncommon for the older immigrant generations to be prejudiced against one another. &#8220;The Tunisians here think that all Turkish boys are in gangs, are loud and have no respect, and don&#8217;t achieve anything,&#8221; H claims; &#8220;Tunisians in Tunisia think more positively about Turks than Tunisians in Germany do.&#8221;</p>
<p>When she told her parents about the relationship in 2013, her mother threatened that H was &#8220;ruining her life&#8221; and that if she continued, they would disown her. &#8220;I haven&#8217;t even told them yet that A is Shiite,&#8221; H joked (her family is Sunni).</p>
<div id="attachment_3792" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3792" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3792 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-650x202.jpg" alt="A&amp;H" width="650" height="202" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-650x202.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-300x93.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3792" class="wp-caption-text">A &amp; H</p></div>
<p>According to H, the problem is her mother&#8217;s stubbornness more than anything else. But listening to the stories one can&#8217;t help but notice an underlying theme of fear, logical or not. A fear of losing one&#8217;s child. A fear of not relating to one&#8217;s grandchildren. A fear of the dilution of one&#8217;s cultural lineage over generations. &#8220;Many in the Tunisian-German community are scared that their kids will marry Turks and end up in Turkey,&#8221; H agrees, &#8220;my mother is also afraid her grandchildren will never learn Arabic.&#8221; H and her sisters speak strictly Tunisian Arabic with their parents. When just amongst each other, a mix of Arabic and German.</p>
<p>Language is just one question of many that H and A will face as parents. They have already decided that A will primarily speak Turkish and H mostly German, which she is more comfortable with than Arabic. They have even talked about where they will <em>really</em> end up one day. H tells me that the Tunisian consulate pays for the bodies of Tunisian nationals in Germany to be sent back for burials. A, who came to Berlin at 18 as a student, gave up his Turkish passport to become German.  As an entrepreneur he&#8217;s eager to launch projects in Turkey and maybe even retire there one day, but is limited without citizenship.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">After months of not seeing each other, H and I finally find time last November for one of our Sunday coffee dates. H arrives to the Italian cafe in an uncharacteristically bulky sweater that makes me raise my eyebrows. Shortly after ordering our lattes and chocolate cake, she spills the beans: she and A have gotten married, and she&#8217;s newly pregnant. The religious ceremony was held at their apartment with an Imam presiding and a handful of their closest friends and siblings present. H&#8217;s parents chose not to return early from their vacation in Tunisia to attend. As for their upcoming grandchild, wherever he or she decides to be &#8220;<em>really</em> from&#8221;, they are still in the dark.</p>
<p><em> &#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong> </em></p>
<p><em>&#8220;A&#8221; requested that this article remain anonymous, in order to not further weaken his cause, should H&#8217;s parents somehow come across it.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Seeing Berlin Through The Homeless</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2014 12:22:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bureaucracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GDR-DDR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitte]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Schöneberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2398</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[They wait for the subway doors to close before they address the car with a rehearsed speech. "Excuse the interruption, I am one of Berlin's annoying homeless people"... it usually begins, as they peddle newspapers and scan the crowd for an outstretched hand holding change or food. The majority of us keep our hands tucked away or firmly gripping our phones. Some of us fall into convenient bouts of exhaustion, promptly leaning back and closing our eyes. In this moment, we are restricted to a shared space...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_2604" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2604" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2604 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-650x433.jpg" alt="hermannplatz" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2604" class="wp-caption-text">Photo by Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>In Berlin they are especially visible on the <em>Bahn</em>. They wait for the subway doors to close before they address the car with a rehearsed speech. <em>Excuse the interruption, I am one of Berlin&#8217;s annoying homeless people&#8230;</em> it usually begins, as they peddle newspapers and scan<em> </em>the crowd for an outstretched hand holding change or food. The majority of us keep our hands tucked away or firmly gripping our phones. Some of us fall into convenient bouts of exhaustion, promptly leaning back and closing our eyes. In this moment, we are restricted to a moving car, a shared space. We can&#8217;t dodge a corner or cross the street, but we still find ways to make them invisible. We don&#8217;t look up because we feel uncomfortable. We become frustrated at them for making us feel this way. We may even become angry &#8211; at them, at society, at ourselves.</p>
<p>How the simple presence of one person can incite so much emotion, judgement, and shame.</p>
<p>How it must feel, to be simultaneously so visible and invisible.</p>
<div id="attachment_2605" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2605" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2605 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-650x459.jpg" alt="eye" width="650" height="459" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-650x459.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-300x212.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2605" class="wp-caption-text">Photo by Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><em>It&#8217;s one of the worst things for homeless people, being treated as invisible. Answer them when they speak to you, make eye contact, acknowledge them!</em> our guide Carsten Voss urges us by the end of our walk. We are wrapping up a tour called &#8220;Obdachslose zeigen ihr Berlin&#8221; (The homeless present their Berlin), run by non-profit organization <em>Querstadtein. </em>The group offers tours in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Mitte that show the reality of homelessness in the city.</p>
<p>Our guide speaks from personal experience. Decked out in designer glasses and a well-fitting sweater, it&#8217;s challenging to picture this man as the subject of the powerful story he delivers in front of stately <span class="st">Viktoria-Luise-Platz</span>. Carsten worked 80+ hours a week as a manager of an international tradeshow before burning-out and falling into depression. First came the loss of his job, then his apartment. He refused help from loved ones, other than taking refuge in a friend&#8217;s shed for a few months. It would be a year before he clawed his way back out. He cites one defining moment: <em>I happened to glance into someone&#8217;s window from the street. The woman was cooking and the man was watching </em>Tagesschau<em> on TV&#8230; I realized that if I didn&#8217;t make a change then, I would never have that again.</em></p>
<p>That year Carsten counted among Berlin&#8217;s estimated 4,000 <em>Obdachslose</em> (literally translates to &#8220;without shelter&#8221;). Not to be confused with <em>Wohnungslose</em> (&#8220;house-less&#8221;), which refers to those without homes but still in the system, <em>Obdachslose</em> are no longer in the system and may or may not have a place to sleep. Berlin has Germany&#8217;s highest concentration of <em>Obdachslose, </em>both from within and outside of the country.</p>
<p><em>There are three main categories of </em>Obdachslose <em>in Berlin</em>, Carsten explains early on in the tour. <em>Former refugees from East Germany, those groups of young people who usually have dogs with them, and immigrants.<br />
</em></p>
<p><a href="http://ec.europa.eu/social/main.jsp?catId=1061&amp;langId=en">Migrant homelessness throughout the EU</a> has risen in recent years, exacerbated by the economic crisis. This may come as no great surprise, though it&#8217;s a blow to hear that many in Berlin<em> end up staying because they find the conditions of being homeless here better than their lives back home. </em>Carsten describes this group in three geographic waves: the first from Poland, second from the Baltics, and third from Bulgaria and Romania<em>. Of course they came here planning to find jobs, start families, create a life. Some make it, but many don&#8217;t. </em></p>
<div id="attachment_2586" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-23-14-33-35.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2586" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2586 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-23-14-33-35.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-23 14.33.35" width="640" height="480" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2586" class="wp-caption-text">Cold Weather Assistance for Berlin&#8217;s Homeless by District, Winter 2013/14</p></div>
<p>Berlin has a long tradition of homelessness. It&#8217;s a poor city &#8211; Germany&#8217;s poorest &#8211; but also equipped with robust social services. Berlin has a history of attracting those who are &#8220;different&#8221;, including many immigrants, due to its diversity and tolerant atmosphere. During the days of the Berlin Wall, it was also a haven for males escaping military conscription (which ended altogether in 2011). Carsten moved to Berlin for this reason, and says he and many others like him entered fields like social work and education. This, he claims, has contributed to the city&#8217;s liberal nature and strong social net.</p>
<p>Berlin&#8217;s homeless tend to cluster in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Charlottenburg, two districts in West Berlin now more associated with high rents and artisanal cafes than alternative lifestyles. Carsten guides us to Nollendorfplatz, Berlin&#8217;s LGBT hub and site of the annual pride parade, Christopher Street Day. We stand across from the colorful <em>Regenbogen-Stele, </em>a r<span class="userContent">ainbow column erected in 2000 to celebrate the area&#8217;s high concentration of homosexual residents and open-minded atmosp<span class="text_exposed_show">here. The statue itself carries two symbols: the rainbow flag for gay pride and the <em>Rosa Winkel</em>, a pink badge first used by Nazis to distinguish homosexuals in concentration camps, and what later became an international symbol for gay rights.<br />
</span></span></p>
<div id="attachment_2507" style="width: 538px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/2014-03-23-14-21-00-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2507" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2507" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/2014-03-23-14-21-00-1.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-23 14.21.00-1" width="528" height="528" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2507" class="wp-caption-text">Nollendorf Platz&#8217;s &#8220;Regenbogen-Stele&#8221; or rainbow column celebrating gay rights</p></div>
<p>As we inspect the square, Carsten points out what our untrained eyes fail to see: a 24-hour grocery store well-equipped with bottle deposit machines, a van selling the street newspaper, a well-lit intersection. <em>Homeless people are part of this neighborhood, they have a community here</em>, he says.</p>
<p>But another faction of the city&#8217;s homeless blend in so well that we don&#8217;t see them at all. <em>Most people have an image in mind of the bag lady (or guy), unkempt and dirty, pushing around a cart filled to the brim with random items, muttering crazy things to themselves.</em>.<em>. most homeless people don&#8217;t look or act like that. </em> Carsten estimates that 60% fall into this category, homeless people who look &#8220;normal&#8221; so they can use spaces and services within the city without being noticed. They schedule their day in such a way that they always have a place to be, something to eat, even a bed to sleep in. They know when the citizens&#8217; office opens and when they can grab a shower, when they can rest in the library or supermarket, who is offering a free lunch or haircut in the city. <em>It&#8217;s an exhausting life, they have to be very organized, and they are constantly in public</em>, Carsten emphasizes: <em>the only time they have to themselves is in the shower.</em></p>
<div id="attachment_2621" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-24-08-25-20.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2621" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2621 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-24-08-25-20.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-24 08.25.20" width="640" height="480" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2621" class="wp-caption-text">Assistance notice for homeless youth in Charlottenburg</p></div>
<p>Carsten&#8217;s happy ending is a welcome take-away from an otherwise harrowing topic, but he warns against the assumption that all homeless people are unhappy or need to be saved. While many do suffer from mental illness and drug and alcohol abuse, others have deliberately chosen this lifestyle. <em>Some people want to live this way, and we have to respect that. We have to recognize them as part of society.</em></p>
<p><span class="userContent"><span class="text_exposed_show">It&#8217;s easy to dodge corners and cross streets, to switch subway cars to avoid someone&#8217;s stench or words, to grip our phones and look down. </span></span></p>
<p>It&#8217;s not as easy to look up.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>The Querstadtein homeless tours (in German) take place in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Mitte, usually on Sundays and for approximately 2 hours. Tickets cost <span class="st">€</span>9,40, and <span class="st">€</span>5,40 for students, seniors, and individuals on welfare. More information can be found at <em>http://querstadtein.org/de/stadtfuehrungen/.<br />
</em></p>
<p>For more on the Querstadtein tours in English, click <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/zeitgeist/berlin-tour-gives-a-glimpse-of-berlin-as-seen-by-homeless-people-a-913758.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>For more on the increasing restrictions on public space for homeless people across Europe, <a href="http://www.surveillance-and-society.org/articles5%283%29/homelessness.pdf">click here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Collidoscope Manifesto</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/22/the-collidoscope-manifesto/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/22/the-collidoscope-manifesto/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[collidoscopeks]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 09:45:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cities]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2395</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A couple months ago, Collidoscope Berlin was invited to write its first guest post for the Global Citizens Initiative - an organization that aims “to build a network of people who see themselves as global citizens and want to build a better world”. Part of the task was to connect what we do here to the significance of borders. “Borders?”, we wondered, unsure how to proceed but mostly questioning why we had never concretely addressed the topic before...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_6374.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2441 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_6374.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_6374" width="640" height="426" /></a></strong></p>
<p><strong>A couple months ago, Collidoscope Berlin was invited to write its first guest post for the <a href="http://us5.campaign-archive2.com/?u=34e2670d2b1df6a04603724fa&amp;id=3a6a8f6948&amp;e=b0926c0e88">Global Citizens Initiative</a> </strong>&#8211; an organization that aims &#8220;to build a network of people who see themselves as global citizens and want to build a better world&#8221;. Part of the task was to connect what we do here to the significance of borders. &#8220;Borders?&#8221;, we wondered, unsure how to proceed but mostly questioning why we had never concretely addressed the topic before. What kind of immigration project doesn&#8217;t discuss borders?</p>
<p>When we launched this project in April of last year, we knew we wanted to do something <em>different </em>related to the topic of<em> difference. </em>We knew of groups that promoted and celebrated cultural and ethnic diversity. We had worked for institutions that research and analyze immigrant integration. Our goal was to do something in between, producing articles and commentary that both told a story and provided facts and context. And we wanted to do this through the lens of one city that, although formed by a unique historical and political context, could perhaps provide lessons for others.</p>
<p><strong>A few days ago, Collidoscope Berlin turned one-year old </strong>&#8211; and as we took the opportunity to reflect back, we realized that not talking about borders was, in fact, making a statement about borders. It wasn&#8217;t that we thought borders were unimportant or that we were advocating their complete erosion. Rather, we were advocating for the idea that every city <span style="letter-spacing: 0;">is home to its very own “collision” of cultures and thus has <em>unique</em> stories about diversity and difference. Through the lens of migration &#8211; the movement and coming together of people &#8211; we believe that we can understand more about what makes &#8216;us&#8217; who we are on the individual, local, and global scales. Through our personal lens of moving and living across borders, we aim to make sense of what defines and shapes the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/26/lens-coming-home/">places we call home</a>, as well as the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/16/lens-going-away/">places we leave</a>. Cities, as a reflection of &#8216;the we&#8217;, are a good place to start.</span></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/cropped-2012-08-22-19-03-431.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-18" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/cropped-2012-08-22-19-03-431.jpg?w=640" alt="cropped-2012-08-22-19-03-431.jpg" width="640" height="221" /></a></p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>The Collidoscope Manifesto </strong></span></p>
<p><em>Originally published as a guest post for the <a href="http://us5.campaign-archive2.com/?u=34e2670d2b1df6a04603724fa&amp;id=3a6a8f6948&amp;e=b0926c0e88">Global Citizens Initiative</a><strong><br />
</strong></em></p>
<p>Individuals are born within borders. On a map, these borders seem relatively arbitrary: meandering lines awkwardly encircling blurbs of land. And yet in our lives, the purpose they are meant to serve is anything but, as borders demarcate political, legal, and bureaucratic spaces, as much as they do geographic ones. For it is not geography &#8211; the land itself &#8211; that keeps us from coming and going. It is our (hu)man-made political systems and governments that determine who is permitted to enter or leave, to immigrate or emigrate, to belong or not to belong.</p>
<p>Despite the presence of these borders, we all make our way across these lines one way or another. Whether through relationships abroad, use of technology, involvement in international groups, or participation in the global economy: our lives are increasingly global and less tied to the borders in which we were born or reside. While this does not automatically make us all global citizens (which necessitates awareness and action), it fosters connections across borders that reinforce the idea of a world community. How can we reconcile this ever-present reality with our understanding of borders and restrictions on an individual’s freedom of movement?</p>
<p>The majority of us – more than ever before &#8211; lives in cities. Thanks largely to migration, modern cities have become microcosms of the global community, home to spectacular cultural, ethnic, and religious diversity. While this “collision” of cultures can pose challenges, it is also a tremendous opportunity for growth and enrichment. If we begin to view our cities’ pockets and spaces of difference as opportunities – becoming more empathetic, inclusive, and participatory in the process – we can begin to realize global values within local communities.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_0388.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2577 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719-650x433.jpg" alt="Collidoscope Berlin Manifesto" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Berlin, Germany is one example: a city with a long history of attracting those who are “different”, where 1 in every 4 residents is of foreign origin and 138 countries are represented. A city that is undergoing constant transformation, while undertaking the challenge of integrating not only newcomers, but the 2nd and 3rd generations. A city that is brimming with rich diversity and teeming with opportunities. <span style="letter-spacing: 0;">Collidoscope Berlin is a celebration of these stories and opportunities, a conversation-starter, a democratic and inclusive view of the many peoples, spaces, and settings that constitute the modern city. </span></p>
<p><strong>Lessons from Berlin: </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/">Ramadan with Neighbors</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/12/20/happy-weekend-review-an-old-new-christmas-market/">The Thai Park</a>,<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/12/20/happy-weekend-review-an-old-new-christmas-market/"> An Old-New Christmas Market</a></p>
<p><strong>Lessons from Beyond: </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/29/beyond-berlin-the-istanbul-connection/">The Istanbul Connection</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/">The American Northwest</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/03/beyond-berlin-difference-on-the-blessed-isle/">Difference in Sri Lanka </a></p>
<p><strong>What is Multiculturalism? </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/">Diversity &amp; the Big City</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/10/whose-multikulti-is-it-the-elusive-definition-of-multiculturalism/">Whose Multikulti is it?</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/18/happy-weekend-karneval-der-kulturen-carnival-of-cultures/">Carnival of Cultures</a></p>
<p><strong>Our Stories: </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/16/lens-going-away/">Going Away</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/26/lens-coming-home/">Coming Home</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/29/lens-linsanity-and-linguine/">Linsanity and Linguine</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/25/lens-lamb-on-fridays/">Lamb on Fridays</a></p>
<p><strong>Local Stories:</strong> <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/09/interview-ali-zoe-and-the-gentrification-debate/">Ali &amp; Zoe</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/">Orhan</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/21/lens-warm-nights-are-for-cricket/">Warm Nights are for Cricket</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">Moran &amp; Tommy</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/30/interview-hamid-stardom-and-the-difference-threshold/">Hamid</a></p>
<p><strong>We&#8217;d like to conclude this anniversary post by thanking everyone who has been part of the discussion this past year</strong> &#8211; reading, commenting, critiquing, supporting, following, contributing photos and story ideas and event announcements &#8211; we appreciate it all and look forward to another year of <span class="userContent">diversity, difference, and positive discourse!</span></p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By</em> <em><strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em> <em>and</em> <em><strong>Kelly Miller</strong> </em></p>
<p>First photo by Anna Meister, second photo by Collidoscope Berlin, third photo by <a href="http://jurigottschau.com/">Juri Gottschau</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/22/the-collidoscope-manifesto/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Roma in Berlin: Bureaucracy in Lichtenberg</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/20/roma-in-berlin-bureaucracy-in-lichtenberg/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/20/roma-in-berlin-bureaucracy-in-lichtenberg/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2013 14:39:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bureaucracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[discrimination]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lichtenberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1736</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On the first Tuesday of every month, the <em><a href="http://www.migrantenrat.de/">Migrantenrat Lichtenberg</a> </em>(immigrants' plenary) meets to address issues of migration affecting the district and its neighborhoods. The gospel of November's session: The Roma are coming! 2014 will be a year of change for Roma in Berlin, primarily for those who have come from Bulgaria and Romania. They will have access to the social welfare system, the situation will change dramatically. But this is about families, not simply numbers...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;<a href="http://www.bild.de/geld/wirtschaft/zuwanderung/droht-uns-eine-roma-welle-29296194.bild.htmlhttp://www.bild.de/geld/wirtschaft/zuwanderung/droht-uns-eine-roma-welle-29296194.bild.html">Is a wave of Roma threatening Germany?</a>&#8221; was the recent headline of a popular paper, known for its tabloid-esque reporting. In the Eastern district of Lichtenberg, this headline becomes bureaucracy. In reality, it is about parents, children, and families, who happen to be Roma.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/roma-familie_dokumentationszentrum.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/roma-familie_dokumentationszentrum.jpg?w=640" alt="Roma Familie_Dokumentationszentrum" width="512" height="392" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.sintiundroma.de/start.html">Source</a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">For my fieldwork in sociocultural anthropology, I run from one site of so-called immigrant integration to the next in the Berlin districts of Lichtenberg and Marzahn, doing my best to put together a structure that informs a system of practice. Within the waiting rooms and narrow offices of institutions serving immigrants, Roma are present and obvious, sticking out like a sore thumb without the opportunity for dialogue; they are talked about or talked around. <strong>And so one cannot talk about migration, diversity, and multicultural inclusion in Berlin without talking about how Lichtenberg talks about Roma.</strong></p>
<p>On the first Tuesday of every month, the <em><a href="http://www.migrantenrat.de/">Migrantenrat Lichtenberg</a> </em>(immigrants&#8217; plenary) meets to address issues of migration affecting the district and its neighborhoods. Tables are pushed together to frame a discussion, and the renovated walls of the Lichtenberg city hall fill with urgent  deliberation. The gospel of November&#8217;s session: <strong>The Roma are coming!</strong></p>
<p>At this month&#8217;s plenary, approx. 20 Berliners were in attendance. Based on attire and commentary, bureaucrats from the district employment office (Job Center) and volunteer representatives of  ethnic-cultural organizations of immigrant populations mingled with local political officers. The new district <a href="http://www.berlin.de/ba-lichtenberg/politik/integrationsbeauftragte01.html">commissioner for integration</a>, Bärbel Olhagaray, was presiding &#8211; speaking perfect <em>hochdeutsch, </em>pursing her lips after every third word. But <em>I am married to a Chilean</em>, she remarked in her introduction, one among many reasons why she is an advocate for immigrant integration.</p>
<div id="attachment_1761" style="width: 425px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/baerbel.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1761" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1761 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/baerbel.jpg" alt="baerbel" width="415" height="620" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/baerbel.jpg 415w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/baerbel-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 415px) 100vw, 415px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1761" class="wp-caption-text">Frau Bärbel Olhagaray, Integration Commissioner of Lichtenberg</p></div>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.berliner-woche.de/nachrichten/bezirk-lichtenberg/artikel/29620-baerbel-olhagaray-ist-die-neue-beauftragte-fuer-integration-in-lichtenberg/">Source</a></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5;">She offered the opening address, the title of which was &#8216;Roma in Lichtenberg&#8217;. </span><span style="line-height: 1.5;">The speech began with numbers.</span></p>
<p><em><span style="line-height: 1.5;">Roma number about 800 to 900 in Lichtenberg, though many, many more are to be expected. There are three apartment complexes known to house predominately Roma families in our district, characterized by negligent landlords and overpriced rent. We approached these residences as a reaction to complaints in the area. <strong>Families of 6 occupy 30 square meters for a price of 600 Euros, sleeping nearly shoulder-to-shoulder.</strong> The houses lack consistent ways to dispose of waste. Our priorities are to reinstate order and cleanliness and to visit the families regularly to see what is needed.</span></em></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/fennpfuhl.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1758" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/fennpfuhl.jpg?w=640" alt="Fennpfuhl" width="640" height="382" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/fennpfuhl.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/fennpfuhl-300x179.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/fennpfuhl-650x388.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.jeder-qm-du.de/platten-doku/platten-wissen/detail/wbsqp-71-r/">Source</a></p>
<p>But figures and living situations do not matter as much as Euros, at least as policy demonstrates. The economic element of Roma immigration is the primary reason the &#8216;Roma problem&#8217; has gained attention and notoriety, particularly in districts overwhelmed by rumors that may prove to be true.</p>
<p>Since Bulgaria and Romania&#8217;s entrance into the European Union&#8217;s economic area, which allows for the transference of work permission and skills from one member state to the next, only partial admission into the German job market has been granted for citizens from these countries. Citing a wave of unqualified workers, often illiterate, into a strong market-driven economy, i.e. a wave of Roma, this act of exclusion became German federal policy. According to the European Union, Germany was acting in violation of economic rules of engagement and must retract its restricted work policy for immigrants from Bulgaria and Romania at the start of 2014. This affects Roma.</p>
<p><strong><em>Most of the families are registered as self-employed</em>, Mrs. Olhagaray continued, <em>since they do not yet have the full benefits of EU citizenship, which grants them state assistance in many cases of difficulty. </em></strong>They wash windshields at traffic lights, peddle on the U-Bahn, play music in front of the mall entrance and somehow make ends meet.<em> They send most of their kids to school, as far as we are aware, and ensure that they learn German while they are there.</em></p>
<p>When she and her colleagues go by for a visit, she added, they are greeted with open arms, tea, and cake. <em>They know we are there to help them&#8230;and they need our help.</em></p>
<p>The room became silent, waiting for the evident problem to become clear.</p>
<p><strong><em>2014 will be a year of change for Roma in Berlin, primarily for those who have come from Bulgaria and Romania.</em> </strong><em><strong>They will have access to the social welfare system, the situation will change dramatically</strong>, </em>full stop.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/zigeuner.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1762" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/zigeuner.jpg" alt="zigeuner" width="312" height="412" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/zigeuner.jpg 312w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/zigeuner-227x300.jpg 227w" sizes="(max-width: 312px) 100vw, 312px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.pi-news.net/2013/01/einbrecher-asyl-antrage-von-zigeunern/">Source</a></p>
<p>Legal change may not change bureaucracy over night. In fact, it may take years until needy families receive any sort of visibility or assistance in the political arena. The <em>Migrantenrat</em> may set the agenda in the community and have an influence on local government, but laws are passed elsewhere.</p>
<p>Part of the problem with assisting Roma in Lichtenberg is the presence of stereotypes, seldom confirmed and often well-spread, evidenced by the contribution of one bureaucrat in employment services. Mrs. Olhagaray listened intently, as the woman &#8211; originally from Bulgaria &#8211; began to describe the situation of &#8216;<em>Zigeuner</em>&#8216; (gypsies), a <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/panorama/gesellschaft/zigeunersossen-streit-interview-mit-silvio-peritore-a-916760.html">word that has since become derogatory</a>, particularly in the culinary world. In a slight Slavic accent, she told of <strong><em>these people: stripping their living quarters of metal and valuable materials for money, over populating neighborhoods, lacking hygiene and order.</em></strong> With one finger pointed out the window at the end of the room:<em> the Pentecostal church, poverty, and illiteracy have led to too many children and no way to care for them!</em></p>
<p>But the cycle is slowly being broken. Many Roma children in Berlin are indeed going to school, and Berlin boasts <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/18/rave-education-per-square-kilometer/">initiatives which help them excel, as Sophia profiled back in June.</a> In many countries where Roma have lived before immigrating to Germany, school was not compulsory and in many cases was informally forbidden to them.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/roma-kids-in-school.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1759" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/roma-kids-in-school.jpg" alt="Roma kids in school" width="300" height="200" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://kubus-berlin.de/de/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/opener.jpg">Source</a></p>
<p>It seemed that our task in the <em>Migrantenrat </em>was simply to absorb the fragments of a crisis: the Roma problem unfolding like a heavy, scarlet rug out onto the plenary floor. <strong>Bureaucracy is often about working within the rules set by others, not about solving problems.</strong></p>
<p><em>But why do they come here? Why do the countries where they come from not intervene?</em>, asked a literacy volunteer in Lichtenberg schools, now working to absorb the newly-arrived children of Roma families, who may have never seen a book in their home but <em>come eagerly to learn, nonetheless, </em>she shared.</p>
<p>Without <a href="http://fra.europa.eu/sites/default/files/fra_uploads/413-EU-MIDIS_ROMA_EN.pdf">the story of systemic segregation and discrimination</a> behind the Roma (and Sinti) experience in Europe, answering this question is a difficult task. The situation becomes one of economics and not of humanism or even moral action &#8211; something enshrined in Germany&#8217;s constitution under its provisions for asylum and human rights.</p>
<p><em>So, if they can now access social services like any other EU-citizen, how many are expected to come?</em>, asked a representative from the Russian community, his voice lightened by compassion, though cut with a hint of anxiety.</p>
<p><em>Many</em>, was the message, <em>simply thousands</em>. With some other countries <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/02/opinion/02garcia.html?_r=2&amp;ref=romanipeople&amp;">forcefully rejecting Roma and clearing settlements, as in France</a>, Germany, especially Berlin, will become key destinations in the future.</p>
<p>Fortunately, social work agencies for immigrant populations have developed many projects for Roma-related challenges in Berlin, long before the problem was as acute as it is now. Talking to a <a href="http://www.dicvberlin.caritas.de/">Caritas </a>social worker from my fieldwork, I was told that it was the NGOs and not the government who pushed for <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">integration courses</a> to contain a path to literacy. <strong><em>How are they meant to learn German and get a job if they do not know the alphabet, we thought, so we asked for 900 hours of instruction instead of just 600, where they at least have a chance</em>,</strong> she said, exasperated.  <em><br />
</em></p>
<p>Another Caritas colleague was present at the <em>Migrantenrat </em>on this November day.  She sat quietly next to me, taking few notes, her arms crossed. As a social worker with more knowledge of German immigration and employment laws than any bureaucrat I have ever met, she looked a bit frustrated at the shock and awe that surrounding the discussion of a so-called impending crisis.</p>
<p>At the end of the plenary, she turned to me: <strong><em>This problem has been here a long time, we have been telling them&#8230;they didn&#8217;t listen.</em></strong></p>
<p>I turned off my recorder. After reviewing the sound bites from the evening, one thing was clear: Of course, the Roma are coming. Why wouldn&#8217;t they? <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Yrgnkd-Lsl8">Everyone is coming to Berlin.</a> This time, however, these people are not starving artists but rather a persecuted minority, seeking everything they have been denied. Even bureaucrats know that.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>There is no single <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/01/happy-weekend-a-roma-reimage/">Roma identity</a> or one Roma community, but for starters, some further resources are in order. Roma in Berlin: <a href="http://www.sinti-roma-berlin.de/">Landesverband Deutscher Sinti und Roma Berlin-Brandenburg e.V</a>., the German Roma and Sinti <a href="http://www.sintiundroma.de/start.html">documentation and educational center </a>for current debates and cultural awareness in Heidelberg, the European Union&#8217;s <a href="http://fra.europa.eu/sites/default/files/fra_uploads/413-EU-MIDIS_ROMA_EN.pdf">report on discrimination against Roma</a>. Finally, the <a href="http://www.migrantenrat.de/"><em>Migrantenrat Lichtenberg</em></a> is open to the public, if further discussions involving Roma and district politics happen to be of interest.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/20/roma-in-berlin-bureaucracy-in-lichtenberg/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: With Wings, Roots, and Sweaty Hands</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2013 11:56:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1678</guid>

					<description><![CDATA["Punctual. Exact. Productive. Closed off. Careful. Inflexible. Humorless." And some "Goethe" and "Einstein" thrown in for good measure. Was this really all a group of seemingly well-educated professionals had to say about German identity? No wonder the facilitator had started to draw sad faces on the list...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;">&#8220;Punctual. Exact. Productive. Closed off. Careful. Inflexible. Humorless.&#8221; And some &#8220;Goethe&#8221; and &#8220;Einstein&#8221; thrown in for good measure. Was this really all a group of seemingly well-educated professionals had to say about <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/">German identity</a>? No wonder the facilitator had started to draw sad faces on the list.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/2013-11-08-14-16-29-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1682" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/2013-11-08-14-16-29-1.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-11-08 14.16.29-1" width="640" height="640" /></a></p>
<p><em>My hands get sweaty when I hear this sort of talk</em>, a woman piped up from the front row, a shred of anger in her voice. <em>Is this really all we identify with, as Germans?</em></p>
<p>I shared her frustration. We were over three hours into the &#8220;German Identity and Identities in Germany&#8221; workshop, having already watched a documentary clip and listened to a panel discussion on the nuances of (im)migration, national identity, and belonging. Yet when asked by our facilitator <em>What is German?</em>, all we could come up with were stereotypes or nothing at all. I was in the latter camp, sitting quietly in the corner, scribbling down notes, the occasional eyebrow raise or eye roll gracing my face. An older man on the other side of the room began criticizing globalization and everything &#8220;becoming the same&#8221;, proclaiming that when it comes down to it, identity is tied to region. <em>I have fire in my belly,</em> my friend whispered to me, leaning over. <em>So do I</em>, I thought, but I wasn&#8217;t sure what to do with it. On some level our hybrid-identities felt under attack, as if our <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/26/lens-coming-home/">sense of home</a> tied to people, language, and experience was not as legitimate as one tied to geography. As if we weren&#8217;t quite part of the discussion in the same way as the others.</p>
<div id="attachment_1683" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/2013-11-08-15-31-39-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1683" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-1683" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/2013-11-08-15-31-39-1.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-11-08 15.31.39-1" width="640" height="640" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1683" class="wp-caption-text">Making friends at the workshop</p></div>
<p>I was surprised at myself. For years I&#8217;d been navigating a slew of cultures, confidently code-switching, getting by and blending in pretty much anywhere with relative ease and advantage. Dual citizen, trilingual, well-traveled, ethnically ambiguous, international education professional, American-German-Jewish-Algerian mutt. I&#8217;d always felt <em>just different enough</em>, rather than <em>too different</em>. I&#8217;m a pretty ruthless cherry-picker, highlighting a particular part of my background when it suits the moment. <em>My dad&#8217;s Jewish and I went on Birthright</em>, I declare to Israeli airport security. <em>My mom&#8217;s German and I&#8217;m a dual citizen,</em> I respond when asked why I live in Berlin. <em>I&#8217;m part Algerian</em>, I say proudly to a cute Arab-German on a date. <em>I also grew up with two languages and have trouble with German</em>, I share with the Vietnamese girls I tutor. I&#8217;d positioned my international identity as the centerpiece of my life a long time ago, letting it guide me both personally and professionally. Perhaps it&#8217;s self-serving or even greedy, but it&#8217;s always felt like my choice.</p>
<p>Others have their choice ripped from them with one ostensibly innocent question: &#8220;<strong>But where are you from from?&#8221; </strong><em><strong>Wo kommst du wirklich her? </strong></em>Translation: &#8220;You must come from somewhere other than here, because you look/sound/pray/move/eat/celebrate differently than <em>we</em> do.&#8221; The plight of the &#8220;<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DWynJkN5HbQ">perpetual foreigner</a>&#8220;.</p>
<p>During my past two years in Berlin I&#8217;d started to get a little taste of what that felt like, an after-taste really. <em>No, I&#8217;m not Spanish</em>, I find myself saying at least once a week to those who wonder out-loud or even just start speaking to me in Spanish. I get it, there are an increasing number of Spaniards in Berlin (and Germany). I get it, I have darker features. But whereas I would normally enjoy talking about my background, I now find myself getting irritated and defensive having to explain myself against a recurrent assumption.</p>
<p><em>&#8220;People always ask how my German is so good. I tell them I&#8217;ll try to speak worse German from now on,&#8221; a Vietnamese immigrant says ironically in his studio.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>&#8220;I know people expect me to be a certain way, or have ideas about what type of person I am, of what I&#8217;m capable of, based on how I look,&#8221; a young Eritrean girl ponders at the window.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>&#8220;I&#8217;m not really Turkish, and I&#8217;m not really German. I identify as a Turkish-German, which is something else,&#8221; reflects a woman from her apartment.<br />
</em></p>
<p>[paraphrased quotes from the &#8220;with WINGS and ROOTS&#8221; documentary]</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/withwingsandroots_reimaginebelonging_website_small.png"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1709" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/withwingsandroots_reimaginebelonging_website_small.png?w=640" alt="withWINGSandROOTS_reimagineBelonging_website_small" width="640" height="344" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/withwingsandroots_reimaginebelonging_website_small.png 720w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/withwingsandroots_reimaginebelonging_website_small-300x161.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/withwingsandroots_reimaginebelonging_website_small-650x349.png 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.withwingsandroots.com/">Source</a></p>
<p>While the woman with the sweaty hands was perhaps frustrated by the selection of adjectives on the list, I realized I was worked up about why there had to be a list at all. For the first time in two years in Berlin, I not only wondered, but cared, whether the others in the room considered me German. Or even German enough.</p>
<p><em>I grew up with German culture, speak the language, have the passport, and now live here</em>, I finally summoned up the courage and coherence to say. <em>But I&#8217;m only one fourth German &#8220;ethnically&#8221;. I know people back in the US who have more German blood than I but have no connection to the country, language, people, history. I don&#8217;t fit everything on that list, but neither do any of you.<br />
</em></p>
<p>Identity is a social construction, I wanted to go on. A fluid and on-going process on both the individual and national level. Increased levels of migration and diversity often spark an instinct to distinguish, retreat, and protect- on both the &#8220;native&#8221; and &#8220;(im)migrant&#8221; sides. But it&#8217;s also an opportunity to reflect, learn, and reinvent. By the end of the workshop, we were getting there.</p>
<p><em>What is your vision for a modern perception of &#8220;Germanness&#8221;?</em> the facilitator prompted us.</p>
<p>&#8220;Being open. Intercultural understanding from authorities. Focusing on plurality. Promoting language proficiency. Fostering awareness. Accepting (not only tolerating) others. Self-reflection.&#8221;</p>
<p>A list of adjectives can only put us into a box. A list of actions lets us move forward.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>How serendipitous: a fantastic article on the same topic just came out in Spiegel. Read <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/essay-on-racism-growing-up-turkish-in-germany-a-932154.html">here</a> about one woman&#8217;s reality of growing up as a third-generation Turkish-German in Hamburg and being asked about everything from circumcision, staying out late, and being a &#8220;different Turk&#8221;. </em></p>
<p><em>The documentary clip we watched is from &#8220;with WINGS and ROOTS&#8221; that juxtaposes the realities of (im)migrant life, national identity, and belonging in Berlin and New York City. You can watch the trailer <a href="http://www.withwingsandroots.com/video/trailer">here</a> and <strong>support the project <a href="http://www.withwingsandroots.com/get-involved/donate">here</a></strong><strong>.</strong> According to representatives from the film at the workshop there will be new ways of getting involved in January, so stay tuned! </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: the Istanbul Connection</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/29/beyond-berlin-the-istanbul-connection/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2013 18:14:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastarbeiter-guestworker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Istanbul]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1643</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Istanbul gives Berlin its baseline. In kind, Berlin is richly integrated into the complexity of Istanbul. For no relationship is ever purely one-sided. And so a Berlin : Istanbul connection, which moves beyond <i>Gastarbeiter</i> music and Fatih Akin films, is what one can find after six days immersed in the shapes and silhouettes of this city of 13 million...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Istanbul gives Berlin its baseline. In kind, Berlin is richly integrated into the complexity of Istanbul. For no relationship is ever purely one-sided. And so a Berlin : Istanbul connection, which moves beyond <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/oct/25/music-germany-migrant-workers-compilation"><em>Gastarbeiter </em>music</a> and <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0015359/">Fatih Akin films</a>, is what one can find after six days immersed in the shapes and silhouettes of this city of 13 million.</p>
<div id="attachment_1654" style="width: 630px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/photogram-20131024120809.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1654" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1654" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/photogram-20131024120809.jpg" alt="Photogram-20131024120809" width="620" height="620" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/photogram-20131024120809.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/photogram-20131024120809-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1654" class="wp-caption-text">Europe meets Asia</p></div>
<p>The <a href="http://www.dw.de/turkish-guest-workers-transformed-german-society/a-15489210">guest-worker program between Turkey and Germany</a> is often cited as the beginning of a long-standing socio-cultural and economic relationship, though such ties <a href="http://www.slowtravelberlin.com/a-short-history-of-turkish-berlin/">got their start long before</a> the post-war boom period of the 1960s. The &#8216;Turkish factor&#8217;, regardless of how it came to be, makes Berlin, and Germany for that matter, the place we know. Without it, students would miss their late night meaty snack in the likes of Döner, the skyline would miss many of its stunning minarets, and the census would be sorely missing the strength of difference (just to name a few).</p>
<p>But being Turkish, German-Turkish, or Turkish-German in Berlin are states of being <a title="Over and Over" href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">without a formula</a>. In other words, there is <a href="http://www.slowtravelberlin.com/a-short-history-of-turkish-berlin/">more to the Turkish factor than just culinary contributions</a> and street-side renditions of &#8220;<em>walla</em>&#8221; taking place on German soil. There is, in fact, also a &#8216;German factor&#8217; abroad.</p>
<p>Traveling to Istanbul opens up the possibility for a more two-sided conversation, where the German traveler can encounter home and the foreign at the same time, in a place familiar but distant in its urban position. And that is just what we (me and my German companion, Juri) did just a few weeks ago.</p>
<p><strong>Day 1 in Istanbul: Stammtisch</strong></p>
<p>Upon our arrival into Istanbul&#8217;s (proudly named) Ataturk airport, we were led like lost sheep into the belly of a beast, i.e. Turkey&#8217;s passport control. All around us the air buzzed in German, repeating the ritual of my everyday commute on the metro, this time with the confusion and frustration of a forced queue in a city far away from German-land. A mustached man holding a sign for <em>Studenten der Humboldt Universität</em> (students of Berlin&#8217;s Humboldt University) stood on the other side of the human barrier, shifting his weight methodically. Entering behind us would certainly be this year&#8217;s study trip from <a href="http://www.sowi.hu-berlin.de/studiengaenge/masowi/getma">Humboldt University&#8217;s Turkish German Master&#8217;s program</a> in the social sciences, which sends Berliners to Ankara and Istanbul every year.</p>
<p>As we wandered into one bookshop after another on our first evening, it seemed that not only visiting German students would be speaking the language of <em>Sauerbraten</em> and Goethe<i>.</i> Residents of Istanbul are learning <em>Almanca </em>(German), maybe now more than ever.</p>
<div style="width: 506px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_almanca.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class=" " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_almanca.jpg" alt="Istanbul_Almanca" width="496" height="496" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">advertisements for German language learning in a bookshop</p></div>
<p><strong>Day 2 in Istanbul: Book Swap</strong></p>
<p>Juri and I stumbled upon a German bookstore on an afternoon of gray and drizzle, just off the pedestrian-friendly thoroughfare of <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2013/06/14/world/europe/taksim-scenes.html?_r=0">Taksim</a>. Within seconds of walking through quaint double doors, we could hear &#8211; once again &#8211; the language of my daily commute. A young German woman chatted enthusiastically with her father, a yellow Reclam paperback of some German classic in her hand. Her father peered over his narrow reading glasses, raising his eyes just to hit the inventory at the back of the store &#8211; stacks of imported magazines and newspapers, including the kitschy tabloids older women with orange hair read at the bus stops in Berlin.</p>
<p>I wandered to the western edge of the dimly lit shop, discovering 20 ft. high shelves of children&#8217;s books in German. Perhaps kids in Istanbul will also grow up reading <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pippi_Longstocking"><em>Pippi Langstrumpf.</em></a></p>
<div id="attachment_1644" style="width: 506px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_books.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1644" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-1644" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_books.jpg" alt="Istanbul_books" width="496" height="496" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_books.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_books-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 496px) 100vw, 496px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1644" class="wp-caption-text">German children&#8217;s literature</p></div>
<p><strong>Day 3 in Istanbul: Sharing the Lunch Box</strong></p>
<p>The Germans take their bread seriously, carefully kneading in all kinds of goodies the average American baker might omit out of concern for dental integrity. The so-called Turkish bread one can purchase in Berlin, from <em>Dönerbrot</em> to <em>Milchbrot</em>, has no fit-for-a-squirrel seeds to offer. Enter <em>Vollkornbrot &#8211; </em>your triple whole grain bread &#8211; to be found in your average Istanbul super market. For all the yoga-bending heath nuts in Berlin: this bread is manufactured in Turkey, though ingredients on the package are also translated into German.</p>
<p>And the bread fun doesn&#8217;t stop here. Even the Döner in Istanbul is served in a bun much robuster than Berlin&#8217;s &#8216;Turkish&#8217; prototype.</p>
<div id="attachment_1648" style="width: 506px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_bread.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1648" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-1648" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_bread.jpg" alt="Istanbul_bread" width="496" height="496" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_bread.jpg 620w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_bread-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 496px) 100vw, 496px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1648" class="wp-caption-text">just your everyday super market</p></div>
<p><strong>Day 4 in Istanbul: The Döner Stories</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">The picture of this Döner? No, it wasn&#8217;t taken in Berlin. This dripping lance of assorted protein can be found on the lively streets of Istanbul, where Döner kiosks are visited with as much enthusiasm as in Berlin (so it appeared). There are slight differences in the composition of the sandwich, or shall we say differences in Döner before it became <em>Döner Kebap</em> in Berlin. As the rumor goes, <em>Döner Kebap</em> was invented by a <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/foodanddrink/4295701/The-man-who-invented-the-doner-kebab-has-died.html">Turkish-German named Mahmut</a>, who happened to serve the traditional vertical meat in a triangular cut of flat bread, instead of in more pita-like Istanbul fashion. The reason, as stated in this same rumor: more bread, so that drunken Berliners might stumble home with saucy meats intact.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Thirty some years later in Istanbul, meat on a spit can now be received with french fries and fried veggies in that bread package. Berliner style.</p>
<div style="width: 568px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_dc3b6ner.jpg"><img loading="lazy" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_dc3b6ner.jpg" alt="Istanbul_Döner" width="558" height="558" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">is it lamb? chicken? beef? everything? it&#8217;s Döner.</p></div>
<p><strong>Day 5 in Istanbul: Gimme Some Cake with that Coffee</strong></p>
<p>The German concept of <em>Kaffee und Kuchen</em> (coffee and cake), which inspires the strip of torte-laden cafes in my neighborhood, has made its way to Istanbul in a rich way. Istanbul has its fair share of home-grown sweets, the most delicious ones in fact, involving large amounts of crude honey and nut-laced syrups. Yet, cake with layers of unsweetened cream and a buttery crust, a small apple tart without cinnamon, or a cream-puff styled torte reminds me of my Sunday afternoons devouring Berlin&#8217;s <em>Kuchen</em> culture with friends. And this in the city of the best Baklava I have ever put in my mouth.</p>
<p>In Istanbul&#8217;s trendy harbor-side district, <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/travel/2013/mar/22/istanbul-karakoy-top-10-cafes-shops-galleries">Karaköy</a>, we doused ourselves in familiar sugars at a cafe called <a href="http://www.karabatak.com/">Karabatak</a>. A locale where locals in tweed jackets and horn-rimmed glasses slowly sip syrup-sweetened black coffee from delicate (read tiny) French presses. The influence of the Viennese coffee genius and founder Julius Meinl saturates the deco. Dressed up like a Freudian coffee salon, tiles lining the walls, jazzy serenades rolling into &#8216;intellectual&#8217; conversations, one could also be in Berlin&#8217;s Prenzlauer Berg. The extensive magazine selection: <em>Der Spiegel</em>, <em>Marie Claire Deutschland</em>, <em>Vogue Deutschland</em>, dispersed among the newest copy of T<em>he New Yorker</em> and Turkish design magazines. A cosmopolitan coffee date full of Berlin swag and Turkish youngsters.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_cafe.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_cafe.jpg?w=640" alt="Istanbul_cafe" width="512" height="682" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Day 6 in Istanbul:</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Repeat cosmopolitan coffee date with Berlin swag and Turkish youngsters. For hours and with many forks.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Day 7 in Istanbul: What I Know</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">We boarded our plane in the dark and found ourselves again in German-land, surrounded by the lucid colors of night and the strangely familiar. The smells that had once been part of a Berlin immigrant cityscape were, after the return, now an experience tied to a place, constitutive of a tangible and pungent cross-continental connection. Two worlds connect. In fact, they were never separated.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">We had only heard one side of the conversation.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">&#8211; <em>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em><a href="http://www.dw.de/turkish-guest-workers-transformed-german-society/a-15489210">Approximately 3 million residents or citizens of Germany have Turkish background</a>, meaning either they or their parents were born in Turkey, according to the German system of demographic classification. The Turkish population in Germany intensified with the guest-worker agreement between Turkey and Germany, which allowed for the reunification of families four years following the initial agreement, thereby turning the &#8216;guest-worker&#8217; into an immigrant with, in many cases, children. Today, <a href="http://www.dw.de/turkeys-economic-boom-lures-german-workers/a-16873373">more and more Germans (with or without background) are considering a move to Turkey</a>, learning about Turkey, or learning Turkish, reflecting the true nature of a two-sided relationship. </em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">All photos were taken by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
