<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>borders &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/borders/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Migration Matters: A Free Video Lecture Series</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/02/29/migration-matters-a-free-video-lecture-series/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[collidoscopeks]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 14:16:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4377</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When we talk about migration on this website, among our friends and colleagues, and particularly across the vast expanse of the internet, we are confronted with many misconceptions about who the immigrants and refugees of the world really are, what brings them to our countries and communities, and whether or not the statements made by politicians on immigration are true, let alone helpful. We write about the movement and coming together of people, because we believe commentary and discussion to be a powerful antidote to this perpetuation of misinformation. But are words, indeed our own voices, ever enough? A New Project: Migration Matters In collaboration with two inspiring women in the field of migration reporting and migration studies, we are embarking on a new chapter of Collidoscope&#8217;s mission in launching a free online course, which will deliver concise, accurate information about migration in just five minutes a day. This course will focus on promoting understanding of the issues: how and why migration happens, how it is being addressed around the world, and how we can become more informed actors in the process. We let &#8220;the experts&#8221; speak: accomplished, peer-reviewed researchers and educators, practitioners in the field, and migrants themselves. In [...]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When we talk about migration on this website, among our friends and colleagues, and particularly across the vast expanse of the internet, we are confronted with many misconceptions about who the immigrants and refugees of the world really are, what brings them to our countries and communities, and whether or not the statements made by politicians on immigration are true, let alone helpful.</p>
<p>We write about the movement and coming together of people, because we believe commentary and discussion to be a powerful antidote to this perpetuation of misinformation. But are words, indeed our own voices, ever enough?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-4371 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/TrailerThumbnail.jpg" width="650" height="366" /></p>
<p><strong>A New Project: <a href="https://www.generosity.com/community-fundraising/migration-matters-a-free-video-lecture-series/x/13390941">Migration Matters</a></strong></p>
<p>In collaboration with two inspiring women in the field of migration reporting and migration studies, we are embarking on a new chapter of Collidoscope&#8217;s mission in launching <a href="https://www.generosity.com/community-fundraising/migration-matters-a-free-video-lecture-series/x/13390941">a free online course</a>, which will deliver concise, accurate information about migration in just five minutes a day.</p>
<p>This course will focus on promoting understanding of the issues: how and why migration happens, how it is being addressed around the world, and how we can become more informed actors in the process. We let &#8220;the experts&#8221; speak: accomplished, peer-reviewed researchers and educators, practitioners in the field, and migrants themselves.</p>
<p>In line with what we have worked to create with the Collidoscope project, this course will foster a space for open conversation, where no concern is ridiculed and no question dismissed.</p>
<p>To learn more, visit the Migration Matters page and <a href="http://www.migrationmatters.me/">pre-enroll for this great course</a>! You can also follow Migration Matters on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/migrmatters">@MigrMatters</a> and on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/MigrationMatters/?fref=ts">Facebook</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Funding</strong></p>
<p>We can&#8217;t do it without your help &#8211; our loyal supporters, readers, friends, colleagues, and friends.</p>
<p>Please help us realize our goal of beginning an open, evidence-based conversation about the issues that matter most to us, to immigrants, to refugees, by <a href="https://www.generosity.com/community-fundraising/migration-matters-a-free-video-lecture-series/x/13390941">contributing to our crowd-funding campaign</a>. You can also help by spreading the word about this project in your community. The greater our reach, the more effective its message.</p>
<p>If you have any questions about Migration Matters or would like to be involved, please contact the team at migrmatters@gmail.com. Currently we are looking for individuals with experience in visual design, interactive online experiences, and data visualizations.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em><strong>Kelly and Sophia</strong></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: Four Hours at Lageso</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2015 00:01:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bureaucracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moabit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4145</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is Lageso (Das Landesamt für Gesundheit und Soziales), the State Office for Health and Social Affairs. This is Berlin's primary registration center for the initial reception of asylum seekers. This is Germany's most infamous symbol of the refugee crisis. Two days prior I had signed up to volunteer on a website called Volunteer Planner. After a cursory registration process, a click of a button was all it took to commit to a shift at a registration center, refugee home, or other institution in the city where help is needed (read: basically everywhere).  ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4323 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-650x319.png" alt="boys_lageso" width="650" height="319" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-650x319.png 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-300x147.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>A curly-haired two year old hangs from my hip. His modest number of pounds start to wear on my side as I spin us back and forth in the narrow space. By some stroke of luck he has yet to start crying (this doesn&#8217;t last). He giggles, bouncing up and down, as if we are playing a game. &#8220;He seems to like you,&#8221; a volunteer next to me looks on and smiles, &#8220;almost like he wants to go home with you.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;He may have to,&#8221; I mutter in response. It has been a long ten minutes since I last saw his mother. I try desperately to remember her face &#8211; or at least the color of her headscarf. My voice starts to crack and I realize in horror a cold is coming on (&#8220;Am I infecting hundreds of refugees?&#8221;). A few minutes later we find her, a pair of black shoes in her hands. She holds them up proudly and points to herself. We are only supposed to be finding clothes for her son and she knows it, but I let her take the shoes and boy (now crying), and go.</p>
<p>Curly-haired boy and his mother are my latest charges from the never-ending mass of parents and children waiting to be accompanied down the hallway of donated clothing. This group is only a microcosm of the larger crowd waiting outside in the evening twilight where volunteers pass out hot tea and coffee. Kids get <em>Kinderschokolade </em>and granola bars. The building entrance is guarded to ensure not everyone infiltrates the chaos at once.</p>
<p>Back inside, a winter jacket and pair of warm shoes are the big prizes. Our chief responsibility is to make sure each child walks out with just one of each. I negotiate with parents: &#8220;She can have that coat, but you&#8217;ll need to give me the one she&#8217;s wearing now.&#8221; When language fails, I make a trading gesture with my hands or remove the jacket from the child&#8217;s back myself. How quickly the urge to be generous is superseded by pragmatism (&#8220;Even <em>I</em> could get by with only one coat&#8221;).</p>
<p>&#8220;You have to be careful,&#8221; a middle-aged female volunteer warns me as I re-fold a stack of jeans, &#8220;Roma families sneak in to take clothing and then sell it at the flea market.&#8221; I nod but am at a loss as to what to do with the information. Is she advocating that we start using racial profiling? Regardless of the Roma, some families may have already taken their turn down the hallway. Others could be successfully registered and in possession of their <a href="http://www.euronews.com/2015/09/16/which-european-countries-offer-the-most-social-benefits-to-migrants/">monthly stipend</a>. There&#8217;s really no way to tell.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4321 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_0599" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Our makeshift shopping strip consists of one narrow hallway and a back room for sorting and storage. On either side of the hallway are smaller rooms the size of coat checks, one holding clothing for adults and the other medicine and hygienic articles. It is very cramped. Fathers plea with volunteers for their family&#8217;s turn down the hallway. Once in, mothers rip clothing off hangers to hold up to their children and approximate size. Some kids are fussy about colors; others peer up with wide eyes and tightly pressed lips. Volunteers buzz by in a flurry of aspired productivity and surveillance, their name-tags as frayed as their nerves.</p>
<p>A cameraman waltzes in with his crew. The bright lens focuses on me as I kneel down to re-velcro a young boy&#8217;s shoes. We have yet to find boots that fit; these blue sandals are the ones in which he arrived to Germany, completely ill-suited for the looming winter. We both turn, squint, and smile anyway. This is the shot they want, and they are gone within the minute.</p>
<p>This is Lageso (<em>Das Landesamt </em><span class="st"><em>für Gesundheit und Soziales)</em>, the State Office for Health and Social Affairs</span>. This is <span class="st">Berlin&#8217;s primary registration center for the initial reception of asylum seekers. This is Germany&#8217;s most infamous symbol of the refugee crisis.</span></p>
<p>Two days prior I had signed up to volunteer on a website called <a href="https://volunteer-planner.org/">Volunteer Planner</a>. After a cursory registration process, a click of a button was all it took to commit to a shift at a registration center, refugee home, or other institution in the city where help is needed (read: basically everywhere).  An impressive resource to get people engaged quickly, though seemingly lacking any accountability for volunteers who fail to show up or for organizations advertising shifts that fall through or no longer exist (the day before I was turned away from a home in Schöneberg because the coordinator was not present).</p>
<p>In addition to locations, one can select specific tasks. This is an all-hands-on-deck scenario and there is something for everyone, from Arabic and Farsi interpretation (in high demand) to kitchen assistance and coffee distribution. At Lageso, I sign up to be a <em>Springer/in </em>or &#8220;Jumper&#8221;, who, according to the website, &#8220;helps wherever is most needed, is assigned to a team, and will be led by hand to their task.&#8221;</p>
<p>But upon arrival I am not assigned to a team nor led anywhere, let alone by hand. After finding a sticker on which to scribble my name, I walk around aimlessly until a smiley blond girl takes pity on me and leads me to the storage room. A few minutes later I am with a new girl who is in a room within this room, sorting through boxes of clothing donations in the dark. I glance at the heaps of dusty sweaters and immediately regret not having brought my allergy medicine.</p>
<p>We start unpacking boxes of blankets. &#8220;Is there somewhere specific we should put these?&#8221; I ask my sorting partner. She shrugs. &#8220;On those shelves, I think,&#8221; she says, pointing to the overstuffed racks behind us. Ten minutes later, another volunteer: &#8220;No, don&#8217;t unpack the blankets,&#8221; he instructs us in a mix of German and English. &#8220;Put them in a corner so we can take them to a refugee home later.&#8221;</p>
<p>I give up on the blankets and turn my attention to the clothes. Thankfully, some boxes are categorized, and I pick up one marked &#8220;children&#8221;. I plan to sort the contents and add them to the shelves, which are loosely organized by gender and size. In one pair of pants I notice a bulge in the pocket and pull out a knife. I pass it along to a guy with a clipboard who looks like he knows what he is doing. He turns and sets it on another shelf, near a box of children&#8217;s toys.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4322 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_0600" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>I&#8217;m finally getting into a groove when another volunteer comes up behind me, visibly frustrated. &#8220;I spent days putting this together and now everyone&#8217;s destroying it,&#8221; she complains to clipboard guy, motioning to the overflowing shelves. He glances up over his glasses. &#8220;We&#8217;ll discuss it at Monday&#8217;s meeting,&#8221; he promises. I don&#8217;t know what I&#8217;ve done wrong, but I am sure of two things: We are all working on top of one another and there is no one in charge.</p>
<p>When the refugee crisis became front page news this past summer, thousands of Germany&#8217;s residents jumped to provide clothing and supplies, offer short-term housing solutions, or pass out sandwiches to refugees as they poured into train stations around the country. Many continue to help, some using vacation days to do so. On a civilian level, the outpouring of support in Germany has been heart-warming, encouraging, even pride-inducing.</p>
<p>Charitable and non-profit initiatives also abound. Groups have launched fundraising efforts to help those in particularly dire situations, like this <a href="https://www.betterplace.org/de/projects/37503-hilfe-fur-familie-ahmed">Iraqi father who suffered a heart attack</a>. There are <a href="http://www.unhcr.org/5655d27f6.html">bike riding lessons</a> for women and <a href="http://www.abendblatt-berlin.de/2015/12/03/ein-zirkus-fuer-die-gute-sache/">circus activities</a> for kids. A local photographer has started a &#8220;<a href="https://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.400616063468410.1073741835.295071407356210&amp;type=3">Humans of Lageso&#8221; page</a> to shed light on individual refugee stories. Herbert Grönemeyer, a famous German singer, has <a href="http://www.stern.de/lifestyle/leute/lageso-in-berlin---herbert-groenemeyer-finanziert-waermebusse-fuer-fluechtlinge-6605406.html">financed heated buses</a> so those waiting to register at Lageso can take turns warming up.</p>
<p><span class="st">But civilian good-will and a display of <span class="st"><em>Willkommenskultur</em></span> (welcome culture) can only go so far in serving the approximately 800,000 asylum seekers that Germany will receive this year &#8211; a figure that is <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/sep/06/refugee-crisis-germany-response-heartwarming-will-pressures-show">more a projection than a guest list</a>. What some in Berlin may call growing pains in learning to accommodate unprecedented waves of refugees, others deem a failure of the system and local leadership. German towns such as Passau, a Bavarian town of 50,000, have cited <a href="http://nmd.bn02750.bethemd.wayport.net/index.adp?MacAddr=68%3aA8%3a6D%3a4B%3a7A%3a8C&amp;IpAddr=10.128.29.239&amp;Ip6Addr=&amp;vsgpId=&amp;vsgId=41975&amp;UserAgent=&amp;ProxyHost=&amp;TunnelIfId=95270&amp;VlanId=20">much more success in handling the inflow</a>.</span></p>
<p><span class="st">The press have reported on the turbulent conditions at Lageso ad nauseam, both locally and <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/11/27/world/europe/germany-berlin-migrants-refugees.html?_r=0">internationally</a>. Refugees wait for weeks if not months to be registered. They line up for hours each day, often beginning the night before. People sleep in the streets. Most don&#8217;t receive enough to eat and drink. Heated tents were only made available <a href="http://www.stilinberlin.de/2015/12/fugeela-refugees-in-berlin-6-html.html">a few days ago</a>. &#8220;Refugee crisis? More like bureaucratic crisis!&#8221; protesters chanted <a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/1678473329031122/">on November 29th</a>, calling the local government to action. Understaffed and overworked employees have anonymously <a href="http://www.rbb-online.de/politik/thema/fluechtlinge/berlin/2015/12/lageso-innenansichten-mitarbeiter.html">detailed the on-going chaos</a> to the press. On December 10th, the Head of Lageso, Franz Allert, was <a href="http://www.focus.de/politik/deutschland/migration-lageso-chef-tritt-zurueck_id_5143744.html">pushed into resignation</a>. </span></p>
<p>Curly-haired boy and his mom are back outside, but at least now with warmer feet and some chocolate in their bellies. I pull my phone out of my pocket: three and a half hours have passed. There isn&#8217;t an eight hour work day in recent memory I can remember having been more exhausting. Admiration for the other volunteers &#8211; many of whom do this regularly, including night shifts &#8211; rushes within me. As does panic. The support is incredible, but is it sustainable?</p>
<p>We need to get this right, and not just in the short-term.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By<strong> Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>For up to date information in English on the refugee situation in Berlin, we recommend reading the <a href="http://www.stilinberlin.de/?s=FuGeeLa">FuGeeLa updates</a> by Stil in Berlin. <a href="http://www.findingberlin.com/how-to-help-refugees-in-berlin-winter-2015/">Finding Berlin</a> also provides comprehensive resources for how to help. </em></p>
<p><em>To sign up for volunteer shifts in Berlin, try <a href="https://volunteer-planner.org/helpdesk/">Volunteer Planner</a> (in German) or look for opportunities through <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">Give Something Back to Berlin</a> (in English). <a href="http://moabit-hilft.com/">MoabitHilft</a> is very engaged at Lageso and many of the regular volunteers at the center are affiliated with this organization.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>If you are donating clothing to refugee homes, please do your best to package them by type (e.g. age and size) and consider buying socks which are often in short supply. Even better: check first with the home to see what is most needed!</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Refugees Welcome: Local Interventions for an EU Dilemma</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/04/30/refugees-welcome-local-interventions-for-an-eu-dilemma/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/04/30/refugees-welcome-local-interventions-for-an-eu-dilemma/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 13:04:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[European Union]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3965</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This article is intended to inform, as well as to encourage advocacy and action. As any seasoned volunteer or activist knows, engagement relies heavily on context, identifying not only how to get involved but why and in which capacity, based on the complex landscape of need one encounters.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Saturday, the 18th of April, a small fishing vessel capsized off the coast of Libya on its way to one of the European Union’s coastal states. On its way, it passed through waters patrolled by the European Union&#8217;s security agency, Frontex. Its demise was quick, only 28 passengers were rescued; an estimated 900 are said to have perished. Of the dead, roughly 200 had had little chance of escape, locked securely in the ship&#8217;s hull by the smugglers commissioned with their passage. A similar event had made headlines just the Sunday before: 400 dead in the water. Yet even more sobering is the UN&#8217;s projected number of migrant deaths by the end of 2015: <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/italy/11548995/Mediterranean-migrant-crisis-hits-Italy-as-EU-ministers-meet-live.html">approximately 30,000</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_3993" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3993" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3993 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-650x488.jpg" alt="Essen_ProAsyl" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3993" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Pro Asyl</p></div>
<p>Although this tally of the dead got its start long ago, both the number and its surrounding political situation seem to be escalating at an alarming rate. It is possible that this escalation is, in part, due to the quick reporting the digital-age affords a global readership. But, given the current death toll and its greater context of inter-regional instability, one thing seems fairly certain: If safer pathways for migration to the European Union continue to remain restricted or inaccessible to many, the intersecting lines of risk and desperation will continue to make safety subordinate to a chance at what is (presented as) a better life.</p>
<p>Yet the most immediate and real consequence of these reports of danger leading to disaster may not be deterrence but desensitization: The drowned and discarded may begin to shock a little less with each headline, and, worse yet, public support for the displaced &#8211; in our communities, off our shores, and even in those far-off lands to which our governments sell arms in exchange for cheap manufactured goods (an oversimplification of the global balance of trade, of course, but the point remains a valid one) &#8211; may wane.</p>
<p>But this doesn&#8217;t have to be the case. This article is intended to inform, as well as to encourage advocacy and action. As any seasoned volunteer or activist knows, engagement relies heavily on context, identifying not only how to get involved but why and in which capacity, based on the complex landscape of need one encounters. And so, I will first offer a summary of information I find important in creating this context, beginning with an understanding of Germany&#8217;s position in the asylum system of the European Union and followed by an unpacking of certain terms and categories. The latter is not meant to distinguish between and thus arrange various grades of human value based on one&#8217;s reasons for migration; rather, examining these categories is an attempt to identify and elucidate the different contours and sites of vulnerability to be found in refugee and immigrant advocacy, with navigating such categories being crucial to successful support. The most important bit follows these term-laden sections &#8211; namely, a list of ways to get involved in Berlin housing facilities and neighborhood support centers for asylum-applicants. Some options for digital activism and direct actions around Germany will also be included for our readers further afield.</p>
<p>In the end, my hope is to transform this article into a helpful resource page for the <em>Collidoscope</em> webpage. Thus feedback on ways to improve its information and add to or amend its list of opportunities for involvement is greatly appreciated!</p>
<p><strong>Asylum in the EU and refugee status in Germany: an overview</strong></p>
<p>It is helpful to continue with numbers as a means of illustrating the magnitude of the situation (despite my preference for qualitative vs. purely quantitative data &#8211; for which this blog tends to be a perfect example). In 2014, Germany housed approximately 173,000 applicants for asylum, an increase of 192% from the previous year. By the end of 2015, upwards of 300,000 applicants for asylum are projected to enter and remain temporarily in the country [source: <a href="http://www.bamf.de/DE/Infothek/Statistiken/Asylzahlen/asylzahlen-node.html">BAMF</a>]. Despite its shock-value, this remains a small number in the grand scheme of immigration flows. Relative to the asylum policies of the other G-20 countries, however, this is a significant number. The United States, for example, processed 121,000 asylum claims in 2014, a country with four times the population of Germany [source: <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/europe/new-migration-crisis-overwhelms-european-refugee-system/2015/04/21/3ab83470-e45c-11e4-ae0f-f8c46aa8c3a4_story.html">Washington Post</a>].</p>
<p>This does not mean that all claims and their applicants are granted residency in Germany. In fact, most are rejected, resulting in deportation either once a decision has been reached or in a temporary stay of inevitable deportation. Only 24% were granted refugee status in 2014, which excludes a guarantee of permanent status, i.e. returning &#8220;status-refugees&#8221; to their countries of origin once conflicts can be said to be resolved. Last year, only 1.8% received the coveted gift of permanent asylum [source: <a href="http://www.bamf.de/SharedDocs/Anlagen/DE/Publikationen/Broschueren/broschuere-bundesamt-in-zahlen-2014-asyl.pdf?__blob=publicationFile">BAMF</a>].</p>
<p>Nevertheless, 2014&#8217;s final tally of approximately 34,000 accepted refugees indicates a lag in the participation of other EU member states, such as the Netherlands, Poland, or Ireland, not to mention the strange and ineffective logic behind the so-called Dublin III convention*. As the commissioner for the German federal agency for migration and refugees, Aydan Özoguz, commented just last week: “The European asylum system doesn’t work. Some countries are doing very little. We are one of the richest countries and we want to help, but it’s not okay that Germany, Sweden and France are taking 50 percent of the refugees, while other countries do nothing” [source: <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/europe/new-migration-crisis-overwhelms-european-refugee-system/2015/04/21/3ab83470-e45c-11e4-ae0f-f8c46aa8c3a4_story.html">Washington Post</a>].</p>
<p>EU leaders met just last week in an emergency summit to discuss changes to this increasingly dysfunctional system. Given Germany&#8217;s position as home to the greatest number of asylum-applicants, decisions made here set both the moral and practical tone for the other states in the European Union&#8217;s common asylum system &#8211; an infrastructure guided less by comprehensive agreements and more by a few select rules. At the summit&#8217;s conclusion, leaders agreed to invest more money in rescue efforts: more boats and life-vests for the Mediterranean. But what of more legal, safe pathways into the European Union?</p>
<p>Over the last few days, arguments have been made for a reform to the immigration policies that prevent potential workers from entering the country by legal means, unrelated to the conditions for asylum but also free from the ardor of submitting a claim and waiting years for a decision. <a href="http://www.iwkoeln.de/presse/interviews/beitrag/michael-huether-in-der-welt-iw-fordert-mehr-fluechtlinge-fuer-deutschen-arbeitsmarkt-223062">According to the Institut für deutsche Wirtschaft</a> (IW), one in five asylum-applicants has a college degree and one in three are skilled in some trade or another. With German industry&#8217;s sustained calls for increased immigration (to compensate for an aging or less technically-skilled population), providing a more accelerated pathway to a safe life in Germany for those migrants who qualify, while meeting the utilitarian imperative of the political establishment, seems like a win-win. Traditional asylum and provisions for refugees would not be eliminated, by any means, but the number of migrants from poor or conflict-ridden countries would be allowed to increase, saving many the eventual rejection most asylum-applicants face once they arrive in Europe, if they are lucky enough to survive the journey (see the <a href="http://heindehaas.blogspot.de/2015/04/let-their-people-drown-how-eu.html">recent appeal from social scientist Hein de Haas</a> for more on this argument).</p>
<p>However, as is often the case in coordinated responses to humanitarian need, calculations of domestic burden vs. benefit will dominate. And an end to these calculations is nowhere in sight. That is to say, if we wait for political change, we may be waiting at a high opportunity cost &#8211; that of everyday advocacy for and support of the displaced. But first, categories&#8230;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Refugee&#8221; or &#8220;asylum-seeker&#8221;?</strong></p>
<p>The distinction between those with refugee status and those who have submitted an application for asylum (referred to as &#8220;asylum-applicant&#8221; thus far) is an important one, as it helps to explain the origins and role of the <em>Flüchtlingsheim</em> (state-sponsored but privately-run housing facility for asylum-applicants) in the everyday landscape of German towns and cities, including Berlin. Of course, the implementation of national asylum law can vary state by state, given Germany&#8217;s federal balance of power; Saxony, Bavaria, and Berlin may differ in the scope and quantity of services provided to asylum-applicants residing in each state&#8217;s respected <em>Flüchtlingsheime,</em> for example,<em> </em>as this <a href="http://www.proasyl.de/de/news/detail/news/pro_asyl_studie_zur_unterbringung_von_fluechtlingen_in_deutschland/">study</a> demonstrates. But, in all cases, the foundation of German asylum law is built on a differentation between those whose claims have been adjudicated (decided by a judge in German administrative court) and those who have filed claims but are awaiting a decision, assigning different rights and restrictions to these different groups, accordingly. The most important rights and restrictions are those affecting the freedom of movement and activity for those migrants to fall in the &#8220;asylum-applicant&#8221; category. They are as follows:</p>
<p>&#8211; Asylum-applicants are generally not allowed to work until they receive formal status: either as a &#8220;refugee&#8221; (a temporary status, in most cases), as an &#8220;asylee&#8221; (long-term or permanent status), or as a &#8220;tolerated person&#8221; (<em>Geduldete</em>). There are, of course, some exceptions to this rule; for example, asylum-applicants in Berlin and Brandenburg are allowed to pursue employment one year after their application has been submitted, though this work allowance remains heavily restricted and qualified. This means that, in general, asylum-applicants are not able to provide for themselves, thereby becoming fully dependent on the services financed by the federal government, the respective state, and third-parties responsible for service provision. The housing facility system of the <em>Flüchtlingsheim</em> was established both to meet the need for accommodation and to enforce this ban on employment.</p>
<p>&#8211; Up until January of this year, all asylum-applicants were to remain in the state and district either in which they had applied for asylum or to which they had been assigned. They were not able to determine this geographical location or the particular facility in which they would live, even in the case of friends or relatives already in the country. These rules for residency and domicile make up the German system of <em>Residenzpflicht.</em> According to the organization Pro Asyl, <a href="http://www.proasyl.de/de/themen/basics/basiswissen/rechte-der-fluechtlinge/bewegungsfreiheit/residenzpflicht/">these restrictions have been partially lifted</a>. It is unclear, however, to what extent the residency requirement will be relaxed. And as with any policy reform, there will certainly be a lag in public officials and bureaucrats implementing changes. In other words, asylum-applicants may still be prohibited (by staff and local enforcement personnel) from leaving their assigned district, and limits to mobility may still be decided on a state-by-state and case-by-case basis.</p>
<p>&#8211; Residents of <em>Flüchtlingsheime</em> are frequently re-distributed to prevent over-crowding and to maintain an equitable distribution of the financial burden, relative to each state&#8217;s population and economic situation. The freedom of movement, which the abolition of <em>Residenzpflicht </em>may have provided, is overruled and/or overshadowed by this re-distribution mandate.</p>
<p>&#8211; Once asylum-applicants have received a decision from the judge &#8211; the time between the initial filing of the application, the hearing, and the eventual decision often proving to be a year-long ordeal -, those without status granted are either returned to their country of origin (often within a few months of the decision) or are given a <i>Duldung</i>, becoming a &#8220;tolerated person&#8221; for as long as the state deems their return difficult (e.g. in the case of illness, psychological distress, age, family relations, financial situation in the country of origin). <em>Geduldete</em> are free to seek employment and live among the general population, securing their own housing, albeit within the town/city of their asylum-application. But, in most cases, they are not entitled to the same social services as those with refugee status and can be deported at any time, particularly in the case of a minor infraction.</p>
<p>These terms serve to complicate the issue of refugees and the work of refugee advocacy, as various levels of status and treatment before the law are at play. In my opinion, when the media and public discourse fail to make these distinctions, the complexity of the issue and its effect on the experience of real human beings is side-lined to a language that prefers the simplicity of pure humanitarianism &#8211; a moral outlook recognized neither by German law-makers nor by the structures of the European Union. In simple terms, those crossing the Mediterranean and those living in close quarters in Berlin&#8217;s many <em>Flüchtlingsheime </em>are not all &#8220;refugees&#8221;. If they were, they would receive the humane treatment popular opinion affords them.</p>
<div id="attachment_3994" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3994" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3994 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind-650x650.jpg" alt="Deichkind" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3994" class="wp-caption-text">German pop group Deichkind; Source: <a href="https://instagram.com/p/0tB_FivQxn/">Instagram</a></p></div>
<p>Yet, when we acknowledge that it is precisely because of the precarity of their status that they need our help, the situation looks much different. And local interventions in the experience of this precarity become most important, beyond #refugeeswelcome.</p>
<p><strong>How to help</strong></p>
<p>A few weeks ago I visited a new housing facility for asylum-applicants in Reinickendorf, one of the northernmost districts of Berlin. In an idyllic setting, surrounded by pine and quiet residential streets, a former High School has been converted into a 300 bed hostel for migrants awaiting status. The space is rudimentary but well-organized, staff making do with donated toys and German courses, among other diverse activities, as a means to entertain the many children &#8211; many of whom have been waiting for more than two months to enroll in the local school. The staff &#8211; about 10 in number &#8211; communicate with residents in what seems to be a mix of German, English, French, and enthusiastic signage. There is an artist working on the aesthetic revitalization of the place &#8211; literally making the dark halls of a High School a place that feels like home for its residents. There are social workers and psychologists who visit on occasion. Basic meals are catered three times a day on a set schedule. &#8220;House Rules&#8221; are posted in various languages in the foyer. And security guards patrol the grounds, which are clearly the remains of a once vibrant schoolyard, complete with a basketball court (nets partially intact) and a covered concrete playground for jumping rope and hopscotch. We chat about setting up in-house cooking activities, to bring residents and staff closer together, and about using the open space to start a garden, giving the families an opportunity to build and realize a strenuous but rewarding project, even harvest its fruits. The plans are piece-meal and heavily reliant on donations and organizational finesse. In many ways, it is simply about showing up (a familiar mantra), trying to be of help, and deferring to the staff who are there throughout the week trying to make the facility a better place for all who live there.</p>
<p>There are more than 40 facilities just like this one across Berlin, housing upwards of 11,000 asylum-applicants. <a href="http://www.morgenpost.de/berlin/article139453814/Senat-baut-36-neue-Fluechtlingsheime-in-Berlin.html">36 more facilities just like them are planned</a> for the end of 2015. The need is great, but so is this city. Here is a list of established groups across Berlin who work directly with <em>Flüchtlingsheime </em>like the one mentioned above; all of these organizations are certainly eager for new volunteers:</p>
<p>Flüchtlingsinitiative Klausener Platz [evagoemuesay(at)gmail.com]</p>
<p><a href="https://hellersdorfhilft.wordpress.com/">Hellersdorf hilft e.V.</a></p>
<p>Initiative Grenzen weg Hellersdorf [grenzenweg(at)gmx.de]</p>
<p><a href="http://www.wir-netzwerk.de/">Willkommen in Reinickendorf</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.willkommensbuendnis-steglitz-zehlendorf.de/">Willkommensbündnis für Flüchtlinge Steglitz-Zehlendorf</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.lichtenbergerbuendnis.de/">Lichtenberger Bündnis für Demokratie und Toleranz</a></p>
<p><a href="https://bunterwind.wordpress.com/">Bunter Wind für Lichtenberg</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.willkommen-im-westend.de/">Willkommen im Westend &#8211; Refugees Welcome</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.zentrum-für-demokratie.de/">Netzwerk für Flüchtlinge in Treptow-Köpenick</a></p>
<p><a href="http://multitude_tk@riseup.net">Multitude Gruppe Köpenick</a> (for German speakers only &#8211; German language instruction)</p>
<p><a href="https://arbeitsgruppefluchtundmenschenrechte.wordpress.com/">Arbeitsgruppe Flucht und Menschenrechte Treptow-Köpenick</a></p>
<p><a href="http://uffmucken-schoeneweide.de/">Initiative &#8220;Uffmucken Schöneweide&#8221;</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.buendnis-neukoelln.de/">Bündnis Neukölln</a></p>
<p><a href="http://fluechtlingshilfe@britzerinitiative.de">Aktionsbündnis Flüchtlingshilfe Britz</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.multitude-berlin.de/">Initiative Multitude e.V.</a> (for German speakers only &#8211; German language instruction in Spandau, Westend, Lichtenberg, Marzahn, Prenzlauer Berg)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.pankow-hilft.de/">Willkommensnetzwerk &#8220;Pankow Hilft!&#8221;</a> (Pankow, Prenzlauer Berg, Weissensee, Buch)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Fl%C3%BCchtlinge-willkommen-in-Buch-und-Karow/1481160482158156">Flüchtlinge willkommen in Buch und Karow</a></p>
<p><a href="http://u_strassburger@posteo.de">Unterstützer_innenkreis Flüchtlingsunterkunft Prenzlauer Berg</a></p>
<p>Initiative &#8220;Wedding Hilft&#8221; [wedding.hilft(at)gmail.com]</p>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/moabithilft">Initiative &#8220;Moabit Hilft&#8221;</a></p>
<p><a href="http://neuenachbarschaft.wordpress.com/">Initiative &#8220;Neue Nachbarschaft Moabit&#8221;</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.willkommensbuendnis-steglitz-zehlendorf.de/">Willkommensbündnis für Flüchtlinge in Steglitz-Zehlendorf</a></p>
<p><a href="http://bglbb.blogsport.de/">Bündnis gegen Lager Berlin-Brandenburg</a></p>
<p><a href="http://asylstrikeberlin.wordpress.com/">Oranienplatz</a></p>
<p>For those without immediate time to spare but keen on staying informed on actions and opportunities as they develop, track the activities of  the <a href="http://www.fluechtlingsrat-berlin.de/">Flüchtlingsrat-Berlin</a> (the local office of the nation-wide &#8220;refugee council&#8221; model) and <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">GiveSomethingBacktoBerlin</a> (a community platform for volunteer engagement, including frequent posts from groups seeking participants in visits to and on-going projects within <em>Flüchtlingsheime</em>).</p>
<p>Of course, this type of on-site involvement is not for everyone. The type of validation that often comes with structured community engagement projects is not likely to be found here. And, although I am a fan of &#8220;showing up&#8221; and getting one&#8217;s hands dirty, applying pressure on policy-makers and raising awareness to the need for asylum and immigration reform remain incredibly important contributions. Here are a few resources on direct actions and politics-oriented digital activism; these options are great for those further afield who would like to participate in some way, even if just with a click:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/367018126842745,%20http://www.amnesty.de/2015/4/20/massensterben-im-mittelmeer-stoppen-seenotrettung-jetzt">Amnesty International Germany&#8217;s campaign against </a><em><a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/367018126842745,%20http://www.amnesty.de/2015/4/20/massensterben-im-mittelmeer-stoppen-seenotrettung-jetzt">Massensterben im Mittelmeer</a> (</em>flash-mobs and rallies around the offices of Parliament and Executive Government)</p>
<p><a href="http://action.amnesty.de/l/ger/p/dia/action3/common/public/?action_KEY=9703&amp;d=1">#SOSEurope Amnesty International petition</a> (calling upon Merkel&#8217;s government to reform immigration and asylum policy)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.proasyl.de/de/home/seenotrettung-jetzt/">ProAsyl petition</a> (for more EU member-state support of rescue efforts in the Mediterranean)</p>
<p>Donate to the organization <a href="http://www.proasyl.de/de/">Pro Asyl:</a> perhaps the best way to assist the many asylum-applicants residing in Germany and other EU member states by way of a great and highly-effective organization. Pro Asyl coordinates volunteer activities, contributes to accurate reporting and research on asylum in the EU, and offers legal counsel to asylum-applicants, among many other great services.</p>
<p><strong>Why local interventions matter</strong></p>
<p>A <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/media/2015-05-16_EFA-Forschungsbericht_Endfassung.pdf">study</a> was just released by the new <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/">Berlin Institute for Empirical Migration and Integration Research</a>* (BIM) on Berlin-based volunteer engagement  in support of asylum-applicants and resettled refugees. It points to severe deficits in state services for which the unpaid contributions of volunteers strive to remedy. In particular, without the engagement of what the study deems predominately secular, middle-class females, many asylum-applicants would have great difficulty communicating with those agencies charged with the processing and, ultimately, the acceptance or rejection of their claim to refugee status. Additionally, despite the <em>Trägerschaft </em>structure, in which third-party organizations assume partial financial responsibility and full operational responsibility for these housing facilities, many goods and services would otherwise be sorely lacking without the donation-drives and supply deliveries of volunteers. The study describes the especially integral role of volunteers in assisting in the navigation of Germany&#8217;s complex bureaucratic structures: something necessary for immigrants of any sort to successfully remain in the country.</p>
<div id="attachment_3995" style="width: 498px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3995" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3995" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider-488x650.jpg" alt="Source: Pro Asyl" width="488" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider.jpg 488w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider-225x300.jpg 225w" sizes="(max-width: 488px) 100vw, 488px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3995" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Pro Asyl</p></div>
<p>And even the simple opportunity for social interaction, which comes with visits from the outside, can have a great effect on an asylum-applicant&#8217;s success, encouraging language and intercultural skills through everyday relationships that will serve them well in the future. From building the capacity to make one&#8217;s case successfully to a judge to preparing for integration into the local job-market once status, whether temporary or permanent, has been granted, seeing to the wellness of a <em>Flüchtlingsheim&#8217;s </em>residents is a powerful intervention in an often bleak process. In the end, it is the state that decides who may be called a &#8220;refugee&#8221; and who might have a chance at a better life, but volunteers may prove to be one of the deciding factors in who will be welcomed.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>As already mentioned, please submit your comments or write us an email with suggestions or changes, so that this can become a helpful and accurate resource for months to come. And please share with your various networks. The more informed our communities, the better activists we can be!</em></p>
<p>*Technically, certain conventions of the European Union (such as the oft-cited Dublin III agreement) requires that migrants seeking asylum, i.e. refugee status, apply for and receive asylum for the first EU country on which they are said to have set foot. In practice, however, Dublin III is inconsistently enforced, thus allowing asylum-applicants to submit a claim in an economically prosperous country like Germany.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/04/30/refugees-welcome-local-interventions-for-an-eu-dilemma/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: On Leaving Home(s)</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/03/23/lens-on-leaving-homes/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 15:32:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[family]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vienna]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3869</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Last month, Kelly wrote about the implications of "collecting ourselves" to make a move back home. While wrought with complications in its own right, returning to where one grew up, has family, or holds full political and legal rights is a move that Makes Sense. One chapter closes, and however painful or messy, the next begins...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3881 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-650x487.jpg" alt="2014-11-16 13.46.44" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Last month, Kelly wrote about the implications of &#8220;<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/02/13/lens-leaving-berlin/">collecting ourselves</a>&#8221; to make a move back home. While wrought with complications in its own right, returning to where one grew up, has family, or holds full political and legal rights is a move that Makes Sense. One chapter closes, and however painful or messy, the next begins.</p>
<p>After graduate school, I started losing the ability to picture my life in chapters. My decisions were no longer dictated by a series of steps culminating in clear milestones. I suddenly felt accosted by the need to figure out what I wanted to Do and Be&#8230; this time for the long run. And, given my international experiences and dual citizenship, the question of &#8220;What&#8221; promptly extended to one of &#8220;Where&#8221;.</p>
<p>So I moved to Berlin.</p>
<p>When I booked my flight to Germany in fall 2011, &#8220;two years&#8221; was my default timeline. &#8220;A couple years,&#8221; I responded confidently when someone asked how long I planned to be gone. &#8220;I should give the job a good two years,&#8221; I thought when I got hired six months in. &#8220;We&#8217;ll all still be here at least two more years,&#8221; I reassured myself about my circle of expat* friends another six months after that.</p>
<p>How foolish I was, to believe that two years would ever be enough. How <span class="st">naïve</span>,<em> </em>to assume there would be a clear demarcation between this chapter and the next.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3885 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-650x487.jpg" alt="2015-01-31 14.28.03-1" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Now almost three and a half years in, I feel firmly entrenched in my world of bilingual conversations, narrow streets, weekend jaunts around the continent, ubiquitous public transport, social welfare nets, and crusty bread. But these roots of mine are flighty. They wiggle at something as simple as a chat with a friend back home, when she catches me up on her life and I realize how much I&#8217;ve missed. When my sister or father leaves for the airport after a visit, they are pulled halfway out of the earth and end up lodged in the middle of my throat. Every time I get on a plane and head back across the ocean, a part of me fears they will be ripped out entirely. Because no matter how long I stay in Europe and embrace the rights my German passport affords me, I will always also be American. No matter how incredible a life I build for myself on this side of the Atlantic, there will always be a Life Back Home.</p>
<p>I was not aware of how much I had internalized this feeling until last summer, when my mother and I visited relatives in northwestern Germany. Sipping coffee on a sunny terrace, a family friend commented, &#8220;I could never do what you&#8217;re doing, be so far away from my family&#8230; I&#8217;m too close to them.&#8221; My reaction to her declaration was nothing short of primal. Of course I missed my family! Of course I felt close to them! I was not away <em>because</em> of, but rather, <em>in spite of</em> them &#8211; an unpleasant reality I struggle with on a near daily basis.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3892 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-650x518.jpg" alt="11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n" width="650" height="518" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-650x518.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-300x239.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Modern advances in travel and technology have enabled more and more people to adopt lifestyles fueled by wanderlust and adventure. But not all of us who leave home are <a href="http://elitedaily.com/life/culture/wanderlust-like-travel-much-no-real-home/959705/">perpetual wanderers with nomadic spirits</a>. Some of us are searching for somewhere to settle. Some of us are even surprised to find ourselves making a life away from where we grew up, away from the ones we love. I know I am.</p>
<p>I consider myself, by nature, to be a sensitive homebody. I crave being close to the people I love and place great importance on maintaining my relationships, both near and far. This explains why any time I am &#8220;away&#8221;, my pack mentality kicks in and I seek out a local community almost immediately. But I concurrently possess the intrinsic need to push myself and explore. For me, this has meant travel. Whether I credit <a href="https://psychologyblogaimee.wordpress.com/2013/12/04/wanderlust-a-genetic-basis-to-a-globetrotting-fanatic/">genetics</a> for this (nope) or my international upbringing, mixed with a little courage and a lot of privilege (that&#8217;s more like it), is not the point. The ups and downs of living somewhere other than where I grew up have become an integral part of my identity and understanding of growth and independence. They just don&#8217;t make the leaving part any easier.</p>
<p>The thing is, leaving is rarely the easy choice, even with the prospect of Something Great on the other side.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3887 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-650x487.jpg" alt="2015-02-21 16.37.36-1" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>While I never expected moving to Berlin to be easy, I did anticipate a gradual ease, and more importantly, clarity, with time. Reality proved instead to be emphatically non-linear. Rough patches hit me sporadically and without warning. My homesickness became a swelling wave, pulling in and out of shore, threatening at its peak to wash me out entirely. What if this chapter never ended? What if I never left my new home and went back to my old one? And now that I live in Vienna, my current home because of work, is my &#8220;old home&#8221; Washington, DC or Berlin? In countless discussions with fellow expat friends on the topics of home and belonging, the resounding theme has been similar: one of overwhelming choice and uncertainty.</p>
<p>A couple months ago, Kelly and I were at a close friend&#8217;s 30th birthday dinner in Berlin. Huddled in the kitchen over bottles of Spanish Temperanillo and mismatched plates of pizza and crudit<span class="st">és</span>, someone proposed we guess where the birthday boy would be 30 years from now. We had plenty of ideas for the &#8220;What&#8221;: running his own cooking school, teaching his kids how to do science experiments, maintaining his impressive beard. It was on the &#8220;Where&#8221; that we got stuck. &#8220;Italy?&#8221; we posed as the obvious choice (where he&#8217;s from). He resolutely shook his head &#8220;no&#8221;. &#8220;Germany?&#8221; He shrugged his shoulders, unsure &#8211; just like the majority of us in the room about our own futures.</p>
<p>Once you&#8217;ve opened yourself up to the world and seen first-hand that you can live, and maybe even thrive, somewhere else, it becomes increasingly difficult to know when or where to stop searching. The list of potential Something Greats becomes never-ending. And with it, the accompanying list of goodbyes.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By</em> <strong><em>Sophia Burton</em></strong></p>
<p>*My choice of the term &#8220;expat&#8221; was deliberate, as it popularly denotes migrants with privilege and mobility. For more on &#8220;expat&#8221; vs. &#8220;immigrant&#8221;, check out <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/global-development-professionals-network/2015/mar/13/white-people-expats-immigrants-migration?CMP=fb_gu">this Guardian article</a>.</p>
<p><em>All photos taken by me, in Vienna and Berlin.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: Scotland and the question of borders</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/10/28/beyond-berlin-question-borders/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/10/28/beyond-berlin-question-borders/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2014 10:30:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Scotland]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3442</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Coming off an evening with Invisible Borders that was all about transcending boundaries, it was an eye-opening juxtaposition to visit a country that had just explored creating more stagnant borders of their own. This was to be my first trip to Scotland, but as I had visited England and Ireland in the past I wasn&#8217;t expecting much in the way of culture shock. I had heard something about an exotic concoction called Haggis, anticipated equal amounts difficulty and delight navigating the Scottish accent, and was prepared for plaid. Oh, and rain. Lots and lots of rain. So during my short stint in Edinburgh and the Highlands, I was especially interested to delve into what it was the Scots themselves believed distinguished them from the rest of the UK enough to merit separating themselves off with tighter borders. Did it really have anything to do with national identity, the sentiment conjured up by media images of teenagers covered in blue and white paint? Or was it really more for economic reasons, tied to access to finite resources like North Sea Oil? Scotland&#8217;s recent independence referendum, arising from a sweeping win by the Scottish National Party in the 2011 Parliament elections, was [...]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Coming off an evening with <a href="http://invisible-borders.com/">Invisible Borders</a> that was all about transcending boundaries, it was an eye-opening juxtaposition to visit a country that had just explored creating more stagnant borders of their own.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-11.58.20-11.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3507 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-11.58.20-11-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-06 11.58.20-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-11.58.20-11.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-11.58.20-11-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>This was to be my first trip to Scotland, but as I had visited England and Ireland in the past I wasn&#8217;t expecting much in the way of culture shock. I had heard something about an exotic concoction called <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haggis">Haggis</a>, anticipated equal amounts difficulty and delight navigating the Scottish accent, and was prepared for plaid. Oh, and rain. Lots and lots of rain. So during my short stint in Edinburgh and the Highlands, I was especially interested to delve into what it was the Scots themselves believed distinguished them from the rest of the UK enough to merit separating themselves off with tighter borders. Did it really have anything to do with national identity, the sentiment conjured up by media images of teenagers covered in blue and white paint? Or was it really more for economic reasons, tied to access to finite resources like North Sea Oil?</p>
<p>Scotland&#8217;s recent independence referendum, arising from a sweeping win by the Scottish National Party in the 2011 Parliament elections, was historic but not exceptional. Separatist movements exist all over the world, including the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/">people of Kurdistan</a> who make up a region of four Middle Eastern countries, Spain&#8217;s economic powerhouse, Catalonia, and Germany&#8217;s conservative southern state, Bavaria. Some may even surprise you &#8211; for example, Venice, where an <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2014/03/europes-latest-secession-movement-venice/284562/">unofficial referendum</a> in May of this year showed the vast majority in favor of secession from Italy. Supporters of more active movements around the globe watched closely as the Scots went to the polls this past September 18th, eager to follow suit or fuel their respective campaigns. The results held weight. After 55.3% of Scotland voted &#8220;no&#8221;, Catalonia cancelled their planned referendum, originally set for November 9th of this year.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.40.09-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3451 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.40.09-1-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-05 15.40.09-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.40.09-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.40.09-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>There are over 20 active separatist movements around the world, the majority in Europe and Asia. Of these, about a third are violent*, due primarily to ethnic and religious tensions. While some fight for human rights or religious freedom, others strive for economic power, control over resources, or wealth potential. The Scotland independence debate was rife with discussions about tax distribution, North Sea Oil, currency, and jobs. &#8220;Scotland is a very wealthy country &#8211; let&#8217;s make it feel like it!&#8221; proclaimed the homepage of the official &#8220;Yes Scotland&#8221; campaign. Meanwhile, Turkey&#8217;s Kurds have been engaged in armed struggle against the Turkish government since 1984, resulting in thousands of deaths. It is therefore an impossible and reductionist task to speak of secessionist movements as a homogenous entity. Yet regardless of the nature of the struggle &#8211; political, economic, social, ethnic, violent, peaceful, or a combination of the above &#8211; when one discusses borders, one is inherently embarking on a discussion about community, belonging, and identity.</p>
<p>As links between countries become stronger through migration, technology, economic trade, and political unions, the idea of separating oneself from the &#8220;global community&#8221; can appear unmodern, backward, even futile. &#8220;I voted no,&#8221; my Airbnb host, a documentary filmmaker originally from England, revealed as we strolled to the supermarket together my first night in rainy Edinburgh, &#8220;not because I&#8217;m against independence for the Scots, but because I believe in a borderless world.&#8221;</p>
<p>At the same time, retreating into a stronger sense of place and identity, as our world becomes more globalized, can feel almost like an instinctive reaction. An exercise in protection, preservation, even control. &#8220;It may have worked in the past, but the way the centralized government in London makes decisions for us now does not reflect who we are anymore,&#8221; my Highlands tour guide explained as we stood at the foot of Stirling Castle, &#8220;I just can&#8217;t be proud of a country that isn&#8217;t its own.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>Which begs the question: how can we embrace the inevitable (and often beneficial) changes that crossing and opening borders may bring, while simultaneously protecting what makes our home(s) &#8220;our own&#8221;?</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.42.39-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3452 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.42.39-1-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-05 15.42.39-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.42.39-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.42.39-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>For starters, the concept of a world with more open borders is conceivably less radical than many perceive it to be. &#8220;Open&#8221; does not mean &#8220;none&#8221;, nor does it mean a lawless world where people come and go as they please without screens or supervision. Within the field of migration, the concept of &#8220;open borders&#8221; generally refers to a reversal from what is, by default, an exclusionary policy, e.g. countries finding a reason to <em>let someone in. </em>Instead, the policy would switch to one of de facto inclusion, e.g. countries finding a reason to <em>keep someone out</em>. Reasons for excluding potential immigrants would lie more with criminal records and health concerns than they would with economic prospects or integration potential. Open borders is also not commensurate with the idea of open citizenship: in a world with open borders, countries could still deem individual qualifications and requirements for acquiring full citizenship rights.</p>
<p>The idea of open borders has gained traction in recent years (think &#8220;No Human is Illegal&#8221;) with the rise in global migration. Many see current immigration restrictions as inconsistent with basic egalitarian principles, such as equal opportunity, human rights, and moral obligations. On the more pragmatic end of the spectrum, there are those who advocate for open borders as a catalyst for economic growth and innovation, responding to phenomena such as lower birth rates and skilled worker shortages in more developed countries.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-13.22.05.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3450 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-13.22.05-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-05 13.22.05" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-13.22.05.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-13.22.05-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>But do questions about opening borders and globalization shifts weaken the importance of nationalism and identity? For many, despite the fact that we all interact with the global community in one form or another, place still matters most. A staggering 70% of those polled who voted &#8220;yes&#8221; to an independent Scotland claimed they did so because of &#8220;<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2014/sep/20/scottish-independence-lord-ashcroft-poll">the principle that all decisions about Scotland should be taken in Scotland</a>.&#8221;</p>
<p>This thinking was reflected in the voting demographics of the Scottish independence vote &#8211; eligible voters were only those currently residing in Scotland and Commonwealth or EU citizens. So while my Airbnb host was included despite being born in England, her Scottish friends living abroad were not (there are approximately <a href="http://worldpopulationreview.com/countries/scotland-population/">2 million Scots</a> living in other parts of the UK), nor were thousands of immigrant residents without the right passport.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-14.42.18-2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3478 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-14.42.18-2-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-06 14.42.18-2" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-14.42.18-2.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-14.42.18-2-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Although the official &#8220;yes&#8221; campaign in Scotland was largely pro-migration (<a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/scottish-independence/11035389/Scottish-immigration-has-to-increase-by-14000-to-meet-Salmond-target.html">mainly for economic reasons</a>) and may have adopted a more open policy than the rest of the UK, the independence vote brought up many questions about the future of migration and refugee policy, as well as citizenship laws. Who would be considered a citizen from &#8220;day one&#8221; of independence? What would the process be like for the foreign-born who wished to become citizens? What would dual citizenship policy look like for Scots living abroad? Would those living on the border, working on one side and living on the other, still have freedom of movement? What legal hurdles would immigrant families have to endure to visit family members spread out across the region?</p>
<p>As we lay out in <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/about/a-manifesto/">our manifesto</a>, borders hold meanings both conceptual and literal. They demarcate ideas of home and kinship as much as they do political, legal, and bureaucratic spaces. They bring people together around shared systems, laws, traditions, languages, and goals, but they also divide, separate, and limit. They influence and make statements about our engagement with local and global communities. They determine how seamlessly we can navigate having more than one home, a reality for an increasing number of us around the globe. But on the most basic level, for many, they simply represent what is possible and what isn&#8217;t.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>*Figures as of 2008. For a comprehensive account of the history of separatist movements and self-determination around the world, click <a href="http://online.sfsu.edu/swilcox/Swilcox/Shelleys_webpage_files/Wilcox,%20The%20Open%20Borders%20Debate%20on%20Immigration.pdf">here</a>.</p>
<p>For a shorter round-up on active secession movements, click <a href="http://www.dnaindia.com/world/report-7-separatist-movements-that-are-closely-watching-scotland-s-independence-referendum-2019372">here</a>.</p>
<p>All photos by yours truly from her recent trip to Edinburgh.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/10/28/beyond-berlin-question-borders/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Collidoscope Manifesto</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/22/the-collidoscope-manifesto/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/22/the-collidoscope-manifesto/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[collidoscopeks]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 09:45:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cities]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2395</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A couple months ago, Collidoscope Berlin was invited to write its first guest post for the Global Citizens Initiative - an organization that aims “to build a network of people who see themselves as global citizens and want to build a better world”. Part of the task was to connect what we do here to the significance of borders. “Borders?”, we wondered, unsure how to proceed but mostly questioning why we had never concretely addressed the topic before...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_6374.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2441 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_6374.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_6374" width="640" height="426" /></a></strong></p>
<p><strong>A couple months ago, Collidoscope Berlin was invited to write its first guest post for the <a href="http://us5.campaign-archive2.com/?u=34e2670d2b1df6a04603724fa&amp;id=3a6a8f6948&amp;e=b0926c0e88">Global Citizens Initiative</a> </strong>&#8211; an organization that aims &#8220;to build a network of people who see themselves as global citizens and want to build a better world&#8221;. Part of the task was to connect what we do here to the significance of borders. &#8220;Borders?&#8221;, we wondered, unsure how to proceed but mostly questioning why we had never concretely addressed the topic before. What kind of immigration project doesn&#8217;t discuss borders?</p>
<p>When we launched this project in April of last year, we knew we wanted to do something <em>different </em>related to the topic of<em> difference. </em>We knew of groups that promoted and celebrated cultural and ethnic diversity. We had worked for institutions that research and analyze immigrant integration. Our goal was to do something in between, producing articles and commentary that both told a story and provided facts and context. And we wanted to do this through the lens of one city that, although formed by a unique historical and political context, could perhaps provide lessons for others.</p>
<p><strong>A few days ago, Collidoscope Berlin turned one-year old </strong>&#8211; and as we took the opportunity to reflect back, we realized that not talking about borders was, in fact, making a statement about borders. It wasn&#8217;t that we thought borders were unimportant or that we were advocating their complete erosion. Rather, we were advocating for the idea that every city <span style="letter-spacing: 0;">is home to its very own “collision” of cultures and thus has <em>unique</em> stories about diversity and difference. Through the lens of migration &#8211; the movement and coming together of people &#8211; we believe that we can understand more about what makes &#8216;us&#8217; who we are on the individual, local, and global scales. Through our personal lens of moving and living across borders, we aim to make sense of what defines and shapes the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/26/lens-coming-home/">places we call home</a>, as well as the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/16/lens-going-away/">places we leave</a>. Cities, as a reflection of &#8216;the we&#8217;, are a good place to start.</span></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/cropped-2012-08-22-19-03-431.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-18" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/cropped-2012-08-22-19-03-431.jpg?w=640" alt="cropped-2012-08-22-19-03-431.jpg" width="640" height="221" /></a></p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>The Collidoscope Manifesto </strong></span></p>
<p><em>Originally published as a guest post for the <a href="http://us5.campaign-archive2.com/?u=34e2670d2b1df6a04603724fa&amp;id=3a6a8f6948&amp;e=b0926c0e88">Global Citizens Initiative</a><strong><br />
</strong></em></p>
<p>Individuals are born within borders. On a map, these borders seem relatively arbitrary: meandering lines awkwardly encircling blurbs of land. And yet in our lives, the purpose they are meant to serve is anything but, as borders demarcate political, legal, and bureaucratic spaces, as much as they do geographic ones. For it is not geography &#8211; the land itself &#8211; that keeps us from coming and going. It is our (hu)man-made political systems and governments that determine who is permitted to enter or leave, to immigrate or emigrate, to belong or not to belong.</p>
<p>Despite the presence of these borders, we all make our way across these lines one way or another. Whether through relationships abroad, use of technology, involvement in international groups, or participation in the global economy: our lives are increasingly global and less tied to the borders in which we were born or reside. While this does not automatically make us all global citizens (which necessitates awareness and action), it fosters connections across borders that reinforce the idea of a world community. How can we reconcile this ever-present reality with our understanding of borders and restrictions on an individual’s freedom of movement?</p>
<p>The majority of us – more than ever before &#8211; lives in cities. Thanks largely to migration, modern cities have become microcosms of the global community, home to spectacular cultural, ethnic, and religious diversity. While this “collision” of cultures can pose challenges, it is also a tremendous opportunity for growth and enrichment. If we begin to view our cities’ pockets and spaces of difference as opportunities – becoming more empathetic, inclusive, and participatory in the process – we can begin to realize global values within local communities.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_0388.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2577 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719-650x433.jpg" alt="Collidoscope Berlin Manifesto" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Berlin, Germany is one example: a city with a long history of attracting those who are “different”, where 1 in every 4 residents is of foreign origin and 138 countries are represented. A city that is undergoing constant transformation, while undertaking the challenge of integrating not only newcomers, but the 2nd and 3rd generations. A city that is brimming with rich diversity and teeming with opportunities. <span style="letter-spacing: 0;">Collidoscope Berlin is a celebration of these stories and opportunities, a conversation-starter, a democratic and inclusive view of the many peoples, spaces, and settings that constitute the modern city. </span></p>
<p><strong>Lessons from Berlin: </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/">Ramadan with Neighbors</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/12/20/happy-weekend-review-an-old-new-christmas-market/">The Thai Park</a>,<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/12/20/happy-weekend-review-an-old-new-christmas-market/"> An Old-New Christmas Market</a></p>
<p><strong>Lessons from Beyond: </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/29/beyond-berlin-the-istanbul-connection/">The Istanbul Connection</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/">The American Northwest</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/03/beyond-berlin-difference-on-the-blessed-isle/">Difference in Sri Lanka </a></p>
<p><strong>What is Multiculturalism? </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/">Diversity &amp; the Big City</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/10/whose-multikulti-is-it-the-elusive-definition-of-multiculturalism/">Whose Multikulti is it?</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/18/happy-weekend-karneval-der-kulturen-carnival-of-cultures/">Carnival of Cultures</a></p>
<p><strong>Our Stories: </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/16/lens-going-away/">Going Away</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/26/lens-coming-home/">Coming Home</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/29/lens-linsanity-and-linguine/">Linsanity and Linguine</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/25/lens-lamb-on-fridays/">Lamb on Fridays</a></p>
<p><strong>Local Stories:</strong> <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/09/interview-ali-zoe-and-the-gentrification-debate/">Ali &amp; Zoe</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/">Orhan</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/21/lens-warm-nights-are-for-cricket/">Warm Nights are for Cricket</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">Moran &amp; Tommy</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/30/interview-hamid-stardom-and-the-difference-threshold/">Hamid</a></p>
<p><strong>We&#8217;d like to conclude this anniversary post by thanking everyone who has been part of the discussion this past year</strong> &#8211; reading, commenting, critiquing, supporting, following, contributing photos and story ideas and event announcements &#8211; we appreciate it all and look forward to another year of <span class="userContent">diversity, difference, and positive discourse!</span></p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By</em> <em><strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em> <em>and</em> <em><strong>Kelly Miller</strong> </em></p>
<p>First photo by Anna Meister, second photo by Collidoscope Berlin, third photo by <a href="http://jurigottschau.com/">Juri Gottschau</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/22/the-collidoscope-manifesto/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
