<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>home &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/home/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Interview: &#8220;I&#8217;m a Human Being&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 11:21:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Austria]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[family]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Taiwan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vienna]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4019</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Vienna. Seat of the former Austro-Hungarian Empire. Widely considered the gateway to Eastern Europe. Home to a United Nations headquarters and numerous international companies and universities. The Austrian capital has long been a city of immigration – even when politics have told a different story – and a staggering 50% of the population has what’s referred to as a “migration background”. So it’s not as if I expected Vienna to not be multicultural...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_4028" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4028" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4028 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-650x581.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender" width="650" height="581" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-650x581.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-300x268.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender.jpg 728w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4028" class="wp-caption-text">Sophia, Christina, and Suzi at the 2015 Vienna Pride Parade</p></div>
<p>Vienna. Seat of the former Austro-Hungarian Empire. Widely considered the gateway to Eastern Europe. Home to a United Nations headquarters and numerous international companies and universities. The Austrian capital has long been a city of immigration – even when politics have told a different story – and a staggering <a href="https://www.wien.gv.at/english/social/integration/basic-work/facts-figures.html">50% of the population</a> has what’s referred to as a “migration background”.</p>
<p>So it’s not as if I expected Vienna to <em>not</em> be multicultural.</p>
<p>What I didn’t expect when <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/03/23/lens-on-leaving-homes/">moving to Vienna from Berlin</a> was to encounter some of the most fascinating “mixes” of my life: A half-Indian, half-Italian who grew up in the US and lives in Vienna with her half-Austrian, half-French boyfriend? A Chinese-American who fell in love with her German boyfriend in Hong Kong? A half-Austrian, half-Sicilian who met her Indian husband in London? The combinations are unexpected, beautiful, and dare I say, collidoscopic? (And their potential future children even more so).</p>
<div id="attachment_4031" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4031" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4031 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-650x475.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(3)" width="650" height="475" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-650x475.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-300x219.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4031" class="wp-caption-text">Christina poses with a cow in Austria on a family roadtrip</p></div>
<p>Christina, the first close friend I made in Vienna, is no different. Born in Taiwan to a Taiwanese mother and Austrian father, at age three her family moved to San Jose, California, where her younger brother was born. Kindergarten was spent in Vienna, where she lived with her father and grandparents while mom and brother stayed in the US. At age six the entire family moved to Taiwan for four years. Then it was back west to Seattle from ages 10-16 where Christina spent the longest stretch of her childhood, what she calls her &#8220;most formative years&#8221;. Her last two years of high school were completed in Taipei, where she graduated with the globally recognized International Baccalaureate Diploma.</p>
<p>“I was missing roots as a kid, our family was always bouncing around,&#8221; she tells me.</p>
<p>This triangular ping ponging between nations resulted in three different passport combinations within a family of four: Christina’s brother, born in the US, is a dual Austrian-American citizen but “avoids Austria now because of the mandatory military service.” Mom is dual Taiwanese-Austrian, “but never felt completely comfortable in Austria”. And Christina and her father are purely Austrian, on paper anyway.</p>
<p>&#8220;A long time ago my dad had the chance to become an American citizen but decided against it,&#8221; she says smirking, &#8220;He&#8217;s a proud Austrian.”</p>
<div id="attachment_4057" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4057" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4057 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_9365" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4057" class="wp-caption-text">Christina with her parents in Taiwan</p></div>
<p>It is to her father and his “pride” that Christina attributes her last 16 years in Vienna. &#8220;My dream was to go to Georgetown [University],&#8221; Christina tells me one warm evening in the <em>Museumsquartier</em>, her fingers tapping the stem of her <em>Hugospritz</em>. &#8220;I applied and got in… my mom supported it, but my dad kept saying I had to go to university in Austria. It was always really important to him that, as the oldest child, I embrace my Austrian roots.&#8221;</p>
<p>Christina ended up moving to Vienna against her will: “I didn&#8217;t have any connection to Austria at that time other than having spent the occasional summer there with my grandparents.” The first year, she expressed her anger by skipping class in favor of exploring the city and having fun.</p>
<p>“And then I got pregnant,” she says laughing, “the biggest rebellion of all!”</p>
<div id="attachment_4059" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4059" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4059 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371-650x650.jpg" alt="IMG_9371" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4059" class="wp-caption-text">Mother-daughter surfing trip in Morocco</p></div>
<p>Christina’s daughter Illeana (Illy) was born when she was 20. She raised Illy as a single mother while completing her degrees in Economics and Sinology, with “lots of help” from friends with similar bi-cultural backgrounds. She counts half-Austrian friends from South Africa and Bolivia among her closest, along with a half-Kosovan, half-Czech hair salon owner named Suzi. “None of us knew what we were doing… it was experimental parenting. I think if I raised a child now I’d be much more nervous!”</p>
<p>After making it over the hump of her first year, Vienna started to feel like home. “I began to realize how much I love it here,” Christina reflects. Now one could say Christina is as Austrian as they come. Her German is flawless and chock full of colloquialisms, she sings along to Austrian <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schlager_music">Schlager</a></em>, and her drink of choice is the ubiquitous <em><a href="http://austrianwineusa.com/2013/12/20/12-days-of-austrian-wine-enjoy-a-gspritzer/">Weisser Spritzer</a></em>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4064" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4064" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4064 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-650x602.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(7)" width="650" height="602" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-650x602.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-300x278.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7.jpg 701w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4064" class="wp-caption-text">Christina skiing in Kaprun, Austria</p></div>
<p>None of that, however, stops her from craving Taiwanese ‘Three-Cups Chicken’ or her favorite American cereal, ‘Lucky Charms’. “I’m biracial and tri-cultural,” she states without hesitation. And while rewarding on personal and professional levels (she’s also fluent in Mandarin), Christina’s background has not gone unchallenged in a city that still struggles to see itself as a place of migration and diversity.</p>
<p>Christina has encountered countless variations of the “<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/">But where are you <em>really</em> from?</a>” question over the years. “When I first got to Vienna, there were fewer minorities and diversity didn&#8217;t work very well,” she remarks, “I remember meeting one guy who could not comprehend why I looked the way I did but had a very common German last name,&#8221; she rolls her eyes at the memory. &#8220;I literally had to spell it out for him by saying, &#8216;If you, an Austrian, had a baby with a Taiwanese woman, the result would be me!’”</p>
<div id="attachment_4034" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4034" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4034 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-650x488.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(6)" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4034" class="wp-caption-text">Christina&#8217;s 3rd Birthday in Los Angeles, California</p></div>
<p>This phenomenon isn’t limited to Vienna. In Japan, a newly crowned biracial beauty queen has been fielding questions on a regular basis about what parts of her are “Japanese”. <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/30/world/asia/biracial-beauty-queen-strives-for-change-in-mono-ethnic-japan.html">“But I am a Japanese,”</a> is her response. On the other side of the world, in the US, Rachel Dolezal was recently exposed for her elaborate deception as a Black woman – a &#8220;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/18/opinion/charles-blow-the-delusions-of-dolezal.html?smid=fb-share">one-directional privilege</a>&#8221; that could never have been successful the other way around, due to socially constructed perceptions of race. The recurring theme? If you are one drop of minority, we will question your Belonging to the majority.</p>
<p>Christina acknowledges that even she is not immune to societal attitudes about migrants in Austria. &#8220;I&#8217;ve learned that, in Austria, migrants get classified into &#8216;good&#8217; and &#8216;bad&#8217;,&#8221; she explains.</p>
<p>&#8220;Asians are considered ‘good’ because they’re quiet, stay out of trouble, and work hard. Turkish people are unpopular because a lot of them refuse to adapt to the Austrian way of life and bring hordes of family members over, all the while claiming benefits from the Austrian government. Blacks have it the worst, though, probably because they stand out the most and are still viewed by many locals as low-lifes and drug dealers.&#8221;</p>
<div id="attachment_4029" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4029" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4029 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-650x472.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(1)" width="650" height="472" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-650x472.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-300x218.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4029" class="wp-caption-text">Christina riding a (fake) bull at Glacier National Park, Montana</p></div>
<p>While Christina is well aware that the US has its own challenges regarding diversity, she does view it as more progressive: “In the US, people at least get it when you tell them that you&#8217;re biracial.”</p>
<p>It was 1999 when Christina was last in the US, before Illy&#8217;s birth and before the 9/11 attacks. While she’s now seriously considering a move back, it&#8217;s unclear when she will be able to. Christina is not a US citizen and needs a green card. Her most recent attempt at the <a href="http://travel.state.gov/content/visas/english/immigrate/diversity-visa/instructions.html">Diversity Visa Lottery</a> was unsuccessful. “My dad told me he is reconsidering becoming an American citizen just so that he can help get us over there,” Christina recently shared. <a href="http://www.migrationpolicy.org/article/family-reunification">Family reunification</a> is one of the four major pathways for foreigners to become legal residents of the US.</p>
<p>Legal challenges are also not Christina’s only concern. “Sometimes I worry that people in the US will annoy me with their ignorance,” she says laughing. At the same time, she is drawn to the lifestyle. She observes her American friends move to houses with pools, which, compared to Viennese city apartments, seem like mansions. Illy, a recovering Justin Bieber addict who recently graduated to a One Direction obsession, is thrilled with the prospect. “A typical Austrian teenager,” Christina chuckles.</p>
<p>You could call Christina many things: A transnational, an immigrant, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">a third-culture kid</a>, a foreigner, a native, an expat. But none of these categories really fit given the fluidity of her upbringing and identity. We use labels to establish connections and try to make sense of things, but they can also dilute the intricacy and beauty of reality.</p>
<p>&#8220;I&#8217;m not 100% of anything,&#8221; is how Christina describes it. &#8220;Sometimes when people ask what I am, I just answer that I&#8217;m a human being.&#8221;</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Photos provided by Christina and Sophia.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: On Leaving Home(s)</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/03/23/lens-on-leaving-homes/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 15:32:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[family]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vienna]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3869</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Last month, Kelly wrote about the implications of "collecting ourselves" to make a move back home. While wrought with complications in its own right, returning to where one grew up, has family, or holds full political and legal rights is a move that Makes Sense. One chapter closes, and however painful or messy, the next begins...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3881 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-650x487.jpg" alt="2014-11-16 13.46.44" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Last month, Kelly wrote about the implications of &#8220;<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/02/13/lens-leaving-berlin/">collecting ourselves</a>&#8221; to make a move back home. While wrought with complications in its own right, returning to where one grew up, has family, or holds full political and legal rights is a move that Makes Sense. One chapter closes, and however painful or messy, the next begins.</p>
<p>After graduate school, I started losing the ability to picture my life in chapters. My decisions were no longer dictated by a series of steps culminating in clear milestones. I suddenly felt accosted by the need to figure out what I wanted to Do and Be&#8230; this time for the long run. And, given my international experiences and dual citizenship, the question of &#8220;What&#8221; promptly extended to one of &#8220;Where&#8221;.</p>
<p>So I moved to Berlin.</p>
<p>When I booked my flight to Germany in fall 2011, &#8220;two years&#8221; was my default timeline. &#8220;A couple years,&#8221; I responded confidently when someone asked how long I planned to be gone. &#8220;I should give the job a good two years,&#8221; I thought when I got hired six months in. &#8220;We&#8217;ll all still be here at least two more years,&#8221; I reassured myself about my circle of expat* friends another six months after that.</p>
<p>How foolish I was, to believe that two years would ever be enough. How <span class="st">naïve</span>,<em> </em>to assume there would be a clear demarcation between this chapter and the next.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3885 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-650x487.jpg" alt="2015-01-31 14.28.03-1" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Now almost three and a half years in, I feel firmly entrenched in my world of bilingual conversations, narrow streets, weekend jaunts around the continent, ubiquitous public transport, social welfare nets, and crusty bread. But these roots of mine are flighty. They wiggle at something as simple as a chat with a friend back home, when she catches me up on her life and I realize how much I&#8217;ve missed. When my sister or father leaves for the airport after a visit, they are pulled halfway out of the earth and end up lodged in the middle of my throat. Every time I get on a plane and head back across the ocean, a part of me fears they will be ripped out entirely. Because no matter how long I stay in Europe and embrace the rights my German passport affords me, I will always also be American. No matter how incredible a life I build for myself on this side of the Atlantic, there will always be a Life Back Home.</p>
<p>I was not aware of how much I had internalized this feeling until last summer, when my mother and I visited relatives in northwestern Germany. Sipping coffee on a sunny terrace, a family friend commented, &#8220;I could never do what you&#8217;re doing, be so far away from my family&#8230; I&#8217;m too close to them.&#8221; My reaction to her declaration was nothing short of primal. Of course I missed my family! Of course I felt close to them! I was not away <em>because</em> of, but rather, <em>in spite of</em> them &#8211; an unpleasant reality I struggle with on a near daily basis.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3892 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-650x518.jpg" alt="11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n" width="650" height="518" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-650x518.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-300x239.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Modern advances in travel and technology have enabled more and more people to adopt lifestyles fueled by wanderlust and adventure. But not all of us who leave home are <a href="http://elitedaily.com/life/culture/wanderlust-like-travel-much-no-real-home/959705/">perpetual wanderers with nomadic spirits</a>. Some of us are searching for somewhere to settle. Some of us are even surprised to find ourselves making a life away from where we grew up, away from the ones we love. I know I am.</p>
<p>I consider myself, by nature, to be a sensitive homebody. I crave being close to the people I love and place great importance on maintaining my relationships, both near and far. This explains why any time I am &#8220;away&#8221;, my pack mentality kicks in and I seek out a local community almost immediately. But I concurrently possess the intrinsic need to push myself and explore. For me, this has meant travel. Whether I credit <a href="https://psychologyblogaimee.wordpress.com/2013/12/04/wanderlust-a-genetic-basis-to-a-globetrotting-fanatic/">genetics</a> for this (nope) or my international upbringing, mixed with a little courage and a lot of privilege (that&#8217;s more like it), is not the point. The ups and downs of living somewhere other than where I grew up have become an integral part of my identity and understanding of growth and independence. They just don&#8217;t make the leaving part any easier.</p>
<p>The thing is, leaving is rarely the easy choice, even with the prospect of Something Great on the other side.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3887 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-650x487.jpg" alt="2015-02-21 16.37.36-1" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>While I never expected moving to Berlin to be easy, I did anticipate a gradual ease, and more importantly, clarity, with time. Reality proved instead to be emphatically non-linear. Rough patches hit me sporadically and without warning. My homesickness became a swelling wave, pulling in and out of shore, threatening at its peak to wash me out entirely. What if this chapter never ended? What if I never left my new home and went back to my old one? And now that I live in Vienna, my current home because of work, is my &#8220;old home&#8221; Washington, DC or Berlin? In countless discussions with fellow expat friends on the topics of home and belonging, the resounding theme has been similar: one of overwhelming choice and uncertainty.</p>
<p>A couple months ago, Kelly and I were at a close friend&#8217;s 30th birthday dinner in Berlin. Huddled in the kitchen over bottles of Spanish Temperanillo and mismatched plates of pizza and crudit<span class="st">és</span>, someone proposed we guess where the birthday boy would be 30 years from now. We had plenty of ideas for the &#8220;What&#8221;: running his own cooking school, teaching his kids how to do science experiments, maintaining his impressive beard. It was on the &#8220;Where&#8221; that we got stuck. &#8220;Italy?&#8221; we posed as the obvious choice (where he&#8217;s from). He resolutely shook his head &#8220;no&#8221;. &#8220;Germany?&#8221; He shrugged his shoulders, unsure &#8211; just like the majority of us in the room about our own futures.</p>
<p>Once you&#8217;ve opened yourself up to the world and seen first-hand that you can live, and maybe even thrive, somewhere else, it becomes increasingly difficult to know when or where to stop searching. The list of potential Something Greats becomes never-ending. And with it, the accompanying list of goodbyes.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By</em> <strong><em>Sophia Burton</em></strong></p>
<p>*My choice of the term &#8220;expat&#8221; was deliberate, as it popularly denotes migrants with privilege and mobility. For more on &#8220;expat&#8221; vs. &#8220;immigrant&#8221;, check out <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/global-development-professionals-network/2015/mar/13/white-people-expats-immigrants-migration?CMP=fb_gu">this Guardian article</a>.</p>
<p><em>All photos taken by me, in Vienna and Berlin.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: Leaving Berlin, collecting ourselves</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/02/13/lens-leaving-berlin/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2015 11:23:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ex-pat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3817</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Leaving Berlin might mean losing some connection to the tangible trek between dreams, realizations, and moments of vulnerability that is our movement through years, our aging and maturation, in any sense. But it is only temporary. Indeed, collecting ourselves means leaving ourselves. But only for now...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Before coming to Berlin, I was an archivist at an educational institution in Seattle, slowly working my way through a collection of artifacts that had been donated largely from Holocaust survivors and their families. Charged with accessioning (and/or digitally cataloging) over fifteen years of diffuse and often inconsistent records, I found myself forced to establish uncomfortable hierarchies. Collections are the result of measured calculations of value, often assessing the significance of one form of memory over another.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/memory_revised.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-3827 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/memory_revised.jpg" alt="memory_revised" width="742" height="603" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/memory_revised.jpg 742w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/memory_revised-300x243.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/memory_revised-650x528.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 742px) 100vw, 742px" /></a></p>
<p>Any museum has to be painfully selective; time, space, and targeted mission result in a lot of rejection. Pure and simple, refusing to &#8216;collect&#8217; something belonging to a victim of the Holocaust or a veteran of WWII means embarking on tricky, emotional terrain.</p>
<p>Despite its challenge, I learned a lot from this experience &#8211; knowledge that has served me well in a different city, a different country. For it was not by chance that my first foot in any of Berlin&#8217;s rapidly revolving doors was in an institution that appraised, tracked, and managed large quantities of objects: an art gallery. Yet, to my relief, I was no longer responsible for the task of sorting, accepting, and rejecting. The hierarchy already existed. I simply had to regularly tighten its nuts and bolts.</p>
<p>Now, I am tasked with doing a little of both. Because, you see, I am eagerly awaiting to learn whether or not any of the PhD fellowships I applied for last year will take me. Did I mention that these programs are in the United States? So, as I chew through a new set of nails and amend an ever-lengthening scroll of plan b&#8217;s, I am mentally and physically preparing for the Great Move Back. By default, this involves packing up what will have been a four-year ride in what I can best &#8211; and momentarily, as I am sure this will change &#8211; describe as a lesson in patience, adaptation, and even &#8216;failure&#8217;.</p>
<p>This is the archivist&#8217;s ultimate challenge: collecting oneself.</p>
<p>It is easier to apply some value equation to the memories of others, a different story entirely when each beloved stage of your life is on the chopping block.</p>
<p><a href="http://faculty.georgetown.edu/irvinem/theory/Clifford-OnCollectingArtandCulture.pdf">According to the anthropologist Clifford Geertz</a>, &#8216;collecting&#8217; is an almost universal process across cultures. Some  sort of &#8220;gathering&#8221; of the objects of both the everyday and the past is an important part of what he calls &#8220;marking off a domain of self&#8221;. Just as meaning, value, and story are carefully created in museums, galleries, and other institutions of public curation and display, so our lives become careful practices in determining what is now important, what might fall away, and what is to follow us to our next (literal and figurative) destination.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3837" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon-650x487.jpg" alt="Wohnwagon" width="580" height="435" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Wohnwagon.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px" /></a></p>
<p>I could not agree more with Clifford Geertz. As I plan which &#8216;artifacts&#8217; to take with me and which to disregard, I am accounting for who I once was, who I am now, and which stages of transformation are important to catalog into the future fabric of my life. Most importantly, I want to make sure I remember what this &#8220;Kelly&#8221; was like as a foreigner, as a U.S. national in the European Union, or as an &#8216;ex-pat resident&#8217; in a city like Berlin. And I want to be able to tangibly review and understand, perhaps again and again, how these stages and categories underwent change.</p>
<p>Thus, I need to &#8220;mark my domain&#8221; and &#8220;gather myself&#8221;.</p>
<p>It should be no surprise that immigrants, in particular, are constantly renegotiating hierarchies of value and meaning. Usually due to the constraints of geography and financial practicality, the contents of one&#8217;s home must be down-sized, even partly abandoned. Inevitably, pieces of childhood and/or integral moments of budding adulthood are left behind. Imagine that: deciding which family albums to send to a distant aunt for storage, which heirlooms to pass on to those who may never know what it is like to say goodbye to the literal bulk of memory, or which books to put up for sale, never-mind the story behind the inscriptions.</p>
<p>And yet, returning to the proverbial bassinet, to the place that promises comfort in familiarity, might be just as difficult for immigrants as was leaving it.</p>
<p>For me, this seems to be increasingly the case. The longer I live apart from the places where material comforts and their consumer habits formed and enveloped my surroundings, the more I recognize significance in those fewer objects I have come to possess. Less has, in this case, become truly more.</p>
<p>In the end, the way in which the self relates to &#8216;stuff&#8217; is, over time, subject to drastic change. The way in which these objects may shape who we think we are in the world does too. And this complicates the process of collection.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/IMG_66181.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3835" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/IMG_66181.jpg" alt="IMG_6618" width="580" height="435" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/IMG_66181.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/IMG_66181-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/IMG_66181-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px" /></a></p>
<p>In an <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/16/lens-going-away/">article</a> I wrote here more than a year ago (on my challenging but enriching relationship with family, friends, and self on both sides of the Atlantic), I mentioned that the two-sided sense of home one experiences living abroad indefinitely affects one&#8217;s purchasing decisions. Towels, for example, fell into this category of things somehow neglected in the everyday of my Berlin consumerism. Now, one year later, I have quite an assortment of towels (thanks, Juri), in addition to newly minted whisky glasses, books both recently bought and borrowed, certainly more dishware, and a growing pile of greeting cards and heartfelt letters I don&#8217;t think will ever land entirely in the recycling.</p>
<p>And so the collecting, the sorting, the hierarchy of value begins. And with it, the worries of abandoning something I won&#8217;t miss until it&#8217;s no longer there.</p>
<p>For who will receive my salvaged desk with its coffee stains and dents &#8211; from years of free-lance, home-bound labor; my ever-growing tropical tree of a houseplant &#8211; a gift from my dear roommates; my antiquated but charming boombox &#8211; discovered in a damp basement; my IKEA comfy-chair &#8211; hauled in two-go&#8217;s from the south of Berlin? Will their future recipients understand what they signify? What they meant, to me?</p>
<p>More recently, I have tried to reconstruct the contents of the pack I first brought with me to Berlin, its meager (if not forced) element of chosen austerity: three pairs of shoes, two copies of classic literature, two copies of hard-knock poetry, one folder of important personal documents,  toothpaste and a toothbrush, a miniature Ganesha statue, a laptop &#8211; you get the picture. Establishing some sort of a contrast is helping me, now, to re-collect.</p>
<p>To complete this act of comparison, I rummaged through boxes of the miscellaneous items one learns to hold on to after more than three years of lived life in a cosmopolitan metropolis, with all the adventures in between: ticket stubs, letters, newspaper clippings (so antiquated-adorable, I know), event flyers, various city maps. What I have found is that the &#8220;Kelly&#8221; from three years ago might have expected to uncover herself in the objects she could fit in one suitcase, while this &#8220;Kelly&#8221; &#8211; as the more recent product of the European Union, parts of the German social system, and a fragmented but very resilient city of complex diversity &#8211; would never expect such a thing.</p>
<p>I am just too different; my surroundings are just too different, too complex even. But perhaps it has always been this way. And it has just taken me three years to see it.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/foot_revised1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3836 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/foot_revised1-556x650.jpg" alt="foot_revised" width="556" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/foot_revised1.jpg 556w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/foot_revised1-256x300.jpg 256w" sizes="(max-width: 556px) 100vw, 556px" /></a></p>
<p>In this exercise of trying to curate the display of current me to future life, I have become (relatively) certain of one thing: that much of what I will take with me and much of what I will leave behind will become obsolete in the years to come. Because our hierarchies of what matters and what matters Right Now are constrained by time and its passage. Because we grow older. And so does our stuff, its significance and relationship to memory fading.</p>
<p>Leaving Berlin might mean losing some connection to the tangible trek between dreams, realizations, and moments of vulnerability that is our movement through years, our aging and maturation, in any sense. But it is only temporary. Indeed, collecting ourselves means leaving ourselves.</p>
<p>But only for now.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>All photos were taken by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: &#8220;I&#8217;m not Turkish, but my husband is&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[love]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tunisia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1251</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In a capital city marked by transformation and transience, where people are perpetually coming and going, it can feel like a true rarity to meet someone actually from that city. “H” was my first Berlin friend from Berlin. We met through a language website, after she sent me a request to practice French in exchange for German. H was working on her degree to become a French teacher. I was still new to the city and could count my local friends on one hand...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_3811" style="width: 733px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://jurigottschau.com/"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3811" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3811 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz.jpg" alt="grillplatz" width="723" height="482" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz.jpg 723w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 723px) 100vw, 723px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3811" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p style="text-align: left;">In a capital city marked by transformation and transience, where people are perpetually coming and going, it can feel like a true rarity to meet someone actually <em>from</em> that city.</p>
<p>&#8220;H&#8221; was my first Berlin friend from Berlin. We met through a language website, after she sent me a request to practice French in exchange for German. H was working on her degree to become a French teacher. I was still new to the city and could count my local friends on one hand. The first time we hung out was in February 2012 at a cafe under the <em>Savignyplatz S-Bahn</em> arches. H ended up helping me with my research on teacher quality in Germany, and I gave her tips for her upcoming study abroad program in France. Soon enough our linguistic meet-ups evolved into a friendship that waved off grammar practice in favor of relaxed Sunday afternoon coffee dates.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Our relationship also became a kind of exchange of culinary cultures. I started joining her annually to break the fast during Ramadan. As the resident atheist I wouldn&#8217;t fast before these meals. Yet I&#8217;d still be the one gnawing away at my fingers until sundown, while H and her sisters waited patiently for their first sips of rose flavored water and soup drizzled with fresh lemon juice. In return, H  joined my international crew of friends for her first Thanksgiving dinner, initiated into the world of cranberry sauce, candied sweet potatoes, and general American gluttony. Her contribution &#8211; mounds of Turkish <em>Lahmacun</em> (spiced lamb pizza) &#8211; was eagerly divvied up like party favors at the end of the night.</p>
<div id="attachment_3611" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3611" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3611 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340-650x650.jpg" alt="IMG_3340" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3611" class="wp-caption-text">Ramadan dinner with H</p></div>
<p style="text-align: left;">It didn&#8217;t take long for us to discover our mutual fascination with questions of citizenship and identity. We attended several events together on the topic and often spent our cafe time discussing our hybrid families and understanding of <em>Deutschsein</em> or &#8220;Germanness&#8221;. See, while H is a true <em>Berlinerin</em> &#8211; she was born and grew up here &#8211; her parents are from Tunisia. We shared the feeling of having more than one home; while I straddled the Atlantic, H had a foot on either side of the Mediterranean. But unlike me, H had grown up with the challenge of having to persistently defend her Germanness, to the wider community and to her own parents.</p>
<p>In countries like Germany that are still embracing their multicultural identities &#8211; Germany first recognized itself as a country of immigration in 2005 &#8211; too many still have a binary understanding of native vs. foreigner that acknowledges bloodlines over birthplace and physical appearance over personal identity. There remains a habit of probing those who look &#8220;different&#8221; about their roots, otherwise known as the dreaded &#8220;But where are you <em>really</em> from?&#8221; <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/">question</a>. Those on the receiving end of this question are often referred to as the &#8220;perpetual foreigner&#8221;, ethnic minorities who will always be seen as the “other” because of how they look.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">In H&#8217;s case, it didn&#8217;t take long to notice that the vast majority of those she came across assumed she was Turkish, including other Turkish-Germans. &#8220;Oh right, the Turkish one,&#8221; a girl on her basketball team responded, when I introduced myself as H&#8217;s friend. H once told me she gets asked if she&#8217;s Turkish more than her best friend, an actual Turkish-German who happens to be blond and fair-skinned.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3697 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-650x487.jpg" alt="2014-01-19 17.26.48" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>The confusion isn&#8217;t all too surprising, considering H&#8217;s darker features, for one, and the demographics of the city, for two. Turkish-Germans are the city&#8217;s largest ethnic minority and the largest community of Turks outside of Turkey. Estimates of the number of Turks in Berlin range from 200,000-500,000 (a combination of those with Turkish passports, partial Turkish ancestry, and ethnic minorities from Turkey). A far cry from the approximately <a href="http://www.berlin.de/lb/intmig/statistik/demografie/einwohner_staatsangehoerigkeit.html">1,500 Tunisian nationals</a> in Berlin.</p>
<p>The story of H&#8217;s parents also mirrors that of many Turkish-Germans. They immigrated to the city separately as part of a guest-worker program in the 1970s and met on the job at corporate giant, Siemens. Originally, they planned to return to Tunisia together. The couple worked 2-3 jobs, sending remittances to family in Tunisia to save up to build a house there. They sent their 3 eldest daughters back for 9 years to live with relatives and go to school. But when Germany tightened family reunification laws in the 80&#8217;s, excluding those older than 16 without German citizenship, they brought the 3 girls back to Berlin to keep the family together, by then consisting of 5 daughters.</p>
<p>H is daughter number 4 and has only visited Tunisia on vacation. She admits that a distinction exists between the older and younger sisters, due to this geographic divide in upbringing, especially apparent in attitudes toward the headscarf and family planning. Her oldest sister &#8220;lives by the Qu&#8217;ran&#8221; and hopes to move back to Tunisia permanently one day. H, on the other hand, identifies as a &#8220;<em>Berlinerin</em> with Tunisian roots&#8221;; she has no intention of leaving Germany anytime soon.</p>
<div id="attachment_3791" style="width: 657px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3791" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3791 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg" alt="htunisia" width="647" height="484" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg 647w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia-300x224.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 647px) 100vw, 647px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3791" class="wp-caption-text">H on vacation in Tunisia</p></div>
<p>When it comes to questions and comments about her being Turkish, I&#8217;ve only ever seen H respond with patience and grace. It&#8217;s the difficulties with her own parents, and especially mother, that affect her most. If you ask her about her upbringing, H will tell you that her parents were &#8220;pretty modern for immigrant standards&#8221;, letting her play sports and stay out with friends until 10pm. Sleepovers and clubs weren&#8217;t allowed, but H found ways around her parents&#8217; rules, such as working at social events like the <em>Volksfest </em>and later heading west to Dortmund for university.</p>
<p>Boyfriends, on the other hand, were out of the question. Particularly those outside of the Tunisian-German community. H dated a little in secret, but didn&#8217;t get serious with anyone until she met &#8220;A&#8221; at 19. At 28, A was almost a decade older and managing a series of internet cafes. The flirtation started small with jokes at the shop, building up slowly to weekend jogs together. Finally, A asked H out on a date.</p>
<p>H managed to keep the relationship hidden from her parents for 6 years. &#8220;I was sure they&#8217;d disapprove because he&#8217;s Turkish,&#8221; she explains. Even though both Tunisians and Turks in Germany are predominantly Muslim, H says it&#8217;s not uncommon for the older immigrant generations to be prejudiced against one another. &#8220;The Tunisians here think that all Turkish boys are in gangs, are loud and have no respect, and don&#8217;t achieve anything,&#8221; H claims; &#8220;Tunisians in Tunisia think more positively about Turks than Tunisians in Germany do.&#8221;</p>
<p>When she told her parents about the relationship in 2013, her mother threatened that H was &#8220;ruining her life&#8221; and that if she continued, they would disown her. &#8220;I haven&#8217;t even told them yet that A is Shiite,&#8221; H joked (her family is Sunni).</p>
<div id="attachment_3792" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3792" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3792 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-650x202.jpg" alt="A&amp;H" width="650" height="202" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-650x202.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-300x93.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3792" class="wp-caption-text">A &amp; H</p></div>
<p>According to H, the problem is her mother&#8217;s stubbornness more than anything else. But listening to the stories one can&#8217;t help but notice an underlying theme of fear, logical or not. A fear of losing one&#8217;s child. A fear of not relating to one&#8217;s grandchildren. A fear of the dilution of one&#8217;s cultural lineage over generations. &#8220;Many in the Tunisian-German community are scared that their kids will marry Turks and end up in Turkey,&#8221; H agrees, &#8220;my mother is also afraid her grandchildren will never learn Arabic.&#8221; H and her sisters speak strictly Tunisian Arabic with their parents. When just amongst each other, a mix of Arabic and German.</p>
<p>Language is just one question of many that H and A will face as parents. They have already decided that A will primarily speak Turkish and H mostly German, which she is more comfortable with than Arabic. They have even talked about where they will <em>really</em> end up one day. H tells me that the Tunisian consulate pays for the bodies of Tunisian nationals in Germany to be sent back for burials. A, who came to Berlin at 18 as a student, gave up his Turkish passport to become German.  As an entrepreneur he&#8217;s eager to launch projects in Turkey and maybe even retire there one day, but is limited without citizenship.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">After months of not seeing each other, H and I finally find time last November for one of our Sunday coffee dates. H arrives to the Italian cafe in an uncharacteristically bulky sweater that makes me raise my eyebrows. Shortly after ordering our lattes and chocolate cake, she spills the beans: she and A have gotten married, and she&#8217;s newly pregnant. The religious ceremony was held at their apartment with an Imam presiding and a handful of their closest friends and siblings present. H&#8217;s parents chose not to return early from their vacation in Tunisia to attend. As for their upcoming grandchild, wherever he or she decides to be &#8220;<em>really</em> from&#8221;, they are still in the dark.</p>
<p><em> &#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong> </em></p>
<p><em>&#8220;A&#8221; requested that this article remain anonymous, in order to not further weaken his cause, should H&#8217;s parents somehow come across it.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: Scotland and the question of borders</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/10/28/beyond-berlin-question-borders/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/10/28/beyond-berlin-question-borders/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2014 10:30:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Scotland]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3442</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Coming off an evening with Invisible Borders that was all about transcending boundaries, it was an eye-opening juxtaposition to visit a country that had just explored creating more stagnant borders of their own. This was to be my first trip to Scotland, but as I had visited England and Ireland in the past I wasn&#8217;t expecting much in the way of culture shock. I had heard something about an exotic concoction called Haggis, anticipated equal amounts difficulty and delight navigating the Scottish accent, and was prepared for plaid. Oh, and rain. Lots and lots of rain. So during my short stint in Edinburgh and the Highlands, I was especially interested to delve into what it was the Scots themselves believed distinguished them from the rest of the UK enough to merit separating themselves off with tighter borders. Did it really have anything to do with national identity, the sentiment conjured up by media images of teenagers covered in blue and white paint? Or was it really more for economic reasons, tied to access to finite resources like North Sea Oil? Scotland&#8217;s recent independence referendum, arising from a sweeping win by the Scottish National Party in the 2011 Parliament elections, was [...]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Coming off an evening with <a href="http://invisible-borders.com/">Invisible Borders</a> that was all about transcending boundaries, it was an eye-opening juxtaposition to visit a country that had just explored creating more stagnant borders of their own.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-11.58.20-11.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3507 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-11.58.20-11-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-06 11.58.20-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-11.58.20-11.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-11.58.20-11-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>This was to be my first trip to Scotland, but as I had visited England and Ireland in the past I wasn&#8217;t expecting much in the way of culture shock. I had heard something about an exotic concoction called <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haggis">Haggis</a>, anticipated equal amounts difficulty and delight navigating the Scottish accent, and was prepared for plaid. Oh, and rain. Lots and lots of rain. So during my short stint in Edinburgh and the Highlands, I was especially interested to delve into what it was the Scots themselves believed distinguished them from the rest of the UK enough to merit separating themselves off with tighter borders. Did it really have anything to do with national identity, the sentiment conjured up by media images of teenagers covered in blue and white paint? Or was it really more for economic reasons, tied to access to finite resources like North Sea Oil?</p>
<p>Scotland&#8217;s recent independence referendum, arising from a sweeping win by the Scottish National Party in the 2011 Parliament elections, was historic but not exceptional. Separatist movements exist all over the world, including the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/">people of Kurdistan</a> who make up a region of four Middle Eastern countries, Spain&#8217;s economic powerhouse, Catalonia, and Germany&#8217;s conservative southern state, Bavaria. Some may even surprise you &#8211; for example, Venice, where an <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2014/03/europes-latest-secession-movement-venice/284562/">unofficial referendum</a> in May of this year showed the vast majority in favor of secession from Italy. Supporters of more active movements around the globe watched closely as the Scots went to the polls this past September 18th, eager to follow suit or fuel their respective campaigns. The results held weight. After 55.3% of Scotland voted &#8220;no&#8221;, Catalonia cancelled their planned referendum, originally set for November 9th of this year.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.40.09-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3451 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.40.09-1-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-05 15.40.09-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.40.09-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.40.09-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>There are over 20 active separatist movements around the world, the majority in Europe and Asia. Of these, about a third are violent*, due primarily to ethnic and religious tensions. While some fight for human rights or religious freedom, others strive for economic power, control over resources, or wealth potential. The Scotland independence debate was rife with discussions about tax distribution, North Sea Oil, currency, and jobs. &#8220;Scotland is a very wealthy country &#8211; let&#8217;s make it feel like it!&#8221; proclaimed the homepage of the official &#8220;Yes Scotland&#8221; campaign. Meanwhile, Turkey&#8217;s Kurds have been engaged in armed struggle against the Turkish government since 1984, resulting in thousands of deaths. It is therefore an impossible and reductionist task to speak of secessionist movements as a homogenous entity. Yet regardless of the nature of the struggle &#8211; political, economic, social, ethnic, violent, peaceful, or a combination of the above &#8211; when one discusses borders, one is inherently embarking on a discussion about community, belonging, and identity.</p>
<p>As links between countries become stronger through migration, technology, economic trade, and political unions, the idea of separating oneself from the &#8220;global community&#8221; can appear unmodern, backward, even futile. &#8220;I voted no,&#8221; my Airbnb host, a documentary filmmaker originally from England, revealed as we strolled to the supermarket together my first night in rainy Edinburgh, &#8220;not because I&#8217;m against independence for the Scots, but because I believe in a borderless world.&#8221;</p>
<p>At the same time, retreating into a stronger sense of place and identity, as our world becomes more globalized, can feel almost like an instinctive reaction. An exercise in protection, preservation, even control. &#8220;It may have worked in the past, but the way the centralized government in London makes decisions for us now does not reflect who we are anymore,&#8221; my Highlands tour guide explained as we stood at the foot of Stirling Castle, &#8220;I just can&#8217;t be proud of a country that isn&#8217;t its own.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>Which begs the question: how can we embrace the inevitable (and often beneficial) changes that crossing and opening borders may bring, while simultaneously protecting what makes our home(s) &#8220;our own&#8221;?</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.42.39-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3452 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.42.39-1-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-05 15.42.39-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.42.39-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-15.42.39-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>For starters, the concept of a world with more open borders is conceivably less radical than many perceive it to be. &#8220;Open&#8221; does not mean &#8220;none&#8221;, nor does it mean a lawless world where people come and go as they please without screens or supervision. Within the field of migration, the concept of &#8220;open borders&#8221; generally refers to a reversal from what is, by default, an exclusionary policy, e.g. countries finding a reason to <em>let someone in. </em>Instead, the policy would switch to one of de facto inclusion, e.g. countries finding a reason to <em>keep someone out</em>. Reasons for excluding potential immigrants would lie more with criminal records and health concerns than they would with economic prospects or integration potential. Open borders is also not commensurate with the idea of open citizenship: in a world with open borders, countries could still deem individual qualifications and requirements for acquiring full citizenship rights.</p>
<p>The idea of open borders has gained traction in recent years (think &#8220;No Human is Illegal&#8221;) with the rise in global migration. Many see current immigration restrictions as inconsistent with basic egalitarian principles, such as equal opportunity, human rights, and moral obligations. On the more pragmatic end of the spectrum, there are those who advocate for open borders as a catalyst for economic growth and innovation, responding to phenomena such as lower birth rates and skilled worker shortages in more developed countries.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-13.22.05.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3450 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-13.22.05-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-05 13.22.05" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-13.22.05.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-05-13.22.05-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>But do questions about opening borders and globalization shifts weaken the importance of nationalism and identity? For many, despite the fact that we all interact with the global community in one form or another, place still matters most. A staggering 70% of those polled who voted &#8220;yes&#8221; to an independent Scotland claimed they did so because of &#8220;<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2014/sep/20/scottish-independence-lord-ashcroft-poll">the principle that all decisions about Scotland should be taken in Scotland</a>.&#8221;</p>
<p>This thinking was reflected in the voting demographics of the Scottish independence vote &#8211; eligible voters were only those currently residing in Scotland and Commonwealth or EU citizens. So while my Airbnb host was included despite being born in England, her Scottish friends living abroad were not (there are approximately <a href="http://worldpopulationreview.com/countries/scotland-population/">2 million Scots</a> living in other parts of the UK), nor were thousands of immigrant residents without the right passport.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-14.42.18-2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3478 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-14.42.18-2-650x650.jpg" alt="2014-10-06 14.42.18-2" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-14.42.18-2.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/2014-10-06-14.42.18-2-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Although the official &#8220;yes&#8221; campaign in Scotland was largely pro-migration (<a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/scottish-independence/11035389/Scottish-immigration-has-to-increase-by-14000-to-meet-Salmond-target.html">mainly for economic reasons</a>) and may have adopted a more open policy than the rest of the UK, the independence vote brought up many questions about the future of migration and refugee policy, as well as citizenship laws. Who would be considered a citizen from &#8220;day one&#8221; of independence? What would the process be like for the foreign-born who wished to become citizens? What would dual citizenship policy look like for Scots living abroad? Would those living on the border, working on one side and living on the other, still have freedom of movement? What legal hurdles would immigrant families have to endure to visit family members spread out across the region?</p>
<p>As we lay out in <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/about/a-manifesto/">our manifesto</a>, borders hold meanings both conceptual and literal. They demarcate ideas of home and kinship as much as they do political, legal, and bureaucratic spaces. They bring people together around shared systems, laws, traditions, languages, and goals, but they also divide, separate, and limit. They influence and make statements about our engagement with local and global communities. They determine how seamlessly we can navigate having more than one home, a reality for an increasing number of us around the globe. But on the most basic level, for many, they simply represent what is possible and what isn&#8217;t.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>*Figures as of 2008. For a comprehensive account of the history of separatist movements and self-determination around the world, click <a href="http://online.sfsu.edu/swilcox/Swilcox/Shelleys_webpage_files/Wilcox,%20The%20Open%20Borders%20Debate%20on%20Immigration.pdf">here</a>.</p>
<p>For a shorter round-up on active secession movements, click <a href="http://www.dnaindia.com/world/report-7-separatist-movements-that-are-closely-watching-scotland-s-independence-referendum-2019372">here</a>.</p>
<p>All photos by yours truly from her recent trip to Edinburgh.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/10/28/beyond-berlin-question-borders/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: Ali for (and from) Germany</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/09/02/interview-ali-for-and-from-germany/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2014 08:27:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3183</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the wake of Germany's World Cup victory, much has been said about a renewed sense of German patriotism and its implications. While some have feared a connection to Germany's dark past, others have welcomed the discourse as a chance to shape a new sense of belonging within the country's evolving demographics. We've already written something about it here. But what a discussion on national identity means on the personal level is another story. Or rather many stories. Here's one...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the wake of Germany&#8217;s World Cup victory, much has been said about a renewed sense of German patriotism and its implications. While some have feared a connection to Germany&#8217;s dark past, others have welcomed the discourse as a chance to shape a new sense of belonging within the country&#8217;s evolving demographics. We&#8217;ve already written something about it <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/28/world-cup-fever-how-malleable-is-german-identity/">here</a>. But what a discussion on national identity means on the personal level is another story. Or rather many stories. Here&#8217;s one.</p>
<div id="attachment_3184" style="width: 439px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3184" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3184 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/ali.jpg" alt="Ali für Deutschland " width="429" height="429" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/ali.jpg 429w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/ali-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 429px) 100vw, 429px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3184" class="wp-caption-text">Ali at the Germany-France game at Train Cocktailbar</p></div>
<p>It took Ali <span class="gD">Riza Gürbüz over 30 years to feel welcome in Germany. Originally from East Anatolia, Ali moved to Berlin at age 12 with his brother and sister. His mother had arrived 8 years prior in 1973 as part of the last wave of guest worker recruitment. She was living in <span class="st">Neukölln and working for a cleaning company</span>. His father stayed behind in Turkey.</span></p>
<p><span class="gD"><em>The beginning wasn&#8217;t easy</em>, Ali recounts. Understanding German society, learning the language, feeling at home&#8230; this all took time. But eventually he gained his footing, finished his schooling, completed an <em>Ausbildung</em> (apprenticeship), and in 1986, began a career in industrial mechanics. Today, he&#8217;s married, has a 12 year old daughter and an active social life, and makes music in his free time. He still lives in N<span class="st">eukölln. </span><br />
</span></p>
<p><span class="gD"><strong>But despite spending the majority of his life in Germany, having German citizenship, and making a home here, he&#8217;s often felt like an outsider.</strong> </span></p>
<p><em>I still don&#8217;t really have any German friends</em>, Ali tells me on the last night of Ramadan in July, after breaking the fast together. We&#8217;re sitting outside on Kreuzberg&#8217;s iconic <span class="st"><em>Oranienstraße</em></span> with his friends, also both named Ali, both German-Turks* born in Berlin. Ali and Ali nod their heads in agreement. A rollerblading demonstration passes by in front of us. <em>I don&#8217;t understand it,</em> Ali says. <em>We all have the same sources of stress &#8211; work, money, family &#8211; so why don&#8217;t we make more of an effort to be nice to one another? </em></p>
<div id="attachment_3358" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3358" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3358 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis-650x473.jpg" alt="Breaking the fast on Oranienstraße" width="650" height="473" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis-650x473.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis-300x218.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3358" class="wp-caption-text">Breaking the fast on Oranienstraße</p></div>
<p><span class="gD">Ali can cite the definitive moment in which he felt that he had finally &#8220;arrived&#8221; in Germany. <em>I was in the Bundeswehrkrankenhaus [German Armed Forces hospital] last December for a week due to a skin issue. I received such kind and affectionate treatment from the nurses and doctors. The same treatment as everyone else. I shared a room with a guy named Wolfgang, and we talked for two days straight, about everything. The atmosphere made me feel really welcome and inspired.</em></span></p>
<p>So inspired, that he started writing a song on his phone while still on his hospital bed. Two days after he was released, he finished &#8220;Ali <span class="st">für</span> Deutschland&#8221; (literally &#8220;Ali for Germany&#8221;), a World Cup song in <span class="gD">support of the </span>German national team. After recording it, Ali ran around to different departments and bureaus in the city, asking for support. Eventually he got a production company to film it for free. The song is available for purchase online (99 cents on iTunes) and half of the proceeds go to a homeless shelter in his neighborhood.<em> I really believed in the song and project, </em>Ali explains, <em>I wanted to show that someone who has my name and looks like me supports the German team. That people from all over the world with different backgrounds live here and consider it their home. </em><em><br />
</em></p>
<p><strong>Ali <span class="st">für</span> Deutschland Music Video: </strong></p>
<p><iframe width="650" height="366" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Mzqz6hCF7uI?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>Singing alongside Ali in the music video is his daughter. <em>I see that she&#8217;s growing up differently than I did, that she&#8217;s happier. I hope this song contributes to that. </em>For Ali, it all comes back to the media. <em>When Mesut Özil [German-Turkish football player] makes a good play, German-Turkish kids get patted on the back. If he does poorly, people shake their heads at us. The migration background is always emphasized. </em></p>
<p>Ali&#8217;s point is backed by research. <a href="http://www.stern.de/panorama/stern-umfrage-knappe-mehrheit-lehnt-islam-als-teil-deutschlands-ab-2128967.html">A recent Stern poll</a> shows that over half of Germans believe that Islam does not belong in German society. <a href="http://mediendienst-integration.de/artikel/der-islam-gehoert-zu-deutschland-spielhaus.html">Experts</a> argue that Islam is often conflated with Turks, the headscarf, and migration due to images perpetuated in the media. Another common image: German-Turkish or Arab youth as more violent or prone to criminal acts than their &#8220;native&#8221; counterparts, a stereotype repeatedly rebuked by <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/schulspiegel/wissen/kriminalitaet-von-migranten-laut-gutachten-nicht-hoeher-a-983536.html">studies</a>. <em>There are so many positive examples of what German-Turks have done and do for this country</em>, Ali says,<em> but news and social media continuously choose to show negative images. I want the media to show more positive images. </em><em><br />
</em></p>
<p>Ali is a positive person by nature. His face lights up when he shares stories of making connections to people at work or through his music. But he also has plenty of examples of feeling unwelcome or misunderstood on account of his background. He makes a conscious effort to speak Turkish with his daughter only at home and German out in public, in order to avoid judgment. More than once he&#8217;s been told &#8220;Du bist mein Lieblingst<span class="st">ürke</span><em>&#8221; </em>(&#8220;You&#8217;re my favorite Turk&#8221;), by a coworker or a club bouncer, for not stirring up trouble. <em>What am I supposed to do with that?</em> Ali asks, his eyes filling with emotion. Recently, a colleague joked to Ali that the reason his work contract was not renewed was because of his new hairstyle. <em>You look like a Turk now</em>, he told Ali.</p>
<p>After 6 years at the company, successfully training incoming employees, Ali had expected to keep his job. <em>After the video, they told me my music was making me slower at work, which wasn&#8217;t true,</em> Ali says, shaking his head<em>. <strong>I always felt like they were waiting for me to explode, to show my &#8220;Turkish temper&#8221;. In the end I think they just couldn&#8217;t deal with my humanness.</strong></em></p>
<div id="attachment_3359" style="width: 579px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3359" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-3359" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/alitsm.jpg" alt="Performing at a Football Academy Gala, August 2014" width="569" height="335" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/alitsm.jpg 569w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/alitsm-300x176.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 569px) 100vw, 569px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3359" class="wp-caption-text">Performing at a Football Academy Gala, August 2014</p></div>
<p>Ali is disappointed but not disheartened. He is taking this unexpected turn as a chance to reconsider career paths. <em>I have so much experience, and I want to use that to do something good</em>, he says. He&#8217;s now thinking seriously about becoming a social worker for kids with migration backgrounds. <em>I know </em><em>what they&#8217;re going through.</em> <em>I can go into their homes and talk to their parents, help them see what options they have and make sure they don&#8217;t give up. </em>More than likely, he&#8217;ll do it with music. <em>I learned early on that music allows you to reach a lot of people. Music is its own language, one that you don&#8217;t need to understand, just feel.</em></p>
<p>Ali is certainly &#8220;for&#8221; Germany, but does he consider himself from Germany? <em>Whew,</em> Ali lets out a deep breath, <em>I&#8217;m not sure. I have parts of German culture and parts of Turkish culture. But I think, most of all, I&#8217;m a Berliner.</em></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>*The term German-Turk is a hyphenation often used for people born and/or raised in Germany with 2nd or 3rd generation Turkish backgrounds. For more on language, migration, and identity, see our article <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">here</a>.</p>
<p>For German interviews with Ali, click <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/video/ali-fuer-deutschland-deutsch-tuerke-nimmt-wm-song-auf-video-1500438.html">here</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kGYNujx3RvQ">here</a>.</p>
<p><em>All of Ali&#8217;s quotes have been translated/paraphrased by Sophia Burton.<br />
</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rave: the California Breakfast Slam Effect</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/30/rave-the-california-breakfast-slam-effect/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2014 12:17:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[expats]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2510</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Identity and belonging are closely intertwined with the foods we eat. The California Breakfast Slam, or CABslam, originally a pop-up breakfast establishment celebrating Americana classics like hash browns and maple syrup-drenched bacon, now hosts an unassuming 'Beta' restaurant space at the far edge of Neukölln's Reuterkiez. A visit allows for the giddy return to childhood memories that lead to goosebumps and pride, or a combination of both. Let's call this the California Breakfast Slam effect...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The relationship between food and identity, or simply food and a sense of belonging, is well-known to those of us who have sought out Hass avocados or Toll House chocolate chips (often in vain) in places beyond the United States. For me, there is something ultimately gratifying, even safe, about opening that jar of Adam&#8217;s peanut butter or letting the smell of buttermilk biscuits fill my Berlin apartment. At once, giving in to &#8216;old urges&#8217; is washed with self-realization. I also just really love buttermilk biscuits.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01329.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2518" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01329.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01329" width="640" height="426" /></a></p>
<p>While critically testing Berlin&#8217;s newest &#8216;American breakfast&#8217; joint a few weekends ago, I had the overwhelming sense that &#8220;hey, I&#8217;m allowed to do this [more than anyone else here]!&#8221;. These are processes of identity and belonging at work.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.facebook.com/cabslam">California Breakfast Slam</a>, or CABslam, originally a pop-up breakfast establishment celebrating Americana classics like hash browns and maple syrup-drenched bacon, now hosts an unassuming &#8216;Beta&#8217; restaurant space at the far edge of Neukölln&#8217;s Reuterkiez. A visit allows for the giddy return to childhood memories that lead to goosebumps and pride or a combination of both. Let&#8217;s call this the California Breakfast Slam effect.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01342.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2531 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01342.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01342" width="640" height="960" /></a></p>
<p>Not all patrons of CABslam&#8217;s new digs are from the Western coast of the United States like myself, but there certainly exists a clientele of the North American variety, motivated more by feelings (or longings) than by taste, I dare to conjecture. Put simply, who knew that a plate full of pancakes, browned potato shavings, bacon, and a fried egg would make one feel so secure? So &#8216;you&#8217; in your own maple-craving skin? This is the CABslam effect.</p>
<p>Anthropologists would suggest that our food choices constitute a large part of how we position ourselves in the world, particularly in a foreign context. In a country for which one possesses no legal or innate right to reside, one learns to miss the general social acceptance and security provided in that <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/16/lens-going-away/">place left behind</a>. Ethnographical studies* of immigrants around the world &#8211; Turkish immigrants vending kebap to keep the nostalgic grill burning, taco trucks re-connecting small towns to distant landscapes, Punjabi import shops outlining a community in the anonymous city &#8211; form an extensive literature in support of this role of food as an identity-maker. Food ways, what and how we eat, often serve to reclaim a definition of self that may be threatened by the indifferent surroundings of the foreign.</p>
<p>Interesting to reflect upon, however, is how much of these positive associations are, in fact, related to the food itself. In other words, is it the constitution and consistency of the yogurt that reminds the Turkish immigrant of home (see <a href="http://www.businessweek.com/articles/2013-01-31/at-chobani-the-turkish-king-of-greek-yogurt">the Chobani story</a>)? Is the sugar content of my peanut butter a key determinant of my sense of belonging &#8211; of how I affirm and embody my American identity in Germany?</p>
<p>One of my father&#8217;s favorite activities, as of late, is going to the local mom &amp; pop diner located just around the corner from his home. He has always loved waffles, bacon, eggs &#8211; preferences I inherited, minus the bacon for environmental reasons (goodbye bacon bowls).</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_20041.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2555 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_20041.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_2004" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>At this local breakfast spot in Vancouver (WA), one sits in a cozy corner &#8211; on that particular kind of squeaky upholstery reserved for diners &#8211; and receives bottom-less coffee and a pint of the good, brown sticky stuff within moments of arriving, without needing to have asked. Luxury and simplicity come together in a routinized ritual that completes a Saturday morning.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_20051.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2556 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_20051.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_2005" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>A visit to Neukölln&#8217;s diner-ish mock up, CABslam, offers a similar experience, albeit with wood in place of the traditional synthetic materials. The waitresses greet guests in English with a smile, a touch of accent on the tongue; plates of meat, starch, and sugar pass through the spacious, half-finished space, disturbed only by the squeal of espresso. Oh, American breakfast in Europe: such a strange delicacy, indeed.</p>
<p>If I were to come upon a similar diner anywhere in the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/">Pacific Northwest</a>, I would be confused by 1. the small portions, 2. the texture of the syrup, 3. the small portions, 4. the fancy coffee, and 5. the small portions. But while in that strange space of not always quite fitting in and not being quite sure how to amend the problem, one takes any moment of assured (if strangely assembled) belonging and identity one can get.</p>
<p>And so I ordered French toast, Juri ordered the original California Breakfast Slam, and I ate his pancakes and felt thoroughly pleased with the entire situation.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01335.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2524" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01335.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01335" width="640" height="960" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01335.jpg 433w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01335-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>Glancing around the perhaps far-too spacious-to-be-cozy restaurant-in-progress, plates of beans and eggs (Huevos Rancheros!),  yellow sauce and bread (Eggs Benedict!), and hearty scrambles made it all just believable enough&#8230;even if it is not possible to get a side of sweet &#8216;Amish bread&#8217; here, as is the case with my favorite diner in Seattle, <a href="http://www.bethscafe.com/index.php">Beth&#8217;s Cafe</a>. Beginnings are always a bit modest, anyway.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01336.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2525 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01336.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01336" width="640" height="426" /></a></p>
<p>After our plates had been cleared, all sauces sopped up with available eatable utensils, I pondered my just-consumed identity and belonging with a nice long sip of espresso. Though perhaps still a bit hungry for American-diner standards, the starvation for the validation that comes from truly fitting in &#8211; in this case, the belonging that comes from just understanding the absurdly starchy rituals that constitute American breakfast &#8211; was momentarily gone.</p>
<p>This felt quite good.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01340.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2529" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01340.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01340" width="640" height="960" /></a></p>
<p>While consuming something in the morning hours that would otherwise be reserved for a combination of dessert, second dessert, and holidays in Germany, the recognition that &#8220;yes, this is perhaps not the healthiest but yes, this is delicious, and I will enjoy it&#8221; bubbles up, almost unexpectedly.</p>
<p>American food culture is shaped and even manipulated by advertising&#8217;s exploitation of this very urge to give-in, indulge, and consume &#8216;freedom&#8217; as embodied in a fried-chicken-pizza or a Big Gulp &#8211; as nicely laid out in an <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/currency/2014/04/fast-food-doubles-down.html">article on the success of such fast-food antics in America</a> in this past week&#8217;s issue of <em>The</em> <em>New Yorker</em>.</p>
<p>But looking around at the improvisational furniture and faux diner fixtures at CABslam, the abstract and even fictive nature of such an experience became strikingly clear: The setting did not necessarily fit my expectations, but the frame was just large enough to allow textures, smells, and memories to gently assemble a replica of &#8216;home&#8217;. Minus the Amish bread.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01326.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2515" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01326.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01326" width="640" height="426" /></a></p>
<p>If one were to survey immigrants and/or expats around the world, one thing would surely be held in common &#8211; a lust after the foods of whence one has come. This does not mean that these foods are objectively good or even at the top of my list. But this is not the point. Even though the mere idea of many American delights makes me a little uneasy and sad for the state of national nutrition (see &#8220;<a href="http://www.takepart.com/place-at-the-table">A Place at the Table</a>&#8221; for the full story), I delight just a little in being associated with such a cuisine. Because it is familiar and mine, in a way intimately intertwined with memory and what identity makes of it.</p>
<p>More than anything else, the moments at my childhood-dream-table, where chocolate-chip pancakes were the best reward and hash browns the coveted snack, are the things that bring me the simplest of glee in a situation that is often colored by uncertainty. And that, folks, is the CABslam effect.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01323.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2533" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01323.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01323" width="640" height="426" /></a></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>Cabslam is located at Innstraße 47, 12045 Neukölln, open (now also for lunch and dinner) Mo-So 11:00-midnight. Their <a href="http://www.cabslam.com/">official website</a> is currently under construction, so best use the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/cabslam/info">facebook page</a> for more information on their rotating menu, as well as to make reservations. Long live American breakfast! All photos by <a href="http://jurigottschau.com/">Juri Gottschau</a>.</p>
<p><em>*If the mention of ethnographical studies sparked your interest, here is some further reading on immigrant identity, diaspora memory, and &#8211; you guessed it &#8211; food, brought to you by the wonderful discipline of sociocultural anthropology:</em><br />
Bahloul, J. 1989, &#8220;From a Muslim banquet to a Jewish seder: food ways and ethnicity among North African Jews&#8221;, in <em>Jews Among Arabs: Contacts and Boundaries</em>, ed. Cohen, M. Camp; A. Udovitch.<br />
Buckser A. 1999, <em>Keeping kosher: eating and social identity among the Jews of Denmark</em>, <em>Ethnology</em>, vol. 38.<br />
Chapman et al. 2011, &#8220;Meanings of food, eating and health in Punjabi families living in Vancouver, Canada&#8221;,<em>Health Education Journal</em>, vol. 70, no. 1.<br />
Harbottle, L. 1997, &#8220;Taste and embodiment: the food preferences of Iranians in Britain&#8221;, in <em>Food Preference and Taste: Continuity and Change</em>, ed. MacBeth, H.<br />
Holtzman, John D. 2006, &#8220;Food and Memory&#8221;, <em>Annual Review of Anthropology</em>, no. 35.<br />
Mankekar, P. 2002, “&#8217;India shopping&#8217;: Indian grocery stores and transnational conﬁguration of belonging&#8221;, <em>Ethnos</em>, vol. 67, no. 1.<br />
Lee, SSJ. 2000, &#8220;Dys-appearing tongues and bodily memories: the aging of ﬁrst-generation resident Koreans in Japan&#8221;, <em>Ethos</em>, vol. 28, no. 2.<br />
Ray, K. 2004, <em>The Migrant’s Table: Meals and Memories in Bengali-American Households</em>.<br />
Şebnem, Timur Ögüt 2008, &#8220;Turkish restaurants in London: An ethnographic study on representation of cultural identity through design&#8221;, <em>ITU A|Z</em>, vol. 5.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Collidoscope Manifesto</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/22/the-collidoscope-manifesto/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/22/the-collidoscope-manifesto/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[collidoscopeks]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 09:45:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cities]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2395</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A couple months ago, Collidoscope Berlin was invited to write its first guest post for the Global Citizens Initiative - an organization that aims “to build a network of people who see themselves as global citizens and want to build a better world”. Part of the task was to connect what we do here to the significance of borders. “Borders?”, we wondered, unsure how to proceed but mostly questioning why we had never concretely addressed the topic before...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_6374.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2441 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_6374.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_6374" width="640" height="426" /></a></strong></p>
<p><strong>A couple months ago, Collidoscope Berlin was invited to write its first guest post for the <a href="http://us5.campaign-archive2.com/?u=34e2670d2b1df6a04603724fa&amp;id=3a6a8f6948&amp;e=b0926c0e88">Global Citizens Initiative</a> </strong>&#8211; an organization that aims &#8220;to build a network of people who see themselves as global citizens and want to build a better world&#8221;. Part of the task was to connect what we do here to the significance of borders. &#8220;Borders?&#8221;, we wondered, unsure how to proceed but mostly questioning why we had never concretely addressed the topic before. What kind of immigration project doesn&#8217;t discuss borders?</p>
<p>When we launched this project in April of last year, we knew we wanted to do something <em>different </em>related to the topic of<em> difference. </em>We knew of groups that promoted and celebrated cultural and ethnic diversity. We had worked for institutions that research and analyze immigrant integration. Our goal was to do something in between, producing articles and commentary that both told a story and provided facts and context. And we wanted to do this through the lens of one city that, although formed by a unique historical and political context, could perhaps provide lessons for others.</p>
<p><strong>A few days ago, Collidoscope Berlin turned one-year old </strong>&#8211; and as we took the opportunity to reflect back, we realized that not talking about borders was, in fact, making a statement about borders. It wasn&#8217;t that we thought borders were unimportant or that we were advocating their complete erosion. Rather, we were advocating for the idea that every city <span style="letter-spacing: 0;">is home to its very own “collision” of cultures and thus has <em>unique</em> stories about diversity and difference. Through the lens of migration &#8211; the movement and coming together of people &#8211; we believe that we can understand more about what makes &#8216;us&#8217; who we are on the individual, local, and global scales. Through our personal lens of moving and living across borders, we aim to make sense of what defines and shapes the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/26/lens-coming-home/">places we call home</a>, as well as the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/16/lens-going-away/">places we leave</a>. Cities, as a reflection of &#8216;the we&#8217;, are a good place to start.</span></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/cropped-2012-08-22-19-03-431.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-18" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/cropped-2012-08-22-19-03-431.jpg?w=640" alt="cropped-2012-08-22-19-03-431.jpg" width="640" height="221" /></a></p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>The Collidoscope Manifesto </strong></span></p>
<p><em>Originally published as a guest post for the <a href="http://us5.campaign-archive2.com/?u=34e2670d2b1df6a04603724fa&amp;id=3a6a8f6948&amp;e=b0926c0e88">Global Citizens Initiative</a><strong><br />
</strong></em></p>
<p>Individuals are born within borders. On a map, these borders seem relatively arbitrary: meandering lines awkwardly encircling blurbs of land. And yet in our lives, the purpose they are meant to serve is anything but, as borders demarcate political, legal, and bureaucratic spaces, as much as they do geographic ones. For it is not geography &#8211; the land itself &#8211; that keeps us from coming and going. It is our (hu)man-made political systems and governments that determine who is permitted to enter or leave, to immigrate or emigrate, to belong or not to belong.</p>
<p>Despite the presence of these borders, we all make our way across these lines one way or another. Whether through relationships abroad, use of technology, involvement in international groups, or participation in the global economy: our lives are increasingly global and less tied to the borders in which we were born or reside. While this does not automatically make us all global citizens (which necessitates awareness and action), it fosters connections across borders that reinforce the idea of a world community. How can we reconcile this ever-present reality with our understanding of borders and restrictions on an individual’s freedom of movement?</p>
<p>The majority of us – more than ever before &#8211; lives in cities. Thanks largely to migration, modern cities have become microcosms of the global community, home to spectacular cultural, ethnic, and religious diversity. While this “collision” of cultures can pose challenges, it is also a tremendous opportunity for growth and enrichment. If we begin to view our cities’ pockets and spaces of difference as opportunities – becoming more empathetic, inclusive, and participatory in the process – we can begin to realize global values within local communities.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_0388.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2577 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719-650x433.jpg" alt="Collidoscope Berlin Manifesto" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Berlin, Germany is one example: a city with a long history of attracting those who are “different”, where 1 in every 4 residents is of foreign origin and 138 countries are represented. A city that is undergoing constant transformation, while undertaking the challenge of integrating not only newcomers, but the 2nd and 3rd generations. A city that is brimming with rich diversity and teeming with opportunities. <span style="letter-spacing: 0;">Collidoscope Berlin is a celebration of these stories and opportunities, a conversation-starter, a democratic and inclusive view of the many peoples, spaces, and settings that constitute the modern city. </span></p>
<p><strong>Lessons from Berlin: </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/">Ramadan with Neighbors</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/12/20/happy-weekend-review-an-old-new-christmas-market/">The Thai Park</a>,<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/12/20/happy-weekend-review-an-old-new-christmas-market/"> An Old-New Christmas Market</a></p>
<p><strong>Lessons from Beyond: </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/29/beyond-berlin-the-istanbul-connection/">The Istanbul Connection</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/">The American Northwest</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/03/beyond-berlin-difference-on-the-blessed-isle/">Difference in Sri Lanka </a></p>
<p><strong>What is Multiculturalism? </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/">Diversity &amp; the Big City</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/10/whose-multikulti-is-it-the-elusive-definition-of-multiculturalism/">Whose Multikulti is it?</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/18/happy-weekend-karneval-der-kulturen-carnival-of-cultures/">Carnival of Cultures</a></p>
<p><strong>Our Stories: </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/16/lens-going-away/">Going Away</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/26/lens-coming-home/">Coming Home</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/29/lens-linsanity-and-linguine/">Linsanity and Linguine</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/25/lens-lamb-on-fridays/">Lamb on Fridays</a></p>
<p><strong>Local Stories:</strong> <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/09/interview-ali-zoe-and-the-gentrification-debate/">Ali &amp; Zoe</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/">Orhan</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/21/lens-warm-nights-are-for-cricket/">Warm Nights are for Cricket</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">Moran &amp; Tommy</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/30/interview-hamid-stardom-and-the-difference-threshold/">Hamid</a></p>
<p><strong>We&#8217;d like to conclude this anniversary post by thanking everyone who has been part of the discussion this past year</strong> &#8211; reading, commenting, critiquing, supporting, following, contributing photos and story ideas and event announcements &#8211; we appreciate it all and look forward to another year of <span class="userContent">diversity, difference, and positive discourse!</span></p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By</em> <em><strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em> <em>and</em> <em><strong>Kelly Miller</strong> </em></p>
<p>First photo by Anna Meister, second photo by Collidoscope Berlin, third photo by <a href="http://jurigottschau.com/">Juri Gottschau</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/22/the-collidoscope-manifesto/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: Difference in the Wet Country</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2014 12:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[provincial]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1986</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For nearly a month this holiday season, I explored the social fabric surrounding my US origins with a German national, who had never before been to the land of plenty. Through the fresh eyes of 'the foreigner', I saw my part of America unfold under a curious and critical lens. America is a country that defines itself by historical narratives of migration and manifest destiny. What one encounters on the road in its northwestern corner, however, is a bit more mundane. At closer glance, emptiness and the prosaic everyday give food for thought, in regards to locating and valuing difference wherever it bubbles up...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>How do you notice difference in a city, in which you yourself are different?</strong></p>
<div id="attachment_1992" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1992" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1992 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-1.jpg" alt="Portland, OR steel-bridge" width="640" height="360" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1992" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>For nearly a month this holiday season, I explored the social fabric surrounding my US origins with a German national, who had never before been to the land of plenty. Through the fresh eyes of &#8216;the foreigner&#8217;, I saw my part of America unfold under a curious and critical lens. Given this blog&#8217;s weekly critical handling of all things multicultural in the big city, why not talk about diversity in an American context? This context proves to be quite different from the aspiring-cosmopolitan intersections of the German capital, as shocking as that may or may not be.</p>
<p>America is a country that defines itself by historical narratives of migration and manifest destiny. What one encounters on the road in its northwestern corner, however, is a bit more mundane. At closer glance, emptiness and the prosaic everyday give food for thought, in regards to locating and valuing difference wherever it bubbles up.</p>
<p><strong>Geography matters</strong></p>
<p>Somehow, when we talk of diversity in society, the role of space therein is a side note. In fact, where we live, work, play, learn, and heal in many ways determines our belonging to or exclusion from social and economic groups that are important in ensuring opportunity.</p>
<p>Maps tell us a lot about how different ways of life can exist cohesively together. Maps may miss, however (<a href="http://www.npr.org/censusmap/#4.00/39.00/-84.00">see NPR&#8217;s US census map</a>), where difference pops up beyond the packed hotbeds for multiculturalism of the city, leaving our eyes to experience what the provinces, the forgotten towns, and the coastal sticks have to offer firsthand.</p>
<div id="attachment_1989" style="width: 311px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1989" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1989 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg" alt="Rebecca Vincent" width="301" height="300" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg 301w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent-300x299.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 301px) 100vw, 301px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1989" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Rebecca Vincent</p></div>
<p>In the Pacific Northwest, like many other regions, cartography shows the urban as an array of ever-revolving grids, residences dotting the margins of concrete webs and precise civil engineering, greenery contained, parks splashed with beige and lived-in browns. One passes through these strange boundaries of growth, as if moving through the trunk of a tree to reach its core, each ring giving way to new densities and shapes of living, suburbia giving way to semi-rural apartment clusters and neatly arranged town homes.</p>
<div id="attachment_2001" style="width: 471px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2001" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2001  " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png?w=640" alt="portland map" width="461" height="347" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png 646w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map-300x226.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map-80x60.png 80w" sizes="(max-width: 461px) 100vw, 461px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2001" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Mappery.com</p></div>
<p>Apart from the patterns and markings of cities, great expanses of forest or farmland separate bundles of life from one another. Beyond the edge of the urban, an emptiness emerges. Where cities end, mountain pass truck-stops, wine-making valleys, flat dairy country, coastal trailer parks, and retired logging towns begin. Vehicles connect what trains used to. Marks on the map created for the movement between these revolving grids begin to surface like geometric occurrences of ink. Here humans somehow ended up, often fairly alone with only the company of a gas station and a corner store.</p>
<div id="attachment_2002" style="width: 476px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2002" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2002   " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png?w=640" alt="oregon map" width="466" height="375" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png 749w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map-300x241.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map-650x522.png 650w" sizes="(max-width: 466px) 100vw, 466px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2002" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Oregon Office of Rural Health</p></div>
<p>Passing through such places on the road from one side of the state of Oregon to the next, the new set of eyes saw only distance, forged together by oil rigs and spinning tires. <em>Density can be an advantage, when it comes to social and cultural encounters needed for intercultural understandings to take root</em>, I thought, as we searched for a place to eat on a long stretch that seemed to allow only signage, fast food, and campgrounds.</p>
<div id="attachment_1990" style="width: 471px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-2.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1990" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-1990 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-2.jpg" alt="Portland, OR steel-bridge " width="461" height="614" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1990" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>And yet, the migrant worker shantytown in Southwest Washington, the Korean BBQ embedded in the Tillamook state forest, the sushi bar near Mt. Hood’s base, the taco trucks at truck-stops, the Chinese waiter at the roadside diner all suggest that even in more expansive geographies, difference can occur.</p>
<p><strong>Just because it is there, doesn&#8217;t mean we will notice it</strong></p>
<p>On our way to the valley of the Rogue River, our over-sized vehicle wound down the Pacific Highway, hugging cliffs of the sea and the edges of a strange poverty. We saw mile after mile of rotting cottages, mobile homes made more mobile by landslides, empty villages with the local pub serving bento, tacos, and chowder, and liquor stores the size of the local church beside it. Catholic churches sprouted up in these towns, in the basin of the interstate or at the rim of the sea &#8211; something I did not take notice of at first, but which suggested some shift, an immigration. Those who find ships in the right season or canneries with need for cheaply-bought hands make their way back to the Saints to thank them for their providence, or so it seemed.</p>
<p>In the foggy valleys of dead logging towns, the basin of the interstate, the depressed dairy lands and empty harbors: here the German traveler experienced my part of America with its shady diners where breakfast and hot sauce are served all day, roadside shacks with a For Sale sign, Walmart’s to nowhere. And in between the lines, difference was there, simply glossed over by the mundanity of its appearance, bearing more than John Wayne&#8217;s Americana.</p>
<div id="attachment_1994" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/streeet.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1994" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-1994 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/streeet.jpg?w=640" alt="street Portland, OR" width="640" height="360" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1994" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>The churches that never cease to be obvious and enormous on major highways; the Mexican restaurants with happy signs and plenty of American families digging into re-fried beans and rice, as if it were the national dish; the Japanese restaurants with pictures of majestic mountains that could be local; medical advertisements with black patients and Asian doctors; a South Asian newscaster in a suit just like everybody else; a black reporter stuck to sports on the local news station: these things I may not have noticed without the presence of the new perspective next to me.</p>
<p><strong>It is not about what we say, but about what is heard</strong></p>
<div id="attachment_1991" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/diner-pwf-0066.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1991" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-1991" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/diner-pwf-0066.jpg?w=300" alt="Photo source: Paul Winch-Furness" width="300" height="199" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1991" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Paul Winch-Furness</p></div>
<p>For the German&#8217;s second breakfast in America, we took him to a local diner in southwest Washington with the classic booths and red upholstery, simple fried numbers, and a healthy rotation of pies. As he ordered, his slight accent turned the words into mildly different sounds, his tongue pushing just a bit too far back for the &#8216;l&#8217; and the &#8216;th&#8217; sticking to the front of his teeth. The letters may have come together in a way that did not quite fit the frames we have learned to repeat, but one could and can simply understand. And so &#8216;the waffle special&#8217; was transmitted to the kitchen with no questions asked. And after we had told the waitress in her darling little apron that it was his first time in an American diner, she beamed at the foreigner sitting there in front of the simple white dishware and the paper napkin. She whispered to the other waitress, who, blushing, came over to our table to pour coffee and welcome him to town.</p>
<p>It is not about the sounds being right. It is about our understanding them.</p>
<p><strong>Being an outsider can come in handy, as I have learned on the other side of the Atlantic</strong></p>
<p>Growing up in the far corner of the Western United States, I am familiar with the figures and curves of this particular landscape and society. I have, however, sorely taken for granted what it means to have tacos in the middle of nowhere, to celebrate Persian New Year with friends, or to consider Phở as American as bratwurst (I can thank Seattle for that). In many ways, difference was a natural part of my private and public education, the neighborhoods where I lived, the sports teams I played on, and the churches I attended. I cannot say that I have consciously valued these experiences for what I learned from them. If such encounters and relationships had popped up in my Berlin world, I would have celebrated them. This is largely due to the ways in which diversity is or is not celebrated by society at large and how we might attempt to remedy this fact.</p>
<p>But what is most striking and assuredly the take-away from this tale is that campaign-worthy diversity in the big city is not all there is, nor is it of greater value than the outcroppings of difference at truck-stops off the interstate. This might be where it counts the most.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Ethno-cultural diversity is changing the face of the rural United States, including states like Oregon and Washington. For a great visual of this transformation, see the <a href="http://www.ers.usda.gov/media/176091/page7.pdf">United States Department of Agriculture&#8217;s map from its Rural Population and Migration Brieﬁng Room</a>. As the roadside taco trucks and shantytowns demonstrate, a large wave of migration from Latin America to the Pacific Northwest region has characterized rural growth from 2000-2012, according to the <a href="http://www.ers.usda.gov/amber-waves/2011-december/hispanics-contribute-to-increasing-diversity.aspx#.Ut5lnRA1iM8">USDA&#8217;s recent report</a> on demography. Reflective of this shift to the out-country from the urban heart, is the <a href="http://www.oregonlive.com/pacific-northwest-news/index.ssf/2011/04/in_portlands_heart_diversity_dwindles.html">dwindling diversity in the heart of Portland, OR</a>. Difference is, thus, not always where you expect to find it.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rave: a Colombian Culinary Homecoming</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/12/11/rave-a-colombian-culinary-homecoming/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/12/11/rave-a-colombian-culinary-homecoming/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2013 12:18:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Colombia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cultural diplomacy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ex-pat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[food]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1851</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What role do embassies play in the lives of foreign nationals abroad? Beyond pure administration and diplomacy, cultural events that allow for a homecoming, a return to childhood, and a bringing together of compatriots might change how immigrants and expats live abroad and the involvement of embassies and consulates therein. The Embassy of Columbia in Berlin sponsored an event that did something just like this. A few weeks ago in Neukölln, Colombians and non-Colombians united over the genius of duck woven into starch - the duck, a true Berliner...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/columbia.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1874" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/columbia.jpg?w=640" alt="columbia" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/columbia.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/columbia-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/columbia-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>What role do embassies play in the lives of foreign nationals abroad? Many of us living in a country for which we do not possess a passport are likely to associate our local embassy with administrative assistance, i.e. replacing documents needed to prove our identity and belonging in the international system. In many public discussions of transnationalism and cosmopolitanism, the nation-state can take on an equally administrative face. <em>It&#8217;s all about technology, no longer about borders or space; the world is post-modern, and so is identity.</em></p>
<p>As the anthropologist <a href="http://www.arjunappadurai.org/">Arjun Appadurai </a>preached in the 1990s, human societies are experiencing a &#8216;deterritorialization&#8217;, making the nation-state less and less relevant for our real lives, its relevance relegated to the small tasks we rely on for bureaucratic systems to function properly.</p>
<p>But it is <em>not </em>this black and white. For those of us who have lived apart from all that was <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/16/lens-going-away/">once familiar and full of memory</a> for a period longer than the term &#8216;abroad&#8217; can afford, the food &#8211; most importantly &#8211; of the former territory of &#8216;home&#8217; becomes something we long for.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/colombian-culinary_fried-plantains.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter  wp-image-1875" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/colombian-culinary_fried-plantains.jpg?w=640" alt="Colombian Culinary_fried plantains" width="384" height="512" /></a></p>
<p>And so this rave asks a simple question: What if (nation-)states and their representative institutions abroad played both a symbolic and tangible role in the lives of immigrants holding passports from these places?</p>
<p>There happens to be an example for such, namely the Embassy of Colombia in Germany and its recent culinary festival:</p>
<p>A few weeks ago, Sophia and I were invited to this special event, meant to recreate the flavors of many a Colombian childhood in a chic Neukölln space for foodies &#8211; <a href="http://www.feinschlicht.de/">Manufaktur Feinschlicht</a> &#8211; complete with a charming Ambassador and homesick interns. The event was the backdrop to the presentation of a cook book straight out of the homeland, entitled <em>Colombia, Cooking by Regions</em> by Maria Lía Neira Restrepo. With a  full culinary program, using ingredients one can find here in Germany, two worlds were forged on a brisk Berlin evening. This union meant homecoming for some and travel for others.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/colombian-culinary_candles-table.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1880" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/colombian-culinary_candles-table.jpg?w=640" alt="Colombian Culinary_Candles table" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>Renowned chef <a href="http://www.restaurantedianagarcia.com/home.html">Diana Garcia</a>, featured in <em>Colombia, Cooking by Regions</em>, was flown out to Berlin for the event, along with pal, chef Magda Hamon. The two women brought decades of experience, a power house of flavor, and the openness and friendly encounter akin to a family Sunday dinner (for those of us that remember those).</p>
<p>The women were paired with two German chefs &#8211; both looking a bit like they should be flinging fish at Pike Place Market, rather than managing finger foods. In minutes the kitchen and serving foyer were a buzz with the good vibes of cross-cultural collaboration. The Germans, Kai and Robert, filleted brined salmon with rough hands, delicately arranging plates of plantain-based crostini, while the two Colombian ladies tended large cuts of pork belly and whisked various sauces to life in the kitchen.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/colombian-embassy-party-001-embassy-deriv.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1877" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/colombian-embassy-party-001-embassy-deriv.jpg?w=640" alt="colombian-embassy-party-001 embassy deriv" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/colombian-embassy-party-001-embassy-deriv.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/colombian-embassy-party-001-embassy-deriv-300x199.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Photo Source: Colombian Embassy</p>
<p>The chefs delivered the beautifully-presented treats to the guests themselves, wandering through the room in white coats, making eye contact with eager mouths, answering questions about ingredients and origin, making all feel welcome to partake in something, well, just great and gluttonous.</p>
<p>Glorifying both the Berlin environs and Colombian roots, it was easy to relate to the enthusiasm and personal connection to the dishes that seemed obvious through taste and composition.</p>
<p>10 waves of savory bites passed through the intimate space where we all gathered around the bar, which never failed to serve up rows of guava-rum puree, delicate glasses of Prosecco, and bottles of rich Colombian wine (both red <em>and </em>white, and both delicious). Surrounded by the chutneys and other jarred creations of <a href="http://www.feinschlicht.de/">Manufaktur Feinschlicht</a>, the ever-increasing guests eyed the prep table and the hall to the kitchen, anxiously awaiting the rolling arrival of new platters and, above all, the kind-eyed and wide-smiled chefs.</p>
<p><em>Colombia is a country of flowers and fruits &#8211; we hope you will taste that! We also love meat, </em>Diana Garcia told the crowd, beaming and laughing a bit in the face of so many cameras.</p>
<p>Pork belly in a muddy water sauce with Berlin&#8217;s (happy) <em>Schwein</em>; fried plantain with a cheese crust; <em>lox</em> on potato-pillows with a healthy dollop of guacamole; breaded and seared scallops on coconut rice (the coconut hailing from the coastal region of Colombia, according to the chefs); creme de leche in pieces big enough to give the teeth something to work on; a creamy pudding enveloping local fruits and Colombian flowers; <em>Currywurst</em> with a bit of guava in the sauce; duck rice with a Berlin-grown bird: all with both decadence and simplicity.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/colombian-culinary_scallop.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter  wp-image-1876" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/colombian-culinary_scallop.jpg?w=640" alt="Colombian Culinary_Scallop" width="384" height="512" /></a></p>
<p>The young Colombians around me, most of them with positions at the embassy or friends with such coveted diplomatic jobs, celebrated every dish, every reference to summers on the coast, to lunches with grandma, to the country&#8217;s everyday bounty becoming so special through distance.</p>
<p><em>Guava, milk pudding: my favorite things! </em>Hector Sanchez, one of the embassy interns told me, after I openly praised the addition of guava to everything forever and ever. He has <em>been away from Colombia for longer than ever</em>, was studying in Geneva before coming to Berlin, and will be in Berlin for at least one year. <em>I enjoy Berlin because here, everyone fits,</em> even the Colombians. <em>Here I can relax and feel at home</em>, he said, eyeing the second round of <em>Chicharrones</em> and speaking a few adoring words to the room and the chef, the crunchy skin sliding into his mouth.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/colombian-culinary_hector.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter  wp-image-1878" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/colombian-culinary_hector.jpg?w=640" alt="Colombian Culinary_Hector" width="384" height="512" /></a></p>
<p>When I asked if it is easy to recreate these Colombian flavors in Berlin &#8211; <em>I have heard that there is a Colombian food store in Mehringdamm, but I&#8217;ve never been there. </em>I couldn&#8217;t seem to find it either. Jaggery, fresh sugar cane, or guava punch are ever elusive, it seems. We talked about the role of the embassy, how such institutions are charged with many often symbolic tasks, such as this one. But it isn&#8217;t symbolic, <em>it reminds me of home</em>, he added.</p>
<p>And so, <em>What do you want Germans to know about Colombia, about Colombians?, </em>I asked, really having no anticipated answer to this question, which is rare, when I choose to ask one. <em>I want them to know that Colombia is changing. It used to be dangerous, but things are getting better. Change, Change! </em>I mentioned that many associate Colombia with films about drug cartels trucking cocaine across the desert in military fatigues. <em>In Bogota it is cold, like 18 degrees all the time and is at a high elevation! And the coastal region is beautiful and where many of these foods come from. You don&#8217;t see that in the</em> <em>movies</em>, he added, a bit flustered. <em> </em></p>
<p>Something about this event &#8211; its emphasis on the cuisine from both the mountainous and the coastal regions &#8211; calls such stereotypes into question.</p>
<p>The Ambassador, dressed in a casual sweater and wearing an academic&#8217;s spectacles, sought eye contact with all in attendance, his wife bejeweled and well-outfitted taking the lead to greet familiar faces. They seemed to be enjoying themselves, indulging and delighting in each and every symbol and real taste of home. The diplomats, other women and men in suits, began to undo ties and remove jackets, as the evening progressed. The room warmed and filled with chatter &#8211; Spanish the dominant language; a few bloggers and friends with mustaches speaking a mix of English and German made the room feel even smaller, though softly lit.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/chandelier-2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1883" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/chandelier-2.jpg?w=640" alt="Chandelier 2" width="640" height="657" /></a></p>
<p>After the first two courses had made their rounds, a petite, young woman with a long-lensed camera and a wide grin marched confidently up to our group of wine-drinking Germans and expats, introducing herself with the line: <i>Hi, I&#8217;m from the Philippines! </i>Her husband, standing next to her in somber blacks, works for the Embassy of the Philippines in Berlin. He was raised in Chicago, Seattle, and Russia by a diplomatic father from the Philippines and a Spanish mother. Quite the childhood. Previously, the two had lived in Jakarta, having first met in Manila. Now, she runs a blog on her everyday life as a <a href="http://thediplomaticwife.com/blog/">Diplomatic Wife</a>, with the tagline &#8220;livin&#8217; life DiploStyle&#8221;.</p>
<p>DiploWife seemed to know many faces at the event. She <em>was invited by the Ambassador&#8217;s wife herself after meeting through the organization <a href="http://www.willkommen-in-berlin.de/">Willkommen in Berlin</a>, </em>she told me &#8211; a club for diplomats and their spouses, sponsored by the German Ministry for Foreign Affairs. The &#8220;Diplo-life&#8221; may be full of constant change and adaptation, but Berlin provides a community just for her type, as I somehow expected it would. <em>Everyone fits</em>, as Hector Sanchez said (or at least many).</p>
<p>As I turned to leave, I made sure to tell Hector that Colombia was no longer just cartels, cocaine, and Hollywood desert in my mind: <em>the food was delicious and exciting &#8211; I love guava!</em>  He seemed pleased, his eyes lightening with pride and appreciation. Delighting in a fresh avocado, picking up grains of pork-soaked rice with finger tips, sipping on guava juice, as if it were the elixir of home: this is how I left Hector Sanchez, culinary talent, and the rest of the Colombian Embassy. I knew, however, that I was not the only one to have fallen in love with Colombian food and two of its best chefs.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/colombian-embassy-party-002.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1882" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/colombian-embassy-party-002.jpg?w=640" alt="colombian-embassy-party-002" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/colombian-embassy-party-002.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/colombian-embassy-party-002-300x199.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Photo Source: Colombian Embassy</p>
<p>Now, don&#8217;t we just wish more embassies would take it upon themselves to allow us momentary homecoming, recreating childhood favorites and bringing people together over a symbolic table, reminiscent of a modern, finger-food Sunday dinner?</p>
<p>Part educational institution, part diplomatic agency, and most importantly, part expat/transnational hub of programming: this should be the new role of embassies, particularly in a city as diverse and adventurous as Berlin. It might just bring more of the locals together with some of its newcomers, uniting over the genius of duck woven into starch, particularly if this duck just happens to be a Berliner.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The Colombian community in Berlin is certainly not all food and drink &#8211; there are organizations which lobby for the kind of &#8216;change&#8217; Hector mentioned, encouraging enhanced human rights and an end to instability and insecurity. More information can be found with <a href="http://kolko.net/">Kolko e.V.</a>, based in Berlin. To find out more about events of the Colombian embassy in Berlin, as well as consulates around Germany, visit their <a href="http://www.botschaft-kolumbien.de/de_index.htm">German website</a> and <a href="http://www.consuladocolombia-berlin.de/">Berlin homepage</a>. And lastly, check out <a href="http://thediplomaticwife.com/blog/?s=Colombia">Diplomatic Wife&#8217;s numerous posts on the Colombian Food Festival.</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/12/11/rave-a-colombian-culinary-homecoming/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
