<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Roma &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/roma/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Lens: Four Hours at Lageso</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2015 00:01:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bureaucracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moabit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4145</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is Lageso (Das Landesamt für Gesundheit und Soziales), the State Office for Health and Social Affairs. This is Berlin's primary registration center for the initial reception of asylum seekers. This is Germany's most infamous symbol of the refugee crisis. Two days prior I had signed up to volunteer on a website called Volunteer Planner. After a cursory registration process, a click of a button was all it took to commit to a shift at a registration center, refugee home, or other institution in the city where help is needed (read: basically everywhere).  ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4323 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-650x319.png" alt="boys_lageso" width="650" height="319" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-650x319.png 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-300x147.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>A curly-haired two year old hangs from my hip. His modest number of pounds start to wear on my side as I spin us back and forth in the narrow space. By some stroke of luck he has yet to start crying (this doesn&#8217;t last). He giggles, bouncing up and down, as if we are playing a game. &#8220;He seems to like you,&#8221; a volunteer next to me looks on and smiles, &#8220;almost like he wants to go home with you.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;He may have to,&#8221; I mutter in response. It has been a long ten minutes since I last saw his mother. I try desperately to remember her face &#8211; or at least the color of her headscarf. My voice starts to crack and I realize in horror a cold is coming on (&#8220;Am I infecting hundreds of refugees?&#8221;). A few minutes later we find her, a pair of black shoes in her hands. She holds them up proudly and points to herself. We are only supposed to be finding clothes for her son and she knows it, but I let her take the shoes and boy (now crying), and go.</p>
<p>Curly-haired boy and his mother are my latest charges from the never-ending mass of parents and children waiting to be accompanied down the hallway of donated clothing. This group is only a microcosm of the larger crowd waiting outside in the evening twilight where volunteers pass out hot tea and coffee. Kids get <em>Kinderschokolade </em>and granola bars. The building entrance is guarded to ensure not everyone infiltrates the chaos at once.</p>
<p>Back inside, a winter jacket and pair of warm shoes are the big prizes. Our chief responsibility is to make sure each child walks out with just one of each. I negotiate with parents: &#8220;She can have that coat, but you&#8217;ll need to give me the one she&#8217;s wearing now.&#8221; When language fails, I make a trading gesture with my hands or remove the jacket from the child&#8217;s back myself. How quickly the urge to be generous is superseded by pragmatism (&#8220;Even <em>I</em> could get by with only one coat&#8221;).</p>
<p>&#8220;You have to be careful,&#8221; a middle-aged female volunteer warns me as I re-fold a stack of jeans, &#8220;Roma families sneak in to take clothing and then sell it at the flea market.&#8221; I nod but am at a loss as to what to do with the information. Is she advocating that we start using racial profiling? Regardless of the Roma, some families may have already taken their turn down the hallway. Others could be successfully registered and in possession of their <a href="http://www.euronews.com/2015/09/16/which-european-countries-offer-the-most-social-benefits-to-migrants/">monthly stipend</a>. There&#8217;s really no way to tell.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4321 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_0599" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Our makeshift shopping strip consists of one narrow hallway and a back room for sorting and storage. On either side of the hallway are smaller rooms the size of coat checks, one holding clothing for adults and the other medicine and hygienic articles. It is very cramped. Fathers plea with volunteers for their family&#8217;s turn down the hallway. Once in, mothers rip clothing off hangers to hold up to their children and approximate size. Some kids are fussy about colors; others peer up with wide eyes and tightly pressed lips. Volunteers buzz by in a flurry of aspired productivity and surveillance, their name-tags as frayed as their nerves.</p>
<p>A cameraman waltzes in with his crew. The bright lens focuses on me as I kneel down to re-velcro a young boy&#8217;s shoes. We have yet to find boots that fit; these blue sandals are the ones in which he arrived to Germany, completely ill-suited for the looming winter. We both turn, squint, and smile anyway. This is the shot they want, and they are gone within the minute.</p>
<p>This is Lageso (<em>Das Landesamt </em><span class="st"><em>für Gesundheit und Soziales)</em>, the State Office for Health and Social Affairs</span>. This is <span class="st">Berlin&#8217;s primary registration center for the initial reception of asylum seekers. This is Germany&#8217;s most infamous symbol of the refugee crisis.</span></p>
<p>Two days prior I had signed up to volunteer on a website called <a href="https://volunteer-planner.org/">Volunteer Planner</a>. After a cursory registration process, a click of a button was all it took to commit to a shift at a registration center, refugee home, or other institution in the city where help is needed (read: basically everywhere).  An impressive resource to get people engaged quickly, though seemingly lacking any accountability for volunteers who fail to show up or for organizations advertising shifts that fall through or no longer exist (the day before I was turned away from a home in Schöneberg because the coordinator was not present).</p>
<p>In addition to locations, one can select specific tasks. This is an all-hands-on-deck scenario and there is something for everyone, from Arabic and Farsi interpretation (in high demand) to kitchen assistance and coffee distribution. At Lageso, I sign up to be a <em>Springer/in </em>or &#8220;Jumper&#8221;, who, according to the website, &#8220;helps wherever is most needed, is assigned to a team, and will be led by hand to their task.&#8221;</p>
<p>But upon arrival I am not assigned to a team nor led anywhere, let alone by hand. After finding a sticker on which to scribble my name, I walk around aimlessly until a smiley blond girl takes pity on me and leads me to the storage room. A few minutes later I am with a new girl who is in a room within this room, sorting through boxes of clothing donations in the dark. I glance at the heaps of dusty sweaters and immediately regret not having brought my allergy medicine.</p>
<p>We start unpacking boxes of blankets. &#8220;Is there somewhere specific we should put these?&#8221; I ask my sorting partner. She shrugs. &#8220;On those shelves, I think,&#8221; she says, pointing to the overstuffed racks behind us. Ten minutes later, another volunteer: &#8220;No, don&#8217;t unpack the blankets,&#8221; he instructs us in a mix of German and English. &#8220;Put them in a corner so we can take them to a refugee home later.&#8221;</p>
<p>I give up on the blankets and turn my attention to the clothes. Thankfully, some boxes are categorized, and I pick up one marked &#8220;children&#8221;. I plan to sort the contents and add them to the shelves, which are loosely organized by gender and size. In one pair of pants I notice a bulge in the pocket and pull out a knife. I pass it along to a guy with a clipboard who looks like he knows what he is doing. He turns and sets it on another shelf, near a box of children&#8217;s toys.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4322 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_0600" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>I&#8217;m finally getting into a groove when another volunteer comes up behind me, visibly frustrated. &#8220;I spent days putting this together and now everyone&#8217;s destroying it,&#8221; she complains to clipboard guy, motioning to the overflowing shelves. He glances up over his glasses. &#8220;We&#8217;ll discuss it at Monday&#8217;s meeting,&#8221; he promises. I don&#8217;t know what I&#8217;ve done wrong, but I am sure of two things: We are all working on top of one another and there is no one in charge.</p>
<p>When the refugee crisis became front page news this past summer, thousands of Germany&#8217;s residents jumped to provide clothing and supplies, offer short-term housing solutions, or pass out sandwiches to refugees as they poured into train stations around the country. Many continue to help, some using vacation days to do so. On a civilian level, the outpouring of support in Germany has been heart-warming, encouraging, even pride-inducing.</p>
<p>Charitable and non-profit initiatives also abound. Groups have launched fundraising efforts to help those in particularly dire situations, like this <a href="https://www.betterplace.org/de/projects/37503-hilfe-fur-familie-ahmed">Iraqi father who suffered a heart attack</a>. There are <a href="http://www.unhcr.org/5655d27f6.html">bike riding lessons</a> for women and <a href="http://www.abendblatt-berlin.de/2015/12/03/ein-zirkus-fuer-die-gute-sache/">circus activities</a> for kids. A local photographer has started a &#8220;<a href="https://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.400616063468410.1073741835.295071407356210&amp;type=3">Humans of Lageso&#8221; page</a> to shed light on individual refugee stories. Herbert Grönemeyer, a famous German singer, has <a href="http://www.stern.de/lifestyle/leute/lageso-in-berlin---herbert-groenemeyer-finanziert-waermebusse-fuer-fluechtlinge-6605406.html">financed heated buses</a> so those waiting to register at Lageso can take turns warming up.</p>
<p><span class="st">But civilian good-will and a display of <span class="st"><em>Willkommenskultur</em></span> (welcome culture) can only go so far in serving the approximately 800,000 asylum seekers that Germany will receive this year &#8211; a figure that is <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/sep/06/refugee-crisis-germany-response-heartwarming-will-pressures-show">more a projection than a guest list</a>. What some in Berlin may call growing pains in learning to accommodate unprecedented waves of refugees, others deem a failure of the system and local leadership. German towns such as Passau, a Bavarian town of 50,000, have cited <a href="http://nmd.bn02750.bethemd.wayport.net/index.adp?MacAddr=68%3aA8%3a6D%3a4B%3a7A%3a8C&amp;IpAddr=10.128.29.239&amp;Ip6Addr=&amp;vsgpId=&amp;vsgId=41975&amp;UserAgent=&amp;ProxyHost=&amp;TunnelIfId=95270&amp;VlanId=20">much more success in handling the inflow</a>.</span></p>
<p><span class="st">The press have reported on the turbulent conditions at Lageso ad nauseam, both locally and <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/11/27/world/europe/germany-berlin-migrants-refugees.html?_r=0">internationally</a>. Refugees wait for weeks if not months to be registered. They line up for hours each day, often beginning the night before. People sleep in the streets. Most don&#8217;t receive enough to eat and drink. Heated tents were only made available <a href="http://www.stilinberlin.de/2015/12/fugeela-refugees-in-berlin-6-html.html">a few days ago</a>. &#8220;Refugee crisis? More like bureaucratic crisis!&#8221; protesters chanted <a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/1678473329031122/">on November 29th</a>, calling the local government to action. Understaffed and overworked employees have anonymously <a href="http://www.rbb-online.de/politik/thema/fluechtlinge/berlin/2015/12/lageso-innenansichten-mitarbeiter.html">detailed the on-going chaos</a> to the press. On December 10th, the Head of Lageso, Franz Allert, was <a href="http://www.focus.de/politik/deutschland/migration-lageso-chef-tritt-zurueck_id_5143744.html">pushed into resignation</a>. </span></p>
<p>Curly-haired boy and his mom are back outside, but at least now with warmer feet and some chocolate in their bellies. I pull my phone out of my pocket: three and a half hours have passed. There isn&#8217;t an eight hour work day in recent memory I can remember having been more exhausting. Admiration for the other volunteers &#8211; many of whom do this regularly, including night shifts &#8211; rushes within me. As does panic. The support is incredible, but is it sustainable?</p>
<p>We need to get this right, and not just in the short-term.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By<strong> Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>For up to date information in English on the refugee situation in Berlin, we recommend reading the <a href="http://www.stilinberlin.de/?s=FuGeeLa">FuGeeLa updates</a> by Stil in Berlin. <a href="http://www.findingberlin.com/how-to-help-refugees-in-berlin-winter-2015/">Finding Berlin</a> also provides comprehensive resources for how to help. </em></p>
<p><em>To sign up for volunteer shifts in Berlin, try <a href="https://volunteer-planner.org/helpdesk/">Volunteer Planner</a> (in German) or look for opportunities through <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">Give Something Back to Berlin</a> (in English). <a href="http://moabit-hilft.com/">MoabitHilft</a> is very engaged at Lageso and many of the regular volunteers at the center are affiliated with this organization.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>If you are donating clothing to refugee homes, please do your best to package them by type (e.g. age and size) and consider buying socks which are often in short supply. Even better: check first with the home to see what is most needed!</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Roma in Berlin: Bureaucracy in Lichtenberg</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/20/roma-in-berlin-bureaucracy-in-lichtenberg/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/20/roma-in-berlin-bureaucracy-in-lichtenberg/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2013 14:39:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bureaucracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[discrimination]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lichtenberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1736</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On the first Tuesday of every month, the <em><a href="http://www.migrantenrat.de/">Migrantenrat Lichtenberg</a> </em>(immigrants' plenary) meets to address issues of migration affecting the district and its neighborhoods. The gospel of November's session: The Roma are coming! 2014 will be a year of change for Roma in Berlin, primarily for those who have come from Bulgaria and Romania. They will have access to the social welfare system, the situation will change dramatically. But this is about families, not simply numbers...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;<a href="http://www.bild.de/geld/wirtschaft/zuwanderung/droht-uns-eine-roma-welle-29296194.bild.htmlhttp://www.bild.de/geld/wirtschaft/zuwanderung/droht-uns-eine-roma-welle-29296194.bild.html">Is a wave of Roma threatening Germany?</a>&#8221; was the recent headline of a popular paper, known for its tabloid-esque reporting. In the Eastern district of Lichtenberg, this headline becomes bureaucracy. In reality, it is about parents, children, and families, who happen to be Roma.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/roma-familie_dokumentationszentrum.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/roma-familie_dokumentationszentrum.jpg?w=640" alt="Roma Familie_Dokumentationszentrum" width="512" height="392" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.sintiundroma.de/start.html">Source</a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">For my fieldwork in sociocultural anthropology, I run from one site of so-called immigrant integration to the next in the Berlin districts of Lichtenberg and Marzahn, doing my best to put together a structure that informs a system of practice. Within the waiting rooms and narrow offices of institutions serving immigrants, Roma are present and obvious, sticking out like a sore thumb without the opportunity for dialogue; they are talked about or talked around. <strong>And so one cannot talk about migration, diversity, and multicultural inclusion in Berlin without talking about how Lichtenberg talks about Roma.</strong></p>
<p>On the first Tuesday of every month, the <em><a href="http://www.migrantenrat.de/">Migrantenrat Lichtenberg</a> </em>(immigrants&#8217; plenary) meets to address issues of migration affecting the district and its neighborhoods. Tables are pushed together to frame a discussion, and the renovated walls of the Lichtenberg city hall fill with urgent  deliberation. The gospel of November&#8217;s session: <strong>The Roma are coming!</strong></p>
<p>At this month&#8217;s plenary, approx. 20 Berliners were in attendance. Based on attire and commentary, bureaucrats from the district employment office (Job Center) and volunteer representatives of  ethnic-cultural organizations of immigrant populations mingled with local political officers. The new district <a href="http://www.berlin.de/ba-lichtenberg/politik/integrationsbeauftragte01.html">commissioner for integration</a>, Bärbel Olhagaray, was presiding &#8211; speaking perfect <em>hochdeutsch, </em>pursing her lips after every third word. But <em>I am married to a Chilean</em>, she remarked in her introduction, one among many reasons why she is an advocate for immigrant integration.</p>
<div id="attachment_1761" style="width: 425px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/baerbel.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1761" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1761 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/baerbel.jpg" alt="baerbel" width="415" height="620" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/baerbel.jpg 415w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/baerbel-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 415px) 100vw, 415px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1761" class="wp-caption-text">Frau Bärbel Olhagaray, Integration Commissioner of Lichtenberg</p></div>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.berliner-woche.de/nachrichten/bezirk-lichtenberg/artikel/29620-baerbel-olhagaray-ist-die-neue-beauftragte-fuer-integration-in-lichtenberg/">Source</a></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5;">She offered the opening address, the title of which was &#8216;Roma in Lichtenberg&#8217;. </span><span style="line-height: 1.5;">The speech began with numbers.</span></p>
<p><em><span style="line-height: 1.5;">Roma number about 800 to 900 in Lichtenberg, though many, many more are to be expected. There are three apartment complexes known to house predominately Roma families in our district, characterized by negligent landlords and overpriced rent. We approached these residences as a reaction to complaints in the area. <strong>Families of 6 occupy 30 square meters for a price of 600 Euros, sleeping nearly shoulder-to-shoulder.</strong> The houses lack consistent ways to dispose of waste. Our priorities are to reinstate order and cleanliness and to visit the families regularly to see what is needed.</span></em></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/fennpfuhl.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1758" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/fennpfuhl.jpg?w=640" alt="Fennpfuhl" width="640" height="382" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/fennpfuhl.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/fennpfuhl-300x179.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/fennpfuhl-650x388.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.jeder-qm-du.de/platten-doku/platten-wissen/detail/wbsqp-71-r/">Source</a></p>
<p>But figures and living situations do not matter as much as Euros, at least as policy demonstrates. The economic element of Roma immigration is the primary reason the &#8216;Roma problem&#8217; has gained attention and notoriety, particularly in districts overwhelmed by rumors that may prove to be true.</p>
<p>Since Bulgaria and Romania&#8217;s entrance into the European Union&#8217;s economic area, which allows for the transference of work permission and skills from one member state to the next, only partial admission into the German job market has been granted for citizens from these countries. Citing a wave of unqualified workers, often illiterate, into a strong market-driven economy, i.e. a wave of Roma, this act of exclusion became German federal policy. According to the European Union, Germany was acting in violation of economic rules of engagement and must retract its restricted work policy for immigrants from Bulgaria and Romania at the start of 2014. This affects Roma.</p>
<p><strong><em>Most of the families are registered as self-employed</em>, Mrs. Olhagaray continued, <em>since they do not yet have the full benefits of EU citizenship, which grants them state assistance in many cases of difficulty. </em></strong>They wash windshields at traffic lights, peddle on the U-Bahn, play music in front of the mall entrance and somehow make ends meet.<em> They send most of their kids to school, as far as we are aware, and ensure that they learn German while they are there.</em></p>
<p>When she and her colleagues go by for a visit, she added, they are greeted with open arms, tea, and cake. <em>They know we are there to help them&#8230;and they need our help.</em></p>
<p>The room became silent, waiting for the evident problem to become clear.</p>
<p><strong><em>2014 will be a year of change for Roma in Berlin, primarily for those who have come from Bulgaria and Romania.</em> </strong><em><strong>They will have access to the social welfare system, the situation will change dramatically</strong>, </em>full stop.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/zigeuner.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1762" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/zigeuner.jpg" alt="zigeuner" width="312" height="412" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/zigeuner.jpg 312w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/zigeuner-227x300.jpg 227w" sizes="(max-width: 312px) 100vw, 312px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.pi-news.net/2013/01/einbrecher-asyl-antrage-von-zigeunern/">Source</a></p>
<p>Legal change may not change bureaucracy over night. In fact, it may take years until needy families receive any sort of visibility or assistance in the political arena. The <em>Migrantenrat</em> may set the agenda in the community and have an influence on local government, but laws are passed elsewhere.</p>
<p>Part of the problem with assisting Roma in Lichtenberg is the presence of stereotypes, seldom confirmed and often well-spread, evidenced by the contribution of one bureaucrat in employment services. Mrs. Olhagaray listened intently, as the woman &#8211; originally from Bulgaria &#8211; began to describe the situation of &#8216;<em>Zigeuner</em>&#8216; (gypsies), a <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/panorama/gesellschaft/zigeunersossen-streit-interview-mit-silvio-peritore-a-916760.html">word that has since become derogatory</a>, particularly in the culinary world. In a slight Slavic accent, she told of <strong><em>these people: stripping their living quarters of metal and valuable materials for money, over populating neighborhoods, lacking hygiene and order.</em></strong> With one finger pointed out the window at the end of the room:<em> the Pentecostal church, poverty, and illiteracy have led to too many children and no way to care for them!</em></p>
<p>But the cycle is slowly being broken. Many Roma children in Berlin are indeed going to school, and Berlin boasts <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/18/rave-education-per-square-kilometer/">initiatives which help them excel, as Sophia profiled back in June.</a> In many countries where Roma have lived before immigrating to Germany, school was not compulsory and in many cases was informally forbidden to them.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/roma-kids-in-school.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1759" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/roma-kids-in-school.jpg" alt="Roma kids in school" width="300" height="200" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://kubus-berlin.de/de/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/opener.jpg">Source</a></p>
<p>It seemed that our task in the <em>Migrantenrat </em>was simply to absorb the fragments of a crisis: the Roma problem unfolding like a heavy, scarlet rug out onto the plenary floor. <strong>Bureaucracy is often about working within the rules set by others, not about solving problems.</strong></p>
<p><em>But why do they come here? Why do the countries where they come from not intervene?</em>, asked a literacy volunteer in Lichtenberg schools, now working to absorb the newly-arrived children of Roma families, who may have never seen a book in their home but <em>come eagerly to learn, nonetheless, </em>she shared.</p>
<p>Without <a href="http://fra.europa.eu/sites/default/files/fra_uploads/413-EU-MIDIS_ROMA_EN.pdf">the story of systemic segregation and discrimination</a> behind the Roma (and Sinti) experience in Europe, answering this question is a difficult task. The situation becomes one of economics and not of humanism or even moral action &#8211; something enshrined in Germany&#8217;s constitution under its provisions for asylum and human rights.</p>
<p><em>So, if they can now access social services like any other EU-citizen, how many are expected to come?</em>, asked a representative from the Russian community, his voice lightened by compassion, though cut with a hint of anxiety.</p>
<p><em>Many</em>, was the message, <em>simply thousands</em>. With some other countries <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/02/opinion/02garcia.html?_r=2&amp;ref=romanipeople&amp;">forcefully rejecting Roma and clearing settlements, as in France</a>, Germany, especially Berlin, will become key destinations in the future.</p>
<p>Fortunately, social work agencies for immigrant populations have developed many projects for Roma-related challenges in Berlin, long before the problem was as acute as it is now. Talking to a <a href="http://www.dicvberlin.caritas.de/">Caritas </a>social worker from my fieldwork, I was told that it was the NGOs and not the government who pushed for <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">integration courses</a> to contain a path to literacy. <strong><em>How are they meant to learn German and get a job if they do not know the alphabet, we thought, so we asked for 900 hours of instruction instead of just 600, where they at least have a chance</em>,</strong> she said, exasperated.  <em><br />
</em></p>
<p>Another Caritas colleague was present at the <em>Migrantenrat </em>on this November day.  She sat quietly next to me, taking few notes, her arms crossed. As a social worker with more knowledge of German immigration and employment laws than any bureaucrat I have ever met, she looked a bit frustrated at the shock and awe that surrounding the discussion of a so-called impending crisis.</p>
<p>At the end of the plenary, she turned to me: <strong><em>This problem has been here a long time, we have been telling them&#8230;they didn&#8217;t listen.</em></strong></p>
<p>I turned off my recorder. After reviewing the sound bites from the evening, one thing was clear: Of course, the Roma are coming. Why wouldn&#8217;t they? <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Yrgnkd-Lsl8">Everyone is coming to Berlin.</a> This time, however, these people are not starving artists but rather a persecuted minority, seeking everything they have been denied. Even bureaucrats know that.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>There is no single <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/01/happy-weekend-a-roma-reimage/">Roma identity</a> or one Roma community, but for starters, some further resources are in order. Roma in Berlin: <a href="http://www.sinti-roma-berlin.de/">Landesverband Deutscher Sinti und Roma Berlin-Brandenburg e.V</a>., the German Roma and Sinti <a href="http://www.sintiundroma.de/start.html">documentation and educational center </a>for current debates and cultural awareness in Heidelberg, the European Union&#8217;s <a href="http://fra.europa.eu/sites/default/files/fra_uploads/413-EU-MIDIS_ROMA_EN.pdf">report on discrimination against Roma</a>. Finally, the <a href="http://www.migrantenrat.de/"><em>Migrantenrat Lichtenberg</em></a> is open to the public, if further discussions involving Roma and district politics happen to be of interest.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/20/roma-in-berlin-bureaucracy-in-lichtenberg/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rave: Education Per Square (Kilo)Meter</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/18/rave-education-per-square-kilometer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2013 08:26:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moabit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=787</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[After all this talk about <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/">Nazis</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/">N-Words</a>, and <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/29/prejudice-with-condiments-understanding-schwabenhass/">negative stereotypes</a>, I think it's time we had some good news around here, don't you? <p style="text-align:left;">Enter <em>Ein Quadratkilometer Bildung</em>, or "Square Kilometer Education".</p>
<p style="text-align:left;"><em>Quadratkilometer Bildung</em> (QKB) is an educational development and learning platform that addresses education on a regional basis, with a focus on disadvantaged populations. They call it "closing gaps". I call it common sense...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/galerie1_1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-788" style="margin: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/galerie1_1.jpg" alt="Galerie1_1" width="642" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/galerie1_1.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/galerie1_1-300x199.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/galerie1_1-650x432.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 642px) 100vw, 642px" /></a></p>
<p>After all this talk about <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/">Nazis</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/">N-Words</a>, and <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/29/prejudice-with-condiments-understanding-schwabenhass/">negative stereotypes</a>, I think it&#8217;s time we had some good news around here, don&#8217;t you?</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Enter <em>Ein Quadratkilometer Bildung</em>, or &#8220;Square Kilometer Education&#8221;.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.eu/"><em>Quadratkilometer Bildung</em></a> (QKB) is an educational development and learning platform that addresses education on a regional basis, with a focus on disadvantaged populations. QKB programs bridge schools with other regional institutions relevant to the lives of youth: we&#8217;re talking everything from youth service and day care centers to local authorities and city government. Programs also focus on <a href="http://oecdeducationtoday.blogspot.de/2013/05/evolving-attitudes-towards-early.html">early childhood education</a> and getting parents and community members involved early on. Education is thus attacked from multiple angles and a wider lens, becoming more collaborative, holistic, and effective. They call it &#8220;closing gaps&#8221;. I call it common sense.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/galerie5_1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/galerie5_1.jpg?w=300" alt="Galerie5_1" width="652" height="434" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Like most countries, Germany&#8217;s education system has its strengths and its weaknesses. The strongly adhered to tracking system employed by most German states means that students graduate with recognized qualifications and are better prepared for jobs, but are also separated early (usually in 4th grade) and only interact with students of their &#8220;level&#8221;. The recent focus on <a href="http://www.unesco.de/5588.html?L=1">inclusive education</a> has increased interest in <em>Gesamt</em>&#8211; or <em>Gemeinschaftsschulen</em> (comprehensive schools for all students), yet Germany&#8217;s federal system gives states control over their respective education systems. Read: it&#8217;s up to the individual states and may never happen. As long as tracking persists, and socioeconomic status remains <a href="http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00148-006-0102-y#page-1">the major determinant</a> for which track a child is funneled into, students with <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">migration backgrounds</a> will remain at a disadvantage.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Not surprisingly, QKB is run in two areas of Berlin plagued by low socioeconomic status and high numbers of residents with migration backgrounds: <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/">Neukölln</a> and Moabit. The Neukölln QKB program focuses on experiential learning workshops, early math skills, and talent development. In Moabit, programs emphasize <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/01/happy-weekend-a-roma-reimage/">Roma</a> school mentors and learning therapy for students with disabilities. Both programs pinpoint the need for early childhood language acquisition and increased parental involvement.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/tools11-e1374079477814.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/tools11-e1374079477814.jpg?w=300" alt="Tools1" width="637" height="471" /></a><strong>Unsere Traum Schule/Our Dream School (my favorite response: &#8220;a small petting zoo with small animals because the big ones&#8230;&#8221;)</strong></p>
<p>A few weeks ago, Kelly and I attended QKB&#8217;s second annual Film Night where the organization shared mini-clips of their programs and opened the floor for discussion. Together with the rest of the audience, we giggled through scenes of preschoolers scrunching their faces while trying to balance a scale, cringed at kids fitting themselves into drawers and shoving one another under cupboards, and came close to tears at emotional testimonials from mentors and parents.</p>
<p>The German term for education<em>, Bildung</em>, is more complex and comprehensive than its English counterpart. <em>Sich bilden</em> means &#8220;to form&#8221; or &#8220;to give rise to&#8221;. We&#8217;ve already agreed it takes a village to raise a child. How long before we realize that means the whole village?</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By</em><strong><em> Sophia Burton</em> </strong></p>
<p><em>In September 2013, QKB is opening a <a href="http://campusbildungimquadrat.eu/temporaeregalerie/">temporary gallery</a> at Berlin&#8217;s infamous </em><a href="http://tonymacaroni.wordpress.com/2012/08/24/campus-rutli-cr%C2%B2/">Campus Rütli – CR²</a> <em>school. The exhibit will serve as a communications platform connecting educational institutions with artists and the community. More information about the success of QKB programs by region (in German) can be found <a href="http://www.google.de/imgres?um=1&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sa=N&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;hl=de&amp;biw=1564&amp;bih=872&amp;tbm=isch&amp;tbnid=uqxsaX3evs8U1M:&amp;imgrefurl=http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.org/impressum/&amp;docid=4p0JNgWBJqHJiM&amp;imgurl=http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.org/wp-content/themes/km2/background/hintergrund3.jpg&amp;w=1024&amp;h=768&amp;ei=MormUafvG6nx4QSE9oHoBQ&amp;zoom=1&amp;iact=hc&amp;vpx=497&amp;vpy=219&amp;dur=1489&amp;hovh=194&amp;hovw=259&amp;tx=148&amp;ty=93&amp;page=1&amp;tbnh=141&amp;tbnw=188&amp;start=0&amp;ndsp=40&amp;ved=1t:429,r:3,s:0,i:91">here</a>. Information on QKB in English can be found <a href="http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.eu/">here</a> (click &#8220;km2 Education in English&#8221;).<br />
</em></p>
<p>First and second photo <a href="http://www.google.de/imgres?um=1&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sa=N&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;hl=de&amp;biw=1521&amp;bih=899&amp;tbm=isch&amp;tbnid=T1N-winrd21uFM:&amp;imgrefurl=http://www.land-der-ideen.de/presse/meldungen/ein-quadratkilometer-bildung&amp;docid=uokQqHVMjOJSjM&amp;imgurl=http://www.land-der-ideen.de/sites/default/files/styles/galleryformatter_slide/public/gallery/Galerie1_1.jpg&amp;w=800&amp;h=532&amp;ei=OM7mUcvDNIq1tAaR44CACw&amp;zoom=1&amp;iact=rc&amp;dur=360&amp;page=1&amp;tbnh=137&amp;tbnw=185&amp;start=0&amp;ndsp=39&amp;ved=1t:429,r:25,s:0,i:163&amp;tx=171&amp;ty=51">source</a>; Third photo <a href="http://www.google.de/imgres?um=1&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sa=N&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;hl=de&amp;biw=1521&amp;bih=899&amp;tbm=isch&amp;tbnid=bmcFUeai-R91iM:&amp;imgrefurl=http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.org/tools/&amp;docid=zkAFP8FKT9dE4M&amp;imgurl=http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/06/Tools1.jpg&amp;w=1500&amp;h=1125&amp;ei=VNHmUYjEFNDEtAaY1oDgDg&amp;zoom=1&amp;iact=rc&amp;dur=285&amp;page=1&amp;tbnh=158&amp;tbnw=209&amp;start=0&amp;ndsp=39&amp;ved=1t:429,r:31,s:0,i:181&amp;tx=116&amp;ty=109">source</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Happy Weekend: A Roma (Re)Image</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/01/happy-weekend-a-roma-reimage/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/01/happy-weekend-a-roma-reimage/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2013 10:16:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=687</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Your perception of the Roma is inaccurate. I apologize for the bluntness, but you and I both know it's true. And <em>I</em> know you and I both know it's true because it's true for me, and I've studied this stuff. Not only have I studied this stuff (e.g. migration, integration, intercultural relations), but I consider myself a beacon of political correctness, yet I've <em>still</em> dressed up as a gypsy for Halloween more times than I care to admit. Why? ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I can think of several reasons why you should attend this Roma photography exhibit this weekend, and not just because your outdoor plans are shot thanks to this <em>über</em>-frustrating weather.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/roma-image-ausstellung-572x382.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/roma-image-ausstellung-572x382.jpg" alt="Roma-Image-Ausstellung-572x382" width="515" height="344" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Reason #1: Your perception of the Roma is inaccurate<br />
</strong></p>
<p>I apologize for the bluntness, but you and I both know it&#8217;s true. And <em>I</em> know you and I both know it&#8217;s true because it&#8217;s true for me, and I&#8217;ve studied this stuff. Not only have I studied this stuff (e.g. migration, integration, intercultural relations), but I consider myself a beacon of political correctness, yet I&#8217;ve <em>still</em> dressed up as a gypsy for Halloween more times than I care to admit. Why?</p>
<p><strong>Because the Roma are one of Europe&#8217;s most misunderstood, over-stereotyped, and under-represented groups. </strong></p>
<p>The Roma are known for residing in the outskirts of town &#8211; both physically and mentally &#8211; in &#8220;parallel societies&#8221;. Many believe that the Roma are either incapable or just plain unwilling to integrate. Yet, as is the case with many minority groups, there are much more powerful structural forces at work behind this phenomenon. Periods of political unrest and transition, targeted discrimination, cuts in welfare spending, and school and housing segregation have all contributed to (or caused, depending on how you want to see it)  the struggles and alienation of the European Roma. As a reaction to systematic discrimination, groups often tread even further away from mainstream society than they&#8217;ve already been pushed, which in turn fuels damaging stereotypes. And &#8217;round and &#8217;round we go.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/2w650c0-bild.jpeg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/2w650c0-bild.jpeg" alt="2,w=650,c=0.bild" width="576" height="324" /></a><a href="http://www.bild.de/news/inland/einbuergerung/die-wahrheit-ueber-armuts-einwanderung-in-deutschland-29361086.bild.html">Source</a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Reason #2: A Romani identity may be a misnomer, but it&#8217;s worth exploring</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">&#8220;Roma&#8221; is a blanket term for a group of people who originally migrated to Europe from India almost 1,000 years ago. They&#8217;re most commonly known as &#8220;Gypsies,&#8221; a name that actually comes from &#8220;Egyptian,&#8221; which they were initially mistaken for by Europeans due to their darker skin and colorful attire. Today, European Roma mostly come from the Balkans and their environs, the majority living in Bulgaria and Romania. Characterized by their nomadic lifestyle, the <strong>Roma can be found all throughout Europe and are the continent&#8217;s largest minority group</strong>.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">The Roma are therefore a diverse diaspora &#8211; much more so than they are often portrayed &#8211; which is why some call the search for a shared Romani identity and culture a vain endeavor. It may also play a role in why Germany didn&#8217;t recognize the killing of Roma during the Holocaust as ethnic genocide  until 1982 &#8211; although an estimated <a href="http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/en/article.php?ModuleId=10005219">25% of European Roma</a> were annihilated. By the time many Roma victims finally &#8220;qualified&#8221; for restitution, many of them had passed away.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Today, there is a fear and misconception of massive immigration of Roma to richer Western European countries since the admittance of Bulgaria and Romania to the EU in 2007. France went so far as to <a href="http://www.migrationinformation.org/Feature/display.cfm?ID=803">deport</a> more than 1,000 Roma back to their home countries in 2010. In Germany, the reality is that 80% of immigrants from these countries posses regular work and the net-migration rate (how many are arriving minus how many have left again) has since balanced out.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/eu-umgang-roma.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-703 aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/eu-umgang-roma.jpg" alt="eu-umgang-roma" width="640" height="463" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/eu-umgang-roma.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/eu-umgang-roma-300x217.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/eu-umgang-roma-650x470.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><a href="http://www.google.de/imgres?um=1&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sa=N&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;hl=de&amp;biw=1662&amp;bih=844&amp;tbm=isch&amp;tbnid=9C-iGQ-Mg6jbEM:&amp;imgrefurl=http://www.sueddeutsche.de/politik/roma-in-europa-eine-politische-bombe-1.1003626&amp;docid=zMsY0p6oyv6BTM&amp;imgurl=http://polpix.sueddeutsche.com/bild/1.1003627.1355793366/860x860/eu-umgang-roma.jpg&amp;w=860&amp;h=623&amp;ei=yGKnUZC7JImctQbNy4DIAg&amp;zoom=1&amp;iact=rc&amp;dur=430&amp;page=2&amp;tbnh=139&amp;tbnw=195&amp;start=35&amp;ndsp=43&amp;ved=1t:429,r:76,s:0,i:318&amp;tx=61&amp;ty=80">Source</a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Reason #3: The Roma deserve a space within Berlin&#8217;s (and Europe&#8217;s) cultural scene</strong></p>
<p>The Roma suffer from abject poverty, inadequate access to education and health care, and illiteracy (only <a href="http://www.bild.de/politik/inland/migration/die-6-wahrheiten-ueber-roma-29384608.bild.html">42% </a>of European Roma finish elementary school). They are also the targets of deep-rooted prejudice and stereotypes, a popular one being that they are all beggars and criminals.</p>
<p>Part of this exhibit&#8217;s goal is to explore and showcase the complexity of Roma identity by allocating a space for Romani artists. Rather than portraying images solely <em>of</em> Roma, this exhibit provides a space for the <em>work of</em> Roma, giving the group a space for cultural expression, recognition, and validation.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/roma_dpa.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/roma_dpa.jpg" alt="Roma Camp near Paris" width="640" height="320" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.taz.de/!113346/">Source</a></p>
<p><strong>Reason #4: It&#8217;s your last chance</strong></p>
<p>This weekend marks the last few days of  the Roma Image Studio exhibit, which concludes on June 2. You can find it in Neukölln&#8217;s <em>Galerie im Saalbau</em> on Karl-Marx-Straße 141. Admittance (and stereotype-debunking) free.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>Sources and more reading:</p>
<p>Exhibit description and photo <a href="http://www.neukoellner.net/kunst-kitsch/weg-vom-roma-klischee/">source</a> (German)</p>
<p>http://www.migrationinformation.org/Feature/display.cfm?ID=803 (English)</p>
<p>http://www.bbc.co.uk/insideout/southeast/series6/gypsy_travels.shtml (English)</p>
<p>http://www.dw.de/roma-more-integration-through-education/a-16662455 (English)</p>
<p>http://www.bild.de/politik/inland/migration/die-6-wahrheiten-ueber-roma-29384608.bild.html (German)</p>
<p>http://www.amaroforo.de/ (German)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/01/happy-weekend-a-roma-reimage/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
