<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>United States &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/united-states/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Moralpolitik and the Ressentiments of Change</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 15:35:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4120</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[According to headlines, the German government has pledged haven – albeit temporary in many cases – to up to 800,000 refugees or migrants applying for asylum in the country. The U.S., despite initial wavering, has signaled that it will work to raise its refugee quota yearly, with the goal of a 100,000 cap by 2017. Yet within and around this historical moment of humanitarian crisis and measured political response are the inflammatory words of Donald Trump. He recently roared to a crowd in Iowa that, if elected, he “will deport all of the 11 million illegal migrants in this country.”]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As German and U.S. refugee policies inevitably collide in light of current events, this writer finds herself in the United States. The other writer of this blog will soon be in Germany, taking stock of the so-called “refugee crisis” on the ground. On my side of the Atlantic, a crisis is not yet to be felt… at least not so acutely. This has as much to do with media semantics as it does with history.</p>
<p>According to headlines, the German government has pledged haven – albeit temporary in many cases – <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/aug/20/germany-raises-estimate-refugee-arrivals-800000">to up to 800,000 refugees or migrants applying for asylum in the country</a>. The U.S., despite initial wavering, <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/news/nation/2015/09/20/increase-admission-refugees-kerry-says/fnCweeIlCS8g47VF7VAkBP/story.html">has signaled that it will work to raise its refugee quota</a> yearly, with the goal of a 100,000 cap by 2017. The Pope, as leader of the spiritual state of Catholicism, <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">has planned to make migrants and refugees one of the few central issues of his travels around the Western Hemisphere this week</a>.</p>
<p>All at once, it seems that moral duty, a college ethics course, and politics have fused into one mandate to assist.</p>
<p>Yet within and around this historical moment of humanitarian crisis and measured political response are the inflammatory words of Donald Trump. He recently roared to a crowd in Iowa that, if elected, he “<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">will deport all of the 11 million illegal migrants in this country.</a>” When asked by Univision’s anchor Jorge Ramos how he would accomplish such a feat, he coolly responded, “I’m a great manager.”</p>
<div id="attachment_4127" style="width: 630px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4127" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-4127" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg" alt="Donald Trump immigration" width="620" height="372" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg 620w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP-300x180.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4127" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Charlie Neibergall/AP via <em><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">The Guardian</a></em></p></div>
<p>One can easily get caught up in the absurdity that is the American campaign season, enjoying its theatrics as a harmless part of the celebrity process. But Trump’s words should hold weight, and they should be cause for alarm.</p>
<p>Trump’s message is not as obtuse, as unnecessarily harsh as it might seem; it reflects not only present sentiment but historical precedent… for both the United States and Germany. With the current refugee and migrant crisis, old tensions are slowly and loudly being unearthed. And the mobility of many of the world&#8217;s displaced, traumatized, and poor is not likely to change any time soon.</p>
<p>National Public Radio’s <em>Fresh Air</em> <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/10/439114563/americas-forgotten-history-of-mexican-american-repatriation">recently interviewed</a> one of the scholars behind the book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Decade-Betrayal-Mexican-Repatriation-1930s/dp/0826339735">Decade of Betrayal: Mexican Repatriation in the 1930s</a>”. The volume documents a massive and relentless deportation program at a time when xenophobia and economic distress were rampant. Historians Raymond Rodriguez and Francisco Balderrama document what is nothing short of a terrifying episode in American history – frightening for what right-wing reactionaries in a new age of migration might be capable of.</p>
<p>As Rodriguez shared with <em>Fresh Air</em>’s host, Terry Gross, the 1930s treated Mexican Americans with great malice and abuse. For reason only of their heritage, they were targeted by government programs and private citizens alike. This abuse culminated in the federal government&#8217;s campaign to strip millions of Americans of their citizenship. Not all those rounded up in deportation raids were naturalized citizens, though <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">estimates suggest than ½ of those expelled were</a>. Most were visa-holders of some sort, their only crime having been born a member of a demonized ethnic group.</p>
<p>Governmental programs to round up and expel society’s undesirables often begin in cities, according to history (see the American strategy of Japanese internment or Nazi Germany&#8217;s institution of the urban ghetto). And so Los Angeles was the primary target of the government’s Mexican American deportation program. Largely as a response to the despair the Great Depression had unleashed across the country, officials systematically sent entire families from the L.A. area back to Mexico, with no infrastructure in place to receive them. <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">From 1929 to 1944, 1/3 of L.A.’s Mexican American population was deported</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4128" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4128" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4128" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-650x487.jpg" alt="Los Angeles Mexican Americans 1932" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4128" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Los Angeles Public Library/Herald Examiner Collection via <em><a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">National Public Radio</a></em></p></div>
<p><em>Ressentiments</em> – projection of resentment or fear onto often vulnerable groups in society – were widespread both in the U.S. and in Germany throughout the Great Depression. Xenophobia in the face of severe economic collapse paved the way for Germany’s organized extermination machinery. The U.S.’s internment of Japanese and German citizens, its continued subordination of Black Americans, and its systematic deportation of Mexican Americans demonstrate that this country was in no way spared such a nasty past.</p>
<p>Slowly but surely, such <em>ressentiments</em> have now begun to return. This time, Germany may be more in the right, even despite a few documented attacks on refugee facilities, while America edges closer toward the precipice of wrong.</p>
<p>…</p>
<p>On my side of the ocean, I have arrived into a complicated sector of the nexus of natural diversity and these increasing <em>ressentiments. </em>Vancouver, Washington, where both my parents now live, <a href="http://www.thenation.com/article/browning-america/">is becoming increasingly &#8220;Brown&#8221;</a>. Separated only by a short bridge across the Columbia River, Southwest Washington has become Portland&#8217;s semi-urban/semi-rural extension. Because the northern bank of the river offers families more space for cheaper, better funded schools for fewer private tax dollars, and income tax exemption, immigrants who may have otherwise moved to the Portland, Oregon metro area are now planting themselves on the side of its less expensive neighbor. Portland, as a result, <a href="http://www.oregonlive.com/news/index.ssf/2009/01/in_a_changing_world_portland_r.html">has become increasingly White</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4129" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4129" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4129" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-650x366.jpg" alt="Interstate bridge over the Columbia River, connecting Portland, Oregon and Vancouver, Washington" width="650" height="366" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-650x366.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-300x169.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4129" class="wp-caption-text">Interstate bridge over the Columbia River, connecting Portland, Oregon and Vancouver, Washington</p></div>
<p>According to most recent U.S. census data, Vancouver is now 11% Hispanic, inching closer to the national average. We can expect this number to be much higher in reality, as immigrants will often opt out of participation in the census. There are other ethnic groups represented in Vancouver’s demographic development: For example, 18% of families speak a language other than English at home, and the traditional taco truck has recently seen competition in North African, Japanese, and Thai flavors.</p>
<p>None of this would seem all that significant, if I were not writing about a traditionally conservative county, with once sprawling farm land and a historical military base; a county that has now been converted into a rare blend of suburban developments, strip malls, urbane boutiques, and miles and miles of regional road. The nickname of &#8220;Van-tucky&#8221;* &#8211; something I have only heard used on the other side of the water, mind you &#8211; might tell you all you need to know.</p>
<p>The rate of poverty in Vancouver is also higher than the national average. Vancouver&#8217;s mayor recently <a href="http://www.cityofvancouver.us/ced/page/affordable-housing-task-force">launched a task force</a> to investigate the cause of growing homelessness, rising rents, and increased demand for housing in the city’s most accessible and commercially viable areas. Serving as Portland’s &#8220;bedroom community&#8221; brings with it numerous tax and transportation disadvantages, as well, such as costly inter-city transit for a significant commuter population and bridges nationally notorious for being structurally unsound.</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p>In a brand-new cocktail bar in downtown Vancouver, which serves only locally-distilled (read artisanal) spirits, I sip my smoky-cucumber-tequila mixture and listen in on the interaction between the unlikely combination of guests who have just joined me on the patio. Three White bikers &#8211; two older women with smokers&#8217; cough and one machismo with a mustache &#8211; scoff at the price of their beer. Across from them at a nearby table, two women in their mid-20s, both with long black hair, one who speaks English with an accent.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-4130" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-650x366.jpg" alt="cocktail Vancouver, Washington" width="650" height="366" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-650x366.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-300x169.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Older veterans and cowboy-like characters are scattered across Vancouver’s downtown like curated remains of what was once here. They drink Rainier out of cans &#8211; Washington State’s Pabst Blue Ribbon with more local charm &#8211; and chain smoke in the park. They inhabit the dive bars with names like &#8220;Lounge&#8221; and antique neon advertisements. It seems that establishments like this new artisanal cocktail bar threaten to upset a tender balance between familiarity, comfort, and growth.</p>
<p>“$4! Bullshit”, one of the women hollers. The two younger ladies nudge their shoulders closer together, in order to continue a conversation disrupted by the boom of our three new patio companions.</p>
<p>The machismo turns toward the young women’s table, putting his hand on one of their legs. “Where you from, honey?&#8221;, he begins his monologue, &#8220;I’m a native, been here for more than 20 years, Detroit before that. You know how much this place has changed?”</p>
<p>Neither responds; however, the one whose leg is playing host to the man’s hand begins to shift uncomfortably.</p>
<p>&#8220;Where you from honey? You aren&#8217;t from around here, I can tell you that!&#8221;, one of the older women yells between sips from her can. “When did Rainier get this damn expensive? It’s bullshit, $4! I’ll tell you something…”</p>
<p>One of the young, dark-haired women flashes machismo a smile. &#8220;I&#8217;m from Panama!&#8221;, she says, and extends her hand for a shake. He takes it and squeezes it, returning both their hands to the table.</p>
<p>“I’m American, from here&#8221;, the other woman says, her leg now turned as far away from his body as the chair allows.</p>
<p>&#8220;But where are your parents from then?&#8221;, machismo asks with a chuckle. &#8220;That&#8217;s what I&#8217;m asking, ain&#8217;t it?&#8221;</p>
<p>She concedes, but stands to use the restroom (or simply disappear into the building) as she does: &#8220;Well, I&#8217;m Filipino.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p><em>Ressentiments</em> toward the Other can begin and fester in spaces of socioeconomic change. With President Obama’s pledge to take in 100,000 refugees, the question becomes “How will this country prepare its citizens to engage respectfully and kindly with members of a majority Muslim country?” The first step in this process is realizing that we have a lot of work to do, and we need politicians who will help us get there.</p>
<p>Germany has seen a fair share of reporting on the readiness of its population to open its arms to newcomers. It is easy to draw parallels to the past, particularly to Germany’s track record in <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/20/441732811/in-germany-migrants-find-footing-but-also-some-resistance">failing to integrate its guest-worker population and in promoting ethnic-based citizenship until it was almost too late</a>. However, it is Germany the rest of the world now looks to in awe &#8211; for choosing a kind of <em>moralpolitik</em> over patterns of the past.</p>
<p>Being so far away from a society I sometimes feel I know more about than my own (society of origin), I can’t help but beam with pride in watching small towns across Germany distribute clean clothes, socks, new toys, children’s books, and warm meals to the thousands of human beings in need who have crossed their borders. Nevertheless, Germany has since issued temporary border controls. Order still wins out over populist charity.</p>
<p>But aiming for a collective solution to the continuous stream of migrants and refugees into Europe, German leaders have worked to reach agreement upon a refugee quota for EU member states. Just this Tuesday this quota became a provisional reality.</p>
<p>Time will tell if all members comply, and if a sense of moral duty is really as strong as images of kind citizens touting bags of donations suggest. Yet I do have the sense that with each step toward welcoming the Other, <em>ressentiments</em> have fewer chances of surviving. When demonstrations of kindness are just so strong, so publicly undeniable, that Trump-esque hate can find no oxygen for its fire.</p>
<p>That is what I hope for America.</p>
<p>At the moment, the U.S. remains crippled and complicated by its multi-layered fears of all the regions of the world it has wronged. As UN Ambassador <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/23/442761552/10-000-syrian-refugees-just-the-floor-of-u-s-effort-says-ambassador-power">Samantha Power made clear in an NPR interview recently</a>, the country is not ready to simply do the right thing; it has to be a calculated response, taking security into account.</p>
<p>Overcoming fear is America&#8217;s consistent and stubborn challenge. I just hope the mistakes of the 1930s can mean something.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*Van-tucky is a reference to the southern state of Kentucky, the unofficial home of fried-chicken and horse races.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: &#8220;I&#8217;m a Human Being&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 11:21:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Austria]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[family]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Taiwan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vienna]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4019</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Vienna. Seat of the former Austro-Hungarian Empire. Widely considered the gateway to Eastern Europe. Home to a United Nations headquarters and numerous international companies and universities. The Austrian capital has long been a city of immigration – even when politics have told a different story – and a staggering 50% of the population has what’s referred to as a “migration background”. So it’s not as if I expected Vienna to not be multicultural...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_4028" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4028" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4028 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-650x581.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender" width="650" height="581" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-650x581.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-300x268.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender.jpg 728w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4028" class="wp-caption-text">Sophia, Christina, and Suzi at the 2015 Vienna Pride Parade</p></div>
<p>Vienna. Seat of the former Austro-Hungarian Empire. Widely considered the gateway to Eastern Europe. Home to a United Nations headquarters and numerous international companies and universities. The Austrian capital has long been a city of immigration – even when politics have told a different story – and a staggering <a href="https://www.wien.gv.at/english/social/integration/basic-work/facts-figures.html">50% of the population</a> has what’s referred to as a “migration background”.</p>
<p>So it’s not as if I expected Vienna to <em>not</em> be multicultural.</p>
<p>What I didn’t expect when <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/03/23/lens-on-leaving-homes/">moving to Vienna from Berlin</a> was to encounter some of the most fascinating “mixes” of my life: A half-Indian, half-Italian who grew up in the US and lives in Vienna with her half-Austrian, half-French boyfriend? A Chinese-American who fell in love with her German boyfriend in Hong Kong? A half-Austrian, half-Sicilian who met her Indian husband in London? The combinations are unexpected, beautiful, and dare I say, collidoscopic? (And their potential future children even more so).</p>
<div id="attachment_4031" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4031" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4031 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-650x475.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(3)" width="650" height="475" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-650x475.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-300x219.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4031" class="wp-caption-text">Christina poses with a cow in Austria on a family roadtrip</p></div>
<p>Christina, the first close friend I made in Vienna, is no different. Born in Taiwan to a Taiwanese mother and Austrian father, at age three her family moved to San Jose, California, where her younger brother was born. Kindergarten was spent in Vienna, where she lived with her father and grandparents while mom and brother stayed in the US. At age six the entire family moved to Taiwan for four years. Then it was back west to Seattle from ages 10-16 where Christina spent the longest stretch of her childhood, what she calls her &#8220;most formative years&#8221;. Her last two years of high school were completed in Taipei, where she graduated with the globally recognized International Baccalaureate Diploma.</p>
<p>“I was missing roots as a kid, our family was always bouncing around,&#8221; she tells me.</p>
<p>This triangular ping ponging between nations resulted in three different passport combinations within a family of four: Christina’s brother, born in the US, is a dual Austrian-American citizen but “avoids Austria now because of the mandatory military service.” Mom is dual Taiwanese-Austrian, “but never felt completely comfortable in Austria”. And Christina and her father are purely Austrian, on paper anyway.</p>
<p>&#8220;A long time ago my dad had the chance to become an American citizen but decided against it,&#8221; she says smirking, &#8220;He&#8217;s a proud Austrian.”</p>
<div id="attachment_4057" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4057" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4057 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_9365" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4057" class="wp-caption-text">Christina with her parents in Taiwan</p></div>
<p>It is to her father and his “pride” that Christina attributes her last 16 years in Vienna. &#8220;My dream was to go to Georgetown [University],&#8221; Christina tells me one warm evening in the <em>Museumsquartier</em>, her fingers tapping the stem of her <em>Hugospritz</em>. &#8220;I applied and got in… my mom supported it, but my dad kept saying I had to go to university in Austria. It was always really important to him that, as the oldest child, I embrace my Austrian roots.&#8221;</p>
<p>Christina ended up moving to Vienna against her will: “I didn&#8217;t have any connection to Austria at that time other than having spent the occasional summer there with my grandparents.” The first year, she expressed her anger by skipping class in favor of exploring the city and having fun.</p>
<p>“And then I got pregnant,” she says laughing, “the biggest rebellion of all!”</p>
<div id="attachment_4059" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4059" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4059 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371-650x650.jpg" alt="IMG_9371" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4059" class="wp-caption-text">Mother-daughter surfing trip in Morocco</p></div>
<p>Christina’s daughter Illeana (Illy) was born when she was 20. She raised Illy as a single mother while completing her degrees in Economics and Sinology, with “lots of help” from friends with similar bi-cultural backgrounds. She counts half-Austrian friends from South Africa and Bolivia among her closest, along with a half-Kosovan, half-Czech hair salon owner named Suzi. “None of us knew what we were doing… it was experimental parenting. I think if I raised a child now I’d be much more nervous!”</p>
<p>After making it over the hump of her first year, Vienna started to feel like home. “I began to realize how much I love it here,” Christina reflects. Now one could say Christina is as Austrian as they come. Her German is flawless and chock full of colloquialisms, she sings along to Austrian <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schlager_music">Schlager</a></em>, and her drink of choice is the ubiquitous <em><a href="http://austrianwineusa.com/2013/12/20/12-days-of-austrian-wine-enjoy-a-gspritzer/">Weisser Spritzer</a></em>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4064" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4064" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4064 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-650x602.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(7)" width="650" height="602" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-650x602.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-300x278.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7.jpg 701w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4064" class="wp-caption-text">Christina skiing in Kaprun, Austria</p></div>
<p>None of that, however, stops her from craving Taiwanese ‘Three-Cups Chicken’ or her favorite American cereal, ‘Lucky Charms’. “I’m biracial and tri-cultural,” she states without hesitation. And while rewarding on personal and professional levels (she’s also fluent in Mandarin), Christina’s background has not gone unchallenged in a city that still struggles to see itself as a place of migration and diversity.</p>
<p>Christina has encountered countless variations of the “<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/">But where are you <em>really</em> from?</a>” question over the years. “When I first got to Vienna, there were fewer minorities and diversity didn&#8217;t work very well,” she remarks, “I remember meeting one guy who could not comprehend why I looked the way I did but had a very common German last name,&#8221; she rolls her eyes at the memory. &#8220;I literally had to spell it out for him by saying, &#8216;If you, an Austrian, had a baby with a Taiwanese woman, the result would be me!’”</p>
<div id="attachment_4034" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4034" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4034 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-650x488.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(6)" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4034" class="wp-caption-text">Christina&#8217;s 3rd Birthday in Los Angeles, California</p></div>
<p>This phenomenon isn’t limited to Vienna. In Japan, a newly crowned biracial beauty queen has been fielding questions on a regular basis about what parts of her are “Japanese”. <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/30/world/asia/biracial-beauty-queen-strives-for-change-in-mono-ethnic-japan.html">“But I am a Japanese,”</a> is her response. On the other side of the world, in the US, Rachel Dolezal was recently exposed for her elaborate deception as a Black woman – a &#8220;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/18/opinion/charles-blow-the-delusions-of-dolezal.html?smid=fb-share">one-directional privilege</a>&#8221; that could never have been successful the other way around, due to socially constructed perceptions of race. The recurring theme? If you are one drop of minority, we will question your Belonging to the majority.</p>
<p>Christina acknowledges that even she is not immune to societal attitudes about migrants in Austria. &#8220;I&#8217;ve learned that, in Austria, migrants get classified into &#8216;good&#8217; and &#8216;bad&#8217;,&#8221; she explains.</p>
<p>&#8220;Asians are considered ‘good’ because they’re quiet, stay out of trouble, and work hard. Turkish people are unpopular because a lot of them refuse to adapt to the Austrian way of life and bring hordes of family members over, all the while claiming benefits from the Austrian government. Blacks have it the worst, though, probably because they stand out the most and are still viewed by many locals as low-lifes and drug dealers.&#8221;</p>
<div id="attachment_4029" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4029" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4029 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-650x472.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(1)" width="650" height="472" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-650x472.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-300x218.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4029" class="wp-caption-text">Christina riding a (fake) bull at Glacier National Park, Montana</p></div>
<p>While Christina is well aware that the US has its own challenges regarding diversity, she does view it as more progressive: “In the US, people at least get it when you tell them that you&#8217;re biracial.”</p>
<p>It was 1999 when Christina was last in the US, before Illy&#8217;s birth and before the 9/11 attacks. While she’s now seriously considering a move back, it&#8217;s unclear when she will be able to. Christina is not a US citizen and needs a green card. Her most recent attempt at the <a href="http://travel.state.gov/content/visas/english/immigrate/diversity-visa/instructions.html">Diversity Visa Lottery</a> was unsuccessful. “My dad told me he is reconsidering becoming an American citizen just so that he can help get us over there,” Christina recently shared. <a href="http://www.migrationpolicy.org/article/family-reunification">Family reunification</a> is one of the four major pathways for foreigners to become legal residents of the US.</p>
<p>Legal challenges are also not Christina’s only concern. “Sometimes I worry that people in the US will annoy me with their ignorance,” she says laughing. At the same time, she is drawn to the lifestyle. She observes her American friends move to houses with pools, which, compared to Viennese city apartments, seem like mansions. Illy, a recovering Justin Bieber addict who recently graduated to a One Direction obsession, is thrilled with the prospect. “A typical Austrian teenager,” Christina chuckles.</p>
<p>You could call Christina many things: A transnational, an immigrant, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">a third-culture kid</a>, a foreigner, a native, an expat. But none of these categories really fit given the fluidity of her upbringing and identity. We use labels to establish connections and try to make sense of things, but they can also dilute the intricacy and beauty of reality.</p>
<p>&#8220;I&#8217;m not 100% of anything,&#8221; is how Christina describes it. &#8220;Sometimes when people ask what I am, I just answer that I&#8217;m a human being.&#8221;</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Photos provided by Christina and Sophia.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rave: the California Breakfast Slam Effect</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/30/rave-the-california-breakfast-slam-effect/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2014 12:17:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[expats]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2510</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Identity and belonging are closely intertwined with the foods we eat. The California Breakfast Slam, or CABslam, originally a pop-up breakfast establishment celebrating Americana classics like hash browns and maple syrup-drenched bacon, now hosts an unassuming 'Beta' restaurant space at the far edge of Neukölln's Reuterkiez. A visit allows for the giddy return to childhood memories that lead to goosebumps and pride, or a combination of both. Let's call this the California Breakfast Slam effect...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The relationship between food and identity, or simply food and a sense of belonging, is well-known to those of us who have sought out Hass avocados or Toll House chocolate chips (often in vain) in places beyond the United States. For me, there is something ultimately gratifying, even safe, about opening that jar of Adam&#8217;s peanut butter or letting the smell of buttermilk biscuits fill my Berlin apartment. At once, giving in to &#8216;old urges&#8217; is washed with self-realization. I also just really love buttermilk biscuits.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01329.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2518" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01329.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01329" width="640" height="426" /></a></p>
<p>While critically testing Berlin&#8217;s newest &#8216;American breakfast&#8217; joint a few weekends ago, I had the overwhelming sense that &#8220;hey, I&#8217;m allowed to do this [more than anyone else here]!&#8221;. These are processes of identity and belonging at work.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.facebook.com/cabslam">California Breakfast Slam</a>, or CABslam, originally a pop-up breakfast establishment celebrating Americana classics like hash browns and maple syrup-drenched bacon, now hosts an unassuming &#8216;Beta&#8217; restaurant space at the far edge of Neukölln&#8217;s Reuterkiez. A visit allows for the giddy return to childhood memories that lead to goosebumps and pride or a combination of both. Let&#8217;s call this the California Breakfast Slam effect.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01342.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2531 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01342.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01342" width="640" height="960" /></a></p>
<p>Not all patrons of CABslam&#8217;s new digs are from the Western coast of the United States like myself, but there certainly exists a clientele of the North American variety, motivated more by feelings (or longings) than by taste, I dare to conjecture. Put simply, who knew that a plate full of pancakes, browned potato shavings, bacon, and a fried egg would make one feel so secure? So &#8216;you&#8217; in your own maple-craving skin? This is the CABslam effect.</p>
<p>Anthropologists would suggest that our food choices constitute a large part of how we position ourselves in the world, particularly in a foreign context. In a country for which one possesses no legal or innate right to reside, one learns to miss the general social acceptance and security provided in that <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/16/lens-going-away/">place left behind</a>. Ethnographical studies* of immigrants around the world &#8211; Turkish immigrants vending kebap to keep the nostalgic grill burning, taco trucks re-connecting small towns to distant landscapes, Punjabi import shops outlining a community in the anonymous city &#8211; form an extensive literature in support of this role of food as an identity-maker. Food ways, what and how we eat, often serve to reclaim a definition of self that may be threatened by the indifferent surroundings of the foreign.</p>
<p>Interesting to reflect upon, however, is how much of these positive associations are, in fact, related to the food itself. In other words, is it the constitution and consistency of the yogurt that reminds the Turkish immigrant of home (see <a href="http://www.businessweek.com/articles/2013-01-31/at-chobani-the-turkish-king-of-greek-yogurt">the Chobani story</a>)? Is the sugar content of my peanut butter a key determinant of my sense of belonging &#8211; of how I affirm and embody my American identity in Germany?</p>
<p>One of my father&#8217;s favorite activities, as of late, is going to the local mom &amp; pop diner located just around the corner from his home. He has always loved waffles, bacon, eggs &#8211; preferences I inherited, minus the bacon for environmental reasons (goodbye bacon bowls).</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_20041.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2555 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_20041.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_2004" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>At this local breakfast spot in Vancouver (WA), one sits in a cozy corner &#8211; on that particular kind of squeaky upholstery reserved for diners &#8211; and receives bottom-less coffee and a pint of the good, brown sticky stuff within moments of arriving, without needing to have asked. Luxury and simplicity come together in a routinized ritual that completes a Saturday morning.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_20051.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2556 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_20051.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_2005" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>A visit to Neukölln&#8217;s diner-ish mock up, CABslam, offers a similar experience, albeit with wood in place of the traditional synthetic materials. The waitresses greet guests in English with a smile, a touch of accent on the tongue; plates of meat, starch, and sugar pass through the spacious, half-finished space, disturbed only by the squeal of espresso. Oh, American breakfast in Europe: such a strange delicacy, indeed.</p>
<p>If I were to come upon a similar diner anywhere in the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/">Pacific Northwest</a>, I would be confused by 1. the small portions, 2. the texture of the syrup, 3. the small portions, 4. the fancy coffee, and 5. the small portions. But while in that strange space of not always quite fitting in and not being quite sure how to amend the problem, one takes any moment of assured (if strangely assembled) belonging and identity one can get.</p>
<p>And so I ordered French toast, Juri ordered the original California Breakfast Slam, and I ate his pancakes and felt thoroughly pleased with the entire situation.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01335.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2524" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01335.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01335" width="640" height="960" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01335.jpg 433w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01335-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>Glancing around the perhaps far-too spacious-to-be-cozy restaurant-in-progress, plates of beans and eggs (Huevos Rancheros!),  yellow sauce and bread (Eggs Benedict!), and hearty scrambles made it all just believable enough&#8230;even if it is not possible to get a side of sweet &#8216;Amish bread&#8217; here, as is the case with my favorite diner in Seattle, <a href="http://www.bethscafe.com/index.php">Beth&#8217;s Cafe</a>. Beginnings are always a bit modest, anyway.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01336.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2525 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01336.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01336" width="640" height="426" /></a></p>
<p>After our plates had been cleared, all sauces sopped up with available eatable utensils, I pondered my just-consumed identity and belonging with a nice long sip of espresso. Though perhaps still a bit hungry for American-diner standards, the starvation for the validation that comes from truly fitting in &#8211; in this case, the belonging that comes from just understanding the absurdly starchy rituals that constitute American breakfast &#8211; was momentarily gone.</p>
<p>This felt quite good.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01340.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2529" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01340.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01340" width="640" height="960" /></a></p>
<p>While consuming something in the morning hours that would otherwise be reserved for a combination of dessert, second dessert, and holidays in Germany, the recognition that &#8220;yes, this is perhaps not the healthiest but yes, this is delicious, and I will enjoy it&#8221; bubbles up, almost unexpectedly.</p>
<p>American food culture is shaped and even manipulated by advertising&#8217;s exploitation of this very urge to give-in, indulge, and consume &#8216;freedom&#8217; as embodied in a fried-chicken-pizza or a Big Gulp &#8211; as nicely laid out in an <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/currency/2014/04/fast-food-doubles-down.html">article on the success of such fast-food antics in America</a> in this past week&#8217;s issue of <em>The</em> <em>New Yorker</em>.</p>
<p>But looking around at the improvisational furniture and faux diner fixtures at CABslam, the abstract and even fictive nature of such an experience became strikingly clear: The setting did not necessarily fit my expectations, but the frame was just large enough to allow textures, smells, and memories to gently assemble a replica of &#8216;home&#8217;. Minus the Amish bread.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01326.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2515" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01326.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01326" width="640" height="426" /></a></p>
<p>If one were to survey immigrants and/or expats around the world, one thing would surely be held in common &#8211; a lust after the foods of whence one has come. This does not mean that these foods are objectively good or even at the top of my list. But this is not the point. Even though the mere idea of many American delights makes me a little uneasy and sad for the state of national nutrition (see &#8220;<a href="http://www.takepart.com/place-at-the-table">A Place at the Table</a>&#8221; for the full story), I delight just a little in being associated with such a cuisine. Because it is familiar and mine, in a way intimately intertwined with memory and what identity makes of it.</p>
<p>More than anything else, the moments at my childhood-dream-table, where chocolate-chip pancakes were the best reward and hash browns the coveted snack, are the things that bring me the simplest of glee in a situation that is often colored by uncertainty. And that, folks, is the CABslam effect.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01323.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2533" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/dsc01323.jpg?w=640" alt="DSC01323" width="640" height="426" /></a></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>Cabslam is located at Innstraße 47, 12045 Neukölln, open (now also for lunch and dinner) Mo-So 11:00-midnight. Their <a href="http://www.cabslam.com/">official website</a> is currently under construction, so best use the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/cabslam/info">facebook page</a> for more information on their rotating menu, as well as to make reservations. Long live American breakfast! All photos by <a href="http://jurigottschau.com/">Juri Gottschau</a>.</p>
<p><em>*If the mention of ethnographical studies sparked your interest, here is some further reading on immigrant identity, diaspora memory, and &#8211; you guessed it &#8211; food, brought to you by the wonderful discipline of sociocultural anthropology:</em><br />
Bahloul, J. 1989, &#8220;From a Muslim banquet to a Jewish seder: food ways and ethnicity among North African Jews&#8221;, in <em>Jews Among Arabs: Contacts and Boundaries</em>, ed. Cohen, M. Camp; A. Udovitch.<br />
Buckser A. 1999, <em>Keeping kosher: eating and social identity among the Jews of Denmark</em>, <em>Ethnology</em>, vol. 38.<br />
Chapman et al. 2011, &#8220;Meanings of food, eating and health in Punjabi families living in Vancouver, Canada&#8221;,<em>Health Education Journal</em>, vol. 70, no. 1.<br />
Harbottle, L. 1997, &#8220;Taste and embodiment: the food preferences of Iranians in Britain&#8221;, in <em>Food Preference and Taste: Continuity and Change</em>, ed. MacBeth, H.<br />
Holtzman, John D. 2006, &#8220;Food and Memory&#8221;, <em>Annual Review of Anthropology</em>, no. 35.<br />
Mankekar, P. 2002, “&#8217;India shopping&#8217;: Indian grocery stores and transnational conﬁguration of belonging&#8221;, <em>Ethnos</em>, vol. 67, no. 1.<br />
Lee, SSJ. 2000, &#8220;Dys-appearing tongues and bodily memories: the aging of ﬁrst-generation resident Koreans in Japan&#8221;, <em>Ethos</em>, vol. 28, no. 2.<br />
Ray, K. 2004, <em>The Migrant’s Table: Meals and Memories in Bengali-American Households</em>.<br />
Şebnem, Timur Ögüt 2008, &#8220;Turkish restaurants in London: An ethnographic study on representation of cultural identity through design&#8221;, <em>ITU A|Z</em>, vol. 5.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; and the White Audience</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2014 14:00:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Afrodeutsch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nazi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[segregation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theater]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2248</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One attends a play about an Afro-German living in the years of Nazism and Jim Crow not because of the dramaturgy. One buys the ticket because of the topic's near absence in the German discourse. This is not a review of the play, but rather a continuation of the discussion with the cast that followed. As one of the cast-members remarked, it all comes down to audience: "Black folks probably wouldn't go to the theater to see this play in the U.S., let alone have enough money for the ticket. And here, we have a white audience. So, who are we really talking to here? Who is seeing this play?"...
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>As a student of my own history and place in this world, nothing is more difficult for me than to write about issues of privilege, white-ness, black-ness, and justice in one sitting, because there is so much that can go wrong, so many terms that can be mis-used or mis-assigned, and so many truths that cannot be conveyed in one text. I have done my best. And with all my socio-anthropological know-how, I may still miss the point or offend, for which I am sorry: so is the nature of the subject.</em></p>
<p>One attends a play about an <em>Afrodeutscher* &#8211; </em>Afro-German &#8211; living in the years of Nazism and Jim Crow not because of the dramaturgy. One buys the ticket because of the topic, i.e. its novelty and near absence in the German discourse. &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221;, &#8220;Made Black&#8221;, at the <a href="http://www.etberlin.de/">English Theatre Berlin</a> explores the rich text of race in 1930s Berlin through the experience of Klaus, an unknowing Afro-German &#8211; a word that still spikes the air with rarity, German-ness still seen by many as a monopoly of the white-skinned.</p>
<p>But Klaus&#8217;s character and his experience of targeted exclusion are not that far from the present, as a conversation with the cast will demonstrate.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_4.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_4.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht" width="640" height="1016" /></a></p>
<p>The play&#8217;s dense telling of a complicated history of race, citizenship, and post-colonialism through dialogue is impressive. Equally worthy of praise is the playwright&#8217;s collaboration with a well-versed historian.  The Afro-German actor, with a biography startlingly similar to the protagonist he portrays, is also seemingly extraordinary. The most important element, however, relates to its audience and what this means for theater as a medium of cultural critique.</p>
<p>This is not a review of the play, per se, on which the curtains closed this past Sunday. Rather, this is a review of the discussion with the cast, playwright, and director that came after, the sentiments of which will remain prominent and powerful in my mind, long after audience members have discarded their ticket stubs.</p>
<p><strong>The Conversation</strong></p>
<p>Thursday night, we, a primarily white audience, wait patiently for the cast to take their places at the foot of the stage. The protagonist of the play, the actor to play the American jazz musician, the actor to play the German politician, the playwright (Alexander Thomas), and the director file into folding chairs. <strong>&#8220;Black folks probably wouldn&#8217;t go to the theater to see this play in the U.S., let alone have enough money for the ticket. And here, we have a white audience. So, who are we really talking to here? Who is seeing this play?&#8221;</strong>, says the actor who plays the Black American musician &#8211; the play&#8217;s connective thread to Jim Crow.<strong> </strong>The scene seems to agree.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_3.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2259" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_3.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht theater cast" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>Daniel Brunet, the mustached upstate New Yorker who produces the <a href="http://www.etberlin.de/producing-series/the-lab/">LAB series</a> for the English Theatre and directed this play, chimes in about the lack of representation of certain &#8220;communities&#8221; in cultural institutions. The problem of equitable, fair representation is something sure to resound for both American and German audiences, though certainly in different ways.</p>
<p>This problem is an old one. But it rattles and recalls Berlin&#8217;s more recent debates on multiculturalism, intercultural politics, and the integration &#8211; or just plain tolerance &#8211; of difference. &#8220;The topic of being German <em>and </em>of<em> </em>being a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Person_of_color">person of color</a> (p.o.c.) continues, often with little progress&#8221;, a p.o.c. from the audience remarks, a hint of a German accent in the throat. This topic is contemporary, indeed.</p>
<p><strong>Can theater change these parameters? Can theater ask for more diversity from institutions that have no incentive to include them?</strong></p>
<p>The playwright, a Black American married to a white German woman, wrote &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; as a way to process &#8220;the complexity of these issues&#8221;. And yet, as he makes perfectly clear, representing his own stereotypes of Germans and &#8220;the lack of place in [his] mind for an Other of color in Germany&#8221; is central to the play. &#8220;Otherwise, I would have been acting dishonestly&#8221;, he says, looking into the glare, behind which fragments of the audience, of us, must appear.</p>
<p>The protagonist of the play, himself an Afro-German, speaks, his English flooded with German vowels, his mannerisms oddly similar to his character, who re-asserts his German identity proudly throughout the play in deference to the Othering looks of those around him. This Other, created by the Black American writer, is somehow a reflection of himself, he states, admitting how through rehearsals he struggled to read his lines, even bursting into tears; how the first time he read the play, he felt personally implicated and stripped bare. <strong>&#8220;I am German, my father left when I was three years old, I grew up with my mother, was born in Hamburg, that is all I have ever known”</strong>, he says. The biographies are nearly identical, minus 80 years and a certain regime.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2311.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2255" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2311.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht stage" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>The anger he enacts in the play now takes hold of his voice: the desperation and frustration. <strong>“Once I read the script I knew it had to be done, we had to make this play. Though, during intermission, when I was sprawled on the stage in a pile of paper [the stage is composed mainly of bundles and bundles of blank paper], I sometimes thought ‘what am I doing here, who am I talking to&#8217;”</strong>.</p>
<p>Despite these questions of audience and representation, the play successfully sends a message, one of critique. It weaves the complicated history of American segregation and its sub-human treatment of Blacks with the messianic framing of America&#8217;s involvement in WWII. Through the diverse arrangement of its characters, the play scrutinizes American moral authority in the fight against Nazi ideology and fascism, drawing dramatic attention to Jim Crow and the commonalities between racist ideologies.</p>
<p><strong>The parallels between American oppression and Nazi tyranny become painfully clear, eliciting the following question from the audience: &#8220;Would you show this play in America? And under what conditions?&#8221;</strong></p>
<p>&#8220;We would just need a theater to show it&#8221;, the playwright says with a smile, confidently speaking for the work alone. &#8220;The play was actually meant for an American audience&#8221;, he adds, hence the translation of German passages and numerous references to American &#8216;race sciences&#8217;, details often omitted from textbooks. &#8220;This is a history of not only segregation but of a science [eugenics and race-based Social Darwinism] that many Americans do not know about&#8221;.</p>
<p>Such a truth of ignorance is reflected in the young woman in the play, who claims that the protagonist, Klaus, is not like &#8220;the other Negroes back home!&#8221;, though she has &#8220;never met one&#8221;.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2258" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_2.jpg?w=640" alt="colonialism Jim Crow" width="640" height="411" /></a></p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Theater approaches many controversial political topics in the United States, because it can. A very particular demographic is going to the theater; and that is where such issues can be discussed&#8221;</strong>, Brunet adds.</p>
<p>The playwright explains that he is willing to relinquish artistic license and allow others to define the scope and boundaries of the play&#8217;s possible interpretations. Some scenes are based on his own childhood, others on historical research and collaboration with the author of <em><a href="https://www.press.umich.edu/174272/other_germans">Other Germans</a>, </em>Tina M. Campt<em>, </em>about being a person of African heritage in Germany.</p>
<p>&#8220;But what is the point of the play?&#8221;, the jazz musician asks, perhaps to the audience, perhaps to no one present in this room. It is not about carving out identity from the crowd, asserting the value of the image in the attic mirror, but rather &#8220;about convincing society – the powerful – that exclusion is harmful and degrading to human beings. Now, and back then!&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;The point is, speaking truth to power&#8221;</strong>, he says, referencing, most notably, <a href="http://www.cornelwest.com/">Dr. Cornel West</a>, a giant in the continued civil rights movement for people of color, for the exploited lower classes.</p>
<p>Theater is not a dialogue with the masses, nor a dialogue with society in general, however. &#8220;Like cultural media and cultural politics, it is a dialogue with the powerful and their ideas&#8221;, says Brunet. The rest is some trickle down effect or, as the p.o.c. from the audience adds, &#8220;a change in consciousness&#8221;.</p>
<p>The camera man, a towering Black man with an equally large voice, speaks to the political or &#8220;transformative nature of the play&#8221;: <strong>“Most people ask themselves the question, are things really that different now? That is what this play does, it asks that question again of the powerful&#8221;.</strong></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5em;">With these words, I instantly feel implicated by my privilege, the things afforded to me on the basis of the position and body I was born into. The room shrinks. I shift in my seat.</span></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5em;">We are the audience. We are the ones who should see this play. We shape the discourse, often to the detriment of those who do not fit the desired mold. Theater might be a chance to reflect on <a href="http://www.taz.de/!116745/">critical whiteness</a>, even on its limitations.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2296.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2250" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2296.jpg?w=640" alt="English Theatre Berlin" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>One of the members of the cast remarks, perhaps to break a long 15 seconds of silence, <strong>&#8220;Can we imagine a black actor playing Romeo? A white actor playing Othello? Is it bad that we can&#8217;t?&#8221;</strong> For the sake of this question, &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; should be produced in another season, maybe in another city, as a voice in a room with too few listeners.</p>
<p>I sincerely hope that it might be staged in the United States, a country, where diversity often means tolerating the one that is different but disrespecting him or her just the same. As <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/ta-nehisi-coates/">Ta-Nehisi-Coates</a> wrote in <em>The Atlantic</em> this Tuesday, <strong>&#8220;We are in America, where our absence of virtue is presumed, and we must eat disrespect in sight of our sons.<em> </em>And who can be mad in America? Racism is just the wind, here. Racism is but the rain.&#8221; </strong></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*After the Nazi dust had cleared the German capital and West German society had taken root, the Black American poet and activist Audrey Lorde began to popularize the term <em>Afrodeutsche(r) </em>or Afro-German,<em> </em>during <a href="http://www.audrelorde-theberlinyears.com/">her years in the city</a>, effectively building a movement that at least gave a name to an almost invisible population.</p>
<p><em>For more information on Afro-German history in English, click <a href="http://german.about.com/od/culture/a/blackhistger.htm">here</a>. For more information on Afro-German organizations in Berlin and in all of Germany: <a href="http://isdonline.de/">Initiative schwarze Menschen in Deutschland</a>, <a href="http://www.afro-deutsche.de/">Afrodeutsche e.V</a>, <a href="http://www.adefra.com/">Schwarze deutsche Frauen und schwarze Frauen in Deutschland</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>For an interesting twist, check out our <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/">article on Black Germans</a> (the change of language here was intentional) growing up in the United States to adoptive parents, often in the segregated South. </em></p>
<p>Photo source: Kelly Miller and <a href="http://jurigottschau.com/">Juri Gottschau</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: Difference in the Wet Country</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2014 12:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[provincial]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1986</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For nearly a month this holiday season, I explored the social fabric surrounding my US origins with a German national, who had never before been to the land of plenty. Through the fresh eyes of 'the foreigner', I saw my part of America unfold under a curious and critical lens. America is a country that defines itself by historical narratives of migration and manifest destiny. What one encounters on the road in its northwestern corner, however, is a bit more mundane. At closer glance, emptiness and the prosaic everyday give food for thought, in regards to locating and valuing difference wherever it bubbles up...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>How do you notice difference in a city, in which you yourself are different?</strong></p>
<div id="attachment_1992" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1992" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1992 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-1.jpg" alt="Portland, OR steel-bridge" width="640" height="360" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1992" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>For nearly a month this holiday season, I explored the social fabric surrounding my US origins with a German national, who had never before been to the land of plenty. Through the fresh eyes of &#8216;the foreigner&#8217;, I saw my part of America unfold under a curious and critical lens. Given this blog&#8217;s weekly critical handling of all things multicultural in the big city, why not talk about diversity in an American context? This context proves to be quite different from the aspiring-cosmopolitan intersections of the German capital, as shocking as that may or may not be.</p>
<p>America is a country that defines itself by historical narratives of migration and manifest destiny. What one encounters on the road in its northwestern corner, however, is a bit more mundane. At closer glance, emptiness and the prosaic everyday give food for thought, in regards to locating and valuing difference wherever it bubbles up.</p>
<p><strong>Geography matters</strong></p>
<p>Somehow, when we talk of diversity in society, the role of space therein is a side note. In fact, where we live, work, play, learn, and heal in many ways determines our belonging to or exclusion from social and economic groups that are important in ensuring opportunity.</p>
<p>Maps tell us a lot about how different ways of life can exist cohesively together. Maps may miss, however (<a href="http://www.npr.org/censusmap/#4.00/39.00/-84.00">see NPR&#8217;s US census map</a>), where difference pops up beyond the packed hotbeds for multiculturalism of the city, leaving our eyes to experience what the provinces, the forgotten towns, and the coastal sticks have to offer firsthand.</p>
<div id="attachment_1989" style="width: 311px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1989" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1989 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg" alt="Rebecca Vincent" width="301" height="300" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg 301w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent-300x299.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 301px) 100vw, 301px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1989" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Rebecca Vincent</p></div>
<p>In the Pacific Northwest, like many other regions, cartography shows the urban as an array of ever-revolving grids, residences dotting the margins of concrete webs and precise civil engineering, greenery contained, parks splashed with beige and lived-in browns. One passes through these strange boundaries of growth, as if moving through the trunk of a tree to reach its core, each ring giving way to new densities and shapes of living, suburbia giving way to semi-rural apartment clusters and neatly arranged town homes.</p>
<div id="attachment_2001" style="width: 471px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2001" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2001  " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png?w=640" alt="portland map" width="461" height="347" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png 646w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map-300x226.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map-80x60.png 80w" sizes="(max-width: 461px) 100vw, 461px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2001" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Mappery.com</p></div>
<p>Apart from the patterns and markings of cities, great expanses of forest or farmland separate bundles of life from one another. Beyond the edge of the urban, an emptiness emerges. Where cities end, mountain pass truck-stops, wine-making valleys, flat dairy country, coastal trailer parks, and retired logging towns begin. Vehicles connect what trains used to. Marks on the map created for the movement between these revolving grids begin to surface like geometric occurrences of ink. Here humans somehow ended up, often fairly alone with only the company of a gas station and a corner store.</p>
<div id="attachment_2002" style="width: 476px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2002" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2002   " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png?w=640" alt="oregon map" width="466" height="375" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png 749w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map-300x241.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map-650x522.png 650w" sizes="(max-width: 466px) 100vw, 466px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2002" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Oregon Office of Rural Health</p></div>
<p>Passing through such places on the road from one side of the state of Oregon to the next, the new set of eyes saw only distance, forged together by oil rigs and spinning tires. <em>Density can be an advantage, when it comes to social and cultural encounters needed for intercultural understandings to take root</em>, I thought, as we searched for a place to eat on a long stretch that seemed to allow only signage, fast food, and campgrounds.</p>
<div id="attachment_1990" style="width: 471px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-2.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1990" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-1990 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-2.jpg" alt="Portland, OR steel-bridge " width="461" height="614" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1990" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>And yet, the migrant worker shantytown in Southwest Washington, the Korean BBQ embedded in the Tillamook state forest, the sushi bar near Mt. Hood’s base, the taco trucks at truck-stops, the Chinese waiter at the roadside diner all suggest that even in more expansive geographies, difference can occur.</p>
<p><strong>Just because it is there, doesn&#8217;t mean we will notice it</strong></p>
<p>On our way to the valley of the Rogue River, our over-sized vehicle wound down the Pacific Highway, hugging cliffs of the sea and the edges of a strange poverty. We saw mile after mile of rotting cottages, mobile homes made more mobile by landslides, empty villages with the local pub serving bento, tacos, and chowder, and liquor stores the size of the local church beside it. Catholic churches sprouted up in these towns, in the basin of the interstate or at the rim of the sea &#8211; something I did not take notice of at first, but which suggested some shift, an immigration. Those who find ships in the right season or canneries with need for cheaply-bought hands make their way back to the Saints to thank them for their providence, or so it seemed.</p>
<p>In the foggy valleys of dead logging towns, the basin of the interstate, the depressed dairy lands and empty harbors: here the German traveler experienced my part of America with its shady diners where breakfast and hot sauce are served all day, roadside shacks with a For Sale sign, Walmart’s to nowhere. And in between the lines, difference was there, simply glossed over by the mundanity of its appearance, bearing more than John Wayne&#8217;s Americana.</p>
<div id="attachment_1994" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/streeet.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1994" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-1994 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/streeet.jpg?w=640" alt="street Portland, OR" width="640" height="360" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1994" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>The churches that never cease to be obvious and enormous on major highways; the Mexican restaurants with happy signs and plenty of American families digging into re-fried beans and rice, as if it were the national dish; the Japanese restaurants with pictures of majestic mountains that could be local; medical advertisements with black patients and Asian doctors; a South Asian newscaster in a suit just like everybody else; a black reporter stuck to sports on the local news station: these things I may not have noticed without the presence of the new perspective next to me.</p>
<p><strong>It is not about what we say, but about what is heard</strong></p>
<div id="attachment_1991" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/diner-pwf-0066.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1991" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-1991" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/diner-pwf-0066.jpg?w=300" alt="Photo source: Paul Winch-Furness" width="300" height="199" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1991" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Paul Winch-Furness</p></div>
<p>For the German&#8217;s second breakfast in America, we took him to a local diner in southwest Washington with the classic booths and red upholstery, simple fried numbers, and a healthy rotation of pies. As he ordered, his slight accent turned the words into mildly different sounds, his tongue pushing just a bit too far back for the &#8216;l&#8217; and the &#8216;th&#8217; sticking to the front of his teeth. The letters may have come together in a way that did not quite fit the frames we have learned to repeat, but one could and can simply understand. And so &#8216;the waffle special&#8217; was transmitted to the kitchen with no questions asked. And after we had told the waitress in her darling little apron that it was his first time in an American diner, she beamed at the foreigner sitting there in front of the simple white dishware and the paper napkin. She whispered to the other waitress, who, blushing, came over to our table to pour coffee and welcome him to town.</p>
<p>It is not about the sounds being right. It is about our understanding them.</p>
<p><strong>Being an outsider can come in handy, as I have learned on the other side of the Atlantic</strong></p>
<p>Growing up in the far corner of the Western United States, I am familiar with the figures and curves of this particular landscape and society. I have, however, sorely taken for granted what it means to have tacos in the middle of nowhere, to celebrate Persian New Year with friends, or to consider Phở as American as bratwurst (I can thank Seattle for that). In many ways, difference was a natural part of my private and public education, the neighborhoods where I lived, the sports teams I played on, and the churches I attended. I cannot say that I have consciously valued these experiences for what I learned from them. If such encounters and relationships had popped up in my Berlin world, I would have celebrated them. This is largely due to the ways in which diversity is or is not celebrated by society at large and how we might attempt to remedy this fact.</p>
<p>But what is most striking and assuredly the take-away from this tale is that campaign-worthy diversity in the big city is not all there is, nor is it of greater value than the outcroppings of difference at truck-stops off the interstate. This might be where it counts the most.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Ethno-cultural diversity is changing the face of the rural United States, including states like Oregon and Washington. For a great visual of this transformation, see the <a href="http://www.ers.usda.gov/media/176091/page7.pdf">United States Department of Agriculture&#8217;s map from its Rural Population and Migration Brieﬁng Room</a>. As the roadside taco trucks and shantytowns demonstrate, a large wave of migration from Latin America to the Pacific Northwest region has characterized rural growth from 2000-2012, according to the <a href="http://www.ers.usda.gov/amber-waves/2011-december/hispanics-contribute-to-increasing-diversity.aspx#.Ut5lnRA1iM8">USDA&#8217;s recent report</a> on demography. Reflective of this shift to the out-country from the urban heart, is the <a href="http://www.oregonlive.com/pacific-northwest-news/index.ssf/2011/04/in_portlands_heart_diversity_dwindles.html">dwindling diversity in the heart of Portland, OR</a>. Difference is, thus, not always where you expect to find it.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The N-Word</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2013 12:20:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nazi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=658</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When I posted the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/">Who's/Whose Normal?</a> article a few weeks ago, I expected the "N-word" of interest to be<em> Neger</em>, a term that falls somewhere between "negro" and "nigger" on the translation and offensiveness spectrum. Instead, the strongest reactions came in response to another N-Word: Nazi...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;">When I posted the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/">Who&#8217;s/Whose Normal?</a> article a few weeks ago, I expected the &#8220;N-word&#8221; of interest to be<em> Neger</em>, a term that falls somewhere between &#8220;negro&#8221; and &#8220;nigger&#8221; on the translation and offensiveness spectrum. Instead, the strongest reactions came in response to another N-Word: Nazi.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/thenword.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-756" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/thenword.png" alt="thenword" width="546" height="366" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">For those who haven&#8217;t read the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/">original post</a>, the controversy stemmed from a comparison I made between a Berlin storefront poster campaign and Nazi propaganda (on an aesthetic &#8211; not political &#8211; basis). On second thought, I shouldn&#8217;t put that last bit in parentheses, because it&#8217;s the essence of my point. Despite Berlin being <strong>Germany&#8217;s most ethnically and culturally diverse city</strong>, these particular <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/2013-04-11-09-35-05.jpg">storefront posters</a> feature <em>only</em> heterosexual Caucasian families. On an aesthetic basis (skin tone, facial features, body build), they don&#8217;t differ much from the fair blond couples on Nazi posters. A couple brunettes are included here or there, but I don&#8217;t consider that diversity. The bad man himself was a brunette, no? That&#8217;s probably not going to make me any friends either.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">While I am in no way comparing the people from this store to Nazis (I repeat: in no way!), I was disappointed by these posters and the message they send. On multiple posters and within an <a href="http://www.leiser.de/frontend/startseite.htm">entire website</a>, I find it disconcerting to see only one type of ethnicity, sexuality, and idea of beauty. And both creative process scenarios &#8211; whether <em>Leiser</em> consciously made this decision or didn&#8217;t realize that this is what they were doing &#8211; are also disconcerting.</p>
<p>Although many agreed with me that the images were problematic, my Nazi comparison was not as well-received. In the spirit of promoting discourse and &#8220;seeing things from every lens&#8221;, I thought it critical to share a selection of these reactions. Disclaimer: All German comments have been loosely translated by yours truly.</p>
<p><strong>German Commenter 1:</strong> In the U.S., you use the term &#8220;Nazi&#8221; as a joke, e.g. &#8220;You&#8217;re a cleaning Nazi&#8221;, just like we say the term <em>Negerküss</em> [Nigger-kiss]. Neither group considers the history and context of the other. In Germany, we only call really evil and abominable people Nazis, people who seem to be OK with what the Nazis did. It is the worst insult you can give someone. That&#8217;s why it&#8217;s such a hard pill for me to swallow when &#8220;normal&#8221; people (even if they are racist or discriminatory) are compared with Nazis, just like it is hard for Americans when they hear us use the term <em>Neger</em>.</p>
<p><strong>German Commenter 2:</strong> Sophia, you have to be really careful with the use of the term &#8220;Nazi&#8221;. Your comparison [of the storefront posters] to Nazi propaganda goes too far. Germans have a total complex when it comes to our history and you can&#8217;t just make that sort of comparison. As an American, you can&#8217;t understand how hard it is growing up with this history&#8230; You&#8217;re not exactly going to make friends with this sort of comparison.</p>
<p><strong>German/American Commenter in response to above:</strong> Is being critical un-German? Isn&#8217;t that how the Germans got into the Nazi/Holocaust mess to begin with?</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>American Commenter in response to above:</strong> Oh my god! Do these people seriously believe that anti-black racism is the same as calling someone &#8220;a cleaning Nazi&#8221;?? And that you can&#8217;t possibly understand that because you didn&#8217;t grow up there? WTF! I&#8217;m not jumping in because I don&#8217;t want to hijack a thread and you&#8217;re being much more diplomatic than I would be, but dude! What the hell!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-767 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes.jpg" alt="yikes" width="592" height="437" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes-300x221.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 592px) 100vw, 592px" /></a><strong>Me after reading the comments</strong></p>
<p>What these comments have made clear is that context is paramount in the interpretation of language. Perhaps more importantly, however, it has made clear that one shouldn&#8217;t limit themselves to only their immediate context. We can&#8217;t always dissect every word to see if it may offend someone, but we should be more mindful of the political, cultural, and historical contexts of other groups when using potentially hurtful language.</p>
<p>I&#8217;ve often heard that Americans are more PC (politically-correct) than Europeans. Yet, this discussion has shown me that that is not necessarily the case. All nations have sore spots in their histories &#8211; some more recent than others, some that should be sorer than they seem to be &#8211; where we need to tread lightly. We also handle these sensitive topics differently. There&#8217;s still no slavery memorial in Washington, DC, but the German capital is laden with memorials and museums acknowledging their &#8220;black mark on history&#8221;. Americans are known for being the kings (&amp; queens!) of PC language, but the Germans actually came up with a dictionary of Nazi terms to promote awareness of their use.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/350_b22810-2_u1d.gif"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/350_b22810-2_u1d.gif" alt="350_B22810-2_U1D" width="350" height="469" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>&#8220;A &#8216;Coming To Terms With The Past&#8217; Dictionary: The use of Nazi language in public speech&#8221; (</strong><a href="http://www.google.de/imgres?um=1&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sa=N&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;hl=de&amp;biw=1540&amp;bih=844&amp;tbm=isch&amp;tbnid=Ynymf1mQ2JxEDM:&amp;imgrefurl=http://www.wbg-wissenverbindet.de/WBGShop/php/Proxy.php%3Fpurl%3D/wbg/products/show,29637.html&amp;docid=VJO4nm_T0fhTJM&amp;itg=1&amp;imgurl=http://www.wbg-wissenverbindet.de/WBGShop/resources/cover/350_B22810-2_U1D.gif&amp;w=350&amp;h=469&amp;ei=WDWvUYqbB4bTtAapy4C4BA&amp;zoom=1&amp;iact=rc&amp;dur=292&amp;page=1&amp;tbnh=133&amp;tbnw=99&amp;start=0&amp;ndsp=60&amp;ved=1t:429,r:5,s:0,i:99&amp;tx=83&amp;ty=83">Source</a><strong>)</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Yes, the Germans have a word for &#8220;coming to terms with the past&#8221;: <em>Vergangenheitsbewältigung.</em> <em>Vergangenheit</em> simply means &#8220;the past&#8221;, but <em>bewältigen </em>can translate to several verbs, including &#8220;to overcome&#8221;<em>. </em><strong>What does it mean &#8211; as nations and people -to overcome difficult periods in our history?</strong> Does it mean erecting public memorials and monuments? Does it mean holding companies responsible for the images that they portray and promote? Does it mean never using the &#8220;N-word&#8221; or, alternately, being able to use it as a joke? I&#8217;m all ears and mindful speech.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Over and Over</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 09:20:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.wordpress.com/?p=59</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Migrants face the concept of identity more acutely than many other groups</strong>. As they move from one geographic and cultural setting to another, they are presented with a new set of rules and codes for becoming a "member of a group" - their "distinct personality" may be interpreted differently than it was in their home country. The transition from migrant to "resident" or "citizen" is also laden with complications - legally, personally, and socially - both from the perspective of the migrant's identity and the national identity of the host country....]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>Identity.</strong> Derived from the Late Latin term <em>identitas</em> meaning &#8220;over and over&#8221; or &#8220;sameness,&#8221; it&#8217;s defined as “the set of behavioral or personal characteristics by which an individual is recognizable as a member of a group” and “the distinct personality of an individual regarded as a persisting entity.” These are two divergent ideas: <strong>identity makes one belong </strong>(&#8220;member of a group&#8221;)<strong> and it makes one stand out </strong>(&#8220;distinct personality&#8221;).  Identities, therefore, have the potential to both include and exclude. They are socially-constructed, meaning they&#8217;re susceptible to social context and can differ depending on how one sees oneself vs. how one is seen by others. And perhaps most importantly, they&#8217;re not static; they have the potential to shift and adapt with time.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/identity_trailer.png"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/identity_trailer.png" alt="Identity_trailer" width="550" height="311" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Migrants face the concept of identity more acutely than many other groups</strong>. As they move from one geographic and cultural setting to another, they are presented with a new set of rules and codes for becoming a &#8220;member of a group&#8221; &#8211; their &#8220;distinct personality&#8221; may be interpreted differently than it was in their home country. The transition from migrant to &#8220;resident&#8221; or &#8220;citizen&#8221; is also laden with complications &#8211; legally, personally, and socially &#8211; both from the perspective of the migrant&#8217;s identity and the national identity of the host country. <strong>Part of this is due to language.</strong> Countries categorize immigrants differently, which in turn affects how people within that country view immigrants. It&#8217;s certainly not the whole story, but it plays a role, and it merits some thought.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/identity-crisis-for-salisbury.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/identity-crisis-for-salisbury.jpg" alt="identity-crisis-for-salisbury" width="300" height="377" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">For example, I was recently asked by a German why Americans are so quick to evoke information about their heritage (right after I had told him about my heritage, funnily enough). &#8220;Why isn&#8217;t being just American enough?&#8221; he asked. My responding smirk, nod, and shrug were half-agreement and half-annoyance. While I am proud of my mixed background and international family, I also roll my eyes at the 3rd generation, self-proclaimed &#8220;Irish-American&#8221; whose only connection to the country is celebrating St. Patrick&#8217;s Day, or the <a href="http://www.wetpaint.com/jersey-shore/articles/is-the-jersey-shore-cast-really-italian">Jersey Shore star claiming to be Italian</a>. But for good or for worse, Americans have embraced the idea of the hyphenated identity, and it spans generations.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/toast-mit-migrationshintergrund.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/toast-mit-migrationshintergrund.jpg" alt="Toast-mit-Migrationshintergrund" width="477" height="358" /></a><a href="http://anny-thing.de/2011/06/29/caught-in-the-city-of-dust/toast-mit-migrationshintergrund/">Source</a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">In Germany, the language is reversed. Rather than being Turkish-German, Germans with Turkish roots are often called <em>Deutschtürken</em> (German-Turks). <strong>In this linguistic formation, German is modifying Turkish, and Turkish remains the defining attribute.</strong> Within everyday speak, the <em>Deutsch</em> is often dropped and they are simply called <em>Türken</em>, even if they were born in Germany. For official state statistics and in the census, the German government classifies any migrant or their offspring as <em>mit Migrationshintergrund</em> (with migration background). Also common is the term <em>nicht deutsche Herkunft</em> (not of German origin).</p>
<div style="width: 235px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/junge-mit-migrationshintergrund-225x300.jpg"><img loading="lazy" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/junge-mit-migrationshintergrund-225x300.jpg" alt="junge-mit-migrationshintergrund-225x300" width="225" height="300" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Who you calling a migrant?</p></div>
<p style="text-align: left;">While these classifications are useful for targeting migrant groups for integration efforts, they can also be exclusionary within social discourse. This is especially the case for the 2nd and 3rd generations, who are classified virtually no differently than newly arrived migrants despite having been born and grown up in Germany. It was also only a little more than a decade ago, in 2000, when Germany introduced a <em>jus soli</em> (birthplace) citizenship provision to allow children of migrants to apply for German citizenship. Thinking back to that German from earlier: I wonder if he&#8217;s thought about the fact that while many of those <em>mit Migrationshintergrund</em> would find being &#8220;just German&#8221; more than enough, they may never have the opportunity to.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton<br />
</strong></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
