<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Germany &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/germany/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Value of Foreign Life: when the law demands &#8220;integration&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/08/25/the-value-of-foreign-life/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2016 11:23:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bundestag]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[language-learning]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4676</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Until now, immigration policy in Germany has followed a pathway defined by residency, employment, and citizenship restrictions. Put another way, policy has been concerned with 3 primary questions: Who is allowed to stay, who is allowed to work, and who is, ultimately, allowed to participate fully in the political process of the Federal Republic. But something changed this past July, when German Parliament passed its first ever law mandating a particular type of immigrant and refugee integration. Source: DPA The new Integrationsgesetz mandates fulfillment of a German principle of social and economic assimilation. This principle has little precedent, in terms of a comprehensive law. There have been expectations and additions to existing legislation in the past, but never has there been governmental action specifically devoted to the question of whether or not newcomers have found ways to fit in. And never has this governmental action been tied to sanctions, if benchmarks and timelines aren&#8217;t met. The new law measures the ability of newcomers to fare well on the basis of language and employment, with respect to natives: They are to learn German, well, within 5 years and become economically self-sufficient as soon as possible. Welfare and other subsidies are tethered to employment programs. Specific to [...]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Until now, immigration policy in Germany has followed a pathway defined by residency, employment, and citizenship restrictions. Put another way, policy has been concerned with 3 primary questions: Who is allowed to stay, who is allowed to work, and who is, ultimately, allowed to participate fully in the political process of the Federal Republic.</p>
<p>But something changed this past July, when <a href="http://www.bmi.bund.de/SharedDocs/Pressemitteilungen/DE/2016/07/integrationsgesetz-vom-bundestag-verabschiedet.html">German Parliament passed its first ever law mandating a particular type of immigrant and refugee integration</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4686" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4686" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4686 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte-650x365.jpeg" alt="fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte" width="650" height="365" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte-650x365.jpeg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte-300x169.jpeg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte.jpeg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte-310x174.jpeg 310w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4686" class="wp-caption-text">Source: <a href="http://www.bmi.bund.de/SharedDocs/Pressemitteilungen/DE/2016/07/integrationsgesetz-vom-bundestag-verabschiedet.html"> DPA</a></p></div>
<p>The new <em>Integrationsgesetz </em>mandates fulfillment of a German principle of social and economic assimilation. This principle has little precedent, in terms of a comprehensive law. There have been expectations and additions to existing legislation in the past, but never has there been governmental action specifically devoted to the question of whether or not newcomers have found ways to fit in. And never has this governmental action been tied to sanctions, if benchmarks and timelines aren&#8217;t met.</p>
<p>The new law measures the ability of newcomers to fare well on the basis of language and employment, with respect to natives: They are to learn German, well, within 5 years and become economically self-sufficient as soon as possible. Welfare and other subsidies are tethered to employment programs. Specific to refugees, asylum applicants awaiting refugee status will be recruited for low-paying (1 euro/hour) jobs as soon as they are registered with the authorities, no matter the qualifications they bring with them from their home countries.</p>
<p>This approach is known as the welfare-to-work model, popularized by the Clinton administration in the U.S. and implemented in Germany since 2002 in the form of the <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/thema/arbeitslosengeld_ii/">Hartz-IV</a> reforms. <a href="http://99percentinvisible.org/episode/magic-bureaucrat-riverside-miracle/">Research has shown</a> that welfare-to-work programs, rather than re-training newcomers or supporting them while they seek jobs for which they are actually qualified, have serious long-term consequences. Stagnation and even regression is the word.</p>
<p>The integration law presupposes and, indeed, requires a &#8220;help yourself&#8221; attitude. This was precisely the message of the German austerity program of Hartz-IV, forever unpopular among the Left. This correlation between the new integration program and austerity language has led some members of German Parliament to send up flares.</p>
<p>The economist and Green Party representative Brigitte Pothmar <a href="https://www.tagesschau.de/inland/integrationsgesetz-127.html">criticized the intent and scope</a> of the law specifically on the point of low-wage jobs: &#8220;According to its supporters&#8217; own language, the legislature plans to spend 3 million euros on ridding refugees of boredom. But refugees don&#8217;t need occupational therapy. They want to learn and they want to actually get to work!&#8221;</p>
<p>A <a href="https://www.tagesschau.de/inland/integrationsgesetz-127.html">similar critique was wielded </a>by the Left Party representative Sabine Zimmerman, calling the law exclusionary at best. In terms of the economy, in particular, &#8220;This type of work [1 euro jobs] does not provide any opportunity to earn qualifications or to truly learn the language. In effect, it makes it even harder for real opportunities to come about.&#8221;</p>
<p>But it is not only the language of self-help and the threat of stagnation that these parliamentary representatives are worried about. If newcomers are unable to reach German proficiency in 5 years&#8217; time or are unable to maintain employment, residency permits will not be renewed or will be outright denied. Other sanctions, such as restrictions on housing and overall mobility, also apply.</p>
<p>Likewise, those who prove to be &#8220;exceptionally well integrated,&#8221; according to the law&#8217;s system of measurement, will be granted the privilege of ungarnered residency within 5 years. There is a carrot at the end of the integration stick. And it looks a lot like survival.</p>
<p>The media&#8217;s response to the new integration law, as well as that of practitioners in the field, has been swift and strident, criticizing the way in which the word &#8220;integration&#8221; is tied to fundamentals like housing and residency permits. The well-respected German weekly <em>die Zeit </em><a href="http://www.zeit.de/politik/deutschland/2016-05/integrationsgesetz-fluechtlinge-wohnsitz-parlament-meseberg">reported the law&#8217;s final drafting</a> with the headline &#8220;Work better, fail quicker.&#8221; Another well-respected paper, the daily <em>Süddeutsche Zeitung</em>, printed the news with the headline &#8220;An integration law that doesn&#8217;t deserve its name.&#8221;</p>
<p>This new law does intend to simplify and expedite the processing of the many asylum applications Germany continues to receive. For many of the law&#8217;s opponents, this addition of asylum proceeding reform was reason enough to support the law. Yet it may be more restrictive than helpful to those applying for asylum. The <a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article156905294/Unter-einer-Bedingung-koennen-abgelehnte-Asylbewerber-bleiben.html">headline provided by the right-leaning daily</a> <em>die Welt </em>for the new law is telling: &#8220;Asylum-seekers can stay only under one condition.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>Value Judgement</strong></p>
<p>What does this have to do with the title of this article, the value of a foreign life?</p>
<p>Any subject of law, citizen or not, is assigned a particular value, as reflected in and by society. Law most often protects the value of the universal person in that it prevents harm and injustice within the scope of its jurisdiction, no matter the origin of said person. Natives cannot kill tourists or undocumented migrants, for example. This is still a crime.</p>
<p>But this goes both ways. Law is discerning, as are its makers. It can decide when and if certain protections or privileges are granted. In this act of exercising certain judgment, determining who is the recipient and who is not, a value judgement is passed. In the case of Germany&#8217;s new and unprecedented integration law, those who become German in the ways the law prescribes have value enough to stay. Those who fall short do not.</p>
<p>This value judgement is apparent in the language of the law itself, as well as in discussions surrounding it. One example is the usage of the word &#8220;<em>i</em><em>ntegrationsunwillig</em>&#8220;, meaning &#8220;unwilling to integrate.&#8221; Its counterpart, a noun, is <em>Integrationsverweigerung</em>, which takes a stronger tone: It means &#8220;refusal to integrate.&#8221; The subjects who exhibit these traits become subject to the sanctions mentioned above, likely to eventual deportation, thus forfeiture of assets, professional networks, and personal relationships in Germany.</p>
<p>This language makes clear assumptions about intent and character far more than it does about simply the state of things, of whether or not an individual has found him/_/herself to belong in their new home. &#8220;Unwilling&#8221; implies a flouting of both convention and the laws of the land. Cultural difference becomes cultural deviance within this frame, and those who do not fit in effectively become criminals.</p>
<p>The perceived understanding of integration behind this language of &#8220;unwilling&#8221; is most problematic in that it devalues the experience of the newcomer and abdicates the native of certain responsibilities by way of this process.</p>
<p>In other words, what of the many natives who will refuse to grant newcomers a job because of their last name, because of their fear of ISIS or simply of Islam?</p>
<p>What of the slow-moving bureaucracy that will prevent timely and efficient completion of an integration course, or of the notoriously unfriendly bureaucrats who will make registration for state-subsidized language courses or other training programs a painful and humiliating process?</p>
<p>Will the other side, at any point in this hypothetical pathway to official integration, be charged with an unwilling and outright difficult attitude?</p>
<p>The law, by default of its creation, values natives above foreigners. The answers to all the above questions will tend to err on the side of the native for this reason, and responsibility will continue to be a weight born by the weakest, the least valued. These are the immigrants, the asylum-seekers, and the refugees of today.</p>
<p>Germany has done so much good for the refugees of the world in this past year. This new law is an unfortunate development.</p>
<p>It is unfortunate that the integration law negates the complexity of human behavior and the ways in which human beings tend to respond to mechanisms of control. It is unfortunate that it transforms a once two-way street into a narrow, one-way turnpike, failing to recognize that tying belonging to an existential crisis is one sure way to create another type of crisis, one of protracted isolation and despair. <strong><br />
</strong></p>
<p><strong>The Way Out</strong></p>
<p>One does not become a part of a group by the force of policy, nor does one come to belong anywhere by resigning to segregation and the apathy of staying apart.</p>
<p>But I for one would rarely speak to my German neighbors if I didn&#8217;t feel that they would smile at me and wish to speak back. I am too sensitive of feeling unwanted and merely tolerated to make myself so vulnerable. In a similar way, if I were just learning German, I would rarely try to order in German on a busy bakery morning. I would rarely try to ask any questions of the service personnel at the mall. I would be too afraid of looking and feeling defeated for the stern face, the impatient twitch, and the impolite interruption that often peppers such interactions with shame.</p>
<p>And if I cannot imagine doing these things, as someone with no experience of war or traumatic displacement, I cannot imagine it for all newcomers from Syria and elsewhere &#8211; human beings who have suffered the extremes of suffering.</p>
<p><strong>Laws may not be made for empathetic social responses, but norms are. In response to this new law, a little normative empathy is in order. Perhaps it is time not for sanctions but for a new German way of being with each other.<br />
</strong></p>
<p>Small gestures like the prolific smile, like deferring to others in line at the grocery store, like trying (only trying!) to give directions in English, like waiting patiently for a German-learner to get out their form of a German sentence, will bring the empathy this law is so clearly lacking. If this happens, Syrians and Afghans and Eritreans and Kurds (etc) are made to feel that they are also people of value.</p>
<p>For anthropologists and sociologists, value is a social construct. It does not exist inherent to things, to substance. Rather it is made within a system of prioritizing this, disregarding that, supporting the success of this and punishing the success of that. Value is a trait or state to be expressed through norms, such as everyday behavior, as well as structures, such as divisions of labor or the segmentation of achievement within public schools*. It is a process, not a prescription.</p>
<p>We&#8217;ll see soon enough if the process can rise above this law.</p>
<p>&#8211;<em>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*For more on this critical view of how and why value is created in society, see the well-known work of anthropologist David Graeber on the topic, available as a PDF <a href="https://monoskop.org/File:Graeber_David_Toward_an_Anthropological_Theory_of_Value.pdf">here</a>. You will never see prices and social priorities the same!</p>
<p><iframe style="position: absolute; top: 0px; left: 0px; width: 1px; height: 1px; visibility: hidden; background: #ffffff none repeat scroll 0% 0%;" name="xdcom_frame" width="300" height="150"></iframe></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Women Only: The Frauenraum</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 15:42:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gender]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4385</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I'm at Rathaus Wilmersdorf, a former city hall building turned refugee home in Berlin, where I teach a literacy class once a week. The home initially opened its doors to 178 refugees in September 2015, following Merkel's famous "Wir schaffen das" ("We can do it") declaration that sidestepped the Dublin Regulation and opened up Germany's borders to thousands of asylum seekers.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4394 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-01-27 12.51.04" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>It&#8217;s Thursday at 10:55, and I&#8217;m running late. I rush up to the security guards and hand over my ID. <em>Helfer?</em> (&#8220;volunteer?&#8221;) they ask. <em>Ja</em>, I answer, and wait for them to scribble down my name and give me a number so I can sign out later. I thank them and head inside to the office to sign for the room keys and get my name tag. Then it&#8217;s through the foyer and up three floors to room 3092. When breakfast is running late, the right half of the stairwell is still filled by a neat line of people waiting for their turn in the cafeteria. I squeeze by, ruffling the hair of the kids I recognize.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m at Rathaus Wilmersdorf, a former city hall building turned refugee home in Berlin, where I teach a literacy class once a week. The home initially opened its doors to <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/berlin/bezirke/kudamm/notunterkunft-fuer-fluechtlinge-in-berlin-im-rathaus-wilmersdorf-fehlen-duschen-und-dolmetscher/12199798.html">178 refugees</a> in September 2015, following Merkel&#8217;s famous &#8220;Wir schaffen das&#8221; (&#8220;We can do it&#8221;) declaration that <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/germany/11821822/Germany-drops-EU-rules-to-allow-in-Syrian-refugees.html">sidestepped the Dublin Regulation</a> and opened up Germany&#8217;s borders to thousands of asylum seekers.</p>
<p>Today, over 1400 refugees live in the Rathaus &#8211; mostly from Syria, Afghanistan, and Iraq &#8211; and there is talk of opening up an adjacent building to house an additional 900. As is the case all over the city, this home simply wouldn&#8217;t function without the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/">on-going assistance of volunteers</a> who help out with everything from interpretation and teaching to administrative and kitchen support.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4456 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-01-08 10.34.54" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Over the past eight months, Rathaus Wilmersdorf has become somewhat of a success story as far as refugee accommodations in Berlin go. It&#8217;s been visited by President Joachim Gauck and American actor Ben Stiller, as well as received significant media praise for its leadership and facilities. <a href="http://www.morgenpost.de/berlin/article207089933/Vachroi-verabschiedet-sich-als-Heimleiter-in-Wilmersdorf.html">One article</a> listed off the home&#8217;s impressive amenities, which include medical and midwife services, a laundry room, a hair salon, an internet <span class="st">café</span>, and yes, even our literacy class.</p>
<p>The literacy class, or &#8220;AB class&#8221; as we call it, does go beyond what many other refugee homes in Berlin offer. But what the article&#8217;s authors fail to mention (and are likely unaware of), is that the course comes with a complicated backstory that is indicative of a larger debate surrounding refugees in Germany today.</p>
<p>It all started early this year, after one volunteer noticed that a group of women were not showing up for the German class offered on the home&#8217;s fourth floor. These women were mostly Afghan and the majority also illiterate. However, a bit of digging (and a heavy dose of interpretation) revealed that they weren&#8217;t avoiding the class because the level was too difficult, as originally suspected. They weren&#8217;t going because, in the fourth floor class, there were men present. Or depending on who tells the story, “Because their husbands wouldn’t let them”.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4600 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-05-19 12.43.22" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>The decision was therefore made to start a new class on the third floor, taught and attended exclusively by women. The class was to be an extension of the adjacent <em>Frauenraum</em> or &#8220;women&#8217;s room&#8221;. At Rathaus Wilmersdorf, the <em>Frauenraum</em> is a standing room open almost daily, so long as there are volunteers present. At the refugee home in former Tempelhof airport, the <em>Frauenraum</em> operates on a weekly project basis, led by a volunteer platform called <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">Give Something Back to Berlin</a>.</p>
<p>Regardless of the format, the concept remains the same: The <em>Frauenraum</em> is a safe place where women can be amongst themselves. In Rathaus Wilmersdorf, they sew, practice German, or just hang out and have a cup of tea. Small children are allowed, but men are forbidden from entering. We&#8217;ve even had to throw out a male journalist on occasion. The home&#8217;s former director described it as a place where &#8220;<a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/berlin/warum-thomas-de-vachroi-der-perfekte-aufbauhelfer-fuer-fluechtlingsheime-ist-23775578">female residents are enjoying their freedom and unveiling themselves.</a>&#8221; I can only assume he meant this both literally and figuratively, as not all the women wear headscarves, but some who do do indeed take them off when in the <em>Frauenraum</em> or during class.</p>
<p>I fell into the role of literacy teacher by way of the <em>Frauenraum</em>, where I started volunteering in January. The class was already up and running but they wanted to offer it on more days and were having trouble finding willing teachers. Other <em>Frauenraum</em> volunteers, I was told, had flatly refused to teach out of principle, scoffing at the idea that a separate class be created when there was a perfectly good one already on offer. This is Germany, after all, a country where men and women are presumably equal and interact on all levels of society. If the husbands had a problem with that, tough. Isn&#8217;t it in the best interest of these women that we integrate them into our way of life as quickly as possible?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4460 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-05-12 11.42.50" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>These days, it is difficult to have a discussion in Germany about refugees that doesn&#8217;t include a question about gender. <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/02/08/not-our-women-from-cologne-to-berlin/">Post-Cologne</a>, it is near impossible. Despite the fact that the attacks on New Year&#8217;s Eve were carried out by a more diverse group than originally portrayed in the media, that night&#8217;s unfortunate events have marked a turning point in attitudes towards refugees.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.focus.de/politik/deutschland/zdf-umfrage-offenbart-so-haben-die-silvester-uebergriffe-beeinflusst-was-deutsche-ueber-fluechtlinge-denken_id_5213962.html">One poll</a> showed that, between December 2015 and January 2016 alone, the number of Germans who felt the country couldn&#8217;t handle the influx of refugees rose from 46% to 60%. Thirty-three percent stated that Cologne had &#8220;fundamentally changed&#8221; their opinions about refugees. And the ring-wing <span class="st"><em>Alternative für Deutschland</em></span> (AfD) party, which initially emerged in opposition to the euro, has placed anti-refugee sentiment at the core of their increasingly popular platform. Their leader has controversially <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/alternative-for-germany-shows-its-true-right-wing-colors-a-1076259.html">called for the use of firearms against incoming refugees</a>.</p>
<p>This is the same country that was at the forefront of Europe&#8217;s refugee response only nine months ago. The same country that led the continent&#8217;s discourse on establishing a common European solution. The same country that initiated what became globally lauded as <em>Wilkommenskultur</em> (welcome culture).</p>
<p>So, what&#8217;s changed?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4401 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-650x650.jpg" alt="2016-02-10 11.59.46" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-300x300.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>When the “refugee crisis” hit Germany last summer, hundreds of residents felt compelled to slather butter on rolls and pass them out to refugees arriving at train stations. This was by all accounts heart-warming and admirable, but it was also the easy part. The conversation we are having now is a more complicated one, one that even the seemingly simple question of whether to offer a female-only literacy class echoes:</p>
<p>What happens next and how might our society change as a result?</p>
<p>One could blame Cologne, but the foundation for this confrontation was laid long before. A staggering <a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article147280667/Fuer-die-meisten-gehoert-der-Islam-nicht-zu-Deutschland.html">60% of the country</a> is of the opinion that Islam does not belong in Germany. (It is also worth noting that Germans consistently overestimate the number of Muslims living in the country. The real figure, while one of the highest in the EU, <a href="http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2015/11/17/5-facts-about-the-muslim-population-in-europe/">is still only 5.8%</a>.)</p>
<p>There is an underlying preconception in Germany, as in many Western countries, that Islam is synonymous with misogyny and a lack of female rights. That “<a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article149756193/Wie-Sumtes-Wutbuerger-lernten-Fluechtlinge-zu-lieben.html">according to their religion, women are nothing</a>” or even more extreme, that &#8220;<a href="http://www.vice.com/de/read/fluechtlinge-vergewaltigen-deutsche-kinder-wie-rassisten-versuchen-stimmung-gegen-alle-nicht-deutschen-zu-machen-775">these young men will come and rape our daughters</a>&#8220;. This preconception likely stems from a variety of factors: images we see in the media, politicians portraying Muslims as backward or extremist, or current conflicts within the Middle East. An argument heard less often is made by <a href="http://ideas.time.com/2013/11/01/do-muslim-women-need-saving/">Columbia University Professor Lila Abu-Lughod</a>, who explores the conflation of religion and socioeconomic status. Gender inequality within Muslim majority societies stems mainly from economic inequality, and migrants in Germany have traditionally been low-skilled. Therefore what we may label as clashes due to religion may have stronger roots in poverty and lack of opportunity.</p>
<p>Earlier this year in Berlin, <a href="http://www.rbb-online.de/politik/beitrag/2016/04/berlin-kopftuch-streit-vor-arbeitsgericht-keine-guetliche-einigung.html">a young teacher went to court</a> because she was denied a teaching post due to her headscarf (the case was thrown out on grounds of the state&#8217;s Neutrality Act). More recently in Switzerland, a <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-36382596">regional authority ruled</a> that two teenage brothers must shake the hands of their female teachers despite it being against their religious beliefs to touch women they are not related to. Traditionally receiving societies such as Germany are perpetually learning how to manage integration in the face of growing diversity. Unfortunately, we seem insistent on concentrating on how &#8220;their values&#8221; may threaten &#8220;ours&#8221;, rather than on what type of society we want to live in together.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4406 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-02-17 12.07.15" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>To be fair, my own engagement at the Rathaus has not come without challenges. On my first day teaching, I swallowed a lot of frustration as another volunteer and I watched the women turn to their husbands for approval before following us to class. <em>Nur Frauen</em> (&#8220;only women&#8221;), we tried to communicate to the more skeptical looking of the men with a smile, while I stifled the urge to roll my eyes.</p>
<p>We&#8217;ve also heard a host of disturbing stories by way of the interpreters. Rape, abuse, threats of divorce. Some stories are from Afghanistan while others allegedly took place here in Berlin. At times, I am ashamed to find myself relieved that I can&#8217;t talk to the women directly about what I&#8217;ve heard, for fear it might affect the way I interact with them. For now, our exchanges are limited to topics like telling time and types of fruit &#8211; they&#8217;re big fans of banana and pineapple &#8211; as well as the apparently always shocking and never boring topic of me being a 30 year old woman without a husband or children (some of my students have 6, 7, even 9 children).</p>
<p>But until we&#8217;re able to have those more in-depth conversations, I remain convinced that offering a class under imperfect circumstances is better than offering no women&#8217;s class at all. For what, I&#8217;ve asked myself, will give these women more independence than the ability to navigate the city on their own? And what will give them a better chance of being able to navigate the city on their own than the ability to read and write?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4405 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-04-20 10.14.53" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Nothing exhibited this more clearly to me than a few weeks ago, when we held an arts project week for our women. The week consisted of two trips to separate parks so they could learn about various plant types and practice drawing them. The excitement of the women was palpable. They got to have a Middle Eastern picnic, a real treat after months of bland cafeteria fare. They got to pick flowers in the woods to take back to the home. There was laughing, there was dancing, and there were so many selfies.</p>
<p>We later found out through interpreters that, for several of the women, it was their first time in a park without a husband or male relative.</p>
<p>At the end of the week, a local artist took the womens&#8217; drawings and stenciled them onto power boxes near the Rathaus. On the Friday, we took a stroll around the neighborhood together to see them for the first time. The Farsi-speaking volunteer asked the women to point out their drawings and explain why they chose to draw them specifically. &#8220;Who drew this?&#8221; she asked when we got to the second box, pointing to a beautiful palm tree. &#8220;Me,&#8221; answered one of our students, &#8220;I drew it because it reminds me of home. And if you cut off the head, the whole plant dies.&#8221;</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The Frauenraum at Rathaus Wilmersdorf is looking for volunteers. To get involved, sign up at https://volunteer-planner.org/.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>For another take on the headscarf, I recommend watching <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/video/2015/jun/24/hijab-not-oppression-feminist-statement-video">this Guardian video</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>All photos my own.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Moralpolitik and the Ressentiments of Change</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 15:35:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4120</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[According to headlines, the German government has pledged haven – albeit temporary in many cases – to up to 800,000 refugees or migrants applying for asylum in the country. The U.S., despite initial wavering, has signaled that it will work to raise its refugee quota yearly, with the goal of a 100,000 cap by 2017. Yet within and around this historical moment of humanitarian crisis and measured political response are the inflammatory words of Donald Trump. He recently roared to a crowd in Iowa that, if elected, he “will deport all of the 11 million illegal migrants in this country.”]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As German and U.S. refugee policies inevitably collide in light of current events, this writer finds herself in the United States. The other writer of this blog will soon be in Germany, taking stock of the so-called “refugee crisis” on the ground. On my side of the Atlantic, a crisis is not yet to be felt… at least not so acutely. This has as much to do with media semantics as it does with history.</p>
<p>According to headlines, the German government has pledged haven – albeit temporary in many cases – <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/aug/20/germany-raises-estimate-refugee-arrivals-800000">to up to 800,000 refugees or migrants applying for asylum in the country</a>. The U.S., despite initial wavering, <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/news/nation/2015/09/20/increase-admission-refugees-kerry-says/fnCweeIlCS8g47VF7VAkBP/story.html">has signaled that it will work to raise its refugee quota</a> yearly, with the goal of a 100,000 cap by 2017. The Pope, as leader of the spiritual state of Catholicism, <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">has planned to make migrants and refugees one of the few central issues of his travels around the Western Hemisphere this week</a>.</p>
<p>All at once, it seems that moral duty, a college ethics course, and politics have fused into one mandate to assist.</p>
<p>Yet within and around this historical moment of humanitarian crisis and measured political response are the inflammatory words of Donald Trump. He recently roared to a crowd in Iowa that, if elected, he “<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">will deport all of the 11 million illegal migrants in this country.</a>” When asked by Univision’s anchor Jorge Ramos how he would accomplish such a feat, he coolly responded, “I’m a great manager.”</p>
<div id="attachment_4127" style="width: 630px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4127" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-4127" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg" alt="Donald Trump immigration" width="620" height="372" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg 620w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP-300x180.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4127" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Charlie Neibergall/AP via <em><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">The Guardian</a></em></p></div>
<p>One can easily get caught up in the absurdity that is the American campaign season, enjoying its theatrics as a harmless part of the celebrity process. But Trump’s words should hold weight, and they should be cause for alarm.</p>
<p>Trump’s message is not as obtuse, as unnecessarily harsh as it might seem; it reflects not only present sentiment but historical precedent… for both the United States and Germany. With the current refugee and migrant crisis, old tensions are slowly and loudly being unearthed. And the mobility of many of the world&#8217;s displaced, traumatized, and poor is not likely to change any time soon.</p>
<p>National Public Radio’s <em>Fresh Air</em> <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/10/439114563/americas-forgotten-history-of-mexican-american-repatriation">recently interviewed</a> one of the scholars behind the book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Decade-Betrayal-Mexican-Repatriation-1930s/dp/0826339735">Decade of Betrayal: Mexican Repatriation in the 1930s</a>”. The volume documents a massive and relentless deportation program at a time when xenophobia and economic distress were rampant. Historians Raymond Rodriguez and Francisco Balderrama document what is nothing short of a terrifying episode in American history – frightening for what right-wing reactionaries in a new age of migration might be capable of.</p>
<p>As Rodriguez shared with <em>Fresh Air</em>’s host, Terry Gross, the 1930s treated Mexican Americans with great malice and abuse. For reason only of their heritage, they were targeted by government programs and private citizens alike. This abuse culminated in the federal government&#8217;s campaign to strip millions of Americans of their citizenship. Not all those rounded up in deportation raids were naturalized citizens, though <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">estimates suggest than ½ of those expelled were</a>. Most were visa-holders of some sort, their only crime having been born a member of a demonized ethnic group.</p>
<p>Governmental programs to round up and expel society’s undesirables often begin in cities, according to history (see the American strategy of Japanese internment or Nazi Germany&#8217;s institution of the urban ghetto). And so Los Angeles was the primary target of the government’s Mexican American deportation program. Largely as a response to the despair the Great Depression had unleashed across the country, officials systematically sent entire families from the L.A. area back to Mexico, with no infrastructure in place to receive them. <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">From 1929 to 1944, 1/3 of L.A.’s Mexican American population was deported</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4128" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4128" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4128" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-650x487.jpg" alt="Los Angeles Mexican Americans 1932" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4128" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Los Angeles Public Library/Herald Examiner Collection via <em><a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">National Public Radio</a></em></p></div>
<p><em>Ressentiments</em> – projection of resentment or fear onto often vulnerable groups in society – were widespread both in the U.S. and in Germany throughout the Great Depression. Xenophobia in the face of severe economic collapse paved the way for Germany’s organized extermination machinery. The U.S.’s internment of Japanese and German citizens, its continued subordination of Black Americans, and its systematic deportation of Mexican Americans demonstrate that this country was in no way spared such a nasty past.</p>
<p>Slowly but surely, such <em>ressentiments</em> have now begun to return. This time, Germany may be more in the right, even despite a few documented attacks on refugee facilities, while America edges closer toward the precipice of wrong.</p>
<p>…</p>
<p>On my side of the ocean, I have arrived into a complicated sector of the nexus of natural diversity and these increasing <em>ressentiments. </em>Vancouver, Washington, where both my parents now live, <a href="http://www.thenation.com/article/browning-america/">is becoming increasingly &#8220;Brown&#8221;</a>. Separated only by a short bridge across the Columbia River, Southwest Washington has become Portland&#8217;s semi-urban/semi-rural extension. Because the northern bank of the river offers families more space for cheaper, better funded schools for fewer private tax dollars, and income tax exemption, immigrants who may have otherwise moved to the Portland, Oregon metro area are now planting themselves on the side of its less expensive neighbor. Portland, as a result, <a href="http://www.oregonlive.com/news/index.ssf/2009/01/in_a_changing_world_portland_r.html">has become increasingly White</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4129" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4129" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4129" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-650x366.jpg" alt="Interstate bridge over the Columbia River, connecting Portland, Oregon and Vancouver, Washington" width="650" height="366" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-650x366.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-300x169.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4129" class="wp-caption-text">Interstate bridge over the Columbia River, connecting Portland, Oregon and Vancouver, Washington</p></div>
<p>According to most recent U.S. census data, Vancouver is now 11% Hispanic, inching closer to the national average. We can expect this number to be much higher in reality, as immigrants will often opt out of participation in the census. There are other ethnic groups represented in Vancouver’s demographic development: For example, 18% of families speak a language other than English at home, and the traditional taco truck has recently seen competition in North African, Japanese, and Thai flavors.</p>
<p>None of this would seem all that significant, if I were not writing about a traditionally conservative county, with once sprawling farm land and a historical military base; a county that has now been converted into a rare blend of suburban developments, strip malls, urbane boutiques, and miles and miles of regional road. The nickname of &#8220;Van-tucky&#8221;* &#8211; something I have only heard used on the other side of the water, mind you &#8211; might tell you all you need to know.</p>
<p>The rate of poverty in Vancouver is also higher than the national average. Vancouver&#8217;s mayor recently <a href="http://www.cityofvancouver.us/ced/page/affordable-housing-task-force">launched a task force</a> to investigate the cause of growing homelessness, rising rents, and increased demand for housing in the city’s most accessible and commercially viable areas. Serving as Portland’s &#8220;bedroom community&#8221; brings with it numerous tax and transportation disadvantages, as well, such as costly inter-city transit for a significant commuter population and bridges nationally notorious for being structurally unsound.</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p>In a brand-new cocktail bar in downtown Vancouver, which serves only locally-distilled (read artisanal) spirits, I sip my smoky-cucumber-tequila mixture and listen in on the interaction between the unlikely combination of guests who have just joined me on the patio. Three White bikers &#8211; two older women with smokers&#8217; cough and one machismo with a mustache &#8211; scoff at the price of their beer. Across from them at a nearby table, two women in their mid-20s, both with long black hair, one who speaks English with an accent.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-4130" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-650x366.jpg" alt="cocktail Vancouver, Washington" width="650" height="366" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-650x366.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-300x169.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Older veterans and cowboy-like characters are scattered across Vancouver’s downtown like curated remains of what was once here. They drink Rainier out of cans &#8211; Washington State’s Pabst Blue Ribbon with more local charm &#8211; and chain smoke in the park. They inhabit the dive bars with names like &#8220;Lounge&#8221; and antique neon advertisements. It seems that establishments like this new artisanal cocktail bar threaten to upset a tender balance between familiarity, comfort, and growth.</p>
<p>“$4! Bullshit”, one of the women hollers. The two younger ladies nudge their shoulders closer together, in order to continue a conversation disrupted by the boom of our three new patio companions.</p>
<p>The machismo turns toward the young women’s table, putting his hand on one of their legs. “Where you from, honey?&#8221;, he begins his monologue, &#8220;I’m a native, been here for more than 20 years, Detroit before that. You know how much this place has changed?”</p>
<p>Neither responds; however, the one whose leg is playing host to the man’s hand begins to shift uncomfortably.</p>
<p>&#8220;Where you from honey? You aren&#8217;t from around here, I can tell you that!&#8221;, one of the older women yells between sips from her can. “When did Rainier get this damn expensive? It’s bullshit, $4! I’ll tell you something…”</p>
<p>One of the young, dark-haired women flashes machismo a smile. &#8220;I&#8217;m from Panama!&#8221;, she says, and extends her hand for a shake. He takes it and squeezes it, returning both their hands to the table.</p>
<p>“I’m American, from here&#8221;, the other woman says, her leg now turned as far away from his body as the chair allows.</p>
<p>&#8220;But where are your parents from then?&#8221;, machismo asks with a chuckle. &#8220;That&#8217;s what I&#8217;m asking, ain&#8217;t it?&#8221;</p>
<p>She concedes, but stands to use the restroom (or simply disappear into the building) as she does: &#8220;Well, I&#8217;m Filipino.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p><em>Ressentiments</em> toward the Other can begin and fester in spaces of socioeconomic change. With President Obama’s pledge to take in 100,000 refugees, the question becomes “How will this country prepare its citizens to engage respectfully and kindly with members of a majority Muslim country?” The first step in this process is realizing that we have a lot of work to do, and we need politicians who will help us get there.</p>
<p>Germany has seen a fair share of reporting on the readiness of its population to open its arms to newcomers. It is easy to draw parallels to the past, particularly to Germany’s track record in <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/20/441732811/in-germany-migrants-find-footing-but-also-some-resistance">failing to integrate its guest-worker population and in promoting ethnic-based citizenship until it was almost too late</a>. However, it is Germany the rest of the world now looks to in awe &#8211; for choosing a kind of <em>moralpolitik</em> over patterns of the past.</p>
<p>Being so far away from a society I sometimes feel I know more about than my own (society of origin), I can’t help but beam with pride in watching small towns across Germany distribute clean clothes, socks, new toys, children’s books, and warm meals to the thousands of human beings in need who have crossed their borders. Nevertheless, Germany has since issued temporary border controls. Order still wins out over populist charity.</p>
<p>But aiming for a collective solution to the continuous stream of migrants and refugees into Europe, German leaders have worked to reach agreement upon a refugee quota for EU member states. Just this Tuesday this quota became a provisional reality.</p>
<p>Time will tell if all members comply, and if a sense of moral duty is really as strong as images of kind citizens touting bags of donations suggest. Yet I do have the sense that with each step toward welcoming the Other, <em>ressentiments</em> have fewer chances of surviving. When demonstrations of kindness are just so strong, so publicly undeniable, that Trump-esque hate can find no oxygen for its fire.</p>
<p>That is what I hope for America.</p>
<p>At the moment, the U.S. remains crippled and complicated by its multi-layered fears of all the regions of the world it has wronged. As UN Ambassador <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/23/442761552/10-000-syrian-refugees-just-the-floor-of-u-s-effort-says-ambassador-power">Samantha Power made clear in an NPR interview recently</a>, the country is not ready to simply do the right thing; it has to be a calculated response, taking security into account.</p>
<p>Overcoming fear is America&#8217;s consistent and stubborn challenge. I just hope the mistakes of the 1930s can mean something.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*Van-tucky is a reference to the southern state of Kentucky, the unofficial home of fried-chicken and horse races.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Refugees Welcome: Local Interventions for an EU Dilemma</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/04/30/refugees-welcome-local-interventions-for-an-eu-dilemma/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/04/30/refugees-welcome-local-interventions-for-an-eu-dilemma/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 13:04:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[European Union]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3965</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This article is intended to inform, as well as to encourage advocacy and action. As any seasoned volunteer or activist knows, engagement relies heavily on context, identifying not only how to get involved but why and in which capacity, based on the complex landscape of need one encounters.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Saturday, the 18th of April, a small fishing vessel capsized off the coast of Libya on its way to one of the European Union’s coastal states. On its way, it passed through waters patrolled by the European Union&#8217;s security agency, Frontex. Its demise was quick, only 28 passengers were rescued; an estimated 900 are said to have perished. Of the dead, roughly 200 had had little chance of escape, locked securely in the ship&#8217;s hull by the smugglers commissioned with their passage. A similar event had made headlines just the Sunday before: 400 dead in the water. Yet even more sobering is the UN&#8217;s projected number of migrant deaths by the end of 2015: <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/italy/11548995/Mediterranean-migrant-crisis-hits-Italy-as-EU-ministers-meet-live.html">approximately 30,000</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_3993" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3993" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3993 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-650x488.jpg" alt="Essen_ProAsyl" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3993" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Pro Asyl</p></div>
<p>Although this tally of the dead got its start long ago, both the number and its surrounding political situation seem to be escalating at an alarming rate. It is possible that this escalation is, in part, due to the quick reporting the digital-age affords a global readership. But, given the current death toll and its greater context of inter-regional instability, one thing seems fairly certain: If safer pathways for migration to the European Union continue to remain restricted or inaccessible to many, the intersecting lines of risk and desperation will continue to make safety subordinate to a chance at what is (presented as) a better life.</p>
<p>Yet the most immediate and real consequence of these reports of danger leading to disaster may not be deterrence but desensitization: The drowned and discarded may begin to shock a little less with each headline, and, worse yet, public support for the displaced &#8211; in our communities, off our shores, and even in those far-off lands to which our governments sell arms in exchange for cheap manufactured goods (an oversimplification of the global balance of trade, of course, but the point remains a valid one) &#8211; may wane.</p>
<p>But this doesn&#8217;t have to be the case. This article is intended to inform, as well as to encourage advocacy and action. As any seasoned volunteer or activist knows, engagement relies heavily on context, identifying not only how to get involved but why and in which capacity, based on the complex landscape of need one encounters. And so, I will first offer a summary of information I find important in creating this context, beginning with an understanding of Germany&#8217;s position in the asylum system of the European Union and followed by an unpacking of certain terms and categories. The latter is not meant to distinguish between and thus arrange various grades of human value based on one&#8217;s reasons for migration; rather, examining these categories is an attempt to identify and elucidate the different contours and sites of vulnerability to be found in refugee and immigrant advocacy, with navigating such categories being crucial to successful support. The most important bit follows these term-laden sections &#8211; namely, a list of ways to get involved in Berlin housing facilities and neighborhood support centers for asylum-applicants. Some options for digital activism and direct actions around Germany will also be included for our readers further afield.</p>
<p>In the end, my hope is to transform this article into a helpful resource page for the <em>Collidoscope</em> webpage. Thus feedback on ways to improve its information and add to or amend its list of opportunities for involvement is greatly appreciated!</p>
<p><strong>Asylum in the EU and refugee status in Germany: an overview</strong></p>
<p>It is helpful to continue with numbers as a means of illustrating the magnitude of the situation (despite my preference for qualitative vs. purely quantitative data &#8211; for which this blog tends to be a perfect example). In 2014, Germany housed approximately 173,000 applicants for asylum, an increase of 192% from the previous year. By the end of 2015, upwards of 300,000 applicants for asylum are projected to enter and remain temporarily in the country [source: <a href="http://www.bamf.de/DE/Infothek/Statistiken/Asylzahlen/asylzahlen-node.html">BAMF</a>]. Despite its shock-value, this remains a small number in the grand scheme of immigration flows. Relative to the asylum policies of the other G-20 countries, however, this is a significant number. The United States, for example, processed 121,000 asylum claims in 2014, a country with four times the population of Germany [source: <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/europe/new-migration-crisis-overwhelms-european-refugee-system/2015/04/21/3ab83470-e45c-11e4-ae0f-f8c46aa8c3a4_story.html">Washington Post</a>].</p>
<p>This does not mean that all claims and their applicants are granted residency in Germany. In fact, most are rejected, resulting in deportation either once a decision has been reached or in a temporary stay of inevitable deportation. Only 24% were granted refugee status in 2014, which excludes a guarantee of permanent status, i.e. returning &#8220;status-refugees&#8221; to their countries of origin once conflicts can be said to be resolved. Last year, only 1.8% received the coveted gift of permanent asylum [source: <a href="http://www.bamf.de/SharedDocs/Anlagen/DE/Publikationen/Broschueren/broschuere-bundesamt-in-zahlen-2014-asyl.pdf?__blob=publicationFile">BAMF</a>].</p>
<p>Nevertheless, 2014&#8217;s final tally of approximately 34,000 accepted refugees indicates a lag in the participation of other EU member states, such as the Netherlands, Poland, or Ireland, not to mention the strange and ineffective logic behind the so-called Dublin III convention*. As the commissioner for the German federal agency for migration and refugees, Aydan Özoguz, commented just last week: “The European asylum system doesn’t work. Some countries are doing very little. We are one of the richest countries and we want to help, but it’s not okay that Germany, Sweden and France are taking 50 percent of the refugees, while other countries do nothing” [source: <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/europe/new-migration-crisis-overwhelms-european-refugee-system/2015/04/21/3ab83470-e45c-11e4-ae0f-f8c46aa8c3a4_story.html">Washington Post</a>].</p>
<p>EU leaders met just last week in an emergency summit to discuss changes to this increasingly dysfunctional system. Given Germany&#8217;s position as home to the greatest number of asylum-applicants, decisions made here set both the moral and practical tone for the other states in the European Union&#8217;s common asylum system &#8211; an infrastructure guided less by comprehensive agreements and more by a few select rules. At the summit&#8217;s conclusion, leaders agreed to invest more money in rescue efforts: more boats and life-vests for the Mediterranean. But what of more legal, safe pathways into the European Union?</p>
<p>Over the last few days, arguments have been made for a reform to the immigration policies that prevent potential workers from entering the country by legal means, unrelated to the conditions for asylum but also free from the ardor of submitting a claim and waiting years for a decision. <a href="http://www.iwkoeln.de/presse/interviews/beitrag/michael-huether-in-der-welt-iw-fordert-mehr-fluechtlinge-fuer-deutschen-arbeitsmarkt-223062">According to the Institut für deutsche Wirtschaft</a> (IW), one in five asylum-applicants has a college degree and one in three are skilled in some trade or another. With German industry&#8217;s sustained calls for increased immigration (to compensate for an aging or less technically-skilled population), providing a more accelerated pathway to a safe life in Germany for those migrants who qualify, while meeting the utilitarian imperative of the political establishment, seems like a win-win. Traditional asylum and provisions for refugees would not be eliminated, by any means, but the number of migrants from poor or conflict-ridden countries would be allowed to increase, saving many the eventual rejection most asylum-applicants face once they arrive in Europe, if they are lucky enough to survive the journey (see the <a href="http://heindehaas.blogspot.de/2015/04/let-their-people-drown-how-eu.html">recent appeal from social scientist Hein de Haas</a> for more on this argument).</p>
<p>However, as is often the case in coordinated responses to humanitarian need, calculations of domestic burden vs. benefit will dominate. And an end to these calculations is nowhere in sight. That is to say, if we wait for political change, we may be waiting at a high opportunity cost &#8211; that of everyday advocacy for and support of the displaced. But first, categories&#8230;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Refugee&#8221; or &#8220;asylum-seeker&#8221;?</strong></p>
<p>The distinction between those with refugee status and those who have submitted an application for asylum (referred to as &#8220;asylum-applicant&#8221; thus far) is an important one, as it helps to explain the origins and role of the <em>Flüchtlingsheim</em> (state-sponsored but privately-run housing facility for asylum-applicants) in the everyday landscape of German towns and cities, including Berlin. Of course, the implementation of national asylum law can vary state by state, given Germany&#8217;s federal balance of power; Saxony, Bavaria, and Berlin may differ in the scope and quantity of services provided to asylum-applicants residing in each state&#8217;s respected <em>Flüchtlingsheime,</em> for example,<em> </em>as this <a href="http://www.proasyl.de/de/news/detail/news/pro_asyl_studie_zur_unterbringung_von_fluechtlingen_in_deutschland/">study</a> demonstrates. But, in all cases, the foundation of German asylum law is built on a differentation between those whose claims have been adjudicated (decided by a judge in German administrative court) and those who have filed claims but are awaiting a decision, assigning different rights and restrictions to these different groups, accordingly. The most important rights and restrictions are those affecting the freedom of movement and activity for those migrants to fall in the &#8220;asylum-applicant&#8221; category. They are as follows:</p>
<p>&#8211; Asylum-applicants are generally not allowed to work until they receive formal status: either as a &#8220;refugee&#8221; (a temporary status, in most cases), as an &#8220;asylee&#8221; (long-term or permanent status), or as a &#8220;tolerated person&#8221; (<em>Geduldete</em>). There are, of course, some exceptions to this rule; for example, asylum-applicants in Berlin and Brandenburg are allowed to pursue employment one year after their application has been submitted, though this work allowance remains heavily restricted and qualified. This means that, in general, asylum-applicants are not able to provide for themselves, thereby becoming fully dependent on the services financed by the federal government, the respective state, and third-parties responsible for service provision. The housing facility system of the <em>Flüchtlingsheim</em> was established both to meet the need for accommodation and to enforce this ban on employment.</p>
<p>&#8211; Up until January of this year, all asylum-applicants were to remain in the state and district either in which they had applied for asylum or to which they had been assigned. They were not able to determine this geographical location or the particular facility in which they would live, even in the case of friends or relatives already in the country. These rules for residency and domicile make up the German system of <em>Residenzpflicht.</em> According to the organization Pro Asyl, <a href="http://www.proasyl.de/de/themen/basics/basiswissen/rechte-der-fluechtlinge/bewegungsfreiheit/residenzpflicht/">these restrictions have been partially lifted</a>. It is unclear, however, to what extent the residency requirement will be relaxed. And as with any policy reform, there will certainly be a lag in public officials and bureaucrats implementing changes. In other words, asylum-applicants may still be prohibited (by staff and local enforcement personnel) from leaving their assigned district, and limits to mobility may still be decided on a state-by-state and case-by-case basis.</p>
<p>&#8211; Residents of <em>Flüchtlingsheime</em> are frequently re-distributed to prevent over-crowding and to maintain an equitable distribution of the financial burden, relative to each state&#8217;s population and economic situation. The freedom of movement, which the abolition of <em>Residenzpflicht </em>may have provided, is overruled and/or overshadowed by this re-distribution mandate.</p>
<p>&#8211; Once asylum-applicants have received a decision from the judge &#8211; the time between the initial filing of the application, the hearing, and the eventual decision often proving to be a year-long ordeal -, those without status granted are either returned to their country of origin (often within a few months of the decision) or are given a <i>Duldung</i>, becoming a &#8220;tolerated person&#8221; for as long as the state deems their return difficult (e.g. in the case of illness, psychological distress, age, family relations, financial situation in the country of origin). <em>Geduldete</em> are free to seek employment and live among the general population, securing their own housing, albeit within the town/city of their asylum-application. But, in most cases, they are not entitled to the same social services as those with refugee status and can be deported at any time, particularly in the case of a minor infraction.</p>
<p>These terms serve to complicate the issue of refugees and the work of refugee advocacy, as various levels of status and treatment before the law are at play. In my opinion, when the media and public discourse fail to make these distinctions, the complexity of the issue and its effect on the experience of real human beings is side-lined to a language that prefers the simplicity of pure humanitarianism &#8211; a moral outlook recognized neither by German law-makers nor by the structures of the European Union. In simple terms, those crossing the Mediterranean and those living in close quarters in Berlin&#8217;s many <em>Flüchtlingsheime </em>are not all &#8220;refugees&#8221;. If they were, they would receive the humane treatment popular opinion affords them.</p>
<div id="attachment_3994" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3994" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3994 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind-650x650.jpg" alt="Deichkind" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3994" class="wp-caption-text">German pop group Deichkind; Source: <a href="https://instagram.com/p/0tB_FivQxn/">Instagram</a></p></div>
<p>Yet, when we acknowledge that it is precisely because of the precarity of their status that they need our help, the situation looks much different. And local interventions in the experience of this precarity become most important, beyond #refugeeswelcome.</p>
<p><strong>How to help</strong></p>
<p>A few weeks ago I visited a new housing facility for asylum-applicants in Reinickendorf, one of the northernmost districts of Berlin. In an idyllic setting, surrounded by pine and quiet residential streets, a former High School has been converted into a 300 bed hostel for migrants awaiting status. The space is rudimentary but well-organized, staff making do with donated toys and German courses, among other diverse activities, as a means to entertain the many children &#8211; many of whom have been waiting for more than two months to enroll in the local school. The staff &#8211; about 10 in number &#8211; communicate with residents in what seems to be a mix of German, English, French, and enthusiastic signage. There is an artist working on the aesthetic revitalization of the place &#8211; literally making the dark halls of a High School a place that feels like home for its residents. There are social workers and psychologists who visit on occasion. Basic meals are catered three times a day on a set schedule. &#8220;House Rules&#8221; are posted in various languages in the foyer. And security guards patrol the grounds, which are clearly the remains of a once vibrant schoolyard, complete with a basketball court (nets partially intact) and a covered concrete playground for jumping rope and hopscotch. We chat about setting up in-house cooking activities, to bring residents and staff closer together, and about using the open space to start a garden, giving the families an opportunity to build and realize a strenuous but rewarding project, even harvest its fruits. The plans are piece-meal and heavily reliant on donations and organizational finesse. In many ways, it is simply about showing up (a familiar mantra), trying to be of help, and deferring to the staff who are there throughout the week trying to make the facility a better place for all who live there.</p>
<p>There are more than 40 facilities just like this one across Berlin, housing upwards of 11,000 asylum-applicants. <a href="http://www.morgenpost.de/berlin/article139453814/Senat-baut-36-neue-Fluechtlingsheime-in-Berlin.html">36 more facilities just like them are planned</a> for the end of 2015. The need is great, but so is this city. Here is a list of established groups across Berlin who work directly with <em>Flüchtlingsheime </em>like the one mentioned above; all of these organizations are certainly eager for new volunteers:</p>
<p>Flüchtlingsinitiative Klausener Platz [evagoemuesay(at)gmail.com]</p>
<p><a href="https://hellersdorfhilft.wordpress.com/">Hellersdorf hilft e.V.</a></p>
<p>Initiative Grenzen weg Hellersdorf [grenzenweg(at)gmx.de]</p>
<p><a href="http://www.wir-netzwerk.de/">Willkommen in Reinickendorf</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.willkommensbuendnis-steglitz-zehlendorf.de/">Willkommensbündnis für Flüchtlinge Steglitz-Zehlendorf</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.lichtenbergerbuendnis.de/">Lichtenberger Bündnis für Demokratie und Toleranz</a></p>
<p><a href="https://bunterwind.wordpress.com/">Bunter Wind für Lichtenberg</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.willkommen-im-westend.de/">Willkommen im Westend &#8211; Refugees Welcome</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.zentrum-für-demokratie.de/">Netzwerk für Flüchtlinge in Treptow-Köpenick</a></p>
<p><a href="http://multitude_tk@riseup.net">Multitude Gruppe Köpenick</a> (for German speakers only &#8211; German language instruction)</p>
<p><a href="https://arbeitsgruppefluchtundmenschenrechte.wordpress.com/">Arbeitsgruppe Flucht und Menschenrechte Treptow-Köpenick</a></p>
<p><a href="http://uffmucken-schoeneweide.de/">Initiative &#8220;Uffmucken Schöneweide&#8221;</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.buendnis-neukoelln.de/">Bündnis Neukölln</a></p>
<p><a href="http://fluechtlingshilfe@britzerinitiative.de">Aktionsbündnis Flüchtlingshilfe Britz</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.multitude-berlin.de/">Initiative Multitude e.V.</a> (for German speakers only &#8211; German language instruction in Spandau, Westend, Lichtenberg, Marzahn, Prenzlauer Berg)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.pankow-hilft.de/">Willkommensnetzwerk &#8220;Pankow Hilft!&#8221;</a> (Pankow, Prenzlauer Berg, Weissensee, Buch)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Fl%C3%BCchtlinge-willkommen-in-Buch-und-Karow/1481160482158156">Flüchtlinge willkommen in Buch und Karow</a></p>
<p><a href="http://u_strassburger@posteo.de">Unterstützer_innenkreis Flüchtlingsunterkunft Prenzlauer Berg</a></p>
<p>Initiative &#8220;Wedding Hilft&#8221; [wedding.hilft(at)gmail.com]</p>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/moabithilft">Initiative &#8220;Moabit Hilft&#8221;</a></p>
<p><a href="http://neuenachbarschaft.wordpress.com/">Initiative &#8220;Neue Nachbarschaft Moabit&#8221;</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.willkommensbuendnis-steglitz-zehlendorf.de/">Willkommensbündnis für Flüchtlinge in Steglitz-Zehlendorf</a></p>
<p><a href="http://bglbb.blogsport.de/">Bündnis gegen Lager Berlin-Brandenburg</a></p>
<p><a href="http://asylstrikeberlin.wordpress.com/">Oranienplatz</a></p>
<p>For those without immediate time to spare but keen on staying informed on actions and opportunities as they develop, track the activities of  the <a href="http://www.fluechtlingsrat-berlin.de/">Flüchtlingsrat-Berlin</a> (the local office of the nation-wide &#8220;refugee council&#8221; model) and <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">GiveSomethingBacktoBerlin</a> (a community platform for volunteer engagement, including frequent posts from groups seeking participants in visits to and on-going projects within <em>Flüchtlingsheime</em>).</p>
<p>Of course, this type of on-site involvement is not for everyone. The type of validation that often comes with structured community engagement projects is not likely to be found here. And, although I am a fan of &#8220;showing up&#8221; and getting one&#8217;s hands dirty, applying pressure on policy-makers and raising awareness to the need for asylum and immigration reform remain incredibly important contributions. Here are a few resources on direct actions and politics-oriented digital activism; these options are great for those further afield who would like to participate in some way, even if just with a click:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/367018126842745,%20http://www.amnesty.de/2015/4/20/massensterben-im-mittelmeer-stoppen-seenotrettung-jetzt">Amnesty International Germany&#8217;s campaign against </a><em><a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/367018126842745,%20http://www.amnesty.de/2015/4/20/massensterben-im-mittelmeer-stoppen-seenotrettung-jetzt">Massensterben im Mittelmeer</a> (</em>flash-mobs and rallies around the offices of Parliament and Executive Government)</p>
<p><a href="http://action.amnesty.de/l/ger/p/dia/action3/common/public/?action_KEY=9703&amp;d=1">#SOSEurope Amnesty International petition</a> (calling upon Merkel&#8217;s government to reform immigration and asylum policy)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.proasyl.de/de/home/seenotrettung-jetzt/">ProAsyl petition</a> (for more EU member-state support of rescue efforts in the Mediterranean)</p>
<p>Donate to the organization <a href="http://www.proasyl.de/de/">Pro Asyl:</a> perhaps the best way to assist the many asylum-applicants residing in Germany and other EU member states by way of a great and highly-effective organization. Pro Asyl coordinates volunteer activities, contributes to accurate reporting and research on asylum in the EU, and offers legal counsel to asylum-applicants, among many other great services.</p>
<p><strong>Why local interventions matter</strong></p>
<p>A <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/media/2015-05-16_EFA-Forschungsbericht_Endfassung.pdf">study</a> was just released by the new <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/">Berlin Institute for Empirical Migration and Integration Research</a>* (BIM) on Berlin-based volunteer engagement  in support of asylum-applicants and resettled refugees. It points to severe deficits in state services for which the unpaid contributions of volunteers strive to remedy. In particular, without the engagement of what the study deems predominately secular, middle-class females, many asylum-applicants would have great difficulty communicating with those agencies charged with the processing and, ultimately, the acceptance or rejection of their claim to refugee status. Additionally, despite the <em>Trägerschaft </em>structure, in which third-party organizations assume partial financial responsibility and full operational responsibility for these housing facilities, many goods and services would otherwise be sorely lacking without the donation-drives and supply deliveries of volunteers. The study describes the especially integral role of volunteers in assisting in the navigation of Germany&#8217;s complex bureaucratic structures: something necessary for immigrants of any sort to successfully remain in the country.</p>
<div id="attachment_3995" style="width: 498px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3995" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3995" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider-488x650.jpg" alt="Source: Pro Asyl" width="488" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider.jpg 488w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider-225x300.jpg 225w" sizes="(max-width: 488px) 100vw, 488px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3995" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Pro Asyl</p></div>
<p>And even the simple opportunity for social interaction, which comes with visits from the outside, can have a great effect on an asylum-applicant&#8217;s success, encouraging language and intercultural skills through everyday relationships that will serve them well in the future. From building the capacity to make one&#8217;s case successfully to a judge to preparing for integration into the local job-market once status, whether temporary or permanent, has been granted, seeing to the wellness of a <em>Flüchtlingsheim&#8217;s </em>residents is a powerful intervention in an often bleak process. In the end, it is the state that decides who may be called a &#8220;refugee&#8221; and who might have a chance at a better life, but volunteers may prove to be one of the deciding factors in who will be welcomed.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>As already mentioned, please submit your comments or write us an email with suggestions or changes, so that this can become a helpful and accurate resource for months to come. And please share with your various networks. The more informed our communities, the better activists we can be!</em></p>
<p>*Technically, certain conventions of the European Union (such as the oft-cited Dublin III agreement) requires that migrants seeking asylum, i.e. refugee status, apply for and receive asylum for the first EU country on which they are said to have set foot. In practice, however, Dublin III is inconsistently enforced, thus allowing asylum-applicants to submit a claim in an economically prosperous country like Germany.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/04/30/refugees-welcome-local-interventions-for-an-eu-dilemma/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: On Leaving Home(s)</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/03/23/lens-on-leaving-homes/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 15:32:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[family]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vienna]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3869</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Last month, Kelly wrote about the implications of "collecting ourselves" to make a move back home. While wrought with complications in its own right, returning to where one grew up, has family, or holds full political and legal rights is a move that Makes Sense. One chapter closes, and however painful or messy, the next begins...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3881 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-650x487.jpg" alt="2014-11-16 13.46.44" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2014-11-16-13.46.44.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Last month, Kelly wrote about the implications of &#8220;<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/02/13/lens-leaving-berlin/">collecting ourselves</a>&#8221; to make a move back home. While wrought with complications in its own right, returning to where one grew up, has family, or holds full political and legal rights is a move that Makes Sense. One chapter closes, and however painful or messy, the next begins.</p>
<p>After graduate school, I started losing the ability to picture my life in chapters. My decisions were no longer dictated by a series of steps culminating in clear milestones. I suddenly felt accosted by the need to figure out what I wanted to Do and Be&#8230; this time for the long run. And, given my international experiences and dual citizenship, the question of &#8220;What&#8221; promptly extended to one of &#8220;Where&#8221;.</p>
<p>So I moved to Berlin.</p>
<p>When I booked my flight to Germany in fall 2011, &#8220;two years&#8221; was my default timeline. &#8220;A couple years,&#8221; I responded confidently when someone asked how long I planned to be gone. &#8220;I should give the job a good two years,&#8221; I thought when I got hired six months in. &#8220;We&#8217;ll all still be here at least two more years,&#8221; I reassured myself about my circle of expat* friends another six months after that.</p>
<p>How foolish I was, to believe that two years would ever be enough. How <span class="st">naïve</span>,<em> </em>to assume there would be a clear demarcation between this chapter and the next.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3885 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-650x487.jpg" alt="2015-01-31 14.28.03-1" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-01-31-14.28.03-1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Now almost three and a half years in, I feel firmly entrenched in my world of bilingual conversations, narrow streets, weekend jaunts around the continent, ubiquitous public transport, social welfare nets, and crusty bread. But these roots of mine are flighty. They wiggle at something as simple as a chat with a friend back home, when she catches me up on her life and I realize how much I&#8217;ve missed. When my sister or father leaves for the airport after a visit, they are pulled halfway out of the earth and end up lodged in the middle of my throat. Every time I get on a plane and head back across the ocean, a part of me fears they will be ripped out entirely. Because no matter how long I stay in Europe and embrace the rights my German passport affords me, I will always also be American. No matter how incredible a life I build for myself on this side of the Atlantic, there will always be a Life Back Home.</p>
<p>I was not aware of how much I had internalized this feeling until last summer, when my mother and I visited relatives in northwestern Germany. Sipping coffee on a sunny terrace, a family friend commented, &#8220;I could never do what you&#8217;re doing, be so far away from my family&#8230; I&#8217;m too close to them.&#8221; My reaction to her declaration was nothing short of primal. Of course I missed my family! Of course I felt close to them! I was not away <em>because</em> of, but rather, <em>in spite of</em> them &#8211; an unpleasant reality I struggle with on a near daily basis.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3892 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-650x518.jpg" alt="11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n" width="650" height="518" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-650x518.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n-300x239.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/11036659_10103525117802518_5005038170152801547_n.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Modern advances in travel and technology have enabled more and more people to adopt lifestyles fueled by wanderlust and adventure. But not all of us who leave home are <a href="http://elitedaily.com/life/culture/wanderlust-like-travel-much-no-real-home/959705/">perpetual wanderers with nomadic spirits</a>. Some of us are searching for somewhere to settle. Some of us are even surprised to find ourselves making a life away from where we grew up, away from the ones we love. I know I am.</p>
<p>I consider myself, by nature, to be a sensitive homebody. I crave being close to the people I love and place great importance on maintaining my relationships, both near and far. This explains why any time I am &#8220;away&#8221;, my pack mentality kicks in and I seek out a local community almost immediately. But I concurrently possess the intrinsic need to push myself and explore. For me, this has meant travel. Whether I credit <a href="https://psychologyblogaimee.wordpress.com/2013/12/04/wanderlust-a-genetic-basis-to-a-globetrotting-fanatic/">genetics</a> for this (nope) or my international upbringing, mixed with a little courage and a lot of privilege (that&#8217;s more like it), is not the point. The ups and downs of living somewhere other than where I grew up have become an integral part of my identity and understanding of growth and independence. They just don&#8217;t make the leaving part any easier.</p>
<p>The thing is, leaving is rarely the easy choice, even with the prospect of Something Great on the other side.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3887 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-650x487.jpg" alt="2015-02-21 16.37.36-1" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/2015-02-21-16.37.36-1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>While I never expected moving to Berlin to be easy, I did anticipate a gradual ease, and more importantly, clarity, with time. Reality proved instead to be emphatically non-linear. Rough patches hit me sporadically and without warning. My homesickness became a swelling wave, pulling in and out of shore, threatening at its peak to wash me out entirely. What if this chapter never ended? What if I never left my new home and went back to my old one? And now that I live in Vienna, my current home because of work, is my &#8220;old home&#8221; Washington, DC or Berlin? In countless discussions with fellow expat friends on the topics of home and belonging, the resounding theme has been similar: one of overwhelming choice and uncertainty.</p>
<p>A couple months ago, Kelly and I were at a close friend&#8217;s 30th birthday dinner in Berlin. Huddled in the kitchen over bottles of Spanish Temperanillo and mismatched plates of pizza and crudit<span class="st">és</span>, someone proposed we guess where the birthday boy would be 30 years from now. We had plenty of ideas for the &#8220;What&#8221;: running his own cooking school, teaching his kids how to do science experiments, maintaining his impressive beard. It was on the &#8220;Where&#8221; that we got stuck. &#8220;Italy?&#8221; we posed as the obvious choice (where he&#8217;s from). He resolutely shook his head &#8220;no&#8221;. &#8220;Germany?&#8221; He shrugged his shoulders, unsure &#8211; just like the majority of us in the room about our own futures.</p>
<p>Once you&#8217;ve opened yourself up to the world and seen first-hand that you can live, and maybe even thrive, somewhere else, it becomes increasingly difficult to know when or where to stop searching. The list of potential Something Greats becomes never-ending. And with it, the accompanying list of goodbyes.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By</em> <strong><em>Sophia Burton</em></strong></p>
<p>*My choice of the term &#8220;expat&#8221; was deliberate, as it popularly denotes migrants with privilege and mobility. For more on &#8220;expat&#8221; vs. &#8220;immigrant&#8221;, check out <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/global-development-professionals-network/2015/mar/13/white-people-expats-immigrants-migration?CMP=fb_gu">this Guardian article</a>.</p>
<p><em>All photos taken by me, in Vienna and Berlin.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: Ali for (and from) Germany</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/09/02/interview-ali-for-and-from-germany/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2014 08:27:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3183</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the wake of Germany's World Cup victory, much has been said about a renewed sense of German patriotism and its implications. While some have feared a connection to Germany's dark past, others have welcomed the discourse as a chance to shape a new sense of belonging within the country's evolving demographics. We've already written something about it here. But what a discussion on national identity means on the personal level is another story. Or rather many stories. Here's one...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the wake of Germany&#8217;s World Cup victory, much has been said about a renewed sense of German patriotism and its implications. While some have feared a connection to Germany&#8217;s dark past, others have welcomed the discourse as a chance to shape a new sense of belonging within the country&#8217;s evolving demographics. We&#8217;ve already written something about it <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/28/world-cup-fever-how-malleable-is-german-identity/">here</a>. But what a discussion on national identity means on the personal level is another story. Or rather many stories. Here&#8217;s one.</p>
<div id="attachment_3184" style="width: 439px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3184" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3184 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/ali.jpg" alt="Ali für Deutschland " width="429" height="429" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/ali.jpg 429w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/ali-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 429px) 100vw, 429px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3184" class="wp-caption-text">Ali at the Germany-France game at Train Cocktailbar</p></div>
<p>It took Ali <span class="gD">Riza Gürbüz over 30 years to feel welcome in Germany. Originally from East Anatolia, Ali moved to Berlin at age 12 with his brother and sister. His mother had arrived 8 years prior in 1973 as part of the last wave of guest worker recruitment. She was living in <span class="st">Neukölln and working for a cleaning company</span>. His father stayed behind in Turkey.</span></p>
<p><span class="gD"><em>The beginning wasn&#8217;t easy</em>, Ali recounts. Understanding German society, learning the language, feeling at home&#8230; this all took time. But eventually he gained his footing, finished his schooling, completed an <em>Ausbildung</em> (apprenticeship), and in 1986, began a career in industrial mechanics. Today, he&#8217;s married, has a 12 year old daughter and an active social life, and makes music in his free time. He still lives in N<span class="st">eukölln. </span><br />
</span></p>
<p><span class="gD"><strong>But despite spending the majority of his life in Germany, having German citizenship, and making a home here, he&#8217;s often felt like an outsider.</strong> </span></p>
<p><em>I still don&#8217;t really have any German friends</em>, Ali tells me on the last night of Ramadan in July, after breaking the fast together. We&#8217;re sitting outside on Kreuzberg&#8217;s iconic <span class="st"><em>Oranienstraße</em></span> with his friends, also both named Ali, both German-Turks* born in Berlin. Ali and Ali nod their heads in agreement. A rollerblading demonstration passes by in front of us. <em>I don&#8217;t understand it,</em> Ali says. <em>We all have the same sources of stress &#8211; work, money, family &#8211; so why don&#8217;t we make more of an effort to be nice to one another? </em></p>
<div id="attachment_3358" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3358" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3358 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis-650x473.jpg" alt="Breaking the fast on Oranienstraße" width="650" height="473" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis-650x473.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis-300x218.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3358" class="wp-caption-text">Breaking the fast on Oranienstraße</p></div>
<p><span class="gD">Ali can cite the definitive moment in which he felt that he had finally &#8220;arrived&#8221; in Germany. <em>I was in the Bundeswehrkrankenhaus [German Armed Forces hospital] last December for a week due to a skin issue. I received such kind and affectionate treatment from the nurses and doctors. The same treatment as everyone else. I shared a room with a guy named Wolfgang, and we talked for two days straight, about everything. The atmosphere made me feel really welcome and inspired.</em></span></p>
<p>So inspired, that he started writing a song on his phone while still on his hospital bed. Two days after he was released, he finished &#8220;Ali <span class="st">für</span> Deutschland&#8221; (literally &#8220;Ali for Germany&#8221;), a World Cup song in <span class="gD">support of the </span>German national team. After recording it, Ali ran around to different departments and bureaus in the city, asking for support. Eventually he got a production company to film it for free. The song is available for purchase online (99 cents on iTunes) and half of the proceeds go to a homeless shelter in his neighborhood.<em> I really believed in the song and project, </em>Ali explains, <em>I wanted to show that someone who has my name and looks like me supports the German team. That people from all over the world with different backgrounds live here and consider it their home. </em><em><br />
</em></p>
<p><strong>Ali <span class="st">für</span> Deutschland Music Video: </strong></p>
<p><iframe width="650" height="366" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Mzqz6hCF7uI?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>Singing alongside Ali in the music video is his daughter. <em>I see that she&#8217;s growing up differently than I did, that she&#8217;s happier. I hope this song contributes to that. </em>For Ali, it all comes back to the media. <em>When Mesut Özil [German-Turkish football player] makes a good play, German-Turkish kids get patted on the back. If he does poorly, people shake their heads at us. The migration background is always emphasized. </em></p>
<p>Ali&#8217;s point is backed by research. <a href="http://www.stern.de/panorama/stern-umfrage-knappe-mehrheit-lehnt-islam-als-teil-deutschlands-ab-2128967.html">A recent Stern poll</a> shows that over half of Germans believe that Islam does not belong in German society. <a href="http://mediendienst-integration.de/artikel/der-islam-gehoert-zu-deutschland-spielhaus.html">Experts</a> argue that Islam is often conflated with Turks, the headscarf, and migration due to images perpetuated in the media. Another common image: German-Turkish or Arab youth as more violent or prone to criminal acts than their &#8220;native&#8221; counterparts, a stereotype repeatedly rebuked by <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/schulspiegel/wissen/kriminalitaet-von-migranten-laut-gutachten-nicht-hoeher-a-983536.html">studies</a>. <em>There are so many positive examples of what German-Turks have done and do for this country</em>, Ali says,<em> but news and social media continuously choose to show negative images. I want the media to show more positive images. </em><em><br />
</em></p>
<p>Ali is a positive person by nature. His face lights up when he shares stories of making connections to people at work or through his music. But he also has plenty of examples of feeling unwelcome or misunderstood on account of his background. He makes a conscious effort to speak Turkish with his daughter only at home and German out in public, in order to avoid judgment. More than once he&#8217;s been told &#8220;Du bist mein Lieblingst<span class="st">ürke</span><em>&#8221; </em>(&#8220;You&#8217;re my favorite Turk&#8221;), by a coworker or a club bouncer, for not stirring up trouble. <em>What am I supposed to do with that?</em> Ali asks, his eyes filling with emotion. Recently, a colleague joked to Ali that the reason his work contract was not renewed was because of his new hairstyle. <em>You look like a Turk now</em>, he told Ali.</p>
<p>After 6 years at the company, successfully training incoming employees, Ali had expected to keep his job. <em>After the video, they told me my music was making me slower at work, which wasn&#8217;t true,</em> Ali says, shaking his head<em>. <strong>I always felt like they were waiting for me to explode, to show my &#8220;Turkish temper&#8221;. In the end I think they just couldn&#8217;t deal with my humanness.</strong></em></p>
<div id="attachment_3359" style="width: 579px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3359" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-3359" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/alitsm.jpg" alt="Performing at a Football Academy Gala, August 2014" width="569" height="335" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/alitsm.jpg 569w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/alitsm-300x176.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 569px) 100vw, 569px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3359" class="wp-caption-text">Performing at a Football Academy Gala, August 2014</p></div>
<p>Ali is disappointed but not disheartened. He is taking this unexpected turn as a chance to reconsider career paths. <em>I have so much experience, and I want to use that to do something good</em>, he says. He&#8217;s now thinking seriously about becoming a social worker for kids with migration backgrounds. <em>I know </em><em>what they&#8217;re going through.</em> <em>I can go into their homes and talk to their parents, help them see what options they have and make sure they don&#8217;t give up. </em>More than likely, he&#8217;ll do it with music. <em>I learned early on that music allows you to reach a lot of people. Music is its own language, one that you don&#8217;t need to understand, just feel.</em></p>
<p>Ali is certainly &#8220;for&#8221; Germany, but does he consider himself from Germany? <em>Whew,</em> Ali lets out a deep breath, <em>I&#8217;m not sure. I have parts of German culture and parts of Turkish culture. But I think, most of all, I&#8217;m a Berliner.</em></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>*The term German-Turk is a hyphenation often used for people born and/or raised in Germany with 2nd or 3rd generation Turkish backgrounds. For more on language, migration, and identity, see our article <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">here</a>.</p>
<p>For German interviews with Ali, click <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/video/ali-fuer-deutschland-deutsch-tuerke-nimmt-wm-song-auf-video-1500438.html">here</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kGYNujx3RvQ">here</a>.</p>
<p><em>All of Ali&#8217;s quotes have been translated/paraphrased by Sophia Burton.<br />
</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>World Cup Fever: How malleable is German identity?</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/28/world-cup-fever-how-malleable-is-german-identity/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2014 09:43:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[World Cup]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2873</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Germany's World Cup victory has unleashed a new wave of patriotism, as well as a new identity crisis. This patriotism might only be as good as the boundaries it is ready and able to redefine. An act of flowing colors and neighbor-to-neighbor high-fives may have started a new understanding of who is allowed into the club, but policies and institutions need to take it one step further. Otherwise, patriotism is just as good as nationalism, which rules by way of exceptionalism. In the type of inclusive global society many of us would love to build, there is no room for exceptionalism...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In 2006 Germany hosted the World Cup; it also organized a social-marketing campaign for the sole purpose of revamping and re-solidifying patriotism. These things, i.e. national pride, rarely happen organically, particularly for countries with strong regional identities and histories of division. The goal of the campaign: the encouragement of colors-wearing, flag-toting, &#8216;Schland&#8217;-cheering citizens of the federal republic. One image made its way through German newspapers and magazines during this novel World Cup fever, representing what was now allowed, what could again be said without glancing over one&#8217;s shoulder &#8211; a 15-year old girl, <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/spiegel/print/index-2014-29.html">Monique Bienge</a>, waving a scarf on which the German national anthem is printed, as pictured below.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.spiegel.de/spiegel/print/d-47282143.html"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2874 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/die-deutschland-party.jpg" alt="Germany World Cup" width="454" height="599" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/die-deutschland-party.jpg 454w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/die-deutschland-party-227x300.jpg 227w" sizes="(max-width: 454px) 100vw, 454px" /></a></p>
<p>The text on Monique&#8217;s scarf reads:</p>
<p><em>Unity and justice and freedom</em><br />
<em> for the German fatherland!</em><br />
<em> To that let us aspire</em><br />
<em> In a spirit of fraternity,</em><br />
<em> With heart and soul.</em></p>
<p>So-called football nationalism is not limited to one time of the year (or to every four years, for that matter), however. Its colors bleed into the surrounding shapes of civic life, exerting influence and changing norms with each successive step toward normalcy. The iconic image pictured above articulates Germany&#8217;s re-entrance through the gates of national pride &#8211; a process that began <em>en force </em>in 2006 and culminates today with the German national team&#8217;s WC victory.</p>
<p>But back when the gates were still swinging closed, often in classrooms or at the dinner table of <a href="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/68er-Bewegung">68er</a> grandparents, German politicians didn&#8217;t dare proclaim the type of national pride other countries are famous for. The American political landscape I know<em> requires</em> a language of exceptionalism*, as even <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UK7JEYqIfw4">President Obama&#8217;s recent speech at the UN General Assembly</a> demonstrates. In stark contrast, a <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/politik/deutschland/muegelner-buergermeister-ich-bin-stolz-deutscher-zu-sein-a-502950.html">mayor in Saxony in 2007</a> said he was &#8216;proud to be German&#8217;, and public rebukes followed (in part due to accusations of radical-right leanings); the jury was still in session.</p>
<p><strong>This year things were a bit different.</strong></p>
<p>After the German national team took home the trophy, standing before Berlin&#8217;s Brandenburg Gate with faces toward the historic German <em>Siegessäule</em> or &#8216;pillar of victory&#8217;,<em> </em>German flags did not disappear, did not crawl back into the hole from whence they had come. Little old ladies with bags of flowers and desserts kept their colored armbands tightly on the wrist; pubescent school kids kept wearing jerseys to school, in many cases looking a little underwashed and a little over-hormoned.</p>
<p>And it all seemed so normal, at least for some of us. And yet, as <a href="http://www.zeit.de/kultur/2014-07/schweinsteiger-blutkrieger-dfb-medienkritik">an article in <em>die Zeit</em></a> (a German weekly) pointed out, this was again anything but an organic process: &#8220;The German Football Association managed to become a synonym for Germany&#8221;, explained in part by what the author called &#8217;embedded journalism&#8217; of a different type, AKA German media sources working closely to manufacture a patriotic relationship to the German soccer team &#8211; something the association (DFB) does not vehemently deny.</p>
<p>But even if many citizens and residents of Germany were convinced of the linkage between national pride and a football win, latent critique still found its way into the conversation, particularly in response to the team&#8217;s <a href="http://youtu.be/bg6ZFv63URE">controversial parody</a> of the defeated Argentinians.</p>
<p><em>Die taz</em> (a German daily) <a href="http://taz.de/Pro-und-Contra-Gauchogate/!142556/">debated the potential controversy</a>; even a <a href="http://taz.de/Nachlese-zur-Fussball-WM/!142947/">guest post </a>from someone associated with the team asked, <em>if we are allowed to celebrate, how loud, how long, and who is included?</em> <em>Der Spiegel</em> (a tad more conservative national magazine) went after a similar though more general question &#8211; <em>who are we Germans again</em>? With a fully-veiled woman, a <em>Pfand</em>-schlepping chap, a working mother, all cloaked in German colors, the magazine responded: &#8216;We Germans&#8217;<em>, </em>as<em> </em>the cover photo and its video are called, are all a little different.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.spiegel.de/images/image-723794-magazincover300-dmug.gif" rel="http://www.spiegel.de/spiegel/print/index-2014-29.html"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://www.spiegel.de/images/image-723794-magazincover300-dmug.gif" alt="Der Spiegel World Cup" width="300" height="396" /></a></p>
<p>In other countries, patriotic displays would likely not be paired with an existential crisis. But this is Germany. As the above extract from the German national anthem mentions, a fatherland is at stake here &#8211; one that, at the time of the anthem&#8217;s composition, did not exist.</p>
<p>German-speaking public officials and intellectuals debated the question of identity and belonging during the years leading up to the creation of the federal conglomeration of German states (out of the former Holy Roman Empire and environs). And in 1871, (mostly) peasants were absorbed into a territorial construction more or less controlled by Prussia (a state no longer in existence), all based on inklings of a so-called <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pan-Germanism">Pan-Germanism</a>. In other words, <em>whose </em>&#8216;fatherland&#8217; we are really talking about depends not only on who you ask, but also on when this question is and has been posed in the past.</p>
<p><strong>But what might this mean for the public exercise of patriotism?</strong></p>
<p>The historically-rooted &#8216;German question&#8217; &#8211; i.e. who are the Germans? &#8211; has yet to be completely solved. This is the point. How could it be? Countries, their populations, their mandates, their political philosophies of law and justice, even their borders, are constantly changing.</p>
<p><strong>As <em>Der Spiegel&#8217;s</em> &#8220;We Germans&#8221; cover demonstrates, the WC victory might be an opportunity to collectively re-work this changing German identity, while it is still hot and malleable.</strong></p>
<p>For the outsider, all this hullabaloo in the face of three differently colored stripes might seem exaggerated, even just written off as a sign of unresolved historical traumata. But from a philosophical perspective, it is indeed productive to acknowledge all that patriotism implies, i.e. what and whom it excludes. Such a topic is ever-relevant to the productive identity project that might emerge from this World Cup victory&#8230; with the potential to re-create boundaries of belonging for the better.</p>
<p>The cacophony of voices relating to Germanness and all that it encompasses has often been frustrating for German politicians, particularly in relation to defining citizenship laws. But rallies in the streets and public displays of &#8216;belonging to the German club&#8217; have somehow put these oft-exclusionary discussions on hold for a minute, giving journalists the chance to <a href="http://taz.de/WM-und-Integration-in-Berlin/!142407/">write about on-the-ground cohesion </a>or harmony in a country that often fosters a language of <a href="http://www.spiegel.tv/#/filme/duisburg-marxloh/">ghettoization</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_2888" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/wm-berlin.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2888" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-2888" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wm-berlin.jpg?w=640" alt="Photo by Juri Gottschau" width="640" height="401" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2888" class="wp-caption-text">Photo by <a href="http://www.jurigottschau.com/">Juri Gottschau</a></p></div>
<p>That said, after the streets have cleared and the flags have been taken down, <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/meinung/deutschland-ist-weltmeister-wm-traum-wm-trauma/10207938.html"><em>where does this leave the many immigrants or non-traditional members of German society</em>?</a> asked a columnist with immigration background, recently. For patriotism, like nationalism, thrives on exclusion. That is to say, a group is only a group if it has the capacity to actively determine who belongs and who does not. In essence, this is the definition of the modern state. Part of the state&#8217;s mandate is the ability to exercise force (as opposed to violence, according to Hannah Arendt), in order to maintain these boundaries, something rarely questioned in public discourse or by political constituencies.</p>
<p>These boundaries are not a given, however: they result from and are constantly reproduced in political processes,  enshrined not only in law but in everyday institutions, ideologies, and practices of the outsiders vs. the insiders. This means that they can be changed.</p>
<p><strong>In the end, this new German patriotism is only as good as the boundaries it is ready and able to redefine. An act of flowing colors and neighbor-to-neighbor high-fives may have started a new understanding of who is allowed into the club, but policies and institutions need to take it one step further. Otherwise, patriotism is just as good as nationalism &#8211; a political project and instrument of the state with the purpose of coercing national conscription, labor-market participation, and civic legitimacy by way of <em>exceptionalism</em>.</strong></p>
<p>In the type of inclusive global society many of us would love to build, there is no room for exceptionalism.</p>
<p>All big words and ideas aside, patriotism might have the chance to be democratic and inclusive or it might become dangerously exclusive. As I have witnessed in my home country of the United States, this often depends on who sets the governmental agenda but also who shapes discussions as to what types of restrictions are legitimate, particularly in regards to labor-market and immigration policies.</p>
<p>But it doesn&#8217;t have to be so top-down or even so economically-driven. We can decide who belongs to our club, and maybe, in an ideal world, politicians will respond. In my opinion, this should be the German World Cup take-away.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*The phenomenon of national exceptionalism as a political value and even as a &#8216;moral quest&#8217; is demonstrated best by the American political right and the movement to shame political leaders or public opposition who <em>do not</em> believe in the superior story, governmental system, and social values of the United States. Newt Gingrich&#8217;s propaganda-documentary <a href="http://youtu.be/oQsCW1hbOGw">A City Upon a Hill</a> is case-in-point; Ron Paul&#8217;s (of the far-right American Libertarian Party) <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0BOrM6j1-2s">defense of his own views of &#8216;moderate exceptionalism&#8217;</a> to conservative critiques is another.</p>
<p><em>For more on my (and our) philosophy regarding borders and belonging, read the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/about/a-manifesto/">Collidoscope Manifesto</a> on cities, difference, and building community.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Berlin needs you (but why?)</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/04/review-berlin-needs-you-but-why/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/04/review-berlin-needs-you-but-why/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2014 08:20:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2702</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Why is immigration important? The debate takes many angles. There's the demographic argument, that developed countries with low birth rates and aging populations need bodies to maintain the replacement rate. There's the globalization take, that the movement of people in all forms is increasingly inevitable and contributes to global competitiveness and 21st century skills. The moral or even religious spin, emphasizing human dignity, charity, an obligation for prosperous nations to help those more needy. But few arguments are as pervasive as the economic one...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_2738" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdad.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2738" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2738 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad.jpg?w=640" alt="" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad-300x199.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2738" class="wp-caption-text">©Barbara Dietl</p></div>
<p>Why is immigration important? The debate takes many angles. There&#8217;s the <a href="http://www.thelocal.de/20131126/germany-needs-more-immigration">demographic argument</a>, that developed countries with low birth rates and aging populations need bodies to maintain the replacement rate. There&#8217;s the globalization take, that the movement of people in all forms is increasingly inevitable and contributes to global competitiveness and 21st century skills. The moral or even religious spin, emphasizing human dignity, charity, and an obligation for prosperous nations to help those more needy. Yet few arguments are as pervasive as the economic one: that immigrants fill labor shortages, tend to be more innovative, start businesses and create jobs, pay taxes, and contribute to the social welfare net (yes, often more than they &#8220;take away&#8221;).</p>
<p>It is this economic argument that is often relied upon as a point of mutual agreement that immigrants are needed. Maybe not <a href="http://www.dw.de/opinion-foreigners-welcome-sort-of/a-17651819">“wanted”</a>, but at least needed.</p>
<p>This argument extends beyond newcomers to the 2nd and 3rd generations. In countries like Germany where the history of immigration has been primarily low skilled, children of migrants still face numerous linguistic, cultural, and socioeconomic challenges. These are exacerbated by a stratified education system that is associated with lower educational attainment, limited access to higher education, and fewer chances for economic mobility. Germany fares particularly poorly in this arena: it has the <a href="http://www.oecd.org/general/oecdeducationsystemsleavemanyimmigrantchildrenflounderingreportshows.htm">OECD&#8217;s largest performance disparity</a> between native and immigrant students and is one of the only countries where 2nd generation students perform worse on international assessments than the 1st generation.</p>
<p>Enter <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> (Berlin needs you!), a program that works to improve the educational and economic outcomes of students with migrant backgrounds. Launched by the state of Berlin as part of its overall integration plan in 2006, it aims to increase the number of these students entering the public sector by 25% by bridging schools with the professional world. It is coordinated by BQN, <em>das Berufliche Qualifizierungsnetzwerk für Migrantinnen und Migranten in Berlin</em> (the Vocational Qualification Network for Immigrants in Berlin) and is funded by the state of Berlin.</p>
<p><iframe title="Berlin braucht dich! - Diverse Wege in die Arbeitswelt" width="650" height="366" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fwBxQu93g3o?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>The program works in cycles: a day-long introduction to a business or organization for 7th graders, a week-long internship for 8th graders, 3-week internships for 9th graders, and training and application days for 10th graders. Participating schools help their students find training spots with an online matching tool. Spots are currently offered in Berlin&#8217;s public sector, public companies, and the metal and electrical industries, though BQN is working toward expanding the program to include small businesses. The program has also evolved from a focus on the vocational training system (<em>Duales System</em> &#8211; working and learning in a company) to more dual study opportunities <em>(Duales Studium</em> &#8211; studying and working simultaneously).</p>
<p>Mitri Sirin, a German TV reporter of Turkish-Syrian background, moderates the 5th <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> consortium meeting in June. He highlights the culture of low expectations and need for more varied training opportunities for migrant students during a panel on diversity politics.<em> The idea that any kid in the 7th grade would know what they wanted to be when they grow up is a fairy tale,</em> he scoffs. <em>Of course I was funneled into a vocational internship with other kids like me. I was still able to make something or other of myself</em>, he adds to chuckles from the audience,<em> but not all are so lucky.</em></p>
<div id="attachment_2790" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdconsortium.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2790" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2790 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium.jpg?w=640" alt="Berlin braucht dich! Consortium Meeting June 2014" width="640" height="480" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2790" class="wp-caption-text"><em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> Consortium Meeting June 2014 ©BQN Berlin</p></div>
<p>When the panel concludes, a group of giggling students race out from behind the stage to plaster black paper on the windows and switch off the lights. It&#8217;s a bit eerie to be cloaked in darkness with pop music blaring before 11am, but soon enough the black-light theater performance has the audience tapping their feet and grinning widely. While entirely up for interpretation, the images of a ball being passed around between two sets of hands and a student struggling in a white sheet before becoming a colorful butterfly suggests a story-line of transnationalism and diversity.</p>
<p><em>The theater program is</em> <em>a kind of &#8220;empowerment action&#8221;</em>, explains Robert Westermann, PR Manager of Berlin braucht dich! <em>The group comes from one of the 32 schools we cooperate with&#8230; students from this school also take part in our internships. </em></p>
<p>Later that morning, we make sure to join the small workshop where the same students share their experiences. <em>I&#8217;ve been in Germany for 2 years and can&#8217;t speak German that well,</em> <em>but black-light theater is like another language that I can speak to everyone, without having to actually say anything, </em>shares one Iranian girl.  <em>In theater you have to learn to control yourself, but you can also be free</em>, says another. <em>Theater has taught me how to be loud</em>, exclaims a third.</p>
<div id="attachment_2737" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2737" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2737 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht.jpg?w=640" alt="Schule am Schloss students post-performance. Source: Berlin braucht dich!" width="640" height="480" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2737" class="wp-caption-text"><em>Schule am Schloss</em> students take a bow post-performance ©BQN Berlin</p></div>
<p><em>In my view, the most innovative aspect of </em>Berlin braucht dich!<em> is that schools and companies are working together on a constant and sustainable level</em>, describes Robert.<em> This stable network makes it possible to operationalize key ideas around &#8220;intercultural openness&#8221;, by changing structures, processes, and mentalities. </em></p>
<p><em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> has experienced marked success in its 8 years of operation. Since 2006, the ratio of trainees in the public sector with a migration background has been steadily on the rise and by 2009 had doubled to 16.9%. By 2013, every 5th trainee (20.5%) in the public sector and public companies had a migration background.</p>
<p>Yet it is the emphasis on mutually understood and implemented &#8220;intercultural openness&#8221; that implies <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> is about more than Euro signs. In addition to securing a more intercultural workforce through sheer numbers, BQN offers free <a href="http://www.berlin-braucht-dich.de/aktivitaeten/diversity-trainings/">diversity trainings</a> for partner schools and businesses. Migration is acknowledged not only as a reality, but as a key factor that contributes both &#8220;to our quality of life now and the sustainability of our future.&#8221; While the demand for such trainings has been low on the school side, BQN has implemented many with employees from their partner companies.</p>
<div id="attachment_2800" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdstudents.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2800" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2800 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents.jpg?w=640" alt="bbdstudents" width="640" height="480" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2800" class="wp-caption-text">Moderator and TV reporter Mitri Sirin (middle) with theater group students ©BQN Berlin</p></div>
<p>The path to a truly intercultural workforce is still laden with hurdles. Recent studies on Germany show that <a href="http://www.migazin.de/2014/06/02/vorurteil-widerlegt-junge-migranten-nicht-haeufiger-kriminell-als-deutsche-jugendliche/">prejudice</a> and <a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/karriere/studie--mit-tuerkischem-namen-sinken-chancen-auf-ausbildungsmarkt,10808620,26663588.html">hiring discrimination</a> against students with migrant backgrounds is alive and well. Access to higher education and many employment opportunities is entirely off the table, as a disproportionate number &#8211; <a href="http://www.boeckler.de/35923_41774.htm">about half</a> &#8211; of these students are funneled into the lowest vocational school track. As one of the business representatives at the meeting explained to the theater group, <em>If any of you came into an interview at our offices, you would do great. But to get to the interview stage, you would still have to pass the entrance test first, which focuses on German, math, and logic. </em></p>
<p>Challenges such as these require integrated policy approaches. Approaches that distinguish the actors involved and hold them accountable for their roles in changing the structures, norms, and mentalities that fuel these challenges. Approaches that extend beyond just the economic argument and are brave enough to acknowledge everyone&#8217;s role in fostering an intercultural and inclusive society that values the potential of each individual. In short, Berlin doesn&#8217;t just need you. It needs all of us.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>Thank you to Robert Westermann, PR Manager of <em>Berlin braucht dich!, </em>for inviting us to the consortium meeting and providing information for this article.</p>
<p>For more information on <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em>, check out their German website <a href="http://www.berlin-braucht-dich.de/">here</a>. Info in English can be found <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/ewsi/en/practice/details.cfm?ID_ITEMS=13081">here. </a></p>
<p>For another article from us on Berlin based programs for students with migrant backgrounds, click <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/18/rave-education-per-square-kilometer/%20">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/04/review-berlin-needs-you-but-why/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: the Klezmer Gentiles</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2014 09:55:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Holocaust]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jewish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[memory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Poland]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2468</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[International artists in Berlin occupy a semi-privileged position, able to ask critical questions of society without being publicly rebuked. An example of such an artist is Soliman Lawrence. Soli has been photographing the memorialization of Jewish culture in Poland for years, following the tracks of a new form of engagement with the past, as enacted by a more recent generation of Poles. In contrast to Poland, Germany now has its fair share of Jews. What might this mean for memory and its rituals?...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>An interview is never one-sided &#8211; in fact, it is a constructive conversation. I am as much a part of this piece as the artist who answered my questions. Without the contributions of the other, individual statements would hold little significance. So thanks, Soli, for letting me share our conversation. </em></p>
<p>International artists in Berlin are one category of newcomers who, although shaping the cultural politics and economic fabric of Berlin perhaps more than other groups of foreign residents (those without German citizenship), are often left out of the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/11/integration-in-berlin-research-for-a-desolate-landscape/">critical integration debate</a>. Whether or not they learn German or German constitutional law seems to matter little to the politicians and journalists fueling the heavily institutionalized, assimilating discourse. I have yet to meet an artist who has been pressured by the authorities to &#8216;integrate&#8217; him or herself, as is the case with members of different social and economic groups.</p>
<p>This semi-privileged position has its benefits: Berlin&#8217;s creatives are often able to ask critical questions of society without being publicly rebuked, far enough from local history to recognize nuance and apply cultural critique in a non-threatening fashion.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2684 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>An example of such an artist is an old friend <a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/">Soliman Lawrence</a>. Soli has been photographing the memorialization of Jewish culture in Poland for years, following the tracks of a new form of engagement with the past, as enacted by a more recent generation of Poles. His collection of work is titled &#8220;<a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/unquietplacesphoto.html">For those whose faith has been broken</a>&#8220;. They do so, as Soliman&#8217;s stories and their pictures explain, through ritual, one example of which is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Klezmer">Klezmer</a> music. The fascinating part of this story: there are few Jews to speak of in Poland.</p>
<p>Beyond a revived Klezmer tradition, Soliman photographs reconstructed synagogues, Jewish-themed festivals, hand-made figurines, the maintenance of Jewish cemeteries &#8211; all weaving a tale of things past, now re-born as an ode to matzo ball soup or rabbinical characters.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2681 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland" width="640" height="423" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11-300x198.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11-650x429.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>Soliman is not Jewish, though his choice of topic likely gets many thinking that personal biography must inform the interest. I met with Soliman at a little cafe in Neukölln to talk art, history, and memory. Parallels between German memorialization of Jewish culture in Berlin and that which is happening in Poland were not at the tip of his tongue; these parallels were on the tip of mine, however.</p>
<p>Soliman is American by passport, has been a Berlin resident for more than 8 years, making the nationality question a bit tricky. He studied philosophy in the United States, stems originally from the Northern part of Florida, and has a contemplative way about him &#8211; he seems to move slowly, take things in and digest them before forming an opinion.</p>
<p>His artistic career began with a camera, has now evolved into a sort of philosophical exploration of what it means to remember. <em>Memory is at the center of my work</em>, he tells me, <em>how people remember after something has passed, how they remember together</em>. He is interested in the idea of <em><a href="http://www.postmemory.net/">post-memory</a>, the ways in which memory stays alive without the original witnesses</em>. Photography serves a crucial purpose, documentation allowing for connection.</p>
<p>Soliman first started making trips to Poland in 2006, visiting the growing Klezmer festivals in places like Krakaw. <em>Here is the biggest and best festival in Poland</em>, he tells me. I imagine VW buses jammed full with young, alternative Poles, spending warm nights outdoors, not for the beat of electronic sounds but for renditions of clarinet and fiddle. Actually, <em>it is quite mixed</em>, he tells me: young/old, hip/not.</p>
<p><em>When I first showed up in Krakaw, I was taking pictures of everything. I assumed a lot of the stuff I was photographing had something to do with Antisemitism &#8211; graffiti on the walls somehow looked antisemitic to me, these little tiles in the main square with five-pointed stars</em>, <em>for example</em>, he says with a laugh. <em>Then I realized that these stars were actually six-pointed, so </em>not <em>necessarily</em> <em>antisemitic</em>. <em>Very often, one finds what one searches for</em>, I add. This is even more true for a photographer, able to capture and catalog what may be happenstance occurrence, curating images into some sort of narrative about a people or place.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2682 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>That doesn&#8217;t mean that Antisemitism isn&#8217;t present in Polish society, however: <em>it&#8217;s complicated</em>, he says. An interview with Soliman on Jewish memorial culture in Poland appeared in 2012 in <em>die</em> <i>Zeit Online </i>with the headline: &#8220;<em>Wie Nicht-Juden die jüdische Kultur Polens wiederbeleben/</em> &#8220;<a href="http://www.zeit.de/video/2012-12/2032360755001/holocaust-wie-nicht-juden-die-juedische-kultur-polens-wiederbeleben">How Non-Jews Are Resurrecting Poland&#8217;s Jewish Culture</a>&#8220;. I recall watching the interview then, having heard of the beginnings of his Polish adventures back in 2010, when Soli and I first met, and being struck by the oddity of it all, the sense of a manufactured experience to take the place of an entire culture now lost. And yet, it was impossible not to find parallels with the city we both share, I felt: the way in which memory of Jewish culture in Berlin is fractured between recreations of the diaspora experience, a come-back Jewish culture in Germany, and a newer wave of young Israelis.</p>
<p>Soli has given quite a number of interviews in Germany since his project first began to receive attention. A <a href="http://juedische-woche-dresden.de/veranstaltung-2013/items/108.html">recent exhibition of his work in Dresden</a> put him into more contact with the German media. <em>So, did any of these journalists ask about your thoughts on Jewish memorialization in Germany, in Berlin, or on any similarities between Poland and Germany?</em>, I ask. At first, he doesn&#8217;t understand my question, seems a bit perplexed. Then, <em>No</em>,<em> in fact, no one even got close to formulating that question. Interesting that you bring that up. </em></p>
<p>Jewish culture in Berlin is diffuse, hard to put a finger on, as &#8211; with Jews everywhere &#8211; there is no one way to be Jewish and certainly no one way to be Jewish in Berlin. A memorial culture is also difficult to construct, when Jews are in fact present. To boot, there is no <em>one</em> way to memorialize the Holocaust and the thriving Jewish culture in Germany that preceded it. At least no one way that would satisfy the diverse groups who were affected by the genocide. In Poland, very little has happened at an institutional, top-down level. And so revivals of classic Ashkenazi traditions like Klezmer have been a means of memorializing a lost sector of Polish life, many years after its musicians were made to disappear.</p>
<p><em>At my first Klezmer festival, I didn&#8217;t really know what to do with myself. People were dancing, it was celebratory, there was this feeling of community</em>, he says. He was a bit stand-offish, not understanding why active participation was required. <em>This is the ritual</em>, he explains, <em>it is through such a collective ritual that some form of memory is reconstructed and created for the next generation.</em> <em>Many of these young people probably have no real connection to contemporary Jewish people</em>, he adds,<em> but this type of memory doesn&#8217;t require personal connection, rather an attachment to space and a desire to make a place &#8211; a memorial &#8211; out of it.</em></p>
<p>In Berlin, there is a strong attention to memorial sites or objects &#8211; the <a href="http://www.stolpersteine-berlin.de/en/stolpersteine"><em>Stolpersteine</em></a>, <a href="http://www.holocaust-mahnmal.de/en"><em>Memorial to the Murdered Jews of Europe</em></a>, <a href="http://www.slowtravelberlin.com/touching-berlins-ghosts/"><em>Bayerisches Viertel</em></a>, to name a few. These are spaces that are visited and even organized by many but are perhaps not as interactive or collective as a Klezmer ritual. One might simply pass by its insignia, whereas Klezmer is somehow a more active process, Soli explains.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2685 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9-300x199.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9-650x432.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p><em>But are these Klezmer festivals in Poland really about remembering and mourning the Holocaust? </em>I ask. <em>Yes, it is about that but not only about that.</em> <em>It is about thinking about the Jews that were once here, by people who were too young to have had the chance</em>.</p>
<p>There is a tendency<em> </em>in memorializing activities to focus on objects and their stories; materiality is desired, physical connection reconstructed. The Holocaust documentation and education center where I used to work curated a collection called &#8220;<a href="http://www.wsherc.org/museum/everyday-objects">Everyday Objects</a>&#8220;, the National Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM) releases <a href="http://www.ushmm.org/information/exhibitions/curators-corner">weekly stories online from its archival vault of objects</a>, and even the recent <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/sportingscene/2014/04/memory-objects-commemorating-the-boston-marathon-bombings.html?utm_source=dlvr.it&amp;utm_medium=twitter">Boston Marathon bombings are being actively commemorated through the collection of ordinary things</a>.</p>
<p><em>When talking with journalists, they just don&#8217;t really understand why Klezmer music is so popular in Poland, </em>Soli comments, as if to emphasize the stark differences between the German memory process and that of the Poland he knows:<em> Memory is expressed differently across space.</em> <em>My work is about these different memory ways, memory forms. </em></p>
<p>Surprising to many, Berlin is home to a fair number of Jews, and not just returned German Jews or those that fled from the former Soviet Union, but Israeli Jews, secular Israelis, secular Diaspora Jews from Argentina etc. &#8211; colliding in one city, not necessarily finding community among one another, because why should they? To make the argument, however, that perhaps things aren&#8217;t as different as they seem, I add that one does see a sort of stereotypical Jewish culture in Berlin, from the <a href="http://www.exberliner.com/locations/luigi-zuckermann-deli/">classic deli</a><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> </span>serving pastrami sandwiches to the local bagel shop. Both places in mind are not run by anyone of Jewish heritage, catering to a historic Jewish culture, perhaps even to New York Jewry rather than Berlin. This is not to say that there are no Jewish delis or bagel shops in Berlin that are owned by Jews. <em>But might the more theatrical recreations be a form of memorial culture, similar to Klezmer festivals?</em> I ask. <em>Maybe</em>, he says, <em>but I know a  few Israelis, and they don&#8217;t necessarily eat bagels. They go to this one shop on </em>Sonnenallee<em> where they can get hummus served warm, like back home in Israel</em>.</p>
<p>The varied layers of Jewish culture, identity, and memory in the Berlin landscape prevent one from making any static comparison to the situation in Poland, it seems &#8211; a place with very few Jews to speak of and a history wrought with a non-institutionalized form of memory, at least until recently. The Israeli and general Jewish presence in Berlin further complicates a comparison between the memory culture of Poland and that of Berlin in a very real sense. To be the authors of a tradition that re-appropriates Jewish tradition means being responsible for potential misappropriation. In Poland, I doubt there are too many active members of the Jewish community who would heavily criticize the rebirth of Klezmer in this form. <em>There aren&#8217;t</em>, Soli says.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2683 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>If he feels strange about researching this issue as an American artist without Jewish descent &#8211; <em>No</em>. The Holocaust is a large part of how Americans understand Germany, I add, in order validate his work from a place of personal opinion. The past was certainly a key factor in my own interest in contemporary German politics and society, as my <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/">article on Sachsenhausen</a> demonstrates.</p>
<p>The question is, if such a connection between a bleak past and curious future can be made, productively, and with much room for nuance and reflection. Soliman Lawrence&#8217;s work allows for just that. Like other artists, he is able to describe memory ways as they are occurring, not overtly criticizing but allowing others to draw their own conclusions or parallels.</p>
<p>We all remember differently. The most important thing is simply to remember.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>Jewish identity in Berlin, Jews in Germany, Israelis in Berlin: there is no shortage of debate, public presence, or diversity. Here a recent <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/culture/2014/05/so-long-israel-hello-berlin.html">article from <em>The New Yorker</em></a> on this topic and a few articles from us, written from the most varied of positions:</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/">Why Remembering the Holocaust is Good for Immigrants</a> &#8211; integration policy and a visit to Sachsenhausen concentration camp</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/07/rant-or-rave-jew-in-a-box/">Rant or Rave? Jew in a Box</a> &#8211; a controversial exhibit at the Berlin Jewish Museum</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">Interview: TV, the Treasury Minister, and Third Culture Kids</a> &#8211; Israeli in Berlin</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/07/interview-three-dimensions-of-integration/">Interview: Three Dimensions of Integration</a> &#8211; Jewish-American artist in Berlin</p>
<p>Last but not least, a few links for finding that Jewish deli or that Israeli hummus: <a href="http://www.berlinfo.com/Lifetime/Shopping/food/jewish/, http://forward.com/articles/165718/berlins-jewish-comeback/?p=al">Berlins Jewish Comeback</a>, <a href="//www.hagalil.com/deutschland/berlin/gemeinde/kosher.htm">Hagalil</a>, <a href="http://www.jewish-berlin.com/kosher.php">Jewish-Berlin</a>, <a href="http://www.berlinjewish.com/tips-for-your-berlin-vacation">Jewish in Berlin</a>, <a href="http://www.exberliner.com/food/land-of-the-lox-can-you-get-deli-food-in-berlin/">ExBerliner deli food list</a>.</p>
<p><em>All images were graciously provided by Soliman Lawrence as part of the series &#8220;<a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/unquietplacesphoto.html">For those whose faith has been broken</a>&#8220;. To see some of Soliman&#8217;s newer projects, check out his homepage. </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Integration in Berlin: Research for a Desolate Landscape</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/11/integration-in-berlin-research-for-a-desolate-landscape/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/11/integration-in-berlin-research-for-a-desolate-landscape/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2014 09:01:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2390</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On April 2, the new <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/">Berlin Institute for Empirical Research on Integration and Migration</a> (BIM) was launched. Certainly not the first institute of its kind in Germany, Berlin's Humboldt University, the Hertie Foundation, the Federal Employment Agency, and the German Football Association held a press conference to frame this initiative as new and needed. The reason: the field  - what is really known about the integration or inclusion of diversity - is more desert than rain-forest in this country of immigration...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On April 2, the new <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/">Berlin Institute for Empirical Research on Integration and Migration</a> (BIM) was launched. Certainly not the first institute of its kind in Germany, Berlin&#8217;s Humboldt University, the Hertie Foundation, the Federal Employment Agency, and the German Football Association held a <a href="http://www.hu-berlin.de/service/veranstaltungen/veranstaltungen_neu/?stat=show&amp;vk_id=2715">press conference</a> to frame this initiative as new and needed. The reason: the field  &#8211; what is really known about the integration or inclusion of diversity &#8211; is more desert than rain-forest in this country of immigration.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-7.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2419" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-7.jpg?w=550" alt="BIM 7" width="550" height="668" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-7.jpg 535w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-7-247x300.jpg 247w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></a></p>
<p>Improving the civic and social infrastructure of a city often begins with data. Aside from &#8220;Big Data&#8221; being the buzzword of 2014, plain ol&#8217; data is worth discussing. For <a href="http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2014/04/14/huge-new-york-development-project-becomes-a-data-science-lab/?_php=true&amp;_type=blogs&amp;_r=0">data can instruct city planners, lawmakers, social workers etc. to better approach problems of urban spaces</a> and their economies, in ways which benefit residents, including the marginalized. It might just be common sense, but empirical research (the critical boots-on-the-ground kind) is an act of taking stock of what is and what isn&#8217;t, which can prove quite useful in societies undergoing (or just learning to deal with) change.</p>
<p>Data, in this sense, is information gathered to solve a problem or answer a question. According to all panelists at the press conference, whether researchers or community and/or political stakeholders, this data is desperately required to answer the question of integration. Or is integration instead a problem to be solved?</p>
<p>As one of the not-so-timid anthropologists on the stage stated during the round of questions, <em>What we are really taking about, when we talk about integration, is how to learn to deal with and approach difference in society. </em></p>
<p><strong>The data imperative</strong></p>
<p>In light of Germany&#8217;s changing demography and political landscape, regarding immigration policy, the categories and models used to understand and support local populations have become outdated, as the <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/german-coalition-talks-move-closer-to-new-dual-citizenship-law-a-933523.html">dual-citizenship debate</a> in German Parliament over the last few months has indicated. More than just the classic census is required to capture the complexity of today&#8217;s metropolis. In Germany&#8217;s capital, where policy-makers brush shoulders with constituents and neighbors alike, real data could not be more in demand and yet, ironically, easier to find. This data goes beyond numbers.</p>
<p>Given this deficit of information and the few reasons for it, the Federal Ministry for Migration and Refugees (BAMF) <a href="http://www.bundesregierung.de/Content/DE/Pressemitteilungen/BPA/2014/04/2014-04-02-integration-kuratoriumsvorsitz.html">has been actively involved in BMI&#8217;s founding</a> and is set to be involved in its future;  BAMF&#8217;s new federal integration commissioner, Aydan Özo<span style="color: #435050;">ğ</span>uz<span style="color: #435050;">,</span> is a key member of the BIM board. Her vocal presence at the press conference made one thing clear: <em>We don&#8217;t even have the numbers, quite honestly, to determine these differences</em> [between &#8216;foreigners&#8217;, &#8216;foreign-born&#8217;, citizens with migration background etc.]. <em>This makes my job quite difficult</em>, she articulated loudly to the audience of mostly journalists. <em>We just do not have the data.</em></p>
<div style="width: 659px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img loading="lazy" src="http://www.bundesregierung.de/Content/DE/Artikel/IB/Bilder-IB/2014-04-02-eroeffnung-bim2.jpg?__blob=bpaTopmeldung&amp;v=1" alt="Eröffnungsveranstaltung des Berliner Instituts für empirische Integrations- und Migrationsforschung" width="649" height="406" /><p class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: BIM HU, Dirk Enters</p></div>
<p>Wolfgang Niersbach, President of the German Football Association (DFB) &#8211; one of three sponsors of the institute and the DFB&#8217;s first sponsorship of this kind &#8211; reiterated this data-driven impetus for more research at length. In 2006, the DFB employed its very own integration commissioner to better navigate the challenging combination of passionate football fans, visible diversity, and racism. A sweeping anti-racism campaign has been the culmination of these efforts, <em>though much is still to be learned</em>, Niersbach said. <em>Our hope for this institute is to get some more solid ground under our feet, to learn more about what works and what doesn&#8217;t work. </em>It is a learning process, and it begins with better information.</p>
<p>A key research focus of the new institute is the relationship between sports and integration, e.g., the participation of youth with migration backgrounds in local football clubs. But the playing field is different in football; <em>integration happens everyday, as 40% of the players have non-German backgrounds,</em> Niersbach mentioned emphatically, looking down the table at colleagues to see their reactions. To boot, social or ethnic differences are experienced on a more intensive and yet common-place level (at least organizationally) in football, compared to German society at large.</p>
<p>Niersbach explained: <em>Two talented football players grow up in Nuremberg playing together, they both go professional, they both have Turkish backgrounds. One day, one of them calls us up and says that he has decided to play for the Turkish national team, the other for the German national team. We are completely fine with that! We let them do what they want to do! But it was not always like that. </em>Times have changed, and so should terms and categories (the dual-citizenship debate, once again case-in-point).</p>
<p><strong>A clarification of terms</strong></p>
<p>The institute&#8217;s projects, team of researchers, sponsors, as well as its leadership, are truly diverse. Inter-disciplinary and embracing of different methodologies and languages of information, the institute seeks to embody what it studies, something Dr. Sebastian Braun, Director of BIM, emphasized throughout his introduction. A football advocate seated next to a well-known political scientist and culture critic;  anthropologists gawking at the government employee over-using the word &#8216;foreigner&#8217;; clinical psychiatrists tolerating the tactics of the employment agency, in dealing with issues of health and job competency. Diversity has to begin somewhere.</p>
<p>But where it will certainly prove to get messy is in this sticky, touchy realm of language.</p>
<p>Frank J. Weiser of the Federal Employment Agency spoke from the perspective of the market-driven state, the key aim of which is full employment and a balanced checkbook: <em>We want to improve our work with </em>Ausländer (foreigners)&#8230;<em>many of these foreigners have access to entitlement programs and experience higher unemployment than their German counterparts. I just work with the numbers, </em>he said smiling, seeming pleased with his honesty. <em>Social cohesion, approaching difference &#8211; but what about jobs?!</em>, he might have said.</p>
<p>The fissure between practice, policy, and the ideals of academia is still there and not likely to go away.</p>
<div id="attachment_3410" style="width: 646px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3410" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3410 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-3.jpg" alt="Director of German Football Association, Rep. Director of Federal Employment Agency; Photo source: DFB" width="636" height="310" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-3.jpg 636w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-3-300x146.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 636px) 100vw, 636px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3410" class="wp-caption-text">Director of German Football Association, Rep. Director of Federal Employment Agency; Photo source: DFB</p></div>
<p><em>The foreigners on our football teams used to be the exotics. In 1963, when DFB was founded, we only had three players with any sort of migration background. Today, 40% of our players have some relationship to immigration, </em>Niersbach commented.</p>
<p>Hands shot up in a hurry from the rows of journalists filling the hall.</p>
<p>A free-lance reporter and coach for a local football league called the use of the word <em>&#8220;Ausländer&#8221;</em> (foreigner)<em> </em>by both men into question. How strange it was to hear a term describing kids born or raised in Germany, kids that play football in Germany as foreign: <em>There are kids that play on our teams that are different, yes, but they play together&#8230; these kids don&#8217;t need to be integrated just because they happen to have a different skin tone.</em></p>
<p>The most vocal of the anthropologists, Prof. Dr. Wolfgang Kaschuba, director of Humboldt University&#8217;s European-Anthropology Department, agreed with this critique, bringing the other oddly-applied term <em>Menschen mit Migrationshintergrund</em> (people with migration background) into the discussion. It is not just about the word &#8220;foreigner&#8221;, which connotes otherness, apart-ness; rather, the problem lies with the terms themselves, how they shift from one individual or community to the next without time for distinction &#8211; <em>that is the humorous aspect in all of it</em> and the aspect worth exploration, i.e. empirical research. <em>I don&#8217;t used the word Ausländer at all, but I do use </em>Menschen mit Migrationshintergrund<em>, though I shorten it to MMH, and I say it M-M-H just to emphasize the irony of these terms in the German debate.</em></p>
<p>To close this round of questions, the Director of Humboldt University added, <em>When we are talking about integration, we are focusing on those people who have decided to stay in Germany, to live here, to work here. </em>But what does it mean to &#8220;decide&#8221;? To stay? To live? No one at the front of the room mentioned citizenship laws, legal frameworks regarding work and residency permission, or those political ideologies that might bar any empirical work on terminology from having real impact in Parliament. Surely, data for this will be gathered, but the question is, who will listen.</p>
<p><strong>Taking stock</strong></p>
<p>In response to a question from the <em>Tagesspiegel, as to how this institute plans to transfer its knowledge to policy-makers</em>, Naika Forouton, the Representative Director of the institute, responded, <em>One of the purposes of the institute is to move away from a one-sided discourse that we have all experienced&#8230;[However], We do not see that as our job, delivering some report to policy-makers. Pure political performance is not our role.</em></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-4.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2411" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-4.jpg?w=640" alt="BIM 4" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>In 2013 Naika Forouton wrote a highly-informative report in conjunction with the <a href="http://www.migrationpolicy.org/">Migration Policy Institute</a> (MPI), based in Washington D.C., on <a href="http://www.migrationpolicy.org/research/identity-and-muslim-integration-germany">Muslim identity and citizenship in Germany</a>. In 2012, she contributed to a volume of policy analyses for MPI. Policy analysis and the effects thereof constitute a large part of her professional activities, in fact. Perhaps the difference lies in the medium.</p>
<p>In closing, federal integration commissioner, Aydan Özo<span style="color: #435050;">ğ</span>uz, described the field to be investigated by the new BIM as deserted, barren. And to that, <em>Immigrants have been here a long time, but now they are simply increasing. The current discourse is dominated by fear; it is a fear-laden process. It is important, with this in mind, to represent how things really are.</em></p>
<p>But can we amend this desolate landscape through empirical research alone and the data it yields?</p>
<p>The anthropologist, Dr. Wolfgang Kaschuba, seemed to say &#8220;no&#8221;: <em>We need a new form of group understanding, group consensus, even relationships, even in the postmodern age, even in the era of individualism. We need to come together.</em></p>
<p>If all this coming together will produce the data this city and its neighborhoods need, somehow making it to the highest echelons of power, the BIM is a needed initiative, indeed. If not, the ivory-tower-dilemma may leave the German Football Association and others in waiting.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>For more information on the fascinating convergence of football, integration, and political engagement, see projects from the following institutions: <a href="http://www.bosch-stiftung.de/content/language1/html/28056.asp">Robert-Bosch-Stiftung</a> project page, <a href="http://heimatkunde.boell.de/dossier-fussball-integration">Heinrich-Böll-Stiftung</a> project page (here <a href="http://www.nfv-www.de/downloads/s_992/dossier_fussball_integration.pdf">PDF</a> report), <a href="http://www.integration-gelingt-spielend.de/index.php/integration/fussball-integration.html">Bundesliga Stiftung</a> project page (here <a href="http://www.bundesliga.de/media/native/dokument/ebs_broschuere.pdf">PDF </a>report), <a href="http://www.dfb.de/?id=508798">DFB &#8211; German Football Association</a> project page. </em> <em>For more press (German language) on the new institute, here a selection of sources: <a href="http://www.migazin.de/2014/04/07/anpfiff-fuer-die-migrationsforschung/">Migazin</a>, <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/wissen/neues-institut-fuer-migrationsforschung-in-berlin-spielfeld-fuer-die-zuwanderung/9708232.html">Tagesspiegel</a>, <a href="http://www.dfb.de/news/de/d-nachhaltigkeit/dfb-foerdert-neues-institut-fuer-integrationsforschung-in-berlin/56752.html">DFB</a>.</em></p>
<p>All photos unless sourced otherwise were taken by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/11/integration-in-berlin-research-for-a-desolate-landscape/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
