<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>diversity &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/diversity/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Moralpolitik and the Ressentiments of Change</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 15:35:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4120</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[According to headlines, the German government has pledged haven – albeit temporary in many cases – to up to 800,000 refugees or migrants applying for asylum in the country. The U.S., despite initial wavering, has signaled that it will work to raise its refugee quota yearly, with the goal of a 100,000 cap by 2017. Yet within and around this historical moment of humanitarian crisis and measured political response are the inflammatory words of Donald Trump. He recently roared to a crowd in Iowa that, if elected, he “will deport all of the 11 million illegal migrants in this country.”]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As German and U.S. refugee policies inevitably collide in light of current events, this writer finds herself in the United States. The other writer of this blog will soon be in Germany, taking stock of the so-called “refugee crisis” on the ground. On my side of the Atlantic, a crisis is not yet to be felt… at least not so acutely. This has as much to do with media semantics as it does with history.</p>
<p>According to headlines, the German government has pledged haven – albeit temporary in many cases – <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/aug/20/germany-raises-estimate-refugee-arrivals-800000">to up to 800,000 refugees or migrants applying for asylum in the country</a>. The U.S., despite initial wavering, <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/news/nation/2015/09/20/increase-admission-refugees-kerry-says/fnCweeIlCS8g47VF7VAkBP/story.html">has signaled that it will work to raise its refugee quota</a> yearly, with the goal of a 100,000 cap by 2017. The Pope, as leader of the spiritual state of Catholicism, <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">has planned to make migrants and refugees one of the few central issues of his travels around the Western Hemisphere this week</a>.</p>
<p>All at once, it seems that moral duty, a college ethics course, and politics have fused into one mandate to assist.</p>
<p>Yet within and around this historical moment of humanitarian crisis and measured political response are the inflammatory words of Donald Trump. He recently roared to a crowd in Iowa that, if elected, he “<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">will deport all of the 11 million illegal migrants in this country.</a>” When asked by Univision’s anchor Jorge Ramos how he would accomplish such a feat, he coolly responded, “I’m a great manager.”</p>
<div id="attachment_4127" style="width: 630px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4127" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-4127" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg" alt="Donald Trump immigration" width="620" height="372" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg 620w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP-300x180.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4127" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Charlie Neibergall/AP via <em><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">The Guardian</a></em></p></div>
<p>One can easily get caught up in the absurdity that is the American campaign season, enjoying its theatrics as a harmless part of the celebrity process. But Trump’s words should hold weight, and they should be cause for alarm.</p>
<p>Trump’s message is not as obtuse, as unnecessarily harsh as it might seem; it reflects not only present sentiment but historical precedent… for both the United States and Germany. With the current refugee and migrant crisis, old tensions are slowly and loudly being unearthed. And the mobility of many of the world&#8217;s displaced, traumatized, and poor is not likely to change any time soon.</p>
<p>National Public Radio’s <em>Fresh Air</em> <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/10/439114563/americas-forgotten-history-of-mexican-american-repatriation">recently interviewed</a> one of the scholars behind the book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Decade-Betrayal-Mexican-Repatriation-1930s/dp/0826339735">Decade of Betrayal: Mexican Repatriation in the 1930s</a>”. The volume documents a massive and relentless deportation program at a time when xenophobia and economic distress were rampant. Historians Raymond Rodriguez and Francisco Balderrama document what is nothing short of a terrifying episode in American history – frightening for what right-wing reactionaries in a new age of migration might be capable of.</p>
<p>As Rodriguez shared with <em>Fresh Air</em>’s host, Terry Gross, the 1930s treated Mexican Americans with great malice and abuse. For reason only of their heritage, they were targeted by government programs and private citizens alike. This abuse culminated in the federal government&#8217;s campaign to strip millions of Americans of their citizenship. Not all those rounded up in deportation raids were naturalized citizens, though <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">estimates suggest than ½ of those expelled were</a>. Most were visa-holders of some sort, their only crime having been born a member of a demonized ethnic group.</p>
<p>Governmental programs to round up and expel society’s undesirables often begin in cities, according to history (see the American strategy of Japanese internment or Nazi Germany&#8217;s institution of the urban ghetto). And so Los Angeles was the primary target of the government’s Mexican American deportation program. Largely as a response to the despair the Great Depression had unleashed across the country, officials systematically sent entire families from the L.A. area back to Mexico, with no infrastructure in place to receive them. <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">From 1929 to 1944, 1/3 of L.A.’s Mexican American population was deported</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4128" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4128" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4128" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-650x487.jpg" alt="Los Angeles Mexican Americans 1932" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4128" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Los Angeles Public Library/Herald Examiner Collection via <em><a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">National Public Radio</a></em></p></div>
<p><em>Ressentiments</em> – projection of resentment or fear onto often vulnerable groups in society – were widespread both in the U.S. and in Germany throughout the Great Depression. Xenophobia in the face of severe economic collapse paved the way for Germany’s organized extermination machinery. The U.S.’s internment of Japanese and German citizens, its continued subordination of Black Americans, and its systematic deportation of Mexican Americans demonstrate that this country was in no way spared such a nasty past.</p>
<p>Slowly but surely, such <em>ressentiments</em> have now begun to return. This time, Germany may be more in the right, even despite a few documented attacks on refugee facilities, while America edges closer toward the precipice of wrong.</p>
<p>…</p>
<p>On my side of the ocean, I have arrived into a complicated sector of the nexus of natural diversity and these increasing <em>ressentiments. </em>Vancouver, Washington, where both my parents now live, <a href="http://www.thenation.com/article/browning-america/">is becoming increasingly &#8220;Brown&#8221;</a>. Separated only by a short bridge across the Columbia River, Southwest Washington has become Portland&#8217;s semi-urban/semi-rural extension. Because the northern bank of the river offers families more space for cheaper, better funded schools for fewer private tax dollars, and income tax exemption, immigrants who may have otherwise moved to the Portland, Oregon metro area are now planting themselves on the side of its less expensive neighbor. Portland, as a result, <a href="http://www.oregonlive.com/news/index.ssf/2009/01/in_a_changing_world_portland_r.html">has become increasingly White</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4129" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4129" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4129" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-650x366.jpg" alt="Interstate bridge over the Columbia River, connecting Portland, Oregon and Vancouver, Washington" width="650" height="366" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-650x366.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-300x169.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4129" class="wp-caption-text">Interstate bridge over the Columbia River, connecting Portland, Oregon and Vancouver, Washington</p></div>
<p>According to most recent U.S. census data, Vancouver is now 11% Hispanic, inching closer to the national average. We can expect this number to be much higher in reality, as immigrants will often opt out of participation in the census. There are other ethnic groups represented in Vancouver’s demographic development: For example, 18% of families speak a language other than English at home, and the traditional taco truck has recently seen competition in North African, Japanese, and Thai flavors.</p>
<p>None of this would seem all that significant, if I were not writing about a traditionally conservative county, with once sprawling farm land and a historical military base; a county that has now been converted into a rare blend of suburban developments, strip malls, urbane boutiques, and miles and miles of regional road. The nickname of &#8220;Van-tucky&#8221;* &#8211; something I have only heard used on the other side of the water, mind you &#8211; might tell you all you need to know.</p>
<p>The rate of poverty in Vancouver is also higher than the national average. Vancouver&#8217;s mayor recently <a href="http://www.cityofvancouver.us/ced/page/affordable-housing-task-force">launched a task force</a> to investigate the cause of growing homelessness, rising rents, and increased demand for housing in the city’s most accessible and commercially viable areas. Serving as Portland’s &#8220;bedroom community&#8221; brings with it numerous tax and transportation disadvantages, as well, such as costly inter-city transit for a significant commuter population and bridges nationally notorious for being structurally unsound.</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p>In a brand-new cocktail bar in downtown Vancouver, which serves only locally-distilled (read artisanal) spirits, I sip my smoky-cucumber-tequila mixture and listen in on the interaction between the unlikely combination of guests who have just joined me on the patio. Three White bikers &#8211; two older women with smokers&#8217; cough and one machismo with a mustache &#8211; scoff at the price of their beer. Across from them at a nearby table, two women in their mid-20s, both with long black hair, one who speaks English with an accent.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-4130" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-650x366.jpg" alt="cocktail Vancouver, Washington" width="650" height="366" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-650x366.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-300x169.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Older veterans and cowboy-like characters are scattered across Vancouver’s downtown like curated remains of what was once here. They drink Rainier out of cans &#8211; Washington State’s Pabst Blue Ribbon with more local charm &#8211; and chain smoke in the park. They inhabit the dive bars with names like &#8220;Lounge&#8221; and antique neon advertisements. It seems that establishments like this new artisanal cocktail bar threaten to upset a tender balance between familiarity, comfort, and growth.</p>
<p>“$4! Bullshit”, one of the women hollers. The two younger ladies nudge their shoulders closer together, in order to continue a conversation disrupted by the boom of our three new patio companions.</p>
<p>The machismo turns toward the young women’s table, putting his hand on one of their legs. “Where you from, honey?&#8221;, he begins his monologue, &#8220;I’m a native, been here for more than 20 years, Detroit before that. You know how much this place has changed?”</p>
<p>Neither responds; however, the one whose leg is playing host to the man’s hand begins to shift uncomfortably.</p>
<p>&#8220;Where you from honey? You aren&#8217;t from around here, I can tell you that!&#8221;, one of the older women yells between sips from her can. “When did Rainier get this damn expensive? It’s bullshit, $4! I’ll tell you something…”</p>
<p>One of the young, dark-haired women flashes machismo a smile. &#8220;I&#8217;m from Panama!&#8221;, she says, and extends her hand for a shake. He takes it and squeezes it, returning both their hands to the table.</p>
<p>“I’m American, from here&#8221;, the other woman says, her leg now turned as far away from his body as the chair allows.</p>
<p>&#8220;But where are your parents from then?&#8221;, machismo asks with a chuckle. &#8220;That&#8217;s what I&#8217;m asking, ain&#8217;t it?&#8221;</p>
<p>She concedes, but stands to use the restroom (or simply disappear into the building) as she does: &#8220;Well, I&#8217;m Filipino.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p><em>Ressentiments</em> toward the Other can begin and fester in spaces of socioeconomic change. With President Obama’s pledge to take in 100,000 refugees, the question becomes “How will this country prepare its citizens to engage respectfully and kindly with members of a majority Muslim country?” The first step in this process is realizing that we have a lot of work to do, and we need politicians who will help us get there.</p>
<p>Germany has seen a fair share of reporting on the readiness of its population to open its arms to newcomers. It is easy to draw parallels to the past, particularly to Germany’s track record in <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/20/441732811/in-germany-migrants-find-footing-but-also-some-resistance">failing to integrate its guest-worker population and in promoting ethnic-based citizenship until it was almost too late</a>. However, it is Germany the rest of the world now looks to in awe &#8211; for choosing a kind of <em>moralpolitik</em> over patterns of the past.</p>
<p>Being so far away from a society I sometimes feel I know more about than my own (society of origin), I can’t help but beam with pride in watching small towns across Germany distribute clean clothes, socks, new toys, children’s books, and warm meals to the thousands of human beings in need who have crossed their borders. Nevertheless, Germany has since issued temporary border controls. Order still wins out over populist charity.</p>
<p>But aiming for a collective solution to the continuous stream of migrants and refugees into Europe, German leaders have worked to reach agreement upon a refugee quota for EU member states. Just this Tuesday this quota became a provisional reality.</p>
<p>Time will tell if all members comply, and if a sense of moral duty is really as strong as images of kind citizens touting bags of donations suggest. Yet I do have the sense that with each step toward welcoming the Other, <em>ressentiments</em> have fewer chances of surviving. When demonstrations of kindness are just so strong, so publicly undeniable, that Trump-esque hate can find no oxygen for its fire.</p>
<p>That is what I hope for America.</p>
<p>At the moment, the U.S. remains crippled and complicated by its multi-layered fears of all the regions of the world it has wronged. As UN Ambassador <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/23/442761552/10-000-syrian-refugees-just-the-floor-of-u-s-effort-says-ambassador-power">Samantha Power made clear in an NPR interview recently</a>, the country is not ready to simply do the right thing; it has to be a calculated response, taking security into account.</p>
<p>Overcoming fear is America&#8217;s consistent and stubborn challenge. I just hope the mistakes of the 1930s can mean something.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*Van-tucky is a reference to the southern state of Kentucky, the unofficial home of fried-chicken and horse races.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: &#8220;I&#8217;m a Human Being&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 11:21:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Austria]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[family]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Taiwan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vienna]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4019</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Vienna. Seat of the former Austro-Hungarian Empire. Widely considered the gateway to Eastern Europe. Home to a United Nations headquarters and numerous international companies and universities. The Austrian capital has long been a city of immigration – even when politics have told a different story – and a staggering 50% of the population has what’s referred to as a “migration background”. So it’s not as if I expected Vienna to not be multicultural...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_4028" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4028" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4028 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-650x581.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender" width="650" height="581" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-650x581.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-300x268.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender.jpg 728w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4028" class="wp-caption-text">Sophia, Christina, and Suzi at the 2015 Vienna Pride Parade</p></div>
<p>Vienna. Seat of the former Austro-Hungarian Empire. Widely considered the gateway to Eastern Europe. Home to a United Nations headquarters and numerous international companies and universities. The Austrian capital has long been a city of immigration – even when politics have told a different story – and a staggering <a href="https://www.wien.gv.at/english/social/integration/basic-work/facts-figures.html">50% of the population</a> has what’s referred to as a “migration background”.</p>
<p>So it’s not as if I expected Vienna to <em>not</em> be multicultural.</p>
<p>What I didn’t expect when <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/03/23/lens-on-leaving-homes/">moving to Vienna from Berlin</a> was to encounter some of the most fascinating “mixes” of my life: A half-Indian, half-Italian who grew up in the US and lives in Vienna with her half-Austrian, half-French boyfriend? A Chinese-American who fell in love with her German boyfriend in Hong Kong? A half-Austrian, half-Sicilian who met her Indian husband in London? The combinations are unexpected, beautiful, and dare I say, collidoscopic? (And their potential future children even more so).</p>
<div id="attachment_4031" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4031" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4031 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-650x475.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(3)" width="650" height="475" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-650x475.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-300x219.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4031" class="wp-caption-text">Christina poses with a cow in Austria on a family roadtrip</p></div>
<p>Christina, the first close friend I made in Vienna, is no different. Born in Taiwan to a Taiwanese mother and Austrian father, at age three her family moved to San Jose, California, where her younger brother was born. Kindergarten was spent in Vienna, where she lived with her father and grandparents while mom and brother stayed in the US. At age six the entire family moved to Taiwan for four years. Then it was back west to Seattle from ages 10-16 where Christina spent the longest stretch of her childhood, what she calls her &#8220;most formative years&#8221;. Her last two years of high school were completed in Taipei, where she graduated with the globally recognized International Baccalaureate Diploma.</p>
<p>“I was missing roots as a kid, our family was always bouncing around,&#8221; she tells me.</p>
<p>This triangular ping ponging between nations resulted in three different passport combinations within a family of four: Christina’s brother, born in the US, is a dual Austrian-American citizen but “avoids Austria now because of the mandatory military service.” Mom is dual Taiwanese-Austrian, “but never felt completely comfortable in Austria”. And Christina and her father are purely Austrian, on paper anyway.</p>
<p>&#8220;A long time ago my dad had the chance to become an American citizen but decided against it,&#8221; she says smirking, &#8220;He&#8217;s a proud Austrian.”</p>
<div id="attachment_4057" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4057" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4057 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_9365" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4057" class="wp-caption-text">Christina with her parents in Taiwan</p></div>
<p>It is to her father and his “pride” that Christina attributes her last 16 years in Vienna. &#8220;My dream was to go to Georgetown [University],&#8221; Christina tells me one warm evening in the <em>Museumsquartier</em>, her fingers tapping the stem of her <em>Hugospritz</em>. &#8220;I applied and got in… my mom supported it, but my dad kept saying I had to go to university in Austria. It was always really important to him that, as the oldest child, I embrace my Austrian roots.&#8221;</p>
<p>Christina ended up moving to Vienna against her will: “I didn&#8217;t have any connection to Austria at that time other than having spent the occasional summer there with my grandparents.” The first year, she expressed her anger by skipping class in favor of exploring the city and having fun.</p>
<p>“And then I got pregnant,” she says laughing, “the biggest rebellion of all!”</p>
<div id="attachment_4059" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4059" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4059 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371-650x650.jpg" alt="IMG_9371" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4059" class="wp-caption-text">Mother-daughter surfing trip in Morocco</p></div>
<p>Christina’s daughter Illeana (Illy) was born when she was 20. She raised Illy as a single mother while completing her degrees in Economics and Sinology, with “lots of help” from friends with similar bi-cultural backgrounds. She counts half-Austrian friends from South Africa and Bolivia among her closest, along with a half-Kosovan, half-Czech hair salon owner named Suzi. “None of us knew what we were doing… it was experimental parenting. I think if I raised a child now I’d be much more nervous!”</p>
<p>After making it over the hump of her first year, Vienna started to feel like home. “I began to realize how much I love it here,” Christina reflects. Now one could say Christina is as Austrian as they come. Her German is flawless and chock full of colloquialisms, she sings along to Austrian <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schlager_music">Schlager</a></em>, and her drink of choice is the ubiquitous <em><a href="http://austrianwineusa.com/2013/12/20/12-days-of-austrian-wine-enjoy-a-gspritzer/">Weisser Spritzer</a></em>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4064" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4064" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4064 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-650x602.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(7)" width="650" height="602" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-650x602.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-300x278.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7.jpg 701w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4064" class="wp-caption-text">Christina skiing in Kaprun, Austria</p></div>
<p>None of that, however, stops her from craving Taiwanese ‘Three-Cups Chicken’ or her favorite American cereal, ‘Lucky Charms’. “I’m biracial and tri-cultural,” she states without hesitation. And while rewarding on personal and professional levels (she’s also fluent in Mandarin), Christina’s background has not gone unchallenged in a city that still struggles to see itself as a place of migration and diversity.</p>
<p>Christina has encountered countless variations of the “<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/">But where are you <em>really</em> from?</a>” question over the years. “When I first got to Vienna, there were fewer minorities and diversity didn&#8217;t work very well,” she remarks, “I remember meeting one guy who could not comprehend why I looked the way I did but had a very common German last name,&#8221; she rolls her eyes at the memory. &#8220;I literally had to spell it out for him by saying, &#8216;If you, an Austrian, had a baby with a Taiwanese woman, the result would be me!’”</p>
<div id="attachment_4034" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4034" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4034 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-650x488.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(6)" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4034" class="wp-caption-text">Christina&#8217;s 3rd Birthday in Los Angeles, California</p></div>
<p>This phenomenon isn’t limited to Vienna. In Japan, a newly crowned biracial beauty queen has been fielding questions on a regular basis about what parts of her are “Japanese”. <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/30/world/asia/biracial-beauty-queen-strives-for-change-in-mono-ethnic-japan.html">“But I am a Japanese,”</a> is her response. On the other side of the world, in the US, Rachel Dolezal was recently exposed for her elaborate deception as a Black woman – a &#8220;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/18/opinion/charles-blow-the-delusions-of-dolezal.html?smid=fb-share">one-directional privilege</a>&#8221; that could never have been successful the other way around, due to socially constructed perceptions of race. The recurring theme? If you are one drop of minority, we will question your Belonging to the majority.</p>
<p>Christina acknowledges that even she is not immune to societal attitudes about migrants in Austria. &#8220;I&#8217;ve learned that, in Austria, migrants get classified into &#8216;good&#8217; and &#8216;bad&#8217;,&#8221; she explains.</p>
<p>&#8220;Asians are considered ‘good’ because they’re quiet, stay out of trouble, and work hard. Turkish people are unpopular because a lot of them refuse to adapt to the Austrian way of life and bring hordes of family members over, all the while claiming benefits from the Austrian government. Blacks have it the worst, though, probably because they stand out the most and are still viewed by many locals as low-lifes and drug dealers.&#8221;</p>
<div id="attachment_4029" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4029" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4029 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-650x472.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(1)" width="650" height="472" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-650x472.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-300x218.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4029" class="wp-caption-text">Christina riding a (fake) bull at Glacier National Park, Montana</p></div>
<p>While Christina is well aware that the US has its own challenges regarding diversity, she does view it as more progressive: “In the US, people at least get it when you tell them that you&#8217;re biracial.”</p>
<p>It was 1999 when Christina was last in the US, before Illy&#8217;s birth and before the 9/11 attacks. While she’s now seriously considering a move back, it&#8217;s unclear when she will be able to. Christina is not a US citizen and needs a green card. Her most recent attempt at the <a href="http://travel.state.gov/content/visas/english/immigrate/diversity-visa/instructions.html">Diversity Visa Lottery</a> was unsuccessful. “My dad told me he is reconsidering becoming an American citizen just so that he can help get us over there,” Christina recently shared. <a href="http://www.migrationpolicy.org/article/family-reunification">Family reunification</a> is one of the four major pathways for foreigners to become legal residents of the US.</p>
<p>Legal challenges are also not Christina’s only concern. “Sometimes I worry that people in the US will annoy me with their ignorance,” she says laughing. At the same time, she is drawn to the lifestyle. She observes her American friends move to houses with pools, which, compared to Viennese city apartments, seem like mansions. Illy, a recovering Justin Bieber addict who recently graduated to a One Direction obsession, is thrilled with the prospect. “A typical Austrian teenager,” Christina chuckles.</p>
<p>You could call Christina many things: A transnational, an immigrant, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">a third-culture kid</a>, a foreigner, a native, an expat. But none of these categories really fit given the fluidity of her upbringing and identity. We use labels to establish connections and try to make sense of things, but they can also dilute the intricacy and beauty of reality.</p>
<p>&#8220;I&#8217;m not 100% of anything,&#8221; is how Christina describes it. &#8220;Sometimes when people ask what I am, I just answer that I&#8217;m a human being.&#8221;</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Photos provided by Christina and Sophia.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Berlin needs you (but why?)</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/04/review-berlin-needs-you-but-why/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/04/review-berlin-needs-you-but-why/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2014 08:20:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2702</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Why is immigration important? The debate takes many angles. There's the demographic argument, that developed countries with low birth rates and aging populations need bodies to maintain the replacement rate. There's the globalization take, that the movement of people in all forms is increasingly inevitable and contributes to global competitiveness and 21st century skills. The moral or even religious spin, emphasizing human dignity, charity, an obligation for prosperous nations to help those more needy. But few arguments are as pervasive as the economic one...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_2738" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdad.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2738" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2738 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad.jpg?w=640" alt="" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad-300x199.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2738" class="wp-caption-text">©Barbara Dietl</p></div>
<p>Why is immigration important? The debate takes many angles. There&#8217;s the <a href="http://www.thelocal.de/20131126/germany-needs-more-immigration">demographic argument</a>, that developed countries with low birth rates and aging populations need bodies to maintain the replacement rate. There&#8217;s the globalization take, that the movement of people in all forms is increasingly inevitable and contributes to global competitiveness and 21st century skills. The moral or even religious spin, emphasizing human dignity, charity, and an obligation for prosperous nations to help those more needy. Yet few arguments are as pervasive as the economic one: that immigrants fill labor shortages, tend to be more innovative, start businesses and create jobs, pay taxes, and contribute to the social welfare net (yes, often more than they &#8220;take away&#8221;).</p>
<p>It is this economic argument that is often relied upon as a point of mutual agreement that immigrants are needed. Maybe not <a href="http://www.dw.de/opinion-foreigners-welcome-sort-of/a-17651819">“wanted”</a>, but at least needed.</p>
<p>This argument extends beyond newcomers to the 2nd and 3rd generations. In countries like Germany where the history of immigration has been primarily low skilled, children of migrants still face numerous linguistic, cultural, and socioeconomic challenges. These are exacerbated by a stratified education system that is associated with lower educational attainment, limited access to higher education, and fewer chances for economic mobility. Germany fares particularly poorly in this arena: it has the <a href="http://www.oecd.org/general/oecdeducationsystemsleavemanyimmigrantchildrenflounderingreportshows.htm">OECD&#8217;s largest performance disparity</a> between native and immigrant students and is one of the only countries where 2nd generation students perform worse on international assessments than the 1st generation.</p>
<p>Enter <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> (Berlin needs you!), a program that works to improve the educational and economic outcomes of students with migrant backgrounds. Launched by the state of Berlin as part of its overall integration plan in 2006, it aims to increase the number of these students entering the public sector by 25% by bridging schools with the professional world. It is coordinated by BQN, <em>das Berufliche Qualifizierungsnetzwerk für Migrantinnen und Migranten in Berlin</em> (the Vocational Qualification Network for Immigrants in Berlin) and is funded by the state of Berlin.</p>
<p><iframe title="Berlin braucht dich! - Diverse Wege in die Arbeitswelt" width="650" height="366" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fwBxQu93g3o?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>The program works in cycles: a day-long introduction to a business or organization for 7th graders, a week-long internship for 8th graders, 3-week internships for 9th graders, and training and application days for 10th graders. Participating schools help their students find training spots with an online matching tool. Spots are currently offered in Berlin&#8217;s public sector, public companies, and the metal and electrical industries, though BQN is working toward expanding the program to include small businesses. The program has also evolved from a focus on the vocational training system (<em>Duales System</em> &#8211; working and learning in a company) to more dual study opportunities <em>(Duales Studium</em> &#8211; studying and working simultaneously).</p>
<p>Mitri Sirin, a German TV reporter of Turkish-Syrian background, moderates the 5th <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> consortium meeting in June. He highlights the culture of low expectations and need for more varied training opportunities for migrant students during a panel on diversity politics.<em> The idea that any kid in the 7th grade would know what they wanted to be when they grow up is a fairy tale,</em> he scoffs. <em>Of course I was funneled into a vocational internship with other kids like me. I was still able to make something or other of myself</em>, he adds to chuckles from the audience,<em> but not all are so lucky.</em></p>
<div id="attachment_2790" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdconsortium.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2790" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2790 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium.jpg?w=640" alt="Berlin braucht dich! Consortium Meeting June 2014" width="640" height="480" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2790" class="wp-caption-text"><em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> Consortium Meeting June 2014 ©BQN Berlin</p></div>
<p>When the panel concludes, a group of giggling students race out from behind the stage to plaster black paper on the windows and switch off the lights. It&#8217;s a bit eerie to be cloaked in darkness with pop music blaring before 11am, but soon enough the black-light theater performance has the audience tapping their feet and grinning widely. While entirely up for interpretation, the images of a ball being passed around between two sets of hands and a student struggling in a white sheet before becoming a colorful butterfly suggests a story-line of transnationalism and diversity.</p>
<p><em>The theater program is</em> <em>a kind of &#8220;empowerment action&#8221;</em>, explains Robert Westermann, PR Manager of Berlin braucht dich! <em>The group comes from one of the 32 schools we cooperate with&#8230; students from this school also take part in our internships. </em></p>
<p>Later that morning, we make sure to join the small workshop where the same students share their experiences. <em>I&#8217;ve been in Germany for 2 years and can&#8217;t speak German that well,</em> <em>but black-light theater is like another language that I can speak to everyone, without having to actually say anything, </em>shares one Iranian girl.  <em>In theater you have to learn to control yourself, but you can also be free</em>, says another. <em>Theater has taught me how to be loud</em>, exclaims a third.</p>
<div id="attachment_2737" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2737" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2737 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht.jpg?w=640" alt="Schule am Schloss students post-performance. Source: Berlin braucht dich!" width="640" height="480" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2737" class="wp-caption-text"><em>Schule am Schloss</em> students take a bow post-performance ©BQN Berlin</p></div>
<p><em>In my view, the most innovative aspect of </em>Berlin braucht dich!<em> is that schools and companies are working together on a constant and sustainable level</em>, describes Robert.<em> This stable network makes it possible to operationalize key ideas around &#8220;intercultural openness&#8221;, by changing structures, processes, and mentalities. </em></p>
<p><em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> has experienced marked success in its 8 years of operation. Since 2006, the ratio of trainees in the public sector with a migration background has been steadily on the rise and by 2009 had doubled to 16.9%. By 2013, every 5th trainee (20.5%) in the public sector and public companies had a migration background.</p>
<p>Yet it is the emphasis on mutually understood and implemented &#8220;intercultural openness&#8221; that implies <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> is about more than Euro signs. In addition to securing a more intercultural workforce through sheer numbers, BQN offers free <a href="http://www.berlin-braucht-dich.de/aktivitaeten/diversity-trainings/">diversity trainings</a> for partner schools and businesses. Migration is acknowledged not only as a reality, but as a key factor that contributes both &#8220;to our quality of life now and the sustainability of our future.&#8221; While the demand for such trainings has been low on the school side, BQN has implemented many with employees from their partner companies.</p>
<div id="attachment_2800" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdstudents.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2800" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2800 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents.jpg?w=640" alt="bbdstudents" width="640" height="480" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2800" class="wp-caption-text">Moderator and TV reporter Mitri Sirin (middle) with theater group students ©BQN Berlin</p></div>
<p>The path to a truly intercultural workforce is still laden with hurdles. Recent studies on Germany show that <a href="http://www.migazin.de/2014/06/02/vorurteil-widerlegt-junge-migranten-nicht-haeufiger-kriminell-als-deutsche-jugendliche/">prejudice</a> and <a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/karriere/studie--mit-tuerkischem-namen-sinken-chancen-auf-ausbildungsmarkt,10808620,26663588.html">hiring discrimination</a> against students with migrant backgrounds is alive and well. Access to higher education and many employment opportunities is entirely off the table, as a disproportionate number &#8211; <a href="http://www.boeckler.de/35923_41774.htm">about half</a> &#8211; of these students are funneled into the lowest vocational school track. As one of the business representatives at the meeting explained to the theater group, <em>If any of you came into an interview at our offices, you would do great. But to get to the interview stage, you would still have to pass the entrance test first, which focuses on German, math, and logic. </em></p>
<p>Challenges such as these require integrated policy approaches. Approaches that distinguish the actors involved and hold them accountable for their roles in changing the structures, norms, and mentalities that fuel these challenges. Approaches that extend beyond just the economic argument and are brave enough to acknowledge everyone&#8217;s role in fostering an intercultural and inclusive society that values the potential of each individual. In short, Berlin doesn&#8217;t just need you. It needs all of us.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>Thank you to Robert Westermann, PR Manager of <em>Berlin braucht dich!, </em>for inviting us to the consortium meeting and providing information for this article.</p>
<p>For more information on <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em>, check out their German website <a href="http://www.berlin-braucht-dich.de/">here</a>. Info in English can be found <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/ewsi/en/practice/details.cfm?ID_ITEMS=13081">here. </a></p>
<p>For another article from us on Berlin based programs for students with migrant backgrounds, click <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/18/rave-education-per-square-kilometer/%20">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/04/review-berlin-needs-you-but-why/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Collidoscope Manifesto</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/22/the-collidoscope-manifesto/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/22/the-collidoscope-manifesto/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[collidoscopeks]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 09:45:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cities]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2395</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A couple months ago, Collidoscope Berlin was invited to write its first guest post for the Global Citizens Initiative - an organization that aims “to build a network of people who see themselves as global citizens and want to build a better world”. Part of the task was to connect what we do here to the significance of borders. “Borders?”, we wondered, unsure how to proceed but mostly questioning why we had never concretely addressed the topic before...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_6374.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2441 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_6374.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_6374" width="640" height="426" /></a></strong></p>
<p><strong>A couple months ago, Collidoscope Berlin was invited to write its first guest post for the <a href="http://us5.campaign-archive2.com/?u=34e2670d2b1df6a04603724fa&amp;id=3a6a8f6948&amp;e=b0926c0e88">Global Citizens Initiative</a> </strong>&#8211; an organization that aims &#8220;to build a network of people who see themselves as global citizens and want to build a better world&#8221;. Part of the task was to connect what we do here to the significance of borders. &#8220;Borders?&#8221;, we wondered, unsure how to proceed but mostly questioning why we had never concretely addressed the topic before. What kind of immigration project doesn&#8217;t discuss borders?</p>
<p>When we launched this project in April of last year, we knew we wanted to do something <em>different </em>related to the topic of<em> difference. </em>We knew of groups that promoted and celebrated cultural and ethnic diversity. We had worked for institutions that research and analyze immigrant integration. Our goal was to do something in between, producing articles and commentary that both told a story and provided facts and context. And we wanted to do this through the lens of one city that, although formed by a unique historical and political context, could perhaps provide lessons for others.</p>
<p><strong>A few days ago, Collidoscope Berlin turned one-year old </strong>&#8211; and as we took the opportunity to reflect back, we realized that not talking about borders was, in fact, making a statement about borders. It wasn&#8217;t that we thought borders were unimportant or that we were advocating their complete erosion. Rather, we were advocating for the idea that every city <span style="letter-spacing: 0;">is home to its very own “collision” of cultures and thus has <em>unique</em> stories about diversity and difference. Through the lens of migration &#8211; the movement and coming together of people &#8211; we believe that we can understand more about what makes &#8216;us&#8217; who we are on the individual, local, and global scales. Through our personal lens of moving and living across borders, we aim to make sense of what defines and shapes the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/26/lens-coming-home/">places we call home</a>, as well as the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/16/lens-going-away/">places we leave</a>. Cities, as a reflection of &#8216;the we&#8217;, are a good place to start.</span></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/cropped-2012-08-22-19-03-431.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-18" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/cropped-2012-08-22-19-03-431.jpg?w=640" alt="cropped-2012-08-22-19-03-431.jpg" width="640" height="221" /></a></p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>The Collidoscope Manifesto </strong></span></p>
<p><em>Originally published as a guest post for the <a href="http://us5.campaign-archive2.com/?u=34e2670d2b1df6a04603724fa&amp;id=3a6a8f6948&amp;e=b0926c0e88">Global Citizens Initiative</a><strong><br />
</strong></em></p>
<p>Individuals are born within borders. On a map, these borders seem relatively arbitrary: meandering lines awkwardly encircling blurbs of land. And yet in our lives, the purpose they are meant to serve is anything but, as borders demarcate political, legal, and bureaucratic spaces, as much as they do geographic ones. For it is not geography &#8211; the land itself &#8211; that keeps us from coming and going. It is our (hu)man-made political systems and governments that determine who is permitted to enter or leave, to immigrate or emigrate, to belong or not to belong.</p>
<p>Despite the presence of these borders, we all make our way across these lines one way or another. Whether through relationships abroad, use of technology, involvement in international groups, or participation in the global economy: our lives are increasingly global and less tied to the borders in which we were born or reside. While this does not automatically make us all global citizens (which necessitates awareness and action), it fosters connections across borders that reinforce the idea of a world community. How can we reconcile this ever-present reality with our understanding of borders and restrictions on an individual’s freedom of movement?</p>
<p>The majority of us – more than ever before &#8211; lives in cities. Thanks largely to migration, modern cities have become microcosms of the global community, home to spectacular cultural, ethnic, and religious diversity. While this “collision” of cultures can pose challenges, it is also a tremendous opportunity for growth and enrichment. If we begin to view our cities’ pockets and spaces of difference as opportunities – becoming more empathetic, inclusive, and participatory in the process – we can begin to realize global values within local communities.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/img_0388.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2577 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719-650x433.jpg" alt="Collidoscope Berlin Manifesto" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/img_0388-e1412857292719.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Berlin, Germany is one example: a city with a long history of attracting those who are “different”, where 1 in every 4 residents is of foreign origin and 138 countries are represented. A city that is undergoing constant transformation, while undertaking the challenge of integrating not only newcomers, but the 2nd and 3rd generations. A city that is brimming with rich diversity and teeming with opportunities. <span style="letter-spacing: 0;">Collidoscope Berlin is a celebration of these stories and opportunities, a conversation-starter, a democratic and inclusive view of the many peoples, spaces, and settings that constitute the modern city. </span></p>
<p><strong>Lessons from Berlin: </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/">Ramadan with Neighbors</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/12/20/happy-weekend-review-an-old-new-christmas-market/">The Thai Park</a>,<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/12/20/happy-weekend-review-an-old-new-christmas-market/"> An Old-New Christmas Market</a></p>
<p><strong>Lessons from Beyond: </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/29/beyond-berlin-the-istanbul-connection/">The Istanbul Connection</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/">The American Northwest</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/03/beyond-berlin-difference-on-the-blessed-isle/">Difference in Sri Lanka </a></p>
<p><strong>What is Multiculturalism? </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/">Diversity &amp; the Big City</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/10/whose-multikulti-is-it-the-elusive-definition-of-multiculturalism/">Whose Multikulti is it?</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/18/happy-weekend-karneval-der-kulturen-carnival-of-cultures/">Carnival of Cultures</a></p>
<p><strong>Our Stories: </strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/16/lens-going-away/">Going Away</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/26/lens-coming-home/">Coming Home</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/29/lens-linsanity-and-linguine/">Linsanity and Linguine</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/25/lens-lamb-on-fridays/">Lamb on Fridays</a></p>
<p><strong>Local Stories:</strong> <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/09/interview-ali-zoe-and-the-gentrification-debate/">Ali &amp; Zoe</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/">Orhan</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/21/lens-warm-nights-are-for-cricket/">Warm Nights are for Cricket</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">Moran &amp; Tommy</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/30/interview-hamid-stardom-and-the-difference-threshold/">Hamid</a></p>
<p><strong>We&#8217;d like to conclude this anniversary post by thanking everyone who has been part of the discussion this past year</strong> &#8211; reading, commenting, critiquing, supporting, following, contributing photos and story ideas and event announcements &#8211; we appreciate it all and look forward to another year of <span class="userContent">diversity, difference, and positive discourse!</span></p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By</em> <em><strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em> <em>and</em> <em><strong>Kelly Miller</strong> </em></p>
<p>First photo by Anna Meister, second photo by Collidoscope Berlin, third photo by <a href="http://jurigottschau.com/">Juri Gottschau</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/22/the-collidoscope-manifesto/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: Difference in the Wet Country</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2014 12:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[provincial]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1986</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For nearly a month this holiday season, I explored the social fabric surrounding my US origins with a German national, who had never before been to the land of plenty. Through the fresh eyes of 'the foreigner', I saw my part of America unfold under a curious and critical lens. America is a country that defines itself by historical narratives of migration and manifest destiny. What one encounters on the road in its northwestern corner, however, is a bit more mundane. At closer glance, emptiness and the prosaic everyday give food for thought, in regards to locating and valuing difference wherever it bubbles up...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>How do you notice difference in a city, in which you yourself are different?</strong></p>
<div id="attachment_1992" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1992" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1992 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-1.jpg" alt="Portland, OR steel-bridge" width="640" height="360" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1992" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>For nearly a month this holiday season, I explored the social fabric surrounding my US origins with a German national, who had never before been to the land of plenty. Through the fresh eyes of &#8216;the foreigner&#8217;, I saw my part of America unfold under a curious and critical lens. Given this blog&#8217;s weekly critical handling of all things multicultural in the big city, why not talk about diversity in an American context? This context proves to be quite different from the aspiring-cosmopolitan intersections of the German capital, as shocking as that may or may not be.</p>
<p>America is a country that defines itself by historical narratives of migration and manifest destiny. What one encounters on the road in its northwestern corner, however, is a bit more mundane. At closer glance, emptiness and the prosaic everyday give food for thought, in regards to locating and valuing difference wherever it bubbles up.</p>
<p><strong>Geography matters</strong></p>
<p>Somehow, when we talk of diversity in society, the role of space therein is a side note. In fact, where we live, work, play, learn, and heal in many ways determines our belonging to or exclusion from social and economic groups that are important in ensuring opportunity.</p>
<p>Maps tell us a lot about how different ways of life can exist cohesively together. Maps may miss, however (<a href="http://www.npr.org/censusmap/#4.00/39.00/-84.00">see NPR&#8217;s US census map</a>), where difference pops up beyond the packed hotbeds for multiculturalism of the city, leaving our eyes to experience what the provinces, the forgotten towns, and the coastal sticks have to offer firsthand.</p>
<div id="attachment_1989" style="width: 311px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1989" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1989 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg" alt="Rebecca Vincent" width="301" height="300" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent.jpg 301w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/rebecca-vincent-300x299.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 301px) 100vw, 301px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1989" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Rebecca Vincent</p></div>
<p>In the Pacific Northwest, like many other regions, cartography shows the urban as an array of ever-revolving grids, residences dotting the margins of concrete webs and precise civil engineering, greenery contained, parks splashed with beige and lived-in browns. One passes through these strange boundaries of growth, as if moving through the trunk of a tree to reach its core, each ring giving way to new densities and shapes of living, suburbia giving way to semi-rural apartment clusters and neatly arranged town homes.</p>
<div id="attachment_2001" style="width: 471px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2001" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2001  " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png?w=640" alt="portland map" width="461" height="347" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map.png 646w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map-300x226.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/portland-map-80x60.png 80w" sizes="(max-width: 461px) 100vw, 461px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2001" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Mappery.com</p></div>
<p>Apart from the patterns and markings of cities, great expanses of forest or farmland separate bundles of life from one another. Beyond the edge of the urban, an emptiness emerges. Where cities end, mountain pass truck-stops, wine-making valleys, flat dairy country, coastal trailer parks, and retired logging towns begin. Vehicles connect what trains used to. Marks on the map created for the movement between these revolving grids begin to surface like geometric occurrences of ink. Here humans somehow ended up, often fairly alone with only the company of a gas station and a corner store.</p>
<div id="attachment_2002" style="width: 476px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2002" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2002   " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png?w=640" alt="oregon map" width="466" height="375" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map.png 749w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map-300x241.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/oregon-map-650x522.png 650w" sizes="(max-width: 466px) 100vw, 466px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2002" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Oregon Office of Rural Health</p></div>
<p>Passing through such places on the road from one side of the state of Oregon to the next, the new set of eyes saw only distance, forged together by oil rigs and spinning tires. <em>Density can be an advantage, when it comes to social and cultural encounters needed for intercultural understandings to take root</em>, I thought, as we searched for a place to eat on a long stretch that seemed to allow only signage, fast food, and campgrounds.</p>
<div id="attachment_1990" style="width: 471px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-2.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1990" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-1990 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/bridge-2.jpg" alt="Portland, OR steel-bridge " width="461" height="614" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1990" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>And yet, the migrant worker shantytown in Southwest Washington, the Korean BBQ embedded in the Tillamook state forest, the sushi bar near Mt. Hood’s base, the taco trucks at truck-stops, the Chinese waiter at the roadside diner all suggest that even in more expansive geographies, difference can occur.</p>
<p><strong>Just because it is there, doesn&#8217;t mean we will notice it</strong></p>
<p>On our way to the valley of the Rogue River, our over-sized vehicle wound down the Pacific Highway, hugging cliffs of the sea and the edges of a strange poverty. We saw mile after mile of rotting cottages, mobile homes made more mobile by landslides, empty villages with the local pub serving bento, tacos, and chowder, and liquor stores the size of the local church beside it. Catholic churches sprouted up in these towns, in the basin of the interstate or at the rim of the sea &#8211; something I did not take notice of at first, but which suggested some shift, an immigration. Those who find ships in the right season or canneries with need for cheaply-bought hands make their way back to the Saints to thank them for their providence, or so it seemed.</p>
<p>In the foggy valleys of dead logging towns, the basin of the interstate, the depressed dairy lands and empty harbors: here the German traveler experienced my part of America with its shady diners where breakfast and hot sauce are served all day, roadside shacks with a For Sale sign, Walmart’s to nowhere. And in between the lines, difference was there, simply glossed over by the mundanity of its appearance, bearing more than John Wayne&#8217;s Americana.</p>
<div id="attachment_1994" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/streeet.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1994" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-1994 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/streeet.jpg?w=640" alt="street Portland, OR" width="640" height="360" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1994" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>The churches that never cease to be obvious and enormous on major highways; the Mexican restaurants with happy signs and plenty of American families digging into re-fried beans and rice, as if it were the national dish; the Japanese restaurants with pictures of majestic mountains that could be local; medical advertisements with black patients and Asian doctors; a South Asian newscaster in a suit just like everybody else; a black reporter stuck to sports on the local news station: these things I may not have noticed without the presence of the new perspective next to me.</p>
<p><strong>It is not about what we say, but about what is heard</strong></p>
<div id="attachment_1991" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/diner-pwf-0066.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1991" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-1991" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/diner-pwf-0066.jpg?w=300" alt="Photo source: Paul Winch-Furness" width="300" height="199" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1991" class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: Paul Winch-Furness</p></div>
<p>For the German&#8217;s second breakfast in America, we took him to a local diner in southwest Washington with the classic booths and red upholstery, simple fried numbers, and a healthy rotation of pies. As he ordered, his slight accent turned the words into mildly different sounds, his tongue pushing just a bit too far back for the &#8216;l&#8217; and the &#8216;th&#8217; sticking to the front of his teeth. The letters may have come together in a way that did not quite fit the frames we have learned to repeat, but one could and can simply understand. And so &#8216;the waffle special&#8217; was transmitted to the kitchen with no questions asked. And after we had told the waitress in her darling little apron that it was his first time in an American diner, she beamed at the foreigner sitting there in front of the simple white dishware and the paper napkin. She whispered to the other waitress, who, blushing, came over to our table to pour coffee and welcome him to town.</p>
<p>It is not about the sounds being right. It is about our understanding them.</p>
<p><strong>Being an outsider can come in handy, as I have learned on the other side of the Atlantic</strong></p>
<p>Growing up in the far corner of the Western United States, I am familiar with the figures and curves of this particular landscape and society. I have, however, sorely taken for granted what it means to have tacos in the middle of nowhere, to celebrate Persian New Year with friends, or to consider Phở as American as bratwurst (I can thank Seattle for that). In many ways, difference was a natural part of my private and public education, the neighborhoods where I lived, the sports teams I played on, and the churches I attended. I cannot say that I have consciously valued these experiences for what I learned from them. If such encounters and relationships had popped up in my Berlin world, I would have celebrated them. This is largely due to the ways in which diversity is or is not celebrated by society at large and how we might attempt to remedy this fact.</p>
<p>But what is most striking and assuredly the take-away from this tale is that campaign-worthy diversity in the big city is not all there is, nor is it of greater value than the outcroppings of difference at truck-stops off the interstate. This might be where it counts the most.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Ethno-cultural diversity is changing the face of the rural United States, including states like Oregon and Washington. For a great visual of this transformation, see the <a href="http://www.ers.usda.gov/media/176091/page7.pdf">United States Department of Agriculture&#8217;s map from its Rural Population and Migration Brieﬁng Room</a>. As the roadside taco trucks and shantytowns demonstrate, a large wave of migration from Latin America to the Pacific Northwest region has characterized rural growth from 2000-2012, according to the <a href="http://www.ers.usda.gov/amber-waves/2011-december/hispanics-contribute-to-increasing-diversity.aspx#.Ut5lnRA1iM8">USDA&#8217;s recent report</a> on demography. Reflective of this shift to the out-country from the urban heart, is the <a href="http://www.oregonlive.com/pacific-northwest-news/index.ssf/2011/04/in_portlands_heart_diversity_dwindles.html">dwindling diversity in the heart of Portland, OR</a>. Difference is, thus, not always where you expect to find it.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/01/21/beyond-berlin-difference-in-the-wet-country/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: With Wings, Roots, and Sweaty Hands</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2013 11:56:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1678</guid>

					<description><![CDATA["Punctual. Exact. Productive. Closed off. Careful. Inflexible. Humorless." And some "Goethe" and "Einstein" thrown in for good measure. Was this really all a group of seemingly well-educated professionals had to say about German identity? No wonder the facilitator had started to draw sad faces on the list...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;">&#8220;Punctual. Exact. Productive. Closed off. Careful. Inflexible. Humorless.&#8221; And some &#8220;Goethe&#8221; and &#8220;Einstein&#8221; thrown in for good measure. Was this really all a group of seemingly well-educated professionals had to say about <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/">German identity</a>? No wonder the facilitator had started to draw sad faces on the list.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/2013-11-08-14-16-29-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1682" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/2013-11-08-14-16-29-1.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-11-08 14.16.29-1" width="640" height="640" /></a></p>
<p><em>My hands get sweaty when I hear this sort of talk</em>, a woman piped up from the front row, a shred of anger in her voice. <em>Is this really all we identify with, as Germans?</em></p>
<p>I shared her frustration. We were over three hours into the &#8220;German Identity and Identities in Germany&#8221; workshop, having already watched a documentary clip and listened to a panel discussion on the nuances of (im)migration, national identity, and belonging. Yet when asked by our facilitator <em>What is German?</em>, all we could come up with were stereotypes or nothing at all. I was in the latter camp, sitting quietly in the corner, scribbling down notes, the occasional eyebrow raise or eye roll gracing my face. An older man on the other side of the room began criticizing globalization and everything &#8220;becoming the same&#8221;, proclaiming that when it comes down to it, identity is tied to region. <em>I have fire in my belly,</em> my friend whispered to me, leaning over. <em>So do I</em>, I thought, but I wasn&#8217;t sure what to do with it. On some level our hybrid-identities felt under attack, as if our <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/26/lens-coming-home/">sense of home</a> tied to people, language, and experience was not as legitimate as one tied to geography. As if we weren&#8217;t quite part of the discussion in the same way as the others.</p>
<div id="attachment_1683" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/2013-11-08-15-31-39-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1683" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-1683" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/2013-11-08-15-31-39-1.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-11-08 15.31.39-1" width="640" height="640" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1683" class="wp-caption-text">Making friends at the workshop</p></div>
<p>I was surprised at myself. For years I&#8217;d been navigating a slew of cultures, confidently code-switching, getting by and blending in pretty much anywhere with relative ease and advantage. Dual citizen, trilingual, well-traveled, ethnically ambiguous, international education professional, American-German-Jewish-Algerian mutt. I&#8217;d always felt <em>just different enough</em>, rather than <em>too different</em>. I&#8217;m a pretty ruthless cherry-picker, highlighting a particular part of my background when it suits the moment. <em>My dad&#8217;s Jewish and I went on Birthright</em>, I declare to Israeli airport security. <em>My mom&#8217;s German and I&#8217;m a dual citizen,</em> I respond when asked why I live in Berlin. <em>I&#8217;m part Algerian</em>, I say proudly to a cute Arab-German on a date. <em>I also grew up with two languages and have trouble with German</em>, I share with the Vietnamese girls I tutor. I&#8217;d positioned my international identity as the centerpiece of my life a long time ago, letting it guide me both personally and professionally. Perhaps it&#8217;s self-serving or even greedy, but it&#8217;s always felt like my choice.</p>
<p>Others have their choice ripped from them with one ostensibly innocent question: &#8220;<strong>But where are you from from?&#8221; </strong><em><strong>Wo kommst du wirklich her? </strong></em>Translation: &#8220;You must come from somewhere other than here, because you look/sound/pray/move/eat/celebrate differently than <em>we</em> do.&#8221; The plight of the &#8220;<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DWynJkN5HbQ">perpetual foreigner</a>&#8220;.</p>
<p>During my past two years in Berlin I&#8217;d started to get a little taste of what that felt like, an after-taste really. <em>No, I&#8217;m not Spanish</em>, I find myself saying at least once a week to those who wonder out-loud or even just start speaking to me in Spanish. I get it, there are an increasing number of Spaniards in Berlin (and Germany). I get it, I have darker features. But whereas I would normally enjoy talking about my background, I now find myself getting irritated and defensive having to explain myself against a recurrent assumption.</p>
<p><em>&#8220;People always ask how my German is so good. I tell them I&#8217;ll try to speak worse German from now on,&#8221; a Vietnamese immigrant says ironically in his studio.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>&#8220;I know people expect me to be a certain way, or have ideas about what type of person I am, of what I&#8217;m capable of, based on how I look,&#8221; a young Eritrean girl ponders at the window.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>&#8220;I&#8217;m not really Turkish, and I&#8217;m not really German. I identify as a Turkish-German, which is something else,&#8221; reflects a woman from her apartment.<br />
</em></p>
<p>[paraphrased quotes from the &#8220;with WINGS and ROOTS&#8221; documentary]</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/withwingsandroots_reimaginebelonging_website_small.png"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1709" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/withwingsandroots_reimaginebelonging_website_small.png?w=640" alt="withWINGSandROOTS_reimagineBelonging_website_small" width="640" height="344" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/withwingsandroots_reimaginebelonging_website_small.png 720w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/withwingsandroots_reimaginebelonging_website_small-300x161.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/withwingsandroots_reimaginebelonging_website_small-650x349.png 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.withwingsandroots.com/">Source</a></p>
<p>While the woman with the sweaty hands was perhaps frustrated by the selection of adjectives on the list, I realized I was worked up about why there had to be a list at all. For the first time in two years in Berlin, I not only wondered, but cared, whether the others in the room considered me German. Or even German enough.</p>
<p><em>I grew up with German culture, speak the language, have the passport, and now live here</em>, I finally summoned up the courage and coherence to say. <em>But I&#8217;m only one fourth German &#8220;ethnically&#8221;. I know people back in the US who have more German blood than I but have no connection to the country, language, people, history. I don&#8217;t fit everything on that list, but neither do any of you.<br />
</em></p>
<p>Identity is a social construction, I wanted to go on. A fluid and on-going process on both the individual and national level. Increased levels of migration and diversity often spark an instinct to distinguish, retreat, and protect- on both the &#8220;native&#8221; and &#8220;(im)migrant&#8221; sides. But it&#8217;s also an opportunity to reflect, learn, and reinvent. By the end of the workshop, we were getting there.</p>
<p><em>What is your vision for a modern perception of &#8220;Germanness&#8221;?</em> the facilitator prompted us.</p>
<p>&#8220;Being open. Intercultural understanding from authorities. Focusing on plurality. Promoting language proficiency. Fostering awareness. Accepting (not only tolerating) others. Self-reflection.&#8221;</p>
<p>A list of adjectives can only put us into a box. A list of actions lets us move forward.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>How serendipitous: a fantastic article on the same topic just came out in Spiegel. Read <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/essay-on-racism-growing-up-turkish-in-germany-a-932154.html">here</a> about one woman&#8217;s reality of growing up as a third-generation Turkish-German in Hamburg and being asked about everything from circumcision, staying out late, and being a &#8220;different Turk&#8221;. </em></p>
<p><em>The documentary clip we watched is from &#8220;with WINGS and ROOTS&#8221; that juxtaposes the realities of (im)migrant life, national identity, and belonging in Berlin and New York City. You can watch the trailer <a href="http://www.withwingsandroots.com/video/trailer">here</a> and <strong>support the project <a href="http://www.withwingsandroots.com/get-involved/donate">here</a></strong><strong>.</strong> According to representatives from the film at the workshop there will be new ways of getting involved in January, so stay tuned! </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Multiculturalism, Diversity, and the Big City</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2013 18:48:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kreuzberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1358</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[With my back to them at the street-side café I felt like a judge on "<a href="http://www.nbc.com/the-voice/">The Voice</a>", straining my neck for any hint of where they were from or what they looked like, resisting the urge to swirl around and start dancing on my chair. Truth be told my ears had perked up as soon as the trio plopped down at the table behind me, switching between topics like gentrification in Kreuzberg and the cultural difference between <em>Kaffee</em> and "coffee" as quickly as they were switching between German and English...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/photo-1-2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/photo-1-2.jpg" alt="photo-1 (2)" width="640" height="640" /></a></p>
<p>With my back to them at the street-side café I felt like a judge on &#8220;<a href="http://www.nbc.com/the-voice/">The Voice</a>&#8220;, straining my neck for any hint of where they were from or what they looked like, resisting the urge to swirl around and start dancing on my chair. Truth be told my ears had perked up as soon as the trio plopped down at the table behind me, switching between topics like gentrification in Kreuzberg and the cultural difference between <em>Kaffee</em> and &#8220;coffee&#8221; as quickly as they were switching between German and English.</p>
<p>Voice #1: &#8220;I speak differently when I speak to you, or to Brits, or to other Americans. I’m speaking much slower right now and I explain things differently.&#8221; <em> Aha! A fellow American. Is she a teacher? Is this a language class? </em><em>&#8220;</em>Wait, were you just speaking in English or German?&#8221; <em>Hmm, maybe not a teacher. Did she also grow up with both languages? Is that a slight accent I detect? </em></p>
<p>Voice #2: &#8220;My name, Uyen&#8230; well for us the middle name is actually the main name, the name before that is just to make the name more beautiful. And my last name is unique, a combination of my mother&#8217;s and father&#8217;s names. Even my sisters don&#8217;t have it because the province where I was born doesn&#8217;t have the same rules like they do here.&#8221; &#8216;<em>Uyen&#8217;&#8230; is that Vietnamese? Germany has <a href="http://www.germany.info/Vertretung/usa/en/05__Legal/02__Directory__Services/04__Family__Matters/__Name.html">laws</a> about children&#8217;s names.. maybe she was born in Vietnam and then her family moved to Germany and her sisters were born here?</em></p>
<p>Voice #3: &#8220;In another language it&#8217;s always different, the, the&#8230; how do you say <em>Betonung auf Englisch</em>?&#8221; <em>The others are struggling to find the translation, should I interject&#8230;? No that&#8217;d be rude, though maybe they&#8217;d appreciate the&#8230;</em></p>
<p>SLAM! Down went my button and I whirled around.</p>
<p>&#8220;Emphasis!&#8221; I yelped, nearly toppling over on the cobblestones. &#8220;Sorry&#8230; for, uh, listening in on your conversation,&#8221; I continued a bit sheepishly, trying to redeem myself, &#8220;It was just really interesting!&#8221;</p>
<p>Lucky for me they were not only open to the vocabulary assistance but also for a chat with the lady who&#8217;d been shamelessly eavesdropping on them (and typing up parts of their conversation, they&#8217;d later learn).  Ten minutes later it was clear that while my sleuthing wasn&#8217;t entirely off the mark, it wasn&#8217;t the whole picture either. Voice #1 belonged to Lea: originally born in Serbia but living in the US for most of her life, currently pursuing a Master&#8217;s degree in Social Work in Boston, but had spent a few years of her upbringing in Germany. Her German, just like mine, was fluent and <em>almost</em> accent free but peppered by the occasional grammar mistake or forgotten vocabulary word. Voice #2 was Uyen: Vietnamese-German (or <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">German-Vietnamese</a>) as I suspected. Born in Vietnam, grew up in Berlin, also currently studying. And Voice #3 was Nicole&#8217;s: A German also working toward her degree in Social Work. The three were in a class together but it wasn&#8217;t a language one. Instead they were enrolled in an international summer course called &#8220;Diversity in the Big City&#8221;. A course focused on diversity in urban environments for those working in social professions and partly financed by the Federal Foreign Office in cooperation with the DAAD, Germany&#8217;s Academic Exchange Service. The course examines diversity through four lenses: social participation, social structure and urban development, migration and integration, and education.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-22-16-28-54.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-22-16-28-54.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-08-22 16.28.54" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>This is one of those moments I wish Chancellor Angela Merkel had been around to see. Not that I think about Merkel all that often or necessarily consider her a fun café partner, but it would&#8217;ve been satisfying to show the politician who proclaimed that &#8220;<a href="http://www.thenewamerican.com/world-news/europe/item/8685-sarkozy-joins-cameron-merkel-condemns-multiculturalism">multiculturalism has utterly failed</a>&#8221; this positive example of multiculturalism in the everyday.</p>
<p>And there we go again with one of our favorite words, &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221;. If we were so inclined, we could spend this whole damn blog analyzing that term. We wouldn&#8217;t mind so much actually &#8211; Kelly can&#8217;t even use the term &#8220;culture&#8221; without first defining it and I could happily talk your ears off about the relationship between cultural capital and educational achievement. Thankfully we&#8217;re savvy enough to realize it wouldn&#8217;t make things very fun for all of you. <em>Or would it?</em> No, of course it wouldn&#8217;t. Moving on. But write us if it might.</p>
<p>To be fair, it&#8217;s pretty near impossible to create a definitive understanding of &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221;.  The word&#8217;s become increasingly loaded as countries face burgeoning levels of immigration and struggle to incorporate diverse populations within their borders. In turn it&#8217;s dissected by academics, used strategically to shape policy, and tossed around in the everyday. It&#8217;s elusive and as some like to call it, a &#8220;moving target&#8221;. Kelly hit the nail on the head in one of <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/10/whose-multikulti-is-it-the-elusive-definition-of-multiculturalism/">her posts</a> and then bolded that nail so you&#8217;d pay attention: &#8220;The various meanings of <em>Multikulti</em> are just as ‘multi’ as the differences the word aims to describe&#8221;<strong>.</strong></p>
<p>I think we can start by agreeing that there is a stark difference between <em>saying</em> you&#8217;re something and actually <em>doing</em> something. Sociology Professor and Harvard PhD Irene Bloemraad has packaged this difference into a neat little theory called &#8220;symbolic&#8221; vs. &#8220;material&#8221; multiculturalism. In other words, talking the talk vs. walking the walk.</p>
<p>The United States, for example, is all about <em>symbolic multiculturalism</em>. Whichever food related metaphor you prefer &#8211; &#8220;melting pot&#8221;, &#8220;salad bowl&#8221;, or &#8220;ethnic stew&#8221; (yup, people say that) &#8211; the country&#8217;s national identity is forever tied to immigration and diversity. Yet as Bloemraad rightly points out, the US&#8217;s support of multiculturalism is more social than political: the country <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2NpHwYrIXWY">embraces multiculturalism</a> and individual expression but is not big on providing institutionalized resources toward integration and the political participation of immigrants.</p>
<p><em>Material multiculturalism</em> on the other hand is the government stepping in and addressing immigrant integration in an institutionalized way. Merkel&#8217;s certainly right that Germany is far from being a beacon of multiculturalism, but let&#8217;s not ignore the positive &#8220;material&#8221; work the country has recently embarked on: <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">integration courses</a>, new citizenship laws, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/18/rave-education-per-square-kilometer/">educational initiatives</a>, etc. Lea, Uyen, and Nicole&#8217;s &#8220;Diversity in the Big City&#8221; course is another example of how a small effort can promote multiculturalism both symbolically and materially: creating a space for international students to study diversity is a symbolic acknowledgement that those working in social spheres should gain this perspective. Funding these courses through the government is a material backing of this acknowledgement.</p>
<p>Much work still needs to be done, and I&#8217;m the first to acknowledge that four highly educated women chatting diversity over cappuccinos is a far cry from the challenges many other groups face in regards to integration. But whatever &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221; is, may, or should be, it hasn&#8217;t failed. It&#8217;s a symbolic and material work in progress. <em>Our</em> work in progress.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The adorable café pictured above is called</em> <a href="http://www.schoenescafe.de/">schönes café</a> <em>and is located in Kreuzberg&#8217;s Graefekiez. For more information on the &#8220;Diversity in the Big City&#8221; course and others run by DAAD, click <a href="https://www.daad.de/deutschland/studienangebote/sommerkurse/en/?ipp=50&amp;seite=1&amp;sk_akademie=0&amp;skchapter=0&amp;skduration=0&amp;skenter=&amp;skid=841&amp;sksubject=12&amp;skterm=&amp;sktown=&amp;stipendiate=0">here</a>. </em></p>
<p>Non-professional photos by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reviewing the Rave: &#8220;We are the We&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/13/reviewing-the-rave-we-are-the-we/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 21:04:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1269</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We're so used to talking all the time that words tend to lose their effect. Especially when the talking is predominantly happening in one direction, as it so often does in immigration discourse. The <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/02/rave-i-am-not-a-terrorist/">Migrantas</a> organization is unleashing an alternate voice within immigrant women in Germany that is arguably just as powerful: their artistic creativity...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/1085152_547637008637523_1494864328_o.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-1277 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/1085152_547637008637523_1494864328_o.jpg?w=640" alt="1085152_547637008637523_1494864328_o" width="640" height="426" /></a></p>
<p>We&#8217;re so used to talking all the time that words tend to lose their effect. Especially when the talking is predominantly happening in one direction, as it so often does in immigration discourse. The <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/02/rave-i-am-not-a-terrorist/">Migrantas</a> organization is unleashing an alternate voice within immigrant women in Germany that is arguably just as powerful: their artistic creativity. Simple pencil and paper sketches are transformed into pictograms by the Migrantas artists, then shared with the city on billboards, postcards, and public transit. The finished products don&#8217;t utter a sound but are easily worth more than a thousand words.</p>
<p>This past April, Kelly and I participated in one of a series of <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/02/rave-i-am-not-a-terrorist/">Migrantas workshops</a> in Berlin. Though the two of us pretty much <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/about/">live and breathe immigration</a>, we were surprised how much there was left to reflect upon, namely our own migration experiences. For over two hours, we scribbled alongside five other participants in the very fitting <em>Haus der Kulturen der Welt</em> (House of World Cultures), producing a total of 28 sketches for the artists to work with. Our workshop group was younger than average and also more mobile and privileged: we were all well-educated and, except for Kelly, in possession of the highly-coveted EU passport. But the dynamics of integration go far beyond the legal and political. Economically, linguistically, professionally, socially, personally, even romantically&#8230; in one way or another we were all struggling to feel like insiders.  At the same time, we recognized and celebrated the excitement, enrichment, and fulfillment that accompanies the process.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/img_3348.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/img_3348.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_3348" width="640" height="368" /></a><strong>&#8220;Migration = Enrichment&#8221;/&#8221;&#8216;<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">Migrants&#8217; anyway</a>&#8221; <strong>(despite having a German passport)</strong><br />
</strong></p>
<p>This past Friday came the big reveal: we gathered with members of other workshops and the interested public at Berlin&#8217;s <em>Rotes Rathaus</em> for the opening of the exhibit showcasing our work. The exhibit was simple and straightforward, just like the Migrantas concept. A singular stretch of sketches grouped into common themes around accompanying pictograms. No curators, no conjectures, no conclusions. Only an opportunity to see the world through someone else&#8217;s lens and pencil strokes.</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-09-47-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3423" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-09-47-1-650x650.jpg" alt="2013-08-09-20-09-47-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-09-47-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-09-47-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></strong></p>
<p>The biggest take-away for Kelly and me came in how much in common we seemed to have with children of Turkish guest workers, students from Brazil, and grandmothers from Kurdistan. While our migration contexts, freedom of mobility, and future plans certainly vary drastically, our feelings about the integration process were at times strikingly similar. One group of images showed X&#8217;s over a mouth, a knot in a tongue, a speech bubble filled with jibber-jabber, and the phrase &#8220;I&#8217;m not stupid, I&#8217;m just starting to learn German!&#8221;. Where words may have only shown difference, our sketches revealed connection and commonality, finding themselves side-by-side on the board.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-25-01-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3424" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-25-01-1-650x650.jpg" alt="2013-08-09-20-25-01-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-25-01-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-25-01-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><strong>&#8220;Authorities&#8221;. Sketches underneath and to the right of the main pictogram by Kelly.</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/img_3390.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/img_3390.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_3390" width="518" height="518" /></a><strong>&#8220;Job, Effort, Luck, Rejection, Trainee, Intern, Degree, Training&#8221;. Sketch on upper right by Sophia.</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-28-36.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-28-36.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-08-09 20.28.36" width="640" height="480" /></a><strong>&#8220;Language, Communication, Friendship, Feelings, Smile&#8221;</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-24-00-1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3426" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-24-00-1-650x650.jpg" alt="2013-08-09-20-24-00-1" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-24-00-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-24-00-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><strong>&#8220;Heimweh&#8221;/&#8221;Homesickness&#8221;</strong></p>
<p>The points of commonality extended beyond those with migration backgrounds, perhaps one of the most valuable but under-appreciated aspects of the work Migrantas does. As one German presenter shared during her welcome speech, images of twisted tongues and closed mouths transported her back to her first experience abroad in Spain with her family and the frustration and fear she felt about not being able to communicate. &#8220;My mother taught me the term <em>no hablo español</em>, and I noticed that the pronoun was missing. I thought she did it on purpose so that it&#8217;d be really clear I couldn&#8217;t speak the language.&#8221; Immigrants or not, these images deliver the compelling message that we are all individuals, we all have multi-faceted identities, and we have all at some point or another felt different. <em>Wir sind das Wir</em>. We are the we.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3427" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27-650x487.jpg" alt="2013-08-09-20-14-27" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-09-20-14-27.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2migrantas_piktogramm_wir_sind_das_wir_300dpi.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1337" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2migrantas_piktogramm_wir_sind_das_wir_300dpi.jpg?w=640" alt="migrantas_piktogram_wir_sind_das_wir_300dpi" width="589" height="589" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton </strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>Don&#8217;t forget to check out the Migrantas exhibit for yourself at Berlin&#8217;s </em>Rotes Rathaus at <em>Alexanderplatz. Free to the public and open until August 27th. Keep an eye out for upcoming Migrantas workshops and exhibitions around Germany by liking them on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/migrantas/144071052327456">Facebook</a>. Registration is free and open to all with a migration story to the city where they now reside.<br />
</em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">First and last photos by Ruben Gonzalez Escudero/Migrantas; all other photos by Sophia Burton</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Happy Weekend: Toi, Toi, Toi, Thai Park</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/01/happy-weekend-toi-toi-toi-thai-park/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/01/happy-weekend-toi-toi-toi-thai-park/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 17:32:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[food]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thailand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wilmersdorf]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1086</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[During the summer I'm here almost every weekend, inhaling shrimp summer rolls slathered in peanut sauce, papaya salad speckled with red chili, and iced coffee swimming in globs of cloyingly sweet condensed milk. I may meander the colorful rows for food, but my coffee always comes from the same umbrella: Kaffee Oma's...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/france-and-germany-2013-564.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/france-and-germany-2013-564.jpg?w=300" alt="France and Germany 2013-564" width="630" height="442" /></a>A major benefit of living in a city like Berlin is being able to experience its <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/welcome-to-collidoscope/">collision of cultures</a> on an everyday basis. It&#8217;s not everywhere that I can take the Vietnamese twins I tutor to a British café for tea and scones on Monday followed by breaking the Ramadan fast with my Tunisian friend at her Turkish boyfriend&#8217;s home on Tuesday.  Collision in this sense doesn&#8217;t have anything to do with a clash. <strong>It has everything to do with opportunity</strong>.</p>
<p>Another opportunity I take frequent advantage of is the <em>Thaiwiese</em> or Thai Park around the corner from my apartment building in Wilmersdorf. Coined Berlin&#8217;s &#8220;Little Thailand&#8221;, it&#8217;s a park turned semi-legal market where Thai women have been cooking and selling homemade Southeast Asian specialties under umbrellas for almost two decades. During the summer I&#8217;m here almost every weekend, inhaling shrimp summer rolls slathered in peanut sauce, papaya salad speckled with red chili, and iced coffee swimming in globs of cloyingly sweet condensed milk. I may meander the colorful rows for food, but my coffee always comes from the same umbrella: Kaffee Oma&#8217;s.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/france-and-germany-2013-561.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/france-and-germany-2013-561.jpg?w=300" alt="France and Germany 2013-561" width="617" height="410" /></a>Kaffee Oma is the self-appointed &#8220;coffee grandma&#8221; and most vocal vendor I&#8217;ve encountered on the <em>Wiese</em>. In what I&#8217;m not sure is a marking of extreme self-confidence or just limited language proficiency, Kaffee Oma almost exclusively refers to herself in the third person in an endearing mix of German and English. &#8220;Kaffee Oma in Berlin since 29 Jahren,&#8221; she tells me when I ask when she moved from Sukhothai, her home town in Thailand. &#8220;Sukhothai, they say it das Ende der Norden&#8221; she explains, pointing to an invisible map in the air.</p>
<p>Kaffee Oma&#8217;s math doesn&#8217;t always add up &#8211; in Berlin for 29 years, retired for 16, working in the Thai Park every day for 23  &#8211; but it&#8217;s all part of her charm. The same charm that elected her park liaison to the <em>Ordnungsamt, </em>Germany&#8217;s most &#8220;German&#8221; of bureaus in charge of order and regulations. Though the vendors don&#8217;t have official licenses, they are allowed to continue their activities under the watchful eye of these dark blue uniformed bureaucrats. Kaffee Oma says she&#8217;s the &#8220;Big Mouth&#8221; of the Park (because what&#8217;s one more self-proclaimed nickname?), regularly sampling the food to maintain quality and organizing meetings with other vendors about pricing and cleaning. You&#8217;ll notice a plate of <em>pad thai</em> will run you the same 5 Euro from one end of the umbrella row to the other. At the end of the day, trash bags are passed out. Not a strip of trash or papaya is to be found come morning.</p>
<div style="width: 371px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/france-and-germany-2013-550.jpg"><img loading="lazy" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/france-and-germany-2013-550.jpg?w=198" alt="France and Germany 2013-550" width="361" height="549" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Kaffee Oma</p></div>
<p>There are almost 6,000 Thai nationals living in Berlin, a number that doesn&#8217;t include those of Thai origin who have been naturalized as German citizens. While many Vietnamese were recruited to East Germany during the &#8217;60s and &#8217;70s as guest workers by the GDR government, the influx of Thai immigrants mostly began after the Wall came down in the early 1990s. Immigration from Thailand to Germany has been predominantly female, with many initially coming to work as <em>au pairs</em> and nurses. Kaffee Oma is one of many who married a German and made Berlin her home, though she still makes yearly trips back to her other home.</p>
<p>The Thai Park itself has become about more than Berlin&#8217;s Thai community. &#8220;Do a lot of Chinese people come here?&#8221; asked my cousin&#8217;s boyfriend during their visit after recognizing some Mandarin chatter nearby. Before I could properly turn around, I heard English, German, and Thai coming from the same general direction. Everyday the park is rife with nationalities, languages, and multi-ethnic couples and families. The park is not just &#8220;Little Thailand&#8221;: parallel society or ethnic enclave. It&#8217;s an emblem of integration that extends beyond food, beyond Berlin, and even beyond Thailand. A place to enjoy melting pots of culture and curry.</p>
<p>You could go to the Thai Park any weekend &#8211; and I strongly encourage you do so &#8211; but this coming Saturday is particularly special. <strong>The Thai Youth Orchestra &#8211; <a href="http://thaiembassy.de/de/activities-events/activities-news/593-thai-jugendorchester-siam-sinfonietta-am-3-august-im-preussenpark-berlin">Siam Sinfonietta</a> &#8211; will be performing a free open-air concert on August 3 at 18:00.</strong> Come for the music, come for the food, come for Kaffee Oma.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Contrary to popular belief, the Thai Park is open everyday during the warmer months, though the number of vendors does increase greatly on weekends.</em> <em>The park&#8217;s official name is </em>Preußenpark<em> and can be found between U-Fehrbelliner Platz and U-Konstanzerstrasse in Wilmersdorf. </em></p>
<p>All photos: Greg May</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/01/happy-weekend-toi-toi-toi-thai-park/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Whose Multikulti is it? The elusive definition of Multiculturalism</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/10/whose-multikulti-is-it-the-elusive-definition-of-multiculturalism/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2013 21:24:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=985</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The various meanings of the German word <em>Multikulti </em>are just as 'multi' as the differences the word aims to describe. Take the <em>Multikulti </em>breakfast, for example. Apparently, a "<em>Multikulti</em> breakfast" is eating Vegemite with maple syrup. Or is it? ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: justify;">If you put the German word <em>Multikulti* (</em>translated as &#8216;multicultural&#8217;, though it means much more) into Google Images, the many different representations, interpretations, and applications of the word appear in the humorous montage only the inter-webs can produce. Children with varying skin tones and hair textures playing together, ethnically diverse adults holding hands on a lawn, differently colored chess pieces dotting a globe, or &#8211; my favorite &#8211; a cartoon depiction of <em>Multikulti</em> individuals against a backdrop of the percentages of <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/"><em>Menschen mit</em> <em>Migrationshintergrund,</em></a> individuals with migration background, in large cities in Germany. A rosy-cheeked Muslim, a brown boy with a German flag, and&#8230;a strange child with a large gold necklace? <strong>The various meanings of <em>Multikulti </em>are just as &#8216;multi&#8217; as the differences the word aims to describe.</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://www.duesseldorf-blog.de/"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://www.duesseldorf-blog.de/wp-content/uploads/2009/01/integration.jpg" alt="" width="397" height="320" /></a></p>
<p><strong>the Public</strong></p>
<p>On the streets of Berlin, in the local paper, in the city&#8217;s stuffy Metro cars the picture isn&#8217;t any clearer. A sign reading &#8220;Multikulti party catering&#8221;  swings from a Senegalese food cart at the Bergmannstraßenfest. Heaps of thickly-sliced fried plantains with Cocktail sauce. &#8220;Multikulti in Schöneberg&#8221; headlines a newspaper article on real estate development. Dark-haired children frolicking on a sidewalk with no blonde-haired children in sight. &#8220;Multikulti shop&#8221; describes a place where one can find &#8216;party hats&#8217; and exotic party favors, as told from an elderly woman on the U-7. &#8220;Multikulti has absolutely failed&#8221; smeared across the room in the Chancellorin&#8217;s <a href="http://www.sueddeutsche.de/politik/integration-seehofer-sieben-punkte-plan-gegen-zuwanderung-1.1012736">speech</a>. Words planted within an integration discourse just learning to deal with real, long-lasting immigration, rather than the comings and goings of guest-workers.</p>
<p>In the airwaves of Berlin the word <em>Multikulti</em> is used as one might use &#8220;diversity&#8221;, even as one might simply say &#8220;different&#8221; or &#8220;differences&#8221;. <strong>It is sometimes used without comment or value-judgment. It is sometimes used to draw  lines in the sand between <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">integration</a> &#8211; read assimilation &#8211; and segregation &#8211; read parallel societies &#8211; as if any process were ever so clear and immediate.</strong> But when is such a word political and when does it <em>just</em> mean &#8216;different&#8217;?</p>
<p>Take the <em>Multikulti </em>breakfast, for example. A &#8220;<em>Multikulti</em> breakfast&#8221; is eating Vegemite with maple syrup, apparently. Simply put: something a little different from somewhere a little further than Cologne, Munich, or even Rostock, could be <em>Multikulti.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.morgengold.de/live/"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://www.morgengold.de/live/digitalAssets/125/125059_illu_multikulti_l.gif" alt="" width="536" height="225" /></a></p>
<p><strong>the Personal</strong></p>
<p>I spoke to a friend with whom I study sociocultural anthropology here in Berlin about what the word <em>Multikulti</em> means to him. He is young, German, gay, well-educated, well-traveled, and &#8216;anthropologically curious&#8217; (i.e. we love to deconstruct words like &#8216;culture&#8217;, making this whole piece quite a challenge in and of itself). He lives in the African Viertel in Wedding (my old stomping grounds) and spends quite a bit of time in <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/">Neukölln</a> &#8211; the district branded with <em>Multikulti </em>as both claim-to-fame and <a href="http://www.stern.de/tv/sterntv/heinz-buschkowsky-multikulti-ist-gescheitert-1906880.html">scandal</a>.</p>
<p><em>Close your eyes and think of </em>Multikulti. <em>Now open them. What do you see</em>? I was hoping that such an exercise would work a little bit like Google Images, assembling a lovely decoupage of different ideas and popular motifs with the speed of a mouse-click. <em>I just think of Multivitaminsaft</em><em>, </em>multivitamin juice<em>.</em> <em>It just sounds like putting together a bunch of different pieces</em>, then branding the whole jar with a catch-all phrase for society&#8217;s use. <em>Do you see </em>Multikulti<em> in Wedding? </em>I ask. Wedding has a high and growing number of non-German residents, in terms of both citizenship and place of birth. <em>No, because it just exists. So, I wouldn&#8217;t call it Multikulti per say. <strong>It isn&#8217;t hyped up yet, like it is in Neukölln.</strong> <strong>Since everyone is moving to Neukölln, it&#8217;s become </strong></em><strong>Multikulti<em>. </em><em>I also just think of <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/18/happy-weekend-karneval-der-kulturen-carnival-of-cultures/">Karneval der Kulturen</a>. </em></strong><em>Packaged things&#8230;</em>Packaged diversity, rather than the real stuff, which doesn&#8217;t need external PR.</p>
<p><em>Multikulti</em>: the catch-all black-box term for dealing with difference. Its meaning depends on whose mouth delivers it, which  spaces enclose it (or don&#8217;t), and in which situation such a word is flung into the public or personal realm. And that is just the tip of the Vegemite-syrup-breakfast sandwich.</p>
<p>Understanding <em>Multikulti </em>is situational, buried in context and everyday life. <strong>It is a filler word, one to be picked up and laid down in places where our language fails at getting at complexities of urban encounters and differences, at challenging and playful <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/welcome-to-collidoscope/">collisions</a>.</strong> Before any more political discussions continue as to whether Berlin as a city will &#8220;fail&#8221; because of its <em>Multikulti</em> character, perhaps we should confirm just exactly what this <em>Multikulti is</em> to us, to voters, to residents, to admirers, to little children appearing in articles for or against a concept they may have never even heard of. This is a concept, <em>Multikulti</em> and multiculturalism, which, as our societies embrace difference as more the norm than the exception, might become irrelevant.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.eltern.de/kleinkind/erziehung/multikulti.html"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://s1.eltern.de/thumbnails/0001/00000000001/02/01/400pxx300px/0201a2c51441606763fa18b32f8ddd0auniqueidkindergarten_multikulti.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="300" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>*</em>Multikulti<em> is a term in the German language to be found not only in Germany, but in Austria and Switzerland, as well. This piece does not attempt to glorify the practice of &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221; politically or socially, nor does it seek to provide an operational definition for all uses of the term. Multiculturalism, including the more socially-flexible and popular term of </em>Multikulti<em> particularly in Berlin, will never mean one thing to all people. Multiculturalism is, however, often a matter of policy, making it concrete and important for the lives of many &#8211; which begs the question as to the efficacy of shaping society on the basis or in opposition to an elusively undefinable phenomenon. As the above picture illustrates, only through communication between these various poles of whatever </em>Multikulti<em> may be, can policies which are good for everyone be implemented and public discourses celebrating difference passed on.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>For a comprehensive review of the policy side of Multiculturalism in both the Americas and the European Union, see the Migration Policy Institute&#8217;s informative <a href="http://www.duesseldorf-blog.de/">report.</a></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Photo sources: images linked to web source</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
