<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Local Stories &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/category/local-stories/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Women Only: The Frauenraum</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 15:42:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gender]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4385</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I'm at Rathaus Wilmersdorf, a former city hall building turned refugee home in Berlin, where I teach a literacy class once a week. The home initially opened its doors to 178 refugees in September 2015, following Merkel's famous "Wir schaffen das" ("We can do it") declaration that sidestepped the Dublin Regulation and opened up Germany's borders to thousands of asylum seekers.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4394 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-01-27 12.51.04" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>It&#8217;s Thursday at 10:55, and I&#8217;m running late. I rush up to the security guards and hand over my ID. <em>Helfer?</em> (&#8220;volunteer?&#8221;) they ask. <em>Ja</em>, I answer, and wait for them to scribble down my name and give me a number so I can sign out later. I thank them and head inside to the office to sign for the room keys and get my name tag. Then it&#8217;s through the foyer and up three floors to room 3092. When breakfast is running late, the right half of the stairwell is still filled by a neat line of people waiting for their turn in the cafeteria. I squeeze by, ruffling the hair of the kids I recognize.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m at Rathaus Wilmersdorf, a former city hall building turned refugee home in Berlin, where I teach a literacy class once a week. The home initially opened its doors to <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/berlin/bezirke/kudamm/notunterkunft-fuer-fluechtlinge-in-berlin-im-rathaus-wilmersdorf-fehlen-duschen-und-dolmetscher/12199798.html">178 refugees</a> in September 2015, following Merkel&#8217;s famous &#8220;Wir schaffen das&#8221; (&#8220;We can do it&#8221;) declaration that <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/germany/11821822/Germany-drops-EU-rules-to-allow-in-Syrian-refugees.html">sidestepped the Dublin Regulation</a> and opened up Germany&#8217;s borders to thousands of asylum seekers.</p>
<p>Today, over 1400 refugees live in the Rathaus &#8211; mostly from Syria, Afghanistan, and Iraq &#8211; and there is talk of opening up an adjacent building to house an additional 900. As is the case all over the city, this home simply wouldn&#8217;t function without the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/">on-going assistance of volunteers</a> who help out with everything from interpretation and teaching to administrative and kitchen support.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4456 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-01-08 10.34.54" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Over the past eight months, Rathaus Wilmersdorf has become somewhat of a success story as far as refugee accommodations in Berlin go. It&#8217;s been visited by President Joachim Gauck and American actor Ben Stiller, as well as received significant media praise for its leadership and facilities. <a href="http://www.morgenpost.de/berlin/article207089933/Vachroi-verabschiedet-sich-als-Heimleiter-in-Wilmersdorf.html">One article</a> listed off the home&#8217;s impressive amenities, which include medical and midwife services, a laundry room, a hair salon, an internet <span class="st">café</span>, and yes, even our literacy class.</p>
<p>The literacy class, or &#8220;AB class&#8221; as we call it, does go beyond what many other refugee homes in Berlin offer. But what the article&#8217;s authors fail to mention (and are likely unaware of), is that the course comes with a complicated backstory that is indicative of a larger debate surrounding refugees in Germany today.</p>
<p>It all started early this year, after one volunteer noticed that a group of women were not showing up for the German class offered on the home&#8217;s fourth floor. These women were mostly Afghan and the majority also illiterate. However, a bit of digging (and a heavy dose of interpretation) revealed that they weren&#8217;t avoiding the class because the level was too difficult, as originally suspected. They weren&#8217;t going because, in the fourth floor class, there were men present. Or depending on who tells the story, “Because their husbands wouldn’t let them”.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4600 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-05-19 12.43.22" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>The decision was therefore made to start a new class on the third floor, taught and attended exclusively by women. The class was to be an extension of the adjacent <em>Frauenraum</em> or &#8220;women&#8217;s room&#8221;. At Rathaus Wilmersdorf, the <em>Frauenraum</em> is a standing room open almost daily, so long as there are volunteers present. At the refugee home in former Tempelhof airport, the <em>Frauenraum</em> operates on a weekly project basis, led by a volunteer platform called <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">Give Something Back to Berlin</a>.</p>
<p>Regardless of the format, the concept remains the same: The <em>Frauenraum</em> is a safe place where women can be amongst themselves. In Rathaus Wilmersdorf, they sew, practice German, or just hang out and have a cup of tea. Small children are allowed, but men are forbidden from entering. We&#8217;ve even had to throw out a male journalist on occasion. The home&#8217;s former director described it as a place where &#8220;<a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/berlin/warum-thomas-de-vachroi-der-perfekte-aufbauhelfer-fuer-fluechtlingsheime-ist-23775578">female residents are enjoying their freedom and unveiling themselves.</a>&#8221; I can only assume he meant this both literally and figuratively, as not all the women wear headscarves, but some who do do indeed take them off when in the <em>Frauenraum</em> or during class.</p>
<p>I fell into the role of literacy teacher by way of the <em>Frauenraum</em>, where I started volunteering in January. The class was already up and running but they wanted to offer it on more days and were having trouble finding willing teachers. Other <em>Frauenraum</em> volunteers, I was told, had flatly refused to teach out of principle, scoffing at the idea that a separate class be created when there was a perfectly good one already on offer. This is Germany, after all, a country where men and women are presumably equal and interact on all levels of society. If the husbands had a problem with that, tough. Isn&#8217;t it in the best interest of these women that we integrate them into our way of life as quickly as possible?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4460 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-05-12 11.42.50" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>These days, it is difficult to have a discussion in Germany about refugees that doesn&#8217;t include a question about gender. <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/02/08/not-our-women-from-cologne-to-berlin/">Post-Cologne</a>, it is near impossible. Despite the fact that the attacks on New Year&#8217;s Eve were carried out by a more diverse group than originally portrayed in the media, that night&#8217;s unfortunate events have marked a turning point in attitudes towards refugees.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.focus.de/politik/deutschland/zdf-umfrage-offenbart-so-haben-die-silvester-uebergriffe-beeinflusst-was-deutsche-ueber-fluechtlinge-denken_id_5213962.html">One poll</a> showed that, between December 2015 and January 2016 alone, the number of Germans who felt the country couldn&#8217;t handle the influx of refugees rose from 46% to 60%. Thirty-three percent stated that Cologne had &#8220;fundamentally changed&#8221; their opinions about refugees. And the ring-wing <span class="st"><em>Alternative für Deutschland</em></span> (AfD) party, which initially emerged in opposition to the euro, has placed anti-refugee sentiment at the core of their increasingly popular platform. Their leader has controversially <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/alternative-for-germany-shows-its-true-right-wing-colors-a-1076259.html">called for the use of firearms against incoming refugees</a>.</p>
<p>This is the same country that was at the forefront of Europe&#8217;s refugee response only nine months ago. The same country that led the continent&#8217;s discourse on establishing a common European solution. The same country that initiated what became globally lauded as <em>Wilkommenskultur</em> (welcome culture).</p>
<p>So, what&#8217;s changed?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4401 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-650x650.jpg" alt="2016-02-10 11.59.46" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-300x300.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>When the “refugee crisis” hit Germany last summer, hundreds of residents felt compelled to slather butter on rolls and pass them out to refugees arriving at train stations. This was by all accounts heart-warming and admirable, but it was also the easy part. The conversation we are having now is a more complicated one, one that even the seemingly simple question of whether to offer a female-only literacy class echoes:</p>
<p>What happens next and how might our society change as a result?</p>
<p>One could blame Cologne, but the foundation for this confrontation was laid long before. A staggering <a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article147280667/Fuer-die-meisten-gehoert-der-Islam-nicht-zu-Deutschland.html">60% of the country</a> is of the opinion that Islam does not belong in Germany. (It is also worth noting that Germans consistently overestimate the number of Muslims living in the country. The real figure, while one of the highest in the EU, <a href="http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2015/11/17/5-facts-about-the-muslim-population-in-europe/">is still only 5.8%</a>.)</p>
<p>There is an underlying preconception in Germany, as in many Western countries, that Islam is synonymous with misogyny and a lack of female rights. That “<a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article149756193/Wie-Sumtes-Wutbuerger-lernten-Fluechtlinge-zu-lieben.html">according to their religion, women are nothing</a>” or even more extreme, that &#8220;<a href="http://www.vice.com/de/read/fluechtlinge-vergewaltigen-deutsche-kinder-wie-rassisten-versuchen-stimmung-gegen-alle-nicht-deutschen-zu-machen-775">these young men will come and rape our daughters</a>&#8220;. This preconception likely stems from a variety of factors: images we see in the media, politicians portraying Muslims as backward or extremist, or current conflicts within the Middle East. An argument heard less often is made by <a href="http://ideas.time.com/2013/11/01/do-muslim-women-need-saving/">Columbia University Professor Lila Abu-Lughod</a>, who explores the conflation of religion and socioeconomic status. Gender inequality within Muslim majority societies stems mainly from economic inequality, and migrants in Germany have traditionally been low-skilled. Therefore what we may label as clashes due to religion may have stronger roots in poverty and lack of opportunity.</p>
<p>Earlier this year in Berlin, <a href="http://www.rbb-online.de/politik/beitrag/2016/04/berlin-kopftuch-streit-vor-arbeitsgericht-keine-guetliche-einigung.html">a young teacher went to court</a> because she was denied a teaching post due to her headscarf (the case was thrown out on grounds of the state&#8217;s Neutrality Act). More recently in Switzerland, a <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-36382596">regional authority ruled</a> that two teenage brothers must shake the hands of their female teachers despite it being against their religious beliefs to touch women they are not related to. Traditionally receiving societies such as Germany are perpetually learning how to manage integration in the face of growing diversity. Unfortunately, we seem insistent on concentrating on how &#8220;their values&#8221; may threaten &#8220;ours&#8221;, rather than on what type of society we want to live in together.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4406 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-02-17 12.07.15" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>To be fair, my own engagement at the Rathaus has not come without challenges. On my first day teaching, I swallowed a lot of frustration as another volunteer and I watched the women turn to their husbands for approval before following us to class. <em>Nur Frauen</em> (&#8220;only women&#8221;), we tried to communicate to the more skeptical looking of the men with a smile, while I stifled the urge to roll my eyes.</p>
<p>We&#8217;ve also heard a host of disturbing stories by way of the interpreters. Rape, abuse, threats of divorce. Some stories are from Afghanistan while others allegedly took place here in Berlin. At times, I am ashamed to find myself relieved that I can&#8217;t talk to the women directly about what I&#8217;ve heard, for fear it might affect the way I interact with them. For now, our exchanges are limited to topics like telling time and types of fruit &#8211; they&#8217;re big fans of banana and pineapple &#8211; as well as the apparently always shocking and never boring topic of me being a 30 year old woman without a husband or children (some of my students have 6, 7, even 9 children).</p>
<p>But until we&#8217;re able to have those more in-depth conversations, I remain convinced that offering a class under imperfect circumstances is better than offering no women&#8217;s class at all. For what, I&#8217;ve asked myself, will give these women more independence than the ability to navigate the city on their own? And what will give them a better chance of being able to navigate the city on their own than the ability to read and write?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4405 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-04-20 10.14.53" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Nothing exhibited this more clearly to me than a few weeks ago, when we held an arts project week for our women. The week consisted of two trips to separate parks so they could learn about various plant types and practice drawing them. The excitement of the women was palpable. They got to have a Middle Eastern picnic, a real treat after months of bland cafeteria fare. They got to pick flowers in the woods to take back to the home. There was laughing, there was dancing, and there were so many selfies.</p>
<p>We later found out through interpreters that, for several of the women, it was their first time in a park without a husband or male relative.</p>
<p>At the end of the week, a local artist took the womens&#8217; drawings and stenciled them onto power boxes near the Rathaus. On the Friday, we took a stroll around the neighborhood together to see them for the first time. The Farsi-speaking volunteer asked the women to point out their drawings and explain why they chose to draw them specifically. &#8220;Who drew this?&#8221; she asked when we got to the second box, pointing to a beautiful palm tree. &#8220;Me,&#8221; answered one of our students, &#8220;I drew it because it reminds me of home. And if you cut off the head, the whole plant dies.&#8221;</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The Frauenraum at Rathaus Wilmersdorf is looking for volunteers. To get involved, sign up at https://volunteer-planner.org/.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>For another take on the headscarf, I recommend watching <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/video/2015/jun/24/hijab-not-oppression-feminist-statement-video">this Guardian video</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>All photos my own.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: Four Hours at Lageso</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2015 00:01:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bureaucracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moabit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4145</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is Lageso (Das Landesamt für Gesundheit und Soziales), the State Office for Health and Social Affairs. This is Berlin's primary registration center for the initial reception of asylum seekers. This is Germany's most infamous symbol of the refugee crisis. Two days prior I had signed up to volunteer on a website called Volunteer Planner. After a cursory registration process, a click of a button was all it took to commit to a shift at a registration center, refugee home, or other institution in the city where help is needed (read: basically everywhere).  ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4323 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-650x319.png" alt="boys_lageso" width="650" height="319" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-650x319.png 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso-300x147.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/boys_lageso.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>A curly-haired two year old hangs from my hip. His modest number of pounds start to wear on my side as I spin us back and forth in the narrow space. By some stroke of luck he has yet to start crying (this doesn&#8217;t last). He giggles, bouncing up and down, as if we are playing a game. &#8220;He seems to like you,&#8221; a volunteer next to me looks on and smiles, &#8220;almost like he wants to go home with you.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;He may have to,&#8221; I mutter in response. It has been a long ten minutes since I last saw his mother. I try desperately to remember her face &#8211; or at least the color of her headscarf. My voice starts to crack and I realize in horror a cold is coming on (&#8220;Am I infecting hundreds of refugees?&#8221;). A few minutes later we find her, a pair of black shoes in her hands. She holds them up proudly and points to herself. We are only supposed to be finding clothes for her son and she knows it, but I let her take the shoes and boy (now crying), and go.</p>
<p>Curly-haired boy and his mother are my latest charges from the never-ending mass of parents and children waiting to be accompanied down the hallway of donated clothing. This group is only a microcosm of the larger crowd waiting outside in the evening twilight where volunteers pass out hot tea and coffee. Kids get <em>Kinderschokolade </em>and granola bars. The building entrance is guarded to ensure not everyone infiltrates the chaos at once.</p>
<p>Back inside, a winter jacket and pair of warm shoes are the big prizes. Our chief responsibility is to make sure each child walks out with just one of each. I negotiate with parents: &#8220;She can have that coat, but you&#8217;ll need to give me the one she&#8217;s wearing now.&#8221; When language fails, I make a trading gesture with my hands or remove the jacket from the child&#8217;s back myself. How quickly the urge to be generous is superseded by pragmatism (&#8220;Even <em>I</em> could get by with only one coat&#8221;).</p>
<p>&#8220;You have to be careful,&#8221; a middle-aged female volunteer warns me as I re-fold a stack of jeans, &#8220;Roma families sneak in to take clothing and then sell it at the flea market.&#8221; I nod but am at a loss as to what to do with the information. Is she advocating that we start using racial profiling? Regardless of the Roma, some families may have already taken their turn down the hallway. Others could be successfully registered and in possession of their <a href="http://www.euronews.com/2015/09/16/which-european-countries-offer-the-most-social-benefits-to-migrants/">monthly stipend</a>. There&#8217;s really no way to tell.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4321 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_0599" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0599-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Our makeshift shopping strip consists of one narrow hallway and a back room for sorting and storage. On either side of the hallway are smaller rooms the size of coat checks, one holding clothing for adults and the other medicine and hygienic articles. It is very cramped. Fathers plea with volunteers for their family&#8217;s turn down the hallway. Once in, mothers rip clothing off hangers to hold up to their children and approximate size. Some kids are fussy about colors; others peer up with wide eyes and tightly pressed lips. Volunteers buzz by in a flurry of aspired productivity and surveillance, their name-tags as frayed as their nerves.</p>
<p>A cameraman waltzes in with his crew. The bright lens focuses on me as I kneel down to re-velcro a young boy&#8217;s shoes. We have yet to find boots that fit; these blue sandals are the ones in which he arrived to Germany, completely ill-suited for the looming winter. We both turn, squint, and smile anyway. This is the shot they want, and they are gone within the minute.</p>
<p>This is Lageso (<em>Das Landesamt </em><span class="st"><em>für Gesundheit und Soziales)</em>, the State Office for Health and Social Affairs</span>. This is <span class="st">Berlin&#8217;s primary registration center for the initial reception of asylum seekers. This is Germany&#8217;s most infamous symbol of the refugee crisis.</span></p>
<p>Two days prior I had signed up to volunteer on a website called <a href="https://volunteer-planner.org/">Volunteer Planner</a>. After a cursory registration process, a click of a button was all it took to commit to a shift at a registration center, refugee home, or other institution in the city where help is needed (read: basically everywhere).  An impressive resource to get people engaged quickly, though seemingly lacking any accountability for volunteers who fail to show up or for organizations advertising shifts that fall through or no longer exist (the day before I was turned away from a home in Schöneberg because the coordinator was not present).</p>
<p>In addition to locations, one can select specific tasks. This is an all-hands-on-deck scenario and there is something for everyone, from Arabic and Farsi interpretation (in high demand) to kitchen assistance and coffee distribution. At Lageso, I sign up to be a <em>Springer/in </em>or &#8220;Jumper&#8221;, who, according to the website, &#8220;helps wherever is most needed, is assigned to a team, and will be led by hand to their task.&#8221;</p>
<p>But upon arrival I am not assigned to a team nor led anywhere, let alone by hand. After finding a sticker on which to scribble my name, I walk around aimlessly until a smiley blond girl takes pity on me and leads me to the storage room. A few minutes later I am with a new girl who is in a room within this room, sorting through boxes of clothing donations in the dark. I glance at the heaps of dusty sweaters and immediately regret not having brought my allergy medicine.</p>
<p>We start unpacking boxes of blankets. &#8220;Is there somewhere specific we should put these?&#8221; I ask my sorting partner. She shrugs. &#8220;On those shelves, I think,&#8221; she says, pointing to the overstuffed racks behind us. Ten minutes later, another volunteer: &#8220;No, don&#8217;t unpack the blankets,&#8221; he instructs us in a mix of German and English. &#8220;Put them in a corner so we can take them to a refugee home later.&#8221;</p>
<p>I give up on the blankets and turn my attention to the clothes. Thankfully, some boxes are categorized, and I pick up one marked &#8220;children&#8221;. I plan to sort the contents and add them to the shelves, which are loosely organized by gender and size. In one pair of pants I notice a bulge in the pocket and pull out a knife. I pass it along to a guy with a clipboard who looks like he knows what he is doing. He turns and sets it on another shelf, near a box of children&#8217;s toys.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4322 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_0600" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/IMG_0600-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>I&#8217;m finally getting into a groove when another volunteer comes up behind me, visibly frustrated. &#8220;I spent days putting this together and now everyone&#8217;s destroying it,&#8221; she complains to clipboard guy, motioning to the overflowing shelves. He glances up over his glasses. &#8220;We&#8217;ll discuss it at Monday&#8217;s meeting,&#8221; he promises. I don&#8217;t know what I&#8217;ve done wrong, but I am sure of two things: We are all working on top of one another and there is no one in charge.</p>
<p>When the refugee crisis became front page news this past summer, thousands of Germany&#8217;s residents jumped to provide clothing and supplies, offer short-term housing solutions, or pass out sandwiches to refugees as they poured into train stations around the country. Many continue to help, some using vacation days to do so. On a civilian level, the outpouring of support in Germany has been heart-warming, encouraging, even pride-inducing.</p>
<p>Charitable and non-profit initiatives also abound. Groups have launched fundraising efforts to help those in particularly dire situations, like this <a href="https://www.betterplace.org/de/projects/37503-hilfe-fur-familie-ahmed">Iraqi father who suffered a heart attack</a>. There are <a href="http://www.unhcr.org/5655d27f6.html">bike riding lessons</a> for women and <a href="http://www.abendblatt-berlin.de/2015/12/03/ein-zirkus-fuer-die-gute-sache/">circus activities</a> for kids. A local photographer has started a &#8220;<a href="https://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.400616063468410.1073741835.295071407356210&amp;type=3">Humans of Lageso&#8221; page</a> to shed light on individual refugee stories. Herbert Grönemeyer, a famous German singer, has <a href="http://www.stern.de/lifestyle/leute/lageso-in-berlin---herbert-groenemeyer-finanziert-waermebusse-fuer-fluechtlinge-6605406.html">financed heated buses</a> so those waiting to register at Lageso can take turns warming up.</p>
<p><span class="st">But civilian good-will and a display of <span class="st"><em>Willkommenskultur</em></span> (welcome culture) can only go so far in serving the approximately 800,000 asylum seekers that Germany will receive this year &#8211; a figure that is <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/sep/06/refugee-crisis-germany-response-heartwarming-will-pressures-show">more a projection than a guest list</a>. What some in Berlin may call growing pains in learning to accommodate unprecedented waves of refugees, others deem a failure of the system and local leadership. German towns such as Passau, a Bavarian town of 50,000, have cited <a href="http://nmd.bn02750.bethemd.wayport.net/index.adp?MacAddr=68%3aA8%3a6D%3a4B%3a7A%3a8C&amp;IpAddr=10.128.29.239&amp;Ip6Addr=&amp;vsgpId=&amp;vsgId=41975&amp;UserAgent=&amp;ProxyHost=&amp;TunnelIfId=95270&amp;VlanId=20">much more success in handling the inflow</a>.</span></p>
<p><span class="st">The press have reported on the turbulent conditions at Lageso ad nauseam, both locally and <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/11/27/world/europe/germany-berlin-migrants-refugees.html?_r=0">internationally</a>. Refugees wait for weeks if not months to be registered. They line up for hours each day, often beginning the night before. People sleep in the streets. Most don&#8217;t receive enough to eat and drink. Heated tents were only made available <a href="http://www.stilinberlin.de/2015/12/fugeela-refugees-in-berlin-6-html.html">a few days ago</a>. &#8220;Refugee crisis? More like bureaucratic crisis!&#8221; protesters chanted <a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/1678473329031122/">on November 29th</a>, calling the local government to action. Understaffed and overworked employees have anonymously <a href="http://www.rbb-online.de/politik/thema/fluechtlinge/berlin/2015/12/lageso-innenansichten-mitarbeiter.html">detailed the on-going chaos</a> to the press. On December 10th, the Head of Lageso, Franz Allert, was <a href="http://www.focus.de/politik/deutschland/migration-lageso-chef-tritt-zurueck_id_5143744.html">pushed into resignation</a>. </span></p>
<p>Curly-haired boy and his mom are back outside, but at least now with warmer feet and some chocolate in their bellies. I pull my phone out of my pocket: three and a half hours have passed. There isn&#8217;t an eight hour work day in recent memory I can remember having been more exhausting. Admiration for the other volunteers &#8211; many of whom do this regularly, including night shifts &#8211; rushes within me. As does panic. The support is incredible, but is it sustainable?</p>
<p>We need to get this right, and not just in the short-term.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By<strong> Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>For up to date information in English on the refugee situation in Berlin, we recommend reading the <a href="http://www.stilinberlin.de/?s=FuGeeLa">FuGeeLa updates</a> by Stil in Berlin. <a href="http://www.findingberlin.com/how-to-help-refugees-in-berlin-winter-2015/">Finding Berlin</a> also provides comprehensive resources for how to help. </em></p>
<p><em>To sign up for volunteer shifts in Berlin, try <a href="https://volunteer-planner.org/helpdesk/">Volunteer Planner</a> (in German) or look for opportunities through <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">Give Something Back to Berlin</a> (in English). <a href="http://moabit-hilft.com/">MoabitHilft</a> is very engaged at Lageso and many of the regular volunteers at the center are affiliated with this organization.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>If you are donating clothing to refugee homes, please do your best to package them by type (e.g. age and size) and consider buying socks which are often in short supply. Even better: check first with the home to see what is most needed!</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Moralpolitik and the Ressentiments of Change</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 15:35:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4120</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[According to headlines, the German government has pledged haven – albeit temporary in many cases – to up to 800,000 refugees or migrants applying for asylum in the country. The U.S., despite initial wavering, has signaled that it will work to raise its refugee quota yearly, with the goal of a 100,000 cap by 2017. Yet within and around this historical moment of humanitarian crisis and measured political response are the inflammatory words of Donald Trump. He recently roared to a crowd in Iowa that, if elected, he “will deport all of the 11 million illegal migrants in this country.”]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As German and U.S. refugee policies inevitably collide in light of current events, this writer finds herself in the United States. The other writer of this blog will soon be in Germany, taking stock of the so-called “refugee crisis” on the ground. On my side of the Atlantic, a crisis is not yet to be felt… at least not so acutely. This has as much to do with media semantics as it does with history.</p>
<p>According to headlines, the German government has pledged haven – albeit temporary in many cases – <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/aug/20/germany-raises-estimate-refugee-arrivals-800000">to up to 800,000 refugees or migrants applying for asylum in the country</a>. The U.S., despite initial wavering, <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/news/nation/2015/09/20/increase-admission-refugees-kerry-says/fnCweeIlCS8g47VF7VAkBP/story.html">has signaled that it will work to raise its refugee quota</a> yearly, with the goal of a 100,000 cap by 2017. The Pope, as leader of the spiritual state of Catholicism, <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">has planned to make migrants and refugees one of the few central issues of his travels around the Western Hemisphere this week</a>.</p>
<p>All at once, it seems that moral duty, a college ethics course, and politics have fused into one mandate to assist.</p>
<p>Yet within and around this historical moment of humanitarian crisis and measured political response are the inflammatory words of Donald Trump. He recently roared to a crowd in Iowa that, if elected, he “<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">will deport all of the 11 million illegal migrants in this country.</a>” When asked by Univision’s anchor Jorge Ramos how he would accomplish such a feat, he coolly responded, “I’m a great manager.”</p>
<div id="attachment_4127" style="width: 630px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4127" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-4127" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg" alt="Donald Trump immigration" width="620" height="372" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg 620w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP-300x180.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4127" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Charlie Neibergall/AP via <em><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">The Guardian</a></em></p></div>
<p>One can easily get caught up in the absurdity that is the American campaign season, enjoying its theatrics as a harmless part of the celebrity process. But Trump’s words should hold weight, and they should be cause for alarm.</p>
<p>Trump’s message is not as obtuse, as unnecessarily harsh as it might seem; it reflects not only present sentiment but historical precedent… for both the United States and Germany. With the current refugee and migrant crisis, old tensions are slowly and loudly being unearthed. And the mobility of many of the world&#8217;s displaced, traumatized, and poor is not likely to change any time soon.</p>
<p>National Public Radio’s <em>Fresh Air</em> <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/10/439114563/americas-forgotten-history-of-mexican-american-repatriation">recently interviewed</a> one of the scholars behind the book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Decade-Betrayal-Mexican-Repatriation-1930s/dp/0826339735">Decade of Betrayal: Mexican Repatriation in the 1930s</a>”. The volume documents a massive and relentless deportation program at a time when xenophobia and economic distress were rampant. Historians Raymond Rodriguez and Francisco Balderrama document what is nothing short of a terrifying episode in American history – frightening for what right-wing reactionaries in a new age of migration might be capable of.</p>
<p>As Rodriguez shared with <em>Fresh Air</em>’s host, Terry Gross, the 1930s treated Mexican Americans with great malice and abuse. For reason only of their heritage, they were targeted by government programs and private citizens alike. This abuse culminated in the federal government&#8217;s campaign to strip millions of Americans of their citizenship. Not all those rounded up in deportation raids were naturalized citizens, though <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">estimates suggest than ½ of those expelled were</a>. Most were visa-holders of some sort, their only crime having been born a member of a demonized ethnic group.</p>
<p>Governmental programs to round up and expel society’s undesirables often begin in cities, according to history (see the American strategy of Japanese internment or Nazi Germany&#8217;s institution of the urban ghetto). And so Los Angeles was the primary target of the government’s Mexican American deportation program. Largely as a response to the despair the Great Depression had unleashed across the country, officials systematically sent entire families from the L.A. area back to Mexico, with no infrastructure in place to receive them. <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">From 1929 to 1944, 1/3 of L.A.’s Mexican American population was deported</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4128" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4128" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4128" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-650x487.jpg" alt="Los Angeles Mexican Americans 1932" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4128" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Los Angeles Public Library/Herald Examiner Collection via <em><a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">National Public Radio</a></em></p></div>
<p><em>Ressentiments</em> – projection of resentment or fear onto often vulnerable groups in society – were widespread both in the U.S. and in Germany throughout the Great Depression. Xenophobia in the face of severe economic collapse paved the way for Germany’s organized extermination machinery. The U.S.’s internment of Japanese and German citizens, its continued subordination of Black Americans, and its systematic deportation of Mexican Americans demonstrate that this country was in no way spared such a nasty past.</p>
<p>Slowly but surely, such <em>ressentiments</em> have now begun to return. This time, Germany may be more in the right, even despite a few documented attacks on refugee facilities, while America edges closer toward the precipice of wrong.</p>
<p>…</p>
<p>On my side of the ocean, I have arrived into a complicated sector of the nexus of natural diversity and these increasing <em>ressentiments. </em>Vancouver, Washington, where both my parents now live, <a href="http://www.thenation.com/article/browning-america/">is becoming increasingly &#8220;Brown&#8221;</a>. Separated only by a short bridge across the Columbia River, Southwest Washington has become Portland&#8217;s semi-urban/semi-rural extension. Because the northern bank of the river offers families more space for cheaper, better funded schools for fewer private tax dollars, and income tax exemption, immigrants who may have otherwise moved to the Portland, Oregon metro area are now planting themselves on the side of its less expensive neighbor. Portland, as a result, <a href="http://www.oregonlive.com/news/index.ssf/2009/01/in_a_changing_world_portland_r.html">has become increasingly White</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4129" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4129" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4129" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-650x366.jpg" alt="Interstate bridge over the Columbia River, connecting Portland, Oregon and Vancouver, Washington" width="650" height="366" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-650x366.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-300x169.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4129" class="wp-caption-text">Interstate bridge over the Columbia River, connecting Portland, Oregon and Vancouver, Washington</p></div>
<p>According to most recent U.S. census data, Vancouver is now 11% Hispanic, inching closer to the national average. We can expect this number to be much higher in reality, as immigrants will often opt out of participation in the census. There are other ethnic groups represented in Vancouver’s demographic development: For example, 18% of families speak a language other than English at home, and the traditional taco truck has recently seen competition in North African, Japanese, and Thai flavors.</p>
<p>None of this would seem all that significant, if I were not writing about a traditionally conservative county, with once sprawling farm land and a historical military base; a county that has now been converted into a rare blend of suburban developments, strip malls, urbane boutiques, and miles and miles of regional road. The nickname of &#8220;Van-tucky&#8221;* &#8211; something I have only heard used on the other side of the water, mind you &#8211; might tell you all you need to know.</p>
<p>The rate of poverty in Vancouver is also higher than the national average. Vancouver&#8217;s mayor recently <a href="http://www.cityofvancouver.us/ced/page/affordable-housing-task-force">launched a task force</a> to investigate the cause of growing homelessness, rising rents, and increased demand for housing in the city’s most accessible and commercially viable areas. Serving as Portland’s &#8220;bedroom community&#8221; brings with it numerous tax and transportation disadvantages, as well, such as costly inter-city transit for a significant commuter population and bridges nationally notorious for being structurally unsound.</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p>In a brand-new cocktail bar in downtown Vancouver, which serves only locally-distilled (read artisanal) spirits, I sip my smoky-cucumber-tequila mixture and listen in on the interaction between the unlikely combination of guests who have just joined me on the patio. Three White bikers &#8211; two older women with smokers&#8217; cough and one machismo with a mustache &#8211; scoff at the price of their beer. Across from them at a nearby table, two women in their mid-20s, both with long black hair, one who speaks English with an accent.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-4130" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-650x366.jpg" alt="cocktail Vancouver, Washington" width="650" height="366" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-650x366.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-300x169.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Older veterans and cowboy-like characters are scattered across Vancouver’s downtown like curated remains of what was once here. They drink Rainier out of cans &#8211; Washington State’s Pabst Blue Ribbon with more local charm &#8211; and chain smoke in the park. They inhabit the dive bars with names like &#8220;Lounge&#8221; and antique neon advertisements. It seems that establishments like this new artisanal cocktail bar threaten to upset a tender balance between familiarity, comfort, and growth.</p>
<p>“$4! Bullshit”, one of the women hollers. The two younger ladies nudge their shoulders closer together, in order to continue a conversation disrupted by the boom of our three new patio companions.</p>
<p>The machismo turns toward the young women’s table, putting his hand on one of their legs. “Where you from, honey?&#8221;, he begins his monologue, &#8220;I’m a native, been here for more than 20 years, Detroit before that. You know how much this place has changed?”</p>
<p>Neither responds; however, the one whose leg is playing host to the man’s hand begins to shift uncomfortably.</p>
<p>&#8220;Where you from honey? You aren&#8217;t from around here, I can tell you that!&#8221;, one of the older women yells between sips from her can. “When did Rainier get this damn expensive? It’s bullshit, $4! I’ll tell you something…”</p>
<p>One of the young, dark-haired women flashes machismo a smile. &#8220;I&#8217;m from Panama!&#8221;, she says, and extends her hand for a shake. He takes it and squeezes it, returning both their hands to the table.</p>
<p>“I’m American, from here&#8221;, the other woman says, her leg now turned as far away from his body as the chair allows.</p>
<p>&#8220;But where are your parents from then?&#8221;, machismo asks with a chuckle. &#8220;That&#8217;s what I&#8217;m asking, ain&#8217;t it?&#8221;</p>
<p>She concedes, but stands to use the restroom (or simply disappear into the building) as she does: &#8220;Well, I&#8217;m Filipino.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p><em>Ressentiments</em> toward the Other can begin and fester in spaces of socioeconomic change. With President Obama’s pledge to take in 100,000 refugees, the question becomes “How will this country prepare its citizens to engage respectfully and kindly with members of a majority Muslim country?” The first step in this process is realizing that we have a lot of work to do, and we need politicians who will help us get there.</p>
<p>Germany has seen a fair share of reporting on the readiness of its population to open its arms to newcomers. It is easy to draw parallels to the past, particularly to Germany’s track record in <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/20/441732811/in-germany-migrants-find-footing-but-also-some-resistance">failing to integrate its guest-worker population and in promoting ethnic-based citizenship until it was almost too late</a>. However, it is Germany the rest of the world now looks to in awe &#8211; for choosing a kind of <em>moralpolitik</em> over patterns of the past.</p>
<p>Being so far away from a society I sometimes feel I know more about than my own (society of origin), I can’t help but beam with pride in watching small towns across Germany distribute clean clothes, socks, new toys, children’s books, and warm meals to the thousands of human beings in need who have crossed their borders. Nevertheless, Germany has since issued temporary border controls. Order still wins out over populist charity.</p>
<p>But aiming for a collective solution to the continuous stream of migrants and refugees into Europe, German leaders have worked to reach agreement upon a refugee quota for EU member states. Just this Tuesday this quota became a provisional reality.</p>
<p>Time will tell if all members comply, and if a sense of moral duty is really as strong as images of kind citizens touting bags of donations suggest. Yet I do have the sense that with each step toward welcoming the Other, <em>ressentiments</em> have fewer chances of surviving. When demonstrations of kindness are just so strong, so publicly undeniable, that Trump-esque hate can find no oxygen for its fire.</p>
<p>That is what I hope for America.</p>
<p>At the moment, the U.S. remains crippled and complicated by its multi-layered fears of all the regions of the world it has wronged. As UN Ambassador <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/23/442761552/10-000-syrian-refugees-just-the-floor-of-u-s-effort-says-ambassador-power">Samantha Power made clear in an NPR interview recently</a>, the country is not ready to simply do the right thing; it has to be a calculated response, taking security into account.</p>
<p>Overcoming fear is America&#8217;s consistent and stubborn challenge. I just hope the mistakes of the 1930s can mean something.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*Van-tucky is a reference to the southern state of Kentucky, the unofficial home of fried-chicken and horse races.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: &#8220;I&#8217;m a Human Being&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 11:21:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Austria]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[family]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Taiwan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vienna]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4019</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Vienna. Seat of the former Austro-Hungarian Empire. Widely considered the gateway to Eastern Europe. Home to a United Nations headquarters and numerous international companies and universities. The Austrian capital has long been a city of immigration – even when politics have told a different story – and a staggering 50% of the population has what’s referred to as a “migration background”. So it’s not as if I expected Vienna to not be multicultural...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_4028" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4028" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4028 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-650x581.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender" width="650" height="581" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-650x581.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender-300x268.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender.jpg 728w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4028" class="wp-caption-text">Sophia, Christina, and Suzi at the 2015 Vienna Pride Parade</p></div>
<p>Vienna. Seat of the former Austro-Hungarian Empire. Widely considered the gateway to Eastern Europe. Home to a United Nations headquarters and numerous international companies and universities. The Austrian capital has long been a city of immigration – even when politics have told a different story – and a staggering <a href="https://www.wien.gv.at/english/social/integration/basic-work/facts-figures.html">50% of the population</a> has what’s referred to as a “migration background”.</p>
<p>So it’s not as if I expected Vienna to <em>not</em> be multicultural.</p>
<p>What I didn’t expect when <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/03/23/lens-on-leaving-homes/">moving to Vienna from Berlin</a> was to encounter some of the most fascinating “mixes” of my life: A half-Indian, half-Italian who grew up in the US and lives in Vienna with her half-Austrian, half-French boyfriend? A Chinese-American who fell in love with her German boyfriend in Hong Kong? A half-Austrian, half-Sicilian who met her Indian husband in London? The combinations are unexpected, beautiful, and dare I say, collidoscopic? (And their potential future children even more so).</p>
<div id="attachment_4031" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4031" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4031 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-650x475.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(3)" width="650" height="475" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-650x475.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3-300x219.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender3.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4031" class="wp-caption-text">Christina poses with a cow in Austria on a family roadtrip</p></div>
<p>Christina, the first close friend I made in Vienna, is no different. Born in Taiwan to a Taiwanese mother and Austrian father, at age three her family moved to San Jose, California, where her younger brother was born. Kindergarten was spent in Vienna, where she lived with her father and grandparents while mom and brother stayed in the US. At age six the entire family moved to Taiwan for four years. Then it was back west to Seattle from ages 10-16 where Christina spent the longest stretch of her childhood, what she calls her &#8220;most formative years&#8221;. Her last two years of high school were completed in Taipei, where she graduated with the globally recognized International Baccalaureate Diploma.</p>
<p>“I was missing roots as a kid, our family was always bouncing around,&#8221; she tells me.</p>
<p>This triangular ping ponging between nations resulted in three different passport combinations within a family of four: Christina’s brother, born in the US, is a dual Austrian-American citizen but “avoids Austria now because of the mandatory military service.” Mom is dual Taiwanese-Austrian, “but never felt completely comfortable in Austria”. And Christina and her father are purely Austrian, on paper anyway.</p>
<p>&#8220;A long time ago my dad had the chance to become an American citizen but decided against it,&#8221; she says smirking, &#8220;He&#8217;s a proud Austrian.”</p>
<div id="attachment_4057" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4057" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4057 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-650x488.jpg" alt="IMG_9365" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9365.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4057" class="wp-caption-text">Christina with her parents in Taiwan</p></div>
<p>It is to her father and his “pride” that Christina attributes her last 16 years in Vienna. &#8220;My dream was to go to Georgetown [University],&#8221; Christina tells me one warm evening in the <em>Museumsquartier</em>, her fingers tapping the stem of her <em>Hugospritz</em>. &#8220;I applied and got in… my mom supported it, but my dad kept saying I had to go to university in Austria. It was always really important to him that, as the oldest child, I embrace my Austrian roots.&#8221;</p>
<p>Christina ended up moving to Vienna against her will: “I didn&#8217;t have any connection to Austria at that time other than having spent the occasional summer there with my grandparents.” The first year, she expressed her anger by skipping class in favor of exploring the city and having fun.</p>
<p>“And then I got pregnant,” she says laughing, “the biggest rebellion of all!”</p>
<div id="attachment_4059" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4059" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4059 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371-650x650.jpg" alt="IMG_9371" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/IMG_9371-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4059" class="wp-caption-text">Mother-daughter surfing trip in Morocco</p></div>
<p>Christina’s daughter Illeana (Illy) was born when she was 20. She raised Illy as a single mother while completing her degrees in Economics and Sinology, with “lots of help” from friends with similar bi-cultural backgrounds. She counts half-Austrian friends from South Africa and Bolivia among her closest, along with a half-Kosovan, half-Czech hair salon owner named Suzi. “None of us knew what we were doing… it was experimental parenting. I think if I raised a child now I’d be much more nervous!”</p>
<p>After making it over the hump of her first year, Vienna started to feel like home. “I began to realize how much I love it here,” Christina reflects. Now one could say Christina is as Austrian as they come. Her German is flawless and chock full of colloquialisms, she sings along to Austrian <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schlager_music">Schlager</a></em>, and her drink of choice is the ubiquitous <em><a href="http://austrianwineusa.com/2013/12/20/12-days-of-austrian-wine-enjoy-a-gspritzer/">Weisser Spritzer</a></em>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4064" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4064" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4064 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-650x602.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(7)" width="650" height="602" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-650x602.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7-300x278.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender7.jpg 701w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4064" class="wp-caption-text">Christina skiing in Kaprun, Austria</p></div>
<p>None of that, however, stops her from craving Taiwanese ‘Three-Cups Chicken’ or her favorite American cereal, ‘Lucky Charms’. “I’m biracial and tri-cultural,” she states without hesitation. And while rewarding on personal and professional levels (she’s also fluent in Mandarin), Christina’s background has not gone unchallenged in a city that still struggles to see itself as a place of migration and diversity.</p>
<p>Christina has encountered countless variations of the “<a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/">But where are you <em>really</em> from?</a>” question over the years. “When I first got to Vienna, there were fewer minorities and diversity didn&#8217;t work very well,” she remarks, “I remember meeting one guy who could not comprehend why I looked the way I did but had a very common German last name,&#8221; she rolls her eyes at the memory. &#8220;I literally had to spell it out for him by saying, &#8216;If you, an Austrian, had a baby with a Taiwanese woman, the result would be me!’”</p>
<div id="attachment_4034" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4034" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4034 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-650x488.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(6)" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender6.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4034" class="wp-caption-text">Christina&#8217;s 3rd Birthday in Los Angeles, California</p></div>
<p>This phenomenon isn’t limited to Vienna. In Japan, a newly crowned biracial beauty queen has been fielding questions on a regular basis about what parts of her are “Japanese”. <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/30/world/asia/biracial-beauty-queen-strives-for-change-in-mono-ethnic-japan.html">“But I am a Japanese,”</a> is her response. On the other side of the world, in the US, Rachel Dolezal was recently exposed for her elaborate deception as a Black woman – a &#8220;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/18/opinion/charles-blow-the-delusions-of-dolezal.html?smid=fb-share">one-directional privilege</a>&#8221; that could never have been successful the other way around, due to socially constructed perceptions of race. The recurring theme? If you are one drop of minority, we will question your Belonging to the majority.</p>
<p>Christina acknowledges that even she is not immune to societal attitudes about migrants in Austria. &#8220;I&#8217;ve learned that, in Austria, migrants get classified into &#8216;good&#8217; and &#8216;bad&#8217;,&#8221; she explains.</p>
<p>&#8220;Asians are considered ‘good’ because they’re quiet, stay out of trouble, and work hard. Turkish people are unpopular because a lot of them refuse to adapt to the Austrian way of life and bring hordes of family members over, all the while claiming benefits from the Austrian government. Blacks have it the worst, though, probably because they stand out the most and are still viewed by many locals as low-lifes and drug dealers.&#8221;</p>
<div id="attachment_4029" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4029" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4029 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-650x472.jpg" alt="FullSizeRender(1)" width="650" height="472" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-650x472.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1-300x218.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/FullSizeRender1.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4029" class="wp-caption-text">Christina riding a (fake) bull at Glacier National Park, Montana</p></div>
<p>While Christina is well aware that the US has its own challenges regarding diversity, she does view it as more progressive: “In the US, people at least get it when you tell them that you&#8217;re biracial.”</p>
<p>It was 1999 when Christina was last in the US, before Illy&#8217;s birth and before the 9/11 attacks. While she’s now seriously considering a move back, it&#8217;s unclear when she will be able to. Christina is not a US citizen and needs a green card. Her most recent attempt at the <a href="http://travel.state.gov/content/visas/english/immigrate/diversity-visa/instructions.html">Diversity Visa Lottery</a> was unsuccessful. “My dad told me he is reconsidering becoming an American citizen just so that he can help get us over there,” Christina recently shared. <a href="http://www.migrationpolicy.org/article/family-reunification">Family reunification</a> is one of the four major pathways for foreigners to become legal residents of the US.</p>
<p>Legal challenges are also not Christina’s only concern. “Sometimes I worry that people in the US will annoy me with their ignorance,” she says laughing. At the same time, she is drawn to the lifestyle. She observes her American friends move to houses with pools, which, compared to Viennese city apartments, seem like mansions. Illy, a recovering Justin Bieber addict who recently graduated to a One Direction obsession, is thrilled with the prospect. “A typical Austrian teenager,” Christina chuckles.</p>
<p>You could call Christina many things: A transnational, an immigrant, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">a third-culture kid</a>, a foreigner, a native, an expat. But none of these categories really fit given the fluidity of her upbringing and identity. We use labels to establish connections and try to make sense of things, but they can also dilute the intricacy and beauty of reality.</p>
<p>&#8220;I&#8217;m not 100% of anything,&#8221; is how Christina describes it. &#8220;Sometimes when people ask what I am, I just answer that I&#8217;m a human being.&#8221;</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Photos provided by Christina and Sophia.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/07/03/interview-im-a-human-being/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Refugees Welcome: Local Interventions for an EU Dilemma</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/04/30/refugees-welcome-local-interventions-for-an-eu-dilemma/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/04/30/refugees-welcome-local-interventions-for-an-eu-dilemma/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 13:04:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[borders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[European Union]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3965</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This article is intended to inform, as well as to encourage advocacy and action. As any seasoned volunteer or activist knows, engagement relies heavily on context, identifying not only how to get involved but why and in which capacity, based on the complex landscape of need one encounters.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Saturday, the 18th of April, a small fishing vessel capsized off the coast of Libya on its way to one of the European Union’s coastal states. On its way, it passed through waters patrolled by the European Union&#8217;s security agency, Frontex. Its demise was quick, only 28 passengers were rescued; an estimated 900 are said to have perished. Of the dead, roughly 200 had had little chance of escape, locked securely in the ship&#8217;s hull by the smugglers commissioned with their passage. A similar event had made headlines just the Sunday before: 400 dead in the water. Yet even more sobering is the UN&#8217;s projected number of migrant deaths by the end of 2015: <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/italy/11548995/Mediterranean-migrant-crisis-hits-Italy-as-EU-ministers-meet-live.html">approximately 30,000</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_3993" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3993" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3993 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-650x488.jpg" alt="Essen_ProAsyl" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Essen_ProAsyl.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3993" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Pro Asyl</p></div>
<p>Although this tally of the dead got its start long ago, both the number and its surrounding political situation seem to be escalating at an alarming rate. It is possible that this escalation is, in part, due to the quick reporting the digital-age affords a global readership. But, given the current death toll and its greater context of inter-regional instability, one thing seems fairly certain: If safer pathways for migration to the European Union continue to remain restricted or inaccessible to many, the intersecting lines of risk and desperation will continue to make safety subordinate to a chance at what is (presented as) a better life.</p>
<p>Yet the most immediate and real consequence of these reports of danger leading to disaster may not be deterrence but desensitization: The drowned and discarded may begin to shock a little less with each headline, and, worse yet, public support for the displaced &#8211; in our communities, off our shores, and even in those far-off lands to which our governments sell arms in exchange for cheap manufactured goods (an oversimplification of the global balance of trade, of course, but the point remains a valid one) &#8211; may wane.</p>
<p>But this doesn&#8217;t have to be the case. This article is intended to inform, as well as to encourage advocacy and action. As any seasoned volunteer or activist knows, engagement relies heavily on context, identifying not only how to get involved but why and in which capacity, based on the complex landscape of need one encounters. And so, I will first offer a summary of information I find important in creating this context, beginning with an understanding of Germany&#8217;s position in the asylum system of the European Union and followed by an unpacking of certain terms and categories. The latter is not meant to distinguish between and thus arrange various grades of human value based on one&#8217;s reasons for migration; rather, examining these categories is an attempt to identify and elucidate the different contours and sites of vulnerability to be found in refugee and immigrant advocacy, with navigating such categories being crucial to successful support. The most important bit follows these term-laden sections &#8211; namely, a list of ways to get involved in Berlin housing facilities and neighborhood support centers for asylum-applicants. Some options for digital activism and direct actions around Germany will also be included for our readers further afield.</p>
<p>In the end, my hope is to transform this article into a helpful resource page for the <em>Collidoscope</em> webpage. Thus feedback on ways to improve its information and add to or amend its list of opportunities for involvement is greatly appreciated!</p>
<p><strong>Asylum in the EU and refugee status in Germany: an overview</strong></p>
<p>It is helpful to continue with numbers as a means of illustrating the magnitude of the situation (despite my preference for qualitative vs. purely quantitative data &#8211; for which this blog tends to be a perfect example). In 2014, Germany housed approximately 173,000 applicants for asylum, an increase of 192% from the previous year. By the end of 2015, upwards of 300,000 applicants for asylum are projected to enter and remain temporarily in the country [source: <a href="http://www.bamf.de/DE/Infothek/Statistiken/Asylzahlen/asylzahlen-node.html">BAMF</a>]. Despite its shock-value, this remains a small number in the grand scheme of immigration flows. Relative to the asylum policies of the other G-20 countries, however, this is a significant number. The United States, for example, processed 121,000 asylum claims in 2014, a country with four times the population of Germany [source: <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/europe/new-migration-crisis-overwhelms-european-refugee-system/2015/04/21/3ab83470-e45c-11e4-ae0f-f8c46aa8c3a4_story.html">Washington Post</a>].</p>
<p>This does not mean that all claims and their applicants are granted residency in Germany. In fact, most are rejected, resulting in deportation either once a decision has been reached or in a temporary stay of inevitable deportation. Only 24% were granted refugee status in 2014, which excludes a guarantee of permanent status, i.e. returning &#8220;status-refugees&#8221; to their countries of origin once conflicts can be said to be resolved. Last year, only 1.8% received the coveted gift of permanent asylum [source: <a href="http://www.bamf.de/SharedDocs/Anlagen/DE/Publikationen/Broschueren/broschuere-bundesamt-in-zahlen-2014-asyl.pdf?__blob=publicationFile">BAMF</a>].</p>
<p>Nevertheless, 2014&#8217;s final tally of approximately 34,000 accepted refugees indicates a lag in the participation of other EU member states, such as the Netherlands, Poland, or Ireland, not to mention the strange and ineffective logic behind the so-called Dublin III convention*. As the commissioner for the German federal agency for migration and refugees, Aydan Özoguz, commented just last week: “The European asylum system doesn’t work. Some countries are doing very little. We are one of the richest countries and we want to help, but it’s not okay that Germany, Sweden and France are taking 50 percent of the refugees, while other countries do nothing” [source: <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/europe/new-migration-crisis-overwhelms-european-refugee-system/2015/04/21/3ab83470-e45c-11e4-ae0f-f8c46aa8c3a4_story.html">Washington Post</a>].</p>
<p>EU leaders met just last week in an emergency summit to discuss changes to this increasingly dysfunctional system. Given Germany&#8217;s position as home to the greatest number of asylum-applicants, decisions made here set both the moral and practical tone for the other states in the European Union&#8217;s common asylum system &#8211; an infrastructure guided less by comprehensive agreements and more by a few select rules. At the summit&#8217;s conclusion, leaders agreed to invest more money in rescue efforts: more boats and life-vests for the Mediterranean. But what of more legal, safe pathways into the European Union?</p>
<p>Over the last few days, arguments have been made for a reform to the immigration policies that prevent potential workers from entering the country by legal means, unrelated to the conditions for asylum but also free from the ardor of submitting a claim and waiting years for a decision. <a href="http://www.iwkoeln.de/presse/interviews/beitrag/michael-huether-in-der-welt-iw-fordert-mehr-fluechtlinge-fuer-deutschen-arbeitsmarkt-223062">According to the Institut für deutsche Wirtschaft</a> (IW), one in five asylum-applicants has a college degree and one in three are skilled in some trade or another. With German industry&#8217;s sustained calls for increased immigration (to compensate for an aging or less technically-skilled population), providing a more accelerated pathway to a safe life in Germany for those migrants who qualify, while meeting the utilitarian imperative of the political establishment, seems like a win-win. Traditional asylum and provisions for refugees would not be eliminated, by any means, but the number of migrants from poor or conflict-ridden countries would be allowed to increase, saving many the eventual rejection most asylum-applicants face once they arrive in Europe, if they are lucky enough to survive the journey (see the <a href="http://heindehaas.blogspot.de/2015/04/let-their-people-drown-how-eu.html">recent appeal from social scientist Hein de Haas</a> for more on this argument).</p>
<p>However, as is often the case in coordinated responses to humanitarian need, calculations of domestic burden vs. benefit will dominate. And an end to these calculations is nowhere in sight. That is to say, if we wait for political change, we may be waiting at a high opportunity cost &#8211; that of everyday advocacy for and support of the displaced. But first, categories&#8230;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Refugee&#8221; or &#8220;asylum-seeker&#8221;?</strong></p>
<p>The distinction between those with refugee status and those who have submitted an application for asylum (referred to as &#8220;asylum-applicant&#8221; thus far) is an important one, as it helps to explain the origins and role of the <em>Flüchtlingsheim</em> (state-sponsored but privately-run housing facility for asylum-applicants) in the everyday landscape of German towns and cities, including Berlin. Of course, the implementation of national asylum law can vary state by state, given Germany&#8217;s federal balance of power; Saxony, Bavaria, and Berlin may differ in the scope and quantity of services provided to asylum-applicants residing in each state&#8217;s respected <em>Flüchtlingsheime,</em> for example,<em> </em>as this <a href="http://www.proasyl.de/de/news/detail/news/pro_asyl_studie_zur_unterbringung_von_fluechtlingen_in_deutschland/">study</a> demonstrates. But, in all cases, the foundation of German asylum law is built on a differentation between those whose claims have been adjudicated (decided by a judge in German administrative court) and those who have filed claims but are awaiting a decision, assigning different rights and restrictions to these different groups, accordingly. The most important rights and restrictions are those affecting the freedom of movement and activity for those migrants to fall in the &#8220;asylum-applicant&#8221; category. They are as follows:</p>
<p>&#8211; Asylum-applicants are generally not allowed to work until they receive formal status: either as a &#8220;refugee&#8221; (a temporary status, in most cases), as an &#8220;asylee&#8221; (long-term or permanent status), or as a &#8220;tolerated person&#8221; (<em>Geduldete</em>). There are, of course, some exceptions to this rule; for example, asylum-applicants in Berlin and Brandenburg are allowed to pursue employment one year after their application has been submitted, though this work allowance remains heavily restricted and qualified. This means that, in general, asylum-applicants are not able to provide for themselves, thereby becoming fully dependent on the services financed by the federal government, the respective state, and third-parties responsible for service provision. The housing facility system of the <em>Flüchtlingsheim</em> was established both to meet the need for accommodation and to enforce this ban on employment.</p>
<p>&#8211; Up until January of this year, all asylum-applicants were to remain in the state and district either in which they had applied for asylum or to which they had been assigned. They were not able to determine this geographical location or the particular facility in which they would live, even in the case of friends or relatives already in the country. These rules for residency and domicile make up the German system of <em>Residenzpflicht.</em> According to the organization Pro Asyl, <a href="http://www.proasyl.de/de/themen/basics/basiswissen/rechte-der-fluechtlinge/bewegungsfreiheit/residenzpflicht/">these restrictions have been partially lifted</a>. It is unclear, however, to what extent the residency requirement will be relaxed. And as with any policy reform, there will certainly be a lag in public officials and bureaucrats implementing changes. In other words, asylum-applicants may still be prohibited (by staff and local enforcement personnel) from leaving their assigned district, and limits to mobility may still be decided on a state-by-state and case-by-case basis.</p>
<p>&#8211; Residents of <em>Flüchtlingsheime</em> are frequently re-distributed to prevent over-crowding and to maintain an equitable distribution of the financial burden, relative to each state&#8217;s population and economic situation. The freedom of movement, which the abolition of <em>Residenzpflicht </em>may have provided, is overruled and/or overshadowed by this re-distribution mandate.</p>
<p>&#8211; Once asylum-applicants have received a decision from the judge &#8211; the time between the initial filing of the application, the hearing, and the eventual decision often proving to be a year-long ordeal -, those without status granted are either returned to their country of origin (often within a few months of the decision) or are given a <i>Duldung</i>, becoming a &#8220;tolerated person&#8221; for as long as the state deems their return difficult (e.g. in the case of illness, psychological distress, age, family relations, financial situation in the country of origin). <em>Geduldete</em> are free to seek employment and live among the general population, securing their own housing, albeit within the town/city of their asylum-application. But, in most cases, they are not entitled to the same social services as those with refugee status and can be deported at any time, particularly in the case of a minor infraction.</p>
<p>These terms serve to complicate the issue of refugees and the work of refugee advocacy, as various levels of status and treatment before the law are at play. In my opinion, when the media and public discourse fail to make these distinctions, the complexity of the issue and its effect on the experience of real human beings is side-lined to a language that prefers the simplicity of pure humanitarianism &#8211; a moral outlook recognized neither by German law-makers nor by the structures of the European Union. In simple terms, those crossing the Mediterranean and those living in close quarters in Berlin&#8217;s many <em>Flüchtlingsheime </em>are not all &#8220;refugees&#8221;. If they were, they would receive the humane treatment popular opinion affords them.</p>
<div id="attachment_3994" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3994" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3994 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind-650x650.jpg" alt="Deichkind" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Deichkind-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3994" class="wp-caption-text">German pop group Deichkind; Source: <a href="https://instagram.com/p/0tB_FivQxn/">Instagram</a></p></div>
<p>Yet, when we acknowledge that it is precisely because of the precarity of their status that they need our help, the situation looks much different. And local interventions in the experience of this precarity become most important, beyond #refugeeswelcome.</p>
<p><strong>How to help</strong></p>
<p>A few weeks ago I visited a new housing facility for asylum-applicants in Reinickendorf, one of the northernmost districts of Berlin. In an idyllic setting, surrounded by pine and quiet residential streets, a former High School has been converted into a 300 bed hostel for migrants awaiting status. The space is rudimentary but well-organized, staff making do with donated toys and German courses, among other diverse activities, as a means to entertain the many children &#8211; many of whom have been waiting for more than two months to enroll in the local school. The staff &#8211; about 10 in number &#8211; communicate with residents in what seems to be a mix of German, English, French, and enthusiastic signage. There is an artist working on the aesthetic revitalization of the place &#8211; literally making the dark halls of a High School a place that feels like home for its residents. There are social workers and psychologists who visit on occasion. Basic meals are catered three times a day on a set schedule. &#8220;House Rules&#8221; are posted in various languages in the foyer. And security guards patrol the grounds, which are clearly the remains of a once vibrant schoolyard, complete with a basketball court (nets partially intact) and a covered concrete playground for jumping rope and hopscotch. We chat about setting up in-house cooking activities, to bring residents and staff closer together, and about using the open space to start a garden, giving the families an opportunity to build and realize a strenuous but rewarding project, even harvest its fruits. The plans are piece-meal and heavily reliant on donations and organizational finesse. In many ways, it is simply about showing up (a familiar mantra), trying to be of help, and deferring to the staff who are there throughout the week trying to make the facility a better place for all who live there.</p>
<p>There are more than 40 facilities just like this one across Berlin, housing upwards of 11,000 asylum-applicants. <a href="http://www.morgenpost.de/berlin/article139453814/Senat-baut-36-neue-Fluechtlingsheime-in-Berlin.html">36 more facilities just like them are planned</a> for the end of 2015. The need is great, but so is this city. Here is a list of established groups across Berlin who work directly with <em>Flüchtlingsheime </em>like the one mentioned above; all of these organizations are certainly eager for new volunteers:</p>
<p>Flüchtlingsinitiative Klausener Platz [evagoemuesay(at)gmail.com]</p>
<p><a href="https://hellersdorfhilft.wordpress.com/">Hellersdorf hilft e.V.</a></p>
<p>Initiative Grenzen weg Hellersdorf [grenzenweg(at)gmx.de]</p>
<p><a href="http://www.wir-netzwerk.de/">Willkommen in Reinickendorf</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.willkommensbuendnis-steglitz-zehlendorf.de/">Willkommensbündnis für Flüchtlinge Steglitz-Zehlendorf</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.lichtenbergerbuendnis.de/">Lichtenberger Bündnis für Demokratie und Toleranz</a></p>
<p><a href="https://bunterwind.wordpress.com/">Bunter Wind für Lichtenberg</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.willkommen-im-westend.de/">Willkommen im Westend &#8211; Refugees Welcome</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.zentrum-für-demokratie.de/">Netzwerk für Flüchtlinge in Treptow-Köpenick</a></p>
<p><a href="http://multitude_tk@riseup.net">Multitude Gruppe Köpenick</a> (for German speakers only &#8211; German language instruction)</p>
<p><a href="https://arbeitsgruppefluchtundmenschenrechte.wordpress.com/">Arbeitsgruppe Flucht und Menschenrechte Treptow-Köpenick</a></p>
<p><a href="http://uffmucken-schoeneweide.de/">Initiative &#8220;Uffmucken Schöneweide&#8221;</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.buendnis-neukoelln.de/">Bündnis Neukölln</a></p>
<p><a href="http://fluechtlingshilfe@britzerinitiative.de">Aktionsbündnis Flüchtlingshilfe Britz</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.multitude-berlin.de/">Initiative Multitude e.V.</a> (for German speakers only &#8211; German language instruction in Spandau, Westend, Lichtenberg, Marzahn, Prenzlauer Berg)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.pankow-hilft.de/">Willkommensnetzwerk &#8220;Pankow Hilft!&#8221;</a> (Pankow, Prenzlauer Berg, Weissensee, Buch)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Fl%C3%BCchtlinge-willkommen-in-Buch-und-Karow/1481160482158156">Flüchtlinge willkommen in Buch und Karow</a></p>
<p><a href="http://u_strassburger@posteo.de">Unterstützer_innenkreis Flüchtlingsunterkunft Prenzlauer Berg</a></p>
<p>Initiative &#8220;Wedding Hilft&#8221; [wedding.hilft(at)gmail.com]</p>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/moabithilft">Initiative &#8220;Moabit Hilft&#8221;</a></p>
<p><a href="http://neuenachbarschaft.wordpress.com/">Initiative &#8220;Neue Nachbarschaft Moabit&#8221;</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.willkommensbuendnis-steglitz-zehlendorf.de/">Willkommensbündnis für Flüchtlinge in Steglitz-Zehlendorf</a></p>
<p><a href="http://bglbb.blogsport.de/">Bündnis gegen Lager Berlin-Brandenburg</a></p>
<p><a href="http://asylstrikeberlin.wordpress.com/">Oranienplatz</a></p>
<p>For those without immediate time to spare but keen on staying informed on actions and opportunities as they develop, track the activities of  the <a href="http://www.fluechtlingsrat-berlin.de/">Flüchtlingsrat-Berlin</a> (the local office of the nation-wide &#8220;refugee council&#8221; model) and <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">GiveSomethingBacktoBerlin</a> (a community platform for volunteer engagement, including frequent posts from groups seeking participants in visits to and on-going projects within <em>Flüchtlingsheime</em>).</p>
<p>Of course, this type of on-site involvement is not for everyone. The type of validation that often comes with structured community engagement projects is not likely to be found here. And, although I am a fan of &#8220;showing up&#8221; and getting one&#8217;s hands dirty, applying pressure on policy-makers and raising awareness to the need for asylum and immigration reform remain incredibly important contributions. Here are a few resources on direct actions and politics-oriented digital activism; these options are great for those further afield who would like to participate in some way, even if just with a click:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/367018126842745,%20http://www.amnesty.de/2015/4/20/massensterben-im-mittelmeer-stoppen-seenotrettung-jetzt">Amnesty International Germany&#8217;s campaign against </a><em><a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/367018126842745,%20http://www.amnesty.de/2015/4/20/massensterben-im-mittelmeer-stoppen-seenotrettung-jetzt">Massensterben im Mittelmeer</a> (</em>flash-mobs and rallies around the offices of Parliament and Executive Government)</p>
<p><a href="http://action.amnesty.de/l/ger/p/dia/action3/common/public/?action_KEY=9703&amp;d=1">#SOSEurope Amnesty International petition</a> (calling upon Merkel&#8217;s government to reform immigration and asylum policy)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.proasyl.de/de/home/seenotrettung-jetzt/">ProAsyl petition</a> (for more EU member-state support of rescue efforts in the Mediterranean)</p>
<p>Donate to the organization <a href="http://www.proasyl.de/de/">Pro Asyl:</a> perhaps the best way to assist the many asylum-applicants residing in Germany and other EU member states by way of a great and highly-effective organization. Pro Asyl coordinates volunteer activities, contributes to accurate reporting and research on asylum in the EU, and offers legal counsel to asylum-applicants, among many other great services.</p>
<p><strong>Why local interventions matter</strong></p>
<p>A <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/media/2015-05-16_EFA-Forschungsbericht_Endfassung.pdf">study</a> was just released by the new <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/">Berlin Institute for Empirical Migration and Integration Research</a>* (BIM) on Berlin-based volunteer engagement  in support of asylum-applicants and resettled refugees. It points to severe deficits in state services for which the unpaid contributions of volunteers strive to remedy. In particular, without the engagement of what the study deems predominately secular, middle-class females, many asylum-applicants would have great difficulty communicating with those agencies charged with the processing and, ultimately, the acceptance or rejection of their claim to refugee status. Additionally, despite the <em>Trägerschaft </em>structure, in which third-party organizations assume partial financial responsibility and full operational responsibility for these housing facilities, many goods and services would otherwise be sorely lacking without the donation-drives and supply deliveries of volunteers. The study describes the especially integral role of volunteers in assisting in the navigation of Germany&#8217;s complex bureaucratic structures: something necessary for immigrants of any sort to successfully remain in the country.</p>
<div id="attachment_3995" style="width: 498px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3995" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3995" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider-488x650.jpg" alt="Source: Pro Asyl" width="488" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider.jpg 488w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/flashmob_Innsbruck_Julius-Schneider-225x300.jpg 225w" sizes="(max-width: 488px) 100vw, 488px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3995" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Pro Asyl</p></div>
<p>And even the simple opportunity for social interaction, which comes with visits from the outside, can have a great effect on an asylum-applicant&#8217;s success, encouraging language and intercultural skills through everyday relationships that will serve them well in the future. From building the capacity to make one&#8217;s case successfully to a judge to preparing for integration into the local job-market once status, whether temporary or permanent, has been granted, seeing to the wellness of a <em>Flüchtlingsheim&#8217;s </em>residents is a powerful intervention in an often bleak process. In the end, it is the state that decides who may be called a &#8220;refugee&#8221; and who might have a chance at a better life, but volunteers may prove to be one of the deciding factors in who will be welcomed.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>As already mentioned, please submit your comments or write us an email with suggestions or changes, so that this can become a helpful and accurate resource for months to come. And please share with your various networks. The more informed our communities, the better activists we can be!</em></p>
<p>*Technically, certain conventions of the European Union (such as the oft-cited Dublin III agreement) requires that migrants seeking asylum, i.e. refugee status, apply for and receive asylum for the first EU country on which they are said to have set foot. In practice, however, Dublin III is inconsistently enforced, thus allowing asylum-applicants to submit a claim in an economically prosperous country like Germany.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/04/30/refugees-welcome-local-interventions-for-an-eu-dilemma/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: &#8220;I&#8217;m not Turkish, but my husband is&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[love]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tunisia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1251</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In a capital city marked by transformation and transience, where people are perpetually coming and going, it can feel like a true rarity to meet someone actually from that city. “H” was my first Berlin friend from Berlin. We met through a language website, after she sent me a request to practice French in exchange for German. H was working on her degree to become a French teacher. I was still new to the city and could count my local friends on one hand...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_3811" style="width: 733px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://jurigottschau.com/"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3811" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3811 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz.jpg" alt="grillplatz" width="723" height="482" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz.jpg 723w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 723px) 100vw, 723px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3811" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p style="text-align: left;">In a capital city marked by transformation and transience, where people are perpetually coming and going, it can feel like a true rarity to meet someone actually <em>from</em> that city.</p>
<p>&#8220;H&#8221; was my first Berlin friend from Berlin. We met through a language website, after she sent me a request to practice French in exchange for German. H was working on her degree to become a French teacher. I was still new to the city and could count my local friends on one hand. The first time we hung out was in February 2012 at a cafe under the <em>Savignyplatz S-Bahn</em> arches. H ended up helping me with my research on teacher quality in Germany, and I gave her tips for her upcoming study abroad program in France. Soon enough our linguistic meet-ups evolved into a friendship that waved off grammar practice in favor of relaxed Sunday afternoon coffee dates.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Our relationship also became a kind of exchange of culinary cultures. I started joining her annually to break the fast during Ramadan. As the resident atheist I wouldn&#8217;t fast before these meals. Yet I&#8217;d still be the one gnawing away at my fingers until sundown, while H and her sisters waited patiently for their first sips of rose flavored water and soup drizzled with fresh lemon juice. In return, H  joined my international crew of friends for her first Thanksgiving dinner, initiated into the world of cranberry sauce, candied sweet potatoes, and general American gluttony. Her contribution &#8211; mounds of Turkish <em>Lahmacun</em> (spiced lamb pizza) &#8211; was eagerly divvied up like party favors at the end of the night.</p>
<div id="attachment_3611" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3611" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3611 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340-650x650.jpg" alt="IMG_3340" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3611" class="wp-caption-text">Ramadan dinner with H</p></div>
<p style="text-align: left;">It didn&#8217;t take long for us to discover our mutual fascination with questions of citizenship and identity. We attended several events together on the topic and often spent our cafe time discussing our hybrid families and understanding of <em>Deutschsein</em> or &#8220;Germanness&#8221;. See, while H is a true <em>Berlinerin</em> &#8211; she was born and grew up here &#8211; her parents are from Tunisia. We shared the feeling of having more than one home; while I straddled the Atlantic, H had a foot on either side of the Mediterranean. But unlike me, H had grown up with the challenge of having to persistently defend her Germanness, to the wider community and to her own parents.</p>
<p>In countries like Germany that are still embracing their multicultural identities &#8211; Germany first recognized itself as a country of immigration in 2005 &#8211; too many still have a binary understanding of native vs. foreigner that acknowledges bloodlines over birthplace and physical appearance over personal identity. There remains a habit of probing those who look &#8220;different&#8221; about their roots, otherwise known as the dreaded &#8220;But where are you <em>really</em> from?&#8221; <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/">question</a>. Those on the receiving end of this question are often referred to as the &#8220;perpetual foreigner&#8221;, ethnic minorities who will always be seen as the “other” because of how they look.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">In H&#8217;s case, it didn&#8217;t take long to notice that the vast majority of those she came across assumed she was Turkish, including other Turkish-Germans. &#8220;Oh right, the Turkish one,&#8221; a girl on her basketball team responded, when I introduced myself as H&#8217;s friend. H once told me she gets asked if she&#8217;s Turkish more than her best friend, an actual Turkish-German who happens to be blond and fair-skinned.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3697 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-650x487.jpg" alt="2014-01-19 17.26.48" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>The confusion isn&#8217;t all too surprising, considering H&#8217;s darker features, for one, and the demographics of the city, for two. Turkish-Germans are the city&#8217;s largest ethnic minority and the largest community of Turks outside of Turkey. Estimates of the number of Turks in Berlin range from 200,000-500,000 (a combination of those with Turkish passports, partial Turkish ancestry, and ethnic minorities from Turkey). A far cry from the approximately <a href="http://www.berlin.de/lb/intmig/statistik/demografie/einwohner_staatsangehoerigkeit.html">1,500 Tunisian nationals</a> in Berlin.</p>
<p>The story of H&#8217;s parents also mirrors that of many Turkish-Germans. They immigrated to the city separately as part of a guest-worker program in the 1970s and met on the job at corporate giant, Siemens. Originally, they planned to return to Tunisia together. The couple worked 2-3 jobs, sending remittances to family in Tunisia to save up to build a house there. They sent their 3 eldest daughters back for 9 years to live with relatives and go to school. But when Germany tightened family reunification laws in the 80&#8217;s, excluding those older than 16 without German citizenship, they brought the 3 girls back to Berlin to keep the family together, by then consisting of 5 daughters.</p>
<p>H is daughter number 4 and has only visited Tunisia on vacation. She admits that a distinction exists between the older and younger sisters, due to this geographic divide in upbringing, especially apparent in attitudes toward the headscarf and family planning. Her oldest sister &#8220;lives by the Qu&#8217;ran&#8221; and hopes to move back to Tunisia permanently one day. H, on the other hand, identifies as a &#8220;<em>Berlinerin</em> with Tunisian roots&#8221;; she has no intention of leaving Germany anytime soon.</p>
<div id="attachment_3791" style="width: 657px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3791" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3791 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg" alt="htunisia" width="647" height="484" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg 647w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia-300x224.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 647px) 100vw, 647px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3791" class="wp-caption-text">H on vacation in Tunisia</p></div>
<p>When it comes to questions and comments about her being Turkish, I&#8217;ve only ever seen H respond with patience and grace. It&#8217;s the difficulties with her own parents, and especially mother, that affect her most. If you ask her about her upbringing, H will tell you that her parents were &#8220;pretty modern for immigrant standards&#8221;, letting her play sports and stay out with friends until 10pm. Sleepovers and clubs weren&#8217;t allowed, but H found ways around her parents&#8217; rules, such as working at social events like the <em>Volksfest </em>and later heading west to Dortmund for university.</p>
<p>Boyfriends, on the other hand, were out of the question. Particularly those outside of the Tunisian-German community. H dated a little in secret, but didn&#8217;t get serious with anyone until she met &#8220;A&#8221; at 19. At 28, A was almost a decade older and managing a series of internet cafes. The flirtation started small with jokes at the shop, building up slowly to weekend jogs together. Finally, A asked H out on a date.</p>
<p>H managed to keep the relationship hidden from her parents for 6 years. &#8220;I was sure they&#8217;d disapprove because he&#8217;s Turkish,&#8221; she explains. Even though both Tunisians and Turks in Germany are predominantly Muslim, H says it&#8217;s not uncommon for the older immigrant generations to be prejudiced against one another. &#8220;The Tunisians here think that all Turkish boys are in gangs, are loud and have no respect, and don&#8217;t achieve anything,&#8221; H claims; &#8220;Tunisians in Tunisia think more positively about Turks than Tunisians in Germany do.&#8221;</p>
<p>When she told her parents about the relationship in 2013, her mother threatened that H was &#8220;ruining her life&#8221; and that if she continued, they would disown her. &#8220;I haven&#8217;t even told them yet that A is Shiite,&#8221; H joked (her family is Sunni).</p>
<div id="attachment_3792" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3792" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3792 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-650x202.jpg" alt="A&amp;H" width="650" height="202" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-650x202.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-300x93.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3792" class="wp-caption-text">A &amp; H</p></div>
<p>According to H, the problem is her mother&#8217;s stubbornness more than anything else. But listening to the stories one can&#8217;t help but notice an underlying theme of fear, logical or not. A fear of losing one&#8217;s child. A fear of not relating to one&#8217;s grandchildren. A fear of the dilution of one&#8217;s cultural lineage over generations. &#8220;Many in the Tunisian-German community are scared that their kids will marry Turks and end up in Turkey,&#8221; H agrees, &#8220;my mother is also afraid her grandchildren will never learn Arabic.&#8221; H and her sisters speak strictly Tunisian Arabic with their parents. When just amongst each other, a mix of Arabic and German.</p>
<p>Language is just one question of many that H and A will face as parents. They have already decided that A will primarily speak Turkish and H mostly German, which she is more comfortable with than Arabic. They have even talked about where they will <em>really</em> end up one day. H tells me that the Tunisian consulate pays for the bodies of Tunisian nationals in Germany to be sent back for burials. A, who came to Berlin at 18 as a student, gave up his Turkish passport to become German.  As an entrepreneur he&#8217;s eager to launch projects in Turkey and maybe even retire there one day, but is limited without citizenship.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">After months of not seeing each other, H and I finally find time last November for one of our Sunday coffee dates. H arrives to the Italian cafe in an uncharacteristically bulky sweater that makes me raise my eyebrows. Shortly after ordering our lattes and chocolate cake, she spills the beans: she and A have gotten married, and she&#8217;s newly pregnant. The religious ceremony was held at their apartment with an Imam presiding and a handful of their closest friends and siblings present. H&#8217;s parents chose not to return early from their vacation in Tunisia to attend. As for their upcoming grandchild, wherever he or she decides to be &#8220;<em>really</em> from&#8221;, they are still in the dark.</p>
<p><em> &#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong> </em></p>
<p><em>&#8220;A&#8221; requested that this article remain anonymous, in order to not further weaken his cause, should H&#8217;s parents somehow come across it.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: Ali for (and from) Germany</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/09/02/interview-ali-for-and-from-germany/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2014 08:27:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3183</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the wake of Germany's World Cup victory, much has been said about a renewed sense of German patriotism and its implications. While some have feared a connection to Germany's dark past, others have welcomed the discourse as a chance to shape a new sense of belonging within the country's evolving demographics. We've already written something about it here. But what a discussion on national identity means on the personal level is another story. Or rather many stories. Here's one...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the wake of Germany&#8217;s World Cup victory, much has been said about a renewed sense of German patriotism and its implications. While some have feared a connection to Germany&#8217;s dark past, others have welcomed the discourse as a chance to shape a new sense of belonging within the country&#8217;s evolving demographics. We&#8217;ve already written something about it <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/28/world-cup-fever-how-malleable-is-german-identity/">here</a>. But what a discussion on national identity means on the personal level is another story. Or rather many stories. Here&#8217;s one.</p>
<div id="attachment_3184" style="width: 439px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3184" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3184 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/ali.jpg" alt="Ali für Deutschland " width="429" height="429" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/ali.jpg 429w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/ali-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 429px) 100vw, 429px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3184" class="wp-caption-text">Ali at the Germany-France game at Train Cocktailbar</p></div>
<p>It took Ali <span class="gD">Riza Gürbüz over 30 years to feel welcome in Germany. Originally from East Anatolia, Ali moved to Berlin at age 12 with his brother and sister. His mother had arrived 8 years prior in 1973 as part of the last wave of guest worker recruitment. She was living in <span class="st">Neukölln and working for a cleaning company</span>. His father stayed behind in Turkey.</span></p>
<p><span class="gD"><em>The beginning wasn&#8217;t easy</em>, Ali recounts. Understanding German society, learning the language, feeling at home&#8230; this all took time. But eventually he gained his footing, finished his schooling, completed an <em>Ausbildung</em> (apprenticeship), and in 1986, began a career in industrial mechanics. Today, he&#8217;s married, has a 12 year old daughter and an active social life, and makes music in his free time. He still lives in N<span class="st">eukölln. </span><br />
</span></p>
<p><span class="gD"><strong>But despite spending the majority of his life in Germany, having German citizenship, and making a home here, he&#8217;s often felt like an outsider.</strong> </span></p>
<p><em>I still don&#8217;t really have any German friends</em>, Ali tells me on the last night of Ramadan in July, after breaking the fast together. We&#8217;re sitting outside on Kreuzberg&#8217;s iconic <span class="st"><em>Oranienstraße</em></span> with his friends, also both named Ali, both German-Turks* born in Berlin. Ali and Ali nod their heads in agreement. A rollerblading demonstration passes by in front of us. <em>I don&#8217;t understand it,</em> Ali says. <em>We all have the same sources of stress &#8211; work, money, family &#8211; so why don&#8217;t we make more of an effort to be nice to one another? </em></p>
<div id="attachment_3358" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3358" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3358 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis-650x473.jpg" alt="Breaking the fast on Oranienstraße" width="650" height="473" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis-650x473.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis-300x218.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3358" class="wp-caption-text">Breaking the fast on Oranienstraße</p></div>
<p><span class="gD">Ali can cite the definitive moment in which he felt that he had finally &#8220;arrived&#8221; in Germany. <em>I was in the Bundeswehrkrankenhaus [German Armed Forces hospital] last December for a week due to a skin issue. I received such kind and affectionate treatment from the nurses and doctors. The same treatment as everyone else. I shared a room with a guy named Wolfgang, and we talked for two days straight, about everything. The atmosphere made me feel really welcome and inspired.</em></span></p>
<p>So inspired, that he started writing a song on his phone while still on his hospital bed. Two days after he was released, he finished &#8220;Ali <span class="st">für</span> Deutschland&#8221; (literally &#8220;Ali for Germany&#8221;), a World Cup song in <span class="gD">support of the </span>German national team. After recording it, Ali ran around to different departments and bureaus in the city, asking for support. Eventually he got a production company to film it for free. The song is available for purchase online (99 cents on iTunes) and half of the proceeds go to a homeless shelter in his neighborhood.<em> I really believed in the song and project, </em>Ali explains, <em>I wanted to show that someone who has my name and looks like me supports the German team. That people from all over the world with different backgrounds live here and consider it their home. </em><em><br />
</em></p>
<p><strong>Ali <span class="st">für</span> Deutschland Music Video: </strong></p>
<p><iframe width="650" height="366" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Mzqz6hCF7uI?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>Singing alongside Ali in the music video is his daughter. <em>I see that she&#8217;s growing up differently than I did, that she&#8217;s happier. I hope this song contributes to that. </em>For Ali, it all comes back to the media. <em>When Mesut Özil [German-Turkish football player] makes a good play, German-Turkish kids get patted on the back. If he does poorly, people shake their heads at us. The migration background is always emphasized. </em></p>
<p>Ali&#8217;s point is backed by research. <a href="http://www.stern.de/panorama/stern-umfrage-knappe-mehrheit-lehnt-islam-als-teil-deutschlands-ab-2128967.html">A recent Stern poll</a> shows that over half of Germans believe that Islam does not belong in German society. <a href="http://mediendienst-integration.de/artikel/der-islam-gehoert-zu-deutschland-spielhaus.html">Experts</a> argue that Islam is often conflated with Turks, the headscarf, and migration due to images perpetuated in the media. Another common image: German-Turkish or Arab youth as more violent or prone to criminal acts than their &#8220;native&#8221; counterparts, a stereotype repeatedly rebuked by <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/schulspiegel/wissen/kriminalitaet-von-migranten-laut-gutachten-nicht-hoeher-a-983536.html">studies</a>. <em>There are so many positive examples of what German-Turks have done and do for this country</em>, Ali says,<em> but news and social media continuously choose to show negative images. I want the media to show more positive images. </em><em><br />
</em></p>
<p>Ali is a positive person by nature. His face lights up when he shares stories of making connections to people at work or through his music. But he also has plenty of examples of feeling unwelcome or misunderstood on account of his background. He makes a conscious effort to speak Turkish with his daughter only at home and German out in public, in order to avoid judgment. More than once he&#8217;s been told &#8220;Du bist mein Lieblingst<span class="st">ürke</span><em>&#8221; </em>(&#8220;You&#8217;re my favorite Turk&#8221;), by a coworker or a club bouncer, for not stirring up trouble. <em>What am I supposed to do with that?</em> Ali asks, his eyes filling with emotion. Recently, a colleague joked to Ali that the reason his work contract was not renewed was because of his new hairstyle. <em>You look like a Turk now</em>, he told Ali.</p>
<p>After 6 years at the company, successfully training incoming employees, Ali had expected to keep his job. <em>After the video, they told me my music was making me slower at work, which wasn&#8217;t true,</em> Ali says, shaking his head<em>. <strong>I always felt like they were waiting for me to explode, to show my &#8220;Turkish temper&#8221;. In the end I think they just couldn&#8217;t deal with my humanness.</strong></em></p>
<div id="attachment_3359" style="width: 579px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3359" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-3359" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/alitsm.jpg" alt="Performing at a Football Academy Gala, August 2014" width="569" height="335" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/alitsm.jpg 569w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/alitsm-300x176.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 569px) 100vw, 569px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3359" class="wp-caption-text">Performing at a Football Academy Gala, August 2014</p></div>
<p>Ali is disappointed but not disheartened. He is taking this unexpected turn as a chance to reconsider career paths. <em>I have so much experience, and I want to use that to do something good</em>, he says. He&#8217;s now thinking seriously about becoming a social worker for kids with migration backgrounds. <em>I know </em><em>what they&#8217;re going through.</em> <em>I can go into their homes and talk to their parents, help them see what options they have and make sure they don&#8217;t give up. </em>More than likely, he&#8217;ll do it with music. <em>I learned early on that music allows you to reach a lot of people. Music is its own language, one that you don&#8217;t need to understand, just feel.</em></p>
<p>Ali is certainly &#8220;for&#8221; Germany, but does he consider himself from Germany? <em>Whew,</em> Ali lets out a deep breath, <em>I&#8217;m not sure. I have parts of German culture and parts of Turkish culture. But I think, most of all, I&#8217;m a Berliner.</em></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>*The term German-Turk is a hyphenation often used for people born and/or raised in Germany with 2nd or 3rd generation Turkish backgrounds. For more on language, migration, and identity, see our article <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">here</a>.</p>
<p>For German interviews with Ali, click <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/video/ali-fuer-deutschland-deutsch-tuerke-nimmt-wm-song-auf-video-1500438.html">here</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kGYNujx3RvQ">here</a>.</p>
<p><em>All of Ali&#8217;s quotes have been translated/paraphrased by Sophia Burton.<br />
</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: the Klezmer Gentiles</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2014 09:55:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Holocaust]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jewish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[memory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Poland]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2468</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[International artists in Berlin occupy a semi-privileged position, able to ask critical questions of society without being publicly rebuked. An example of such an artist is Soliman Lawrence. Soli has been photographing the memorialization of Jewish culture in Poland for years, following the tracks of a new form of engagement with the past, as enacted by a more recent generation of Poles. In contrast to Poland, Germany now has its fair share of Jews. What might this mean for memory and its rituals?...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>An interview is never one-sided &#8211; in fact, it is a constructive conversation. I am as much a part of this piece as the artist who answered my questions. Without the contributions of the other, individual statements would hold little significance. So thanks, Soli, for letting me share our conversation. </em></p>
<p>International artists in Berlin are one category of newcomers who, although shaping the cultural politics and economic fabric of Berlin perhaps more than other groups of foreign residents (those without German citizenship), are often left out of the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/11/integration-in-berlin-research-for-a-desolate-landscape/">critical integration debate</a>. Whether or not they learn German or German constitutional law seems to matter little to the politicians and journalists fueling the heavily institutionalized, assimilating discourse. I have yet to meet an artist who has been pressured by the authorities to &#8216;integrate&#8217; him or herself, as is the case with members of different social and economic groups.</p>
<p>This semi-privileged position has its benefits: Berlin&#8217;s creatives are often able to ask critical questions of society without being publicly rebuked, far enough from local history to recognize nuance and apply cultural critique in a non-threatening fashion.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2684 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>An example of such an artist is an old friend <a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/">Soliman Lawrence</a>. Soli has been photographing the memorialization of Jewish culture in Poland for years, following the tracks of a new form of engagement with the past, as enacted by a more recent generation of Poles. His collection of work is titled &#8220;<a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/unquietplacesphoto.html">For those whose faith has been broken</a>&#8220;. They do so, as Soliman&#8217;s stories and their pictures explain, through ritual, one example of which is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Klezmer">Klezmer</a> music. The fascinating part of this story: there are few Jews to speak of in Poland.</p>
<p>Beyond a revived Klezmer tradition, Soliman photographs reconstructed synagogues, Jewish-themed festivals, hand-made figurines, the maintenance of Jewish cemeteries &#8211; all weaving a tale of things past, now re-born as an ode to matzo ball soup or rabbinical characters.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2681 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland" width="640" height="423" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11-300x198.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11-650x429.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>Soliman is not Jewish, though his choice of topic likely gets many thinking that personal biography must inform the interest. I met with Soliman at a little cafe in Neukölln to talk art, history, and memory. Parallels between German memorialization of Jewish culture in Berlin and that which is happening in Poland were not at the tip of his tongue; these parallels were on the tip of mine, however.</p>
<p>Soliman is American by passport, has been a Berlin resident for more than 8 years, making the nationality question a bit tricky. He studied philosophy in the United States, stems originally from the Northern part of Florida, and has a contemplative way about him &#8211; he seems to move slowly, take things in and digest them before forming an opinion.</p>
<p>His artistic career began with a camera, has now evolved into a sort of philosophical exploration of what it means to remember. <em>Memory is at the center of my work</em>, he tells me, <em>how people remember after something has passed, how they remember together</em>. He is interested in the idea of <em><a href="http://www.postmemory.net/">post-memory</a>, the ways in which memory stays alive without the original witnesses</em>. Photography serves a crucial purpose, documentation allowing for connection.</p>
<p>Soliman first started making trips to Poland in 2006, visiting the growing Klezmer festivals in places like Krakaw. <em>Here is the biggest and best festival in Poland</em>, he tells me. I imagine VW buses jammed full with young, alternative Poles, spending warm nights outdoors, not for the beat of electronic sounds but for renditions of clarinet and fiddle. Actually, <em>it is quite mixed</em>, he tells me: young/old, hip/not.</p>
<p><em>When I first showed up in Krakaw, I was taking pictures of everything. I assumed a lot of the stuff I was photographing had something to do with Antisemitism &#8211; graffiti on the walls somehow looked antisemitic to me, these little tiles in the main square with five-pointed stars</em>, <em>for example</em>, he says with a laugh. <em>Then I realized that these stars were actually six-pointed, so </em>not <em>necessarily</em> <em>antisemitic</em>. <em>Very often, one finds what one searches for</em>, I add. This is even more true for a photographer, able to capture and catalog what may be happenstance occurrence, curating images into some sort of narrative about a people or place.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2682 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>That doesn&#8217;t mean that Antisemitism isn&#8217;t present in Polish society, however: <em>it&#8217;s complicated</em>, he says. An interview with Soliman on Jewish memorial culture in Poland appeared in 2012 in <em>die</em> <i>Zeit Online </i>with the headline: &#8220;<em>Wie Nicht-Juden die jüdische Kultur Polens wiederbeleben/</em> &#8220;<a href="http://www.zeit.de/video/2012-12/2032360755001/holocaust-wie-nicht-juden-die-juedische-kultur-polens-wiederbeleben">How Non-Jews Are Resurrecting Poland&#8217;s Jewish Culture</a>&#8220;. I recall watching the interview then, having heard of the beginnings of his Polish adventures back in 2010, when Soli and I first met, and being struck by the oddity of it all, the sense of a manufactured experience to take the place of an entire culture now lost. And yet, it was impossible not to find parallels with the city we both share, I felt: the way in which memory of Jewish culture in Berlin is fractured between recreations of the diaspora experience, a come-back Jewish culture in Germany, and a newer wave of young Israelis.</p>
<p>Soli has given quite a number of interviews in Germany since his project first began to receive attention. A <a href="http://juedische-woche-dresden.de/veranstaltung-2013/items/108.html">recent exhibition of his work in Dresden</a> put him into more contact with the German media. <em>So, did any of these journalists ask about your thoughts on Jewish memorialization in Germany, in Berlin, or on any similarities between Poland and Germany?</em>, I ask. At first, he doesn&#8217;t understand my question, seems a bit perplexed. Then, <em>No</em>,<em> in fact, no one even got close to formulating that question. Interesting that you bring that up. </em></p>
<p>Jewish culture in Berlin is diffuse, hard to put a finger on, as &#8211; with Jews everywhere &#8211; there is no one way to be Jewish and certainly no one way to be Jewish in Berlin. A memorial culture is also difficult to construct, when Jews are in fact present. To boot, there is no <em>one</em> way to memorialize the Holocaust and the thriving Jewish culture in Germany that preceded it. At least no one way that would satisfy the diverse groups who were affected by the genocide. In Poland, very little has happened at an institutional, top-down level. And so revivals of classic Ashkenazi traditions like Klezmer have been a means of memorializing a lost sector of Polish life, many years after its musicians were made to disappear.</p>
<p><em>At my first Klezmer festival, I didn&#8217;t really know what to do with myself. People were dancing, it was celebratory, there was this feeling of community</em>, he says. He was a bit stand-offish, not understanding why active participation was required. <em>This is the ritual</em>, he explains, <em>it is through such a collective ritual that some form of memory is reconstructed and created for the next generation.</em> <em>Many of these young people probably have no real connection to contemporary Jewish people</em>, he adds,<em> but this type of memory doesn&#8217;t require personal connection, rather an attachment to space and a desire to make a place &#8211; a memorial &#8211; out of it.</em></p>
<p>In Berlin, there is a strong attention to memorial sites or objects &#8211; the <a href="http://www.stolpersteine-berlin.de/en/stolpersteine"><em>Stolpersteine</em></a>, <a href="http://www.holocaust-mahnmal.de/en"><em>Memorial to the Murdered Jews of Europe</em></a>, <a href="http://www.slowtravelberlin.com/touching-berlins-ghosts/"><em>Bayerisches Viertel</em></a>, to name a few. These are spaces that are visited and even organized by many but are perhaps not as interactive or collective as a Klezmer ritual. One might simply pass by its insignia, whereas Klezmer is somehow a more active process, Soli explains.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2685 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9-300x199.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9-650x432.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p><em>But are these Klezmer festivals in Poland really about remembering and mourning the Holocaust? </em>I ask. <em>Yes, it is about that but not only about that.</em> <em>It is about thinking about the Jews that were once here, by people who were too young to have had the chance</em>.</p>
<p>There is a tendency<em> </em>in memorializing activities to focus on objects and their stories; materiality is desired, physical connection reconstructed. The Holocaust documentation and education center where I used to work curated a collection called &#8220;<a href="http://www.wsherc.org/museum/everyday-objects">Everyday Objects</a>&#8220;, the National Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM) releases <a href="http://www.ushmm.org/information/exhibitions/curators-corner">weekly stories online from its archival vault of objects</a>, and even the recent <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/sportingscene/2014/04/memory-objects-commemorating-the-boston-marathon-bombings.html?utm_source=dlvr.it&amp;utm_medium=twitter">Boston Marathon bombings are being actively commemorated through the collection of ordinary things</a>.</p>
<p><em>When talking with journalists, they just don&#8217;t really understand why Klezmer music is so popular in Poland, </em>Soli comments, as if to emphasize the stark differences between the German memory process and that of the Poland he knows:<em> Memory is expressed differently across space.</em> <em>My work is about these different memory ways, memory forms. </em></p>
<p>Surprising to many, Berlin is home to a fair number of Jews, and not just returned German Jews or those that fled from the former Soviet Union, but Israeli Jews, secular Israelis, secular Diaspora Jews from Argentina etc. &#8211; colliding in one city, not necessarily finding community among one another, because why should they? To make the argument, however, that perhaps things aren&#8217;t as different as they seem, I add that one does see a sort of stereotypical Jewish culture in Berlin, from the <a href="http://www.exberliner.com/locations/luigi-zuckermann-deli/">classic deli</a><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> </span>serving pastrami sandwiches to the local bagel shop. Both places in mind are not run by anyone of Jewish heritage, catering to a historic Jewish culture, perhaps even to New York Jewry rather than Berlin. This is not to say that there are no Jewish delis or bagel shops in Berlin that are owned by Jews. <em>But might the more theatrical recreations be a form of memorial culture, similar to Klezmer festivals?</em> I ask. <em>Maybe</em>, he says, <em>but I know a  few Israelis, and they don&#8217;t necessarily eat bagels. They go to this one shop on </em>Sonnenallee<em> where they can get hummus served warm, like back home in Israel</em>.</p>
<p>The varied layers of Jewish culture, identity, and memory in the Berlin landscape prevent one from making any static comparison to the situation in Poland, it seems &#8211; a place with very few Jews to speak of and a history wrought with a non-institutionalized form of memory, at least until recently. The Israeli and general Jewish presence in Berlin further complicates a comparison between the memory culture of Poland and that of Berlin in a very real sense. To be the authors of a tradition that re-appropriates Jewish tradition means being responsible for potential misappropriation. In Poland, I doubt there are too many active members of the Jewish community who would heavily criticize the rebirth of Klezmer in this form. <em>There aren&#8217;t</em>, Soli says.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2683 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>If he feels strange about researching this issue as an American artist without Jewish descent &#8211; <em>No</em>. The Holocaust is a large part of how Americans understand Germany, I add, in order validate his work from a place of personal opinion. The past was certainly a key factor in my own interest in contemporary German politics and society, as my <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/">article on Sachsenhausen</a> demonstrates.</p>
<p>The question is, if such a connection between a bleak past and curious future can be made, productively, and with much room for nuance and reflection. Soliman Lawrence&#8217;s work allows for just that. Like other artists, he is able to describe memory ways as they are occurring, not overtly criticizing but allowing others to draw their own conclusions or parallels.</p>
<p>We all remember differently. The most important thing is simply to remember.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>Jewish identity in Berlin, Jews in Germany, Israelis in Berlin: there is no shortage of debate, public presence, or diversity. Here a recent <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/culture/2014/05/so-long-israel-hello-berlin.html">article from <em>The New Yorker</em></a> on this topic and a few articles from us, written from the most varied of positions:</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/">Why Remembering the Holocaust is Good for Immigrants</a> &#8211; integration policy and a visit to Sachsenhausen concentration camp</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/07/rant-or-rave-jew-in-a-box/">Rant or Rave? Jew in a Box</a> &#8211; a controversial exhibit at the Berlin Jewish Museum</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">Interview: TV, the Treasury Minister, and Third Culture Kids</a> &#8211; Israeli in Berlin</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/07/interview-three-dimensions-of-integration/">Interview: Three Dimensions of Integration</a> &#8211; Jewish-American artist in Berlin</p>
<p>Last but not least, a few links for finding that Jewish deli or that Israeli hummus: <a href="http://www.berlinfo.com/Lifetime/Shopping/food/jewish/, http://forward.com/articles/165718/berlins-jewish-comeback/?p=al">Berlins Jewish Comeback</a>, <a href="//www.hagalil.com/deutschland/berlin/gemeinde/kosher.htm">Hagalil</a>, <a href="http://www.jewish-berlin.com/kosher.php">Jewish-Berlin</a>, <a href="http://www.berlinjewish.com/tips-for-your-berlin-vacation">Jewish in Berlin</a>, <a href="http://www.exberliner.com/food/land-of-the-lox-can-you-get-deli-food-in-berlin/">ExBerliner deli food list</a>.</p>
<p><em>All images were graciously provided by Soliman Lawrence as part of the series &#8220;<a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/unquietplacesphoto.html">For those whose faith has been broken</a>&#8220;. To see some of Soliman&#8217;s newer projects, check out his homepage. </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Seeing Berlin Through The Homeless</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2014 12:22:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bureaucracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GDR-DDR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitte]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Schöneberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2398</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[They wait for the subway doors to close before they address the car with a rehearsed speech. "Excuse the interruption, I am one of Berlin's annoying homeless people"... it usually begins, as they peddle newspapers and scan the crowd for an outstretched hand holding change or food. The majority of us keep our hands tucked away or firmly gripping our phones. Some of us fall into convenient bouts of exhaustion, promptly leaning back and closing our eyes. In this moment, we are restricted to a shared space...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_2604" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2604" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2604 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-650x433.jpg" alt="hermannplatz" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2604" class="wp-caption-text">Photo by Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>In Berlin they are especially visible on the <em>Bahn</em>. They wait for the subway doors to close before they address the car with a rehearsed speech. <em>Excuse the interruption, I am one of Berlin&#8217;s annoying homeless people&#8230;</em> it usually begins, as they peddle newspapers and scan<em> </em>the crowd for an outstretched hand holding change or food. The majority of us keep our hands tucked away or firmly gripping our phones. Some of us fall into convenient bouts of exhaustion, promptly leaning back and closing our eyes. In this moment, we are restricted to a moving car, a shared space. We can&#8217;t dodge a corner or cross the street, but we still find ways to make them invisible. We don&#8217;t look up because we feel uncomfortable. We become frustrated at them for making us feel this way. We may even become angry &#8211; at them, at society, at ourselves.</p>
<p>How the simple presence of one person can incite so much emotion, judgement, and shame.</p>
<p>How it must feel, to be simultaneously so visible and invisible.</p>
<div id="attachment_2605" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2605" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2605 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-650x459.jpg" alt="eye" width="650" height="459" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-650x459.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-300x212.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2605" class="wp-caption-text">Photo by Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><em>It&#8217;s one of the worst things for homeless people, being treated as invisible. Answer them when they speak to you, make eye contact, acknowledge them!</em> our guide Carsten Voss urges us by the end of our walk. We are wrapping up a tour called &#8220;Obdachslose zeigen ihr Berlin&#8221; (The homeless present their Berlin), run by non-profit organization <em>Querstadtein. </em>The group offers tours in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Mitte that show the reality of homelessness in the city.</p>
<p>Our guide speaks from personal experience. Decked out in designer glasses and a well-fitting sweater, it&#8217;s challenging to picture this man as the subject of the powerful story he delivers in front of stately <span class="st">Viktoria-Luise-Platz</span>. Carsten worked 80+ hours a week as a manager of an international tradeshow before burning-out and falling into depression. First came the loss of his job, then his apartment. He refused help from loved ones, other than taking refuge in a friend&#8217;s shed for a few months. It would be a year before he clawed his way back out. He cites one defining moment: <em>I happened to glance into someone&#8217;s window from the street. The woman was cooking and the man was watching </em>Tagesschau<em> on TV&#8230; I realized that if I didn&#8217;t make a change then, I would never have that again.</em></p>
<p>That year Carsten counted among Berlin&#8217;s estimated 4,000 <em>Obdachslose</em> (literally translates to &#8220;without shelter&#8221;). Not to be confused with <em>Wohnungslose</em> (&#8220;house-less&#8221;), which refers to those without homes but still in the system, <em>Obdachslose</em> are no longer in the system and may or may not have a place to sleep. Berlin has Germany&#8217;s highest concentration of <em>Obdachslose, </em>both from within and outside of the country.</p>
<p><em>There are three main categories of </em>Obdachslose <em>in Berlin</em>, Carsten explains early on in the tour. <em>Former refugees from East Germany, those groups of young people who usually have dogs with them, and immigrants.<br />
</em></p>
<p><a href="http://ec.europa.eu/social/main.jsp?catId=1061&amp;langId=en">Migrant homelessness throughout the EU</a> has risen in recent years, exacerbated by the economic crisis. This may come as no great surprise, though it&#8217;s a blow to hear that many in Berlin<em> end up staying because they find the conditions of being homeless here better than their lives back home. </em>Carsten describes this group in three geographic waves: the first from Poland, second from the Baltics, and third from Bulgaria and Romania<em>. Of course they came here planning to find jobs, start families, create a life. Some make it, but many don&#8217;t. </em></p>
<div id="attachment_2586" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-23-14-33-35.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2586" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2586 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-23-14-33-35.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-23 14.33.35" width="640" height="480" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2586" class="wp-caption-text">Cold Weather Assistance for Berlin&#8217;s Homeless by District, Winter 2013/14</p></div>
<p>Berlin has a long tradition of homelessness. It&#8217;s a poor city &#8211; Germany&#8217;s poorest &#8211; but also equipped with robust social services. Berlin has a history of attracting those who are &#8220;different&#8221;, including many immigrants, due to its diversity and tolerant atmosphere. During the days of the Berlin Wall, it was also a haven for males escaping military conscription (which ended altogether in 2011). Carsten moved to Berlin for this reason, and says he and many others like him entered fields like social work and education. This, he claims, has contributed to the city&#8217;s liberal nature and strong social net.</p>
<p>Berlin&#8217;s homeless tend to cluster in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Charlottenburg, two districts in West Berlin now more associated with high rents and artisanal cafes than alternative lifestyles. Carsten guides us to Nollendorfplatz, Berlin&#8217;s LGBT hub and site of the annual pride parade, Christopher Street Day. We stand across from the colorful <em>Regenbogen-Stele, </em>a r<span class="userContent">ainbow column erected in 2000 to celebrate the area&#8217;s high concentration of homosexual residents and open-minded atmosp<span class="text_exposed_show">here. The statue itself carries two symbols: the rainbow flag for gay pride and the <em>Rosa Winkel</em>, a pink badge first used by Nazis to distinguish homosexuals in concentration camps, and what later became an international symbol for gay rights.<br />
</span></span></p>
<div id="attachment_2507" style="width: 538px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/2014-03-23-14-21-00-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2507" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2507" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/2014-03-23-14-21-00-1.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-23 14.21.00-1" width="528" height="528" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2507" class="wp-caption-text">Nollendorf Platz&#8217;s &#8220;Regenbogen-Stele&#8221; or rainbow column celebrating gay rights</p></div>
<p>As we inspect the square, Carsten points out what our untrained eyes fail to see: a 24-hour grocery store well-equipped with bottle deposit machines, a van selling the street newspaper, a well-lit intersection. <em>Homeless people are part of this neighborhood, they have a community here</em>, he says.</p>
<p>But another faction of the city&#8217;s homeless blend in so well that we don&#8217;t see them at all. <em>Most people have an image in mind of the bag lady (or guy), unkempt and dirty, pushing around a cart filled to the brim with random items, muttering crazy things to themselves.</em>.<em>. most homeless people don&#8217;t look or act like that. </em> Carsten estimates that 60% fall into this category, homeless people who look &#8220;normal&#8221; so they can use spaces and services within the city without being noticed. They schedule their day in such a way that they always have a place to be, something to eat, even a bed to sleep in. They know when the citizens&#8217; office opens and when they can grab a shower, when they can rest in the library or supermarket, who is offering a free lunch or haircut in the city. <em>It&#8217;s an exhausting life, they have to be very organized, and they are constantly in public</em>, Carsten emphasizes: <em>the only time they have to themselves is in the shower.</em></p>
<div id="attachment_2621" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-24-08-25-20.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2621" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2621 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-24-08-25-20.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-24 08.25.20" width="640" height="480" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2621" class="wp-caption-text">Assistance notice for homeless youth in Charlottenburg</p></div>
<p>Carsten&#8217;s happy ending is a welcome take-away from an otherwise harrowing topic, but he warns against the assumption that all homeless people are unhappy or need to be saved. While many do suffer from mental illness and drug and alcohol abuse, others have deliberately chosen this lifestyle. <em>Some people want to live this way, and we have to respect that. We have to recognize them as part of society.</em></p>
<p><span class="userContent"><span class="text_exposed_show">It&#8217;s easy to dodge corners and cross streets, to switch subway cars to avoid someone&#8217;s stench or words, to grip our phones and look down. </span></span></p>
<p>It&#8217;s not as easy to look up.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>The Querstadtein homeless tours (in German) take place in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Mitte, usually on Sundays and for approximately 2 hours. Tickets cost <span class="st">€</span>9,40, and <span class="st">€</span>5,40 for students, seniors, and individuals on welfare. More information can be found at <em>http://querstadtein.org/de/stadtfuehrungen/.<br />
</em></p>
<p>For more on the Querstadtein tours in English, click <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/zeitgeist/berlin-tour-gives-a-glimpse-of-berlin-as-seen-by-homeless-people-a-913758.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>For more on the increasing restrictions on public space for homeless people across Europe, <a href="http://www.surveillance-and-society.org/articles5%283%29/homelessness.pdf">click here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: The Taxi Driver</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2014 14:00:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kurdistan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2314</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Orhan was 5 when his father moved to Berlin in 1972. It was only one year before West Germany would halt guest worker recruitment from non-European countries to fill labor shortages after World War II. His mother followed 7 years later with his youngest sister and they lived in Rudow in southeastern Neukölln - where they still live over 30 years later. "They got jobs as cleaners in an office," Orhan recounts, "but they were fired!" he adds, snorting in laughter.  I look up from my notepad, surprised...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Had I hopped into Orhan&#8217;s taxi en route to the airport, I likely would&#8217;ve assumed he was Turkish and left it at that. He might have asked me where I was flying to and I might have commented on the weather. He would&#8217;ve pulled my suitcase out of the trunk and wished me a good flight, and I would&#8217;ve thanked him. But instead, thankfully, I met Orhan in a very different context &#8211; our half-marathon training group. What follows here is his story about growing up in Kurdistan and Turkey as the child of guest workers and moving to Berlin 20 years ago. The story I would&#8217;ve likely missed. </em></p>
<div id="attachment_2377" style="width: 588px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/2014-03-30-09-50-36-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2377" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2377" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/2014-03-30-09-50-36-1.jpg?w=640" alt="Orhan and Sophia pre 2014 Berlin half marathon" width="578" height="578" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/2014-03-30-09-50-36-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/2014-03-30-09-50-36-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 578px) 100vw, 578px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2377" class="wp-caption-text">Orhan and I pre-race 2014</p></div>
<p>I meet Orhan at Fehrbelliner Platz&#8217;s Park <span class="st">Café</span>. We choose a table outside amongst the masses soaking up the unusually warm March sun. It&#8217;s that strange break between afternoon and evening,  the mood equally fitting for a coffee or beer. The space is buzzing but in a state of exhalation, as the day starts to settle and everyone&#8217;s shoulders wilt a few centimeters. This is where Orhan spends every Thursday between 4:45 and 6pm, while his daughter takes a kickboxing class around the corner.</p>
<p>My first order of business is a selfish one: though I&#8217;ve asked Orhan multiple times to tell me where he grew up, I still can&#8217;t remember the name, let alone comprehend its location geographically. Orhan draws me a little diagram: he grew up in <em>Hotan</em>, a tiny village near a town called <em>Varto</em>, part of a district called <span class="st"><em>Mûş</em></span> that lies in Anatolia, in the predominantly Kurdish southeastern part of Turkey.</p>
<div id="2330" style="width: 582px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://geopoliticsrst.blogspot.de/2012/10/turkei.html"><img aria-describedby="caption-2330" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2330 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/mapkurdistan.jpg" alt="Kurdistan on a map " width="572" height="447" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/mapkurdistan.jpg 572w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/mapkurdistan-300x234.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 572px) 100vw, 572px" /></a><p id="caption-2330" class="wp-caption-text">Varto is slightly northeast of Diyarbakir, the unofficial capital of Turkish Kurdistan</p></div>
<p>Orhan was 5 when his father moved to Berlin in 1972. It was only one year before West Germany would halt guest worker recruitment from non-European countries to fill labor shortages after World War II. His mother followed 7 years later with his youngest sister and they lived in Rudow in southeastern Neukölln &#8211; where they still live over 30 years later. <em>They got jobs as cleaners in an office</em>, Orhan recounts, <em>but they were fired!</em> he adds, snorting in laughter.  I look up from my notepad, surprised. &#8220;Why is that funny?&#8221; <em>Well, they worked with friends &#8211; they&#8217;d moved to Berlin together &#8211; and one of the guys was really funny. So they were always fooling around and making noise..</em>.<em> and one day they got fired! That guy was a real comedian.<br />
</em></p>
<p>Orhan only heard that story years later. He had stayed behind in Kurdistan, in the village with his grandmother. <em>My father didn&#8217;t plan on staying that long, like most guest workers</em>, Orhan explains,<em> but my mom eventually went, too, and my Oma became my main mom. She ended up raising me. </em>After school, Orhan did an apprenticeship in wood-making<em>. It was a 6km walk to work from Oma&#8217;s every day, alone, sometimes in 1m of snow. I was always scared the wolves would get me! </em></p>
<div id="attachment_2368" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/gallery_0610222020109423828131.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2368" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-2368" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/gallery_0610222020109423828131.jpg?w=640" alt="Portrait of a Kurdish woman (Source: Renkliisler)" width="640" height="648" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2368" class="wp-caption-text">Portrait of a Kurdish woman in Varto (Source: Renkliisler)</p></div>
<p>In the 1980s, Orhan&#8217;s parents used money earned in Germany to buy land and build a house in Izmir, on Turkey&#8217;s western coast. Orhan switched from wood-making to electrician work, and got a factory job making stoves. His remaining siblings (of which there are 5 total) started to join his parents in Berlin, applying for visas and leaving one by one. Orhan applied too, but his request was denied. German family reunification policy* has a 16 year old age limit for third country (non EU) nationals to join their parents in Germany. After age 15, other factors apply for a residence permit, such as German language proficiency and the &#8220;ability to integrate&#8221;. Orhan was already in his 20s. So he stayed in Izmir, looking after the house and spending summers in the village with his grandmother and uncle. Then came 1993, when <em>Hotan </em>and many other Kurdish villages were destroyed in a war between Turkish government forces and Kurdish rebels. The war, called &#8220;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/24/world/kurds-are-finally-heard-turkey-burned-our-villages.html">one of the most violent secrets of the 1990&#8217;s</a>&#8220;, killed more than 30,000 and displaced thousands more.</p>
<p>Orhan&#8217;s chance to go to Germany came shortly thereafter. <em>My boss asked me to go to Germany to fix a faulty order we had exported there&#8230; they needed someone who spoke a little German. </em>It was Orhan&#8217;s first trip to Germany, and by the time he returned, he had decided to try moving there again. <em>Since I had gotten a visa for the work trip and come back, I had earned the Embassy&#8217;s trust</em>, Orhan chuckles, <em>it was much easier to apply for a visa the next time.</em> On December 10, 1994, Orhan left Turkey with a 3 month visa. Upon arrival in Germany he applied for asylum. He was 27.</p>
<p>He was sent to an asylum home outside Berlin in <span class="st">Eisenhüttenstadt, Brandenburg</span>. <em>We were fed three times a day and the workers were pretty nice to us, but the conditions weren&#8217;t great&#8230; 7 or 8 of us sleeping together in one room. </em>For a year, Orhan spent one night every two weeks there to comply with policy.<em> They knew my family was in Berlin&#8230; I spent the rest of the time with them. </em>Orhan&#8217;s asylum request was eventually granted, on the grounds that his hometown in Kurdistan had been destroyed. <em><br />
</em></p>
<div id="2341" style="width: 618px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article123743604/Asylbewerberheim-in-Eisenhuettenstadt.html"><img aria-describedby="caption-2341" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2341 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/asylbewerberheim-in-eisenhuettenstadt.jpg" alt="asylum home in Eisenhuettenstadt" width="608" height="405" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/asylbewerberheim-in-eisenhuettenstadt.jpg 620w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/asylbewerberheim-in-eisenhuettenstadt-300x199.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px" /></a><p id="caption-2341" class="wp-caption-text">Asylum seekers arrive to Eisenhüttenstadt (Source: Die Welt)</p></div>
<p>This was in the mid-1990s, a decade before Germany would officially recognize itself as a country of immigration and develop a <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">national integration plan that included integration courses for newcomers</a>. Orhan signed up for a language course on his own, hoping to learn enough German to study economics at university. He quit after 3 months. <em>It wasn&#8217;t fun and always after work</em><em>, when I was so tired </em>(he did construction at the time)<em>. </em><em>The grammar was really hard. It&#8217;s still hard.<br />
</em></p>
<p>A cousin&#8217;s <span class="st">fiancé</span> suggested he try being a taxi driver. <em>I failed my taxi license test 3 times because I couldn&#8217;t pronounce the street names correctly!</em> <em>Being a taxi driver is a bit boring but it&#8217;s a clean job. Not like construction. And I like the freedom.</em></p>
<p>Orhan&#8217;s been a taxi driver ever since, working 10 hour days 5-6 days a week. He has two children, a son from his first marriage to a Turkish-German woman and a daughter with his current wife, whom he met at a gym over 10 years ago &#8211; a gym they still attend together. <em>I live a good life here. I travel a lot and I have a flexible job. </em>Orhan tries to go to Kurdistan at least once or twice a year, and has taken his kids 4 times. His next visit is this May. <em><br />
</em></p>
<p><em>My kids have 59% <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">Migrationshintergrund</a>, </em>Orhan says laughing,<em> when I&#8217;m angry with my son I scold him in Turkish, but usually we speak German. He can understand Kurdish, too.</em> <em>I tried speaking Kurdish with my daughter for a year but then gave up,</em> he adds, a hint of regret in his voice.</p>
<p>&#8220;Do you think German integration policy has gotten better since you first arrived here 20 years ago? With services like the integration courses?&#8221; <em>German immigration policy isn&#8217;t very fair</em>, Orhan replies scowling, <em>If I marry someone from Turkey and want to bring them here, they have to prove they speak German before arriving! But people from <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/20/roma-in-berlin-bureaucracy-in-lichtenberg/">Bulgaria and Romania</a>** can just come here and get social benefits even if they don&#8217;t speak the language</em>.</p>
<p><em>I don&#8217;t have German citizenship and I don&#8217;t want it,</em> Orhan declares, <em>why would I need it? </em><em>My wife and I want to buy a house in Izmir and spend maybe one third of the year there. Four months in Berlin, 4 in Izmir, 4 in Kurdistan. There&#8217;s nothing special there, where I&#8217;m from in Kurdistan&#8230; only mountains, animals </em>(the wolves!)<em>, and rocks, but, </em>Orhan makes a fist and holds it close to his stomach, <em>it still feels like home.</em></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Varto">According to Wikipedia</a>, Berlin holds Europe&#8217;s largest population from Varto, Kurdistan. Germany has Europe&#8217;s largest population of Kurds, <a href="http://www.aljazeera.com/video/europe/2013/05/201358161349732897.html">approximately 800,000</a>, many of whom came as guest workers in the 1960s. For more information on the history of this immigrant community (in German), click <a href="http://www.trend.infopartisan.net/trd0299/t090299.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>*For more information on Germany&#8217;s family reunification policy, click <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/dgs/home-affairs/what-we-do/networks/european_migration_network/reports/docs/emn-studies/family-reunification/2._de_emn_ncp_small-scale_study_iv_family_reunification_final_en_version_en.pdf">here</a> and <a href="http://www.expatica.com/de/essentials_moving_to/essentials/German-permits-for-family-reunification_18892.html%20">here</a>.</p>
<p>**Despite being part of the EU since 2007, Bulgarians and Romanians have only had access to Germany&#8217;s social welfare system since 2014, when Germany lifted work policy restrictions. This was after the EU deemed Germany in violation of economic rules of engagement.</p>
<p><em>All photos linked to source. A big thank you to Orhan for his participation!<br />
</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
