<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Language &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/category/language/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Value of Foreign Life: when the law demands &#8220;integration&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/08/25/the-value-of-foreign-life/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2016 11:23:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bundestag]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[language-learning]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4676</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Until now, immigration policy in Germany has followed a pathway defined by residency, employment, and citizenship restrictions. Put another way, policy has been concerned with 3 primary questions: Who is allowed to stay, who is allowed to work, and who is, ultimately, allowed to participate fully in the political process of the Federal Republic. But something changed this past July, when German Parliament passed its first ever law mandating a particular type of immigrant and refugee integration. Source: DPA The new Integrationsgesetz mandates fulfillment of a German principle of social and economic assimilation. This principle has little precedent, in terms of a comprehensive law. There have been expectations and additions to existing legislation in the past, but never has there been governmental action specifically devoted to the question of whether or not newcomers have found ways to fit in. And never has this governmental action been tied to sanctions, if benchmarks and timelines aren&#8217;t met. The new law measures the ability of newcomers to fare well on the basis of language and employment, with respect to natives: They are to learn German, well, within 5 years and become economically self-sufficient as soon as possible. Welfare and other subsidies are tethered to employment programs. Specific to [...]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Until now, immigration policy in Germany has followed a pathway defined by residency, employment, and citizenship restrictions. Put another way, policy has been concerned with 3 primary questions: Who is allowed to stay, who is allowed to work, and who is, ultimately, allowed to participate fully in the political process of the Federal Republic.</p>
<p>But something changed this past July, when <a href="http://www.bmi.bund.de/SharedDocs/Pressemitteilungen/DE/2016/07/integrationsgesetz-vom-bundestag-verabschiedet.html">German Parliament passed its first ever law mandating a particular type of immigrant and refugee integration</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4686" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4686" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4686 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte-650x365.jpeg" alt="fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte" width="650" height="365" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte-650x365.jpeg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte-300x169.jpeg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte.jpeg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fluechtlinge-integration-gesetz-fakten-streitpunkte-310x174.jpeg 310w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4686" class="wp-caption-text">Source: <a href="http://www.bmi.bund.de/SharedDocs/Pressemitteilungen/DE/2016/07/integrationsgesetz-vom-bundestag-verabschiedet.html"> DPA</a></p></div>
<p>The new <em>Integrationsgesetz </em>mandates fulfillment of a German principle of social and economic assimilation. This principle has little precedent, in terms of a comprehensive law. There have been expectations and additions to existing legislation in the past, but never has there been governmental action specifically devoted to the question of whether or not newcomers have found ways to fit in. And never has this governmental action been tied to sanctions, if benchmarks and timelines aren&#8217;t met.</p>
<p>The new law measures the ability of newcomers to fare well on the basis of language and employment, with respect to natives: They are to learn German, well, within 5 years and become economically self-sufficient as soon as possible. Welfare and other subsidies are tethered to employment programs. Specific to refugees, asylum applicants awaiting refugee status will be recruited for low-paying (1 euro/hour) jobs as soon as they are registered with the authorities, no matter the qualifications they bring with them from their home countries.</p>
<p>This approach is known as the welfare-to-work model, popularized by the Clinton administration in the U.S. and implemented in Germany since 2002 in the form of the <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/thema/arbeitslosengeld_ii/">Hartz-IV</a> reforms. <a href="http://99percentinvisible.org/episode/magic-bureaucrat-riverside-miracle/">Research has shown</a> that welfare-to-work programs, rather than re-training newcomers or supporting them while they seek jobs for which they are actually qualified, have serious long-term consequences. Stagnation and even regression is the word.</p>
<p>The integration law presupposes and, indeed, requires a &#8220;help yourself&#8221; attitude. This was precisely the message of the German austerity program of Hartz-IV, forever unpopular among the Left. This correlation between the new integration program and austerity language has led some members of German Parliament to send up flares.</p>
<p>The economist and Green Party representative Brigitte Pothmar <a href="https://www.tagesschau.de/inland/integrationsgesetz-127.html">criticized the intent and scope</a> of the law specifically on the point of low-wage jobs: &#8220;According to its supporters&#8217; own language, the legislature plans to spend 3 million euros on ridding refugees of boredom. But refugees don&#8217;t need occupational therapy. They want to learn and they want to actually get to work!&#8221;</p>
<p>A <a href="https://www.tagesschau.de/inland/integrationsgesetz-127.html">similar critique was wielded </a>by the Left Party representative Sabine Zimmerman, calling the law exclusionary at best. In terms of the economy, in particular, &#8220;This type of work [1 euro jobs] does not provide any opportunity to earn qualifications or to truly learn the language. In effect, it makes it even harder for real opportunities to come about.&#8221;</p>
<p>But it is not only the language of self-help and the threat of stagnation that these parliamentary representatives are worried about. If newcomers are unable to reach German proficiency in 5 years&#8217; time or are unable to maintain employment, residency permits will not be renewed or will be outright denied. Other sanctions, such as restrictions on housing and overall mobility, also apply.</p>
<p>Likewise, those who prove to be &#8220;exceptionally well integrated,&#8221; according to the law&#8217;s system of measurement, will be granted the privilege of ungarnered residency within 5 years. There is a carrot at the end of the integration stick. And it looks a lot like survival.</p>
<p>The media&#8217;s response to the new integration law, as well as that of practitioners in the field, has been swift and strident, criticizing the way in which the word &#8220;integration&#8221; is tied to fundamentals like housing and residency permits. The well-respected German weekly <em>die Zeit </em><a href="http://www.zeit.de/politik/deutschland/2016-05/integrationsgesetz-fluechtlinge-wohnsitz-parlament-meseberg">reported the law&#8217;s final drafting</a> with the headline &#8220;Work better, fail quicker.&#8221; Another well-respected paper, the daily <em>Süddeutsche Zeitung</em>, printed the news with the headline &#8220;An integration law that doesn&#8217;t deserve its name.&#8221;</p>
<p>This new law does intend to simplify and expedite the processing of the many asylum applications Germany continues to receive. For many of the law&#8217;s opponents, this addition of asylum proceeding reform was reason enough to support the law. Yet it may be more restrictive than helpful to those applying for asylum. The <a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article156905294/Unter-einer-Bedingung-koennen-abgelehnte-Asylbewerber-bleiben.html">headline provided by the right-leaning daily</a> <em>die Welt </em>for the new law is telling: &#8220;Asylum-seekers can stay only under one condition.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>Value Judgement</strong></p>
<p>What does this have to do with the title of this article, the value of a foreign life?</p>
<p>Any subject of law, citizen or not, is assigned a particular value, as reflected in and by society. Law most often protects the value of the universal person in that it prevents harm and injustice within the scope of its jurisdiction, no matter the origin of said person. Natives cannot kill tourists or undocumented migrants, for example. This is still a crime.</p>
<p>But this goes both ways. Law is discerning, as are its makers. It can decide when and if certain protections or privileges are granted. In this act of exercising certain judgment, determining who is the recipient and who is not, a value judgement is passed. In the case of Germany&#8217;s new and unprecedented integration law, those who become German in the ways the law prescribes have value enough to stay. Those who fall short do not.</p>
<p>This value judgement is apparent in the language of the law itself, as well as in discussions surrounding it. One example is the usage of the word &#8220;<em>i</em><em>ntegrationsunwillig</em>&#8220;, meaning &#8220;unwilling to integrate.&#8221; Its counterpart, a noun, is <em>Integrationsverweigerung</em>, which takes a stronger tone: It means &#8220;refusal to integrate.&#8221; The subjects who exhibit these traits become subject to the sanctions mentioned above, likely to eventual deportation, thus forfeiture of assets, professional networks, and personal relationships in Germany.</p>
<p>This language makes clear assumptions about intent and character far more than it does about simply the state of things, of whether or not an individual has found him/_/herself to belong in their new home. &#8220;Unwilling&#8221; implies a flouting of both convention and the laws of the land. Cultural difference becomes cultural deviance within this frame, and those who do not fit in effectively become criminals.</p>
<p>The perceived understanding of integration behind this language of &#8220;unwilling&#8221; is most problematic in that it devalues the experience of the newcomer and abdicates the native of certain responsibilities by way of this process.</p>
<p>In other words, what of the many natives who will refuse to grant newcomers a job because of their last name, because of their fear of ISIS or simply of Islam?</p>
<p>What of the slow-moving bureaucracy that will prevent timely and efficient completion of an integration course, or of the notoriously unfriendly bureaucrats who will make registration for state-subsidized language courses or other training programs a painful and humiliating process?</p>
<p>Will the other side, at any point in this hypothetical pathway to official integration, be charged with an unwilling and outright difficult attitude?</p>
<p>The law, by default of its creation, values natives above foreigners. The answers to all the above questions will tend to err on the side of the native for this reason, and responsibility will continue to be a weight born by the weakest, the least valued. These are the immigrants, the asylum-seekers, and the refugees of today.</p>
<p>Germany has done so much good for the refugees of the world in this past year. This new law is an unfortunate development.</p>
<p>It is unfortunate that the integration law negates the complexity of human behavior and the ways in which human beings tend to respond to mechanisms of control. It is unfortunate that it transforms a once two-way street into a narrow, one-way turnpike, failing to recognize that tying belonging to an existential crisis is one sure way to create another type of crisis, one of protracted isolation and despair. <strong><br />
</strong></p>
<p><strong>The Way Out</strong></p>
<p>One does not become a part of a group by the force of policy, nor does one come to belong anywhere by resigning to segregation and the apathy of staying apart.</p>
<p>But I for one would rarely speak to my German neighbors if I didn&#8217;t feel that they would smile at me and wish to speak back. I am too sensitive of feeling unwanted and merely tolerated to make myself so vulnerable. In a similar way, if I were just learning German, I would rarely try to order in German on a busy bakery morning. I would rarely try to ask any questions of the service personnel at the mall. I would be too afraid of looking and feeling defeated for the stern face, the impatient twitch, and the impolite interruption that often peppers such interactions with shame.</p>
<p>And if I cannot imagine doing these things, as someone with no experience of war or traumatic displacement, I cannot imagine it for all newcomers from Syria and elsewhere &#8211; human beings who have suffered the extremes of suffering.</p>
<p><strong>Laws may not be made for empathetic social responses, but norms are. In response to this new law, a little normative empathy is in order. Perhaps it is time not for sanctions but for a new German way of being with each other.<br />
</strong></p>
<p>Small gestures like the prolific smile, like deferring to others in line at the grocery store, like trying (only trying!) to give directions in English, like waiting patiently for a German-learner to get out their form of a German sentence, will bring the empathy this law is so clearly lacking. If this happens, Syrians and Afghans and Eritreans and Kurds (etc) are made to feel that they are also people of value.</p>
<p>For anthropologists and sociologists, value is a social construct. It does not exist inherent to things, to substance. Rather it is made within a system of prioritizing this, disregarding that, supporting the success of this and punishing the success of that. Value is a trait or state to be expressed through norms, such as everyday behavior, as well as structures, such as divisions of labor or the segmentation of achievement within public schools*. It is a process, not a prescription.</p>
<p>We&#8217;ll see soon enough if the process can rise above this law.</p>
<p>&#8211;<em>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*For more on this critical view of how and why value is created in society, see the well-known work of anthropologist David Graeber on the topic, available as a PDF <a href="https://monoskop.org/File:Graeber_David_Toward_an_Anthropological_Theory_of_Value.pdf">here</a>. You will never see prices and social priorities the same!</p>
<p><iframe style="position: absolute; top: 0px; left: 0px; width: 1px; height: 1px; visibility: hidden; background: #ffffff none repeat scroll 0% 0%;" name="xdcom_frame" width="300" height="150"></iframe></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Women Only: The Frauenraum</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 15:42:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gender]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4385</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I'm at Rathaus Wilmersdorf, a former city hall building turned refugee home in Berlin, where I teach a literacy class once a week. The home initially opened its doors to 178 refugees in September 2015, following Merkel's famous "Wir schaffen das" ("We can do it") declaration that sidestepped the Dublin Regulation and opened up Germany's borders to thousands of asylum seekers.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4394 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-01-27 12.51.04" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-27-12.51.04-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>It&#8217;s Thursday at 10:55, and I&#8217;m running late. I rush up to the security guards and hand over my ID. <em>Helfer?</em> (&#8220;volunteer?&#8221;) they ask. <em>Ja</em>, I answer, and wait for them to scribble down my name and give me a number so I can sign out later. I thank them and head inside to the office to sign for the room keys and get my name tag. Then it&#8217;s through the foyer and up three floors to room 3092. When breakfast is running late, the right half of the stairwell is still filled by a neat line of people waiting for their turn in the cafeteria. I squeeze by, ruffling the hair of the kids I recognize.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m at Rathaus Wilmersdorf, a former city hall building turned refugee home in Berlin, where I teach a literacy class once a week. The home initially opened its doors to <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/berlin/bezirke/kudamm/notunterkunft-fuer-fluechtlinge-in-berlin-im-rathaus-wilmersdorf-fehlen-duschen-und-dolmetscher/12199798.html">178 refugees</a> in September 2015, following Merkel&#8217;s famous &#8220;Wir schaffen das&#8221; (&#8220;We can do it&#8221;) declaration that <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/germany/11821822/Germany-drops-EU-rules-to-allow-in-Syrian-refugees.html">sidestepped the Dublin Regulation</a> and opened up Germany&#8217;s borders to thousands of asylum seekers.</p>
<p>Today, over 1400 refugees live in the Rathaus &#8211; mostly from Syria, Afghanistan, and Iraq &#8211; and there is talk of opening up an adjacent building to house an additional 900. As is the case all over the city, this home simply wouldn&#8217;t function without the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/12/18/lageso/">on-going assistance of volunteers</a> who help out with everything from interpretation and teaching to administrative and kitchen support.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4456 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-01-08 10.34.54" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-01-08-10.34.54-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Over the past eight months, Rathaus Wilmersdorf has become somewhat of a success story as far as refugee accommodations in Berlin go. It&#8217;s been visited by President Joachim Gauck and American actor Ben Stiller, as well as received significant media praise for its leadership and facilities. <a href="http://www.morgenpost.de/berlin/article207089933/Vachroi-verabschiedet-sich-als-Heimleiter-in-Wilmersdorf.html">One article</a> listed off the home&#8217;s impressive amenities, which include medical and midwife services, a laundry room, a hair salon, an internet <span class="st">café</span>, and yes, even our literacy class.</p>
<p>The literacy class, or &#8220;AB class&#8221; as we call it, does go beyond what many other refugee homes in Berlin offer. But what the article&#8217;s authors fail to mention (and are likely unaware of), is that the course comes with a complicated backstory that is indicative of a larger debate surrounding refugees in Germany today.</p>
<p>It all started early this year, after one volunteer noticed that a group of women were not showing up for the German class offered on the home&#8217;s fourth floor. These women were mostly Afghan and the majority also illiterate. However, a bit of digging (and a heavy dose of interpretation) revealed that they weren&#8217;t avoiding the class because the level was too difficult, as originally suspected. They weren&#8217;t going because, in the fourth floor class, there were men present. Or depending on who tells the story, “Because their husbands wouldn’t let them”.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4600 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-05-19 12.43.22" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-19-12.43.22-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>The decision was therefore made to start a new class on the third floor, taught and attended exclusively by women. The class was to be an extension of the adjacent <em>Frauenraum</em> or &#8220;women&#8217;s room&#8221;. At Rathaus Wilmersdorf, the <em>Frauenraum</em> is a standing room open almost daily, so long as there are volunteers present. At the refugee home in former Tempelhof airport, the <em>Frauenraum</em> operates on a weekly project basis, led by a volunteer platform called <a href="http://givesomethingbacktoberlin.com/">Give Something Back to Berlin</a>.</p>
<p>Regardless of the format, the concept remains the same: The <em>Frauenraum</em> is a safe place where women can be amongst themselves. In Rathaus Wilmersdorf, they sew, practice German, or just hang out and have a cup of tea. Small children are allowed, but men are forbidden from entering. We&#8217;ve even had to throw out a male journalist on occasion. The home&#8217;s former director described it as a place where &#8220;<a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/berlin/warum-thomas-de-vachroi-der-perfekte-aufbauhelfer-fuer-fluechtlingsheime-ist-23775578">female residents are enjoying their freedom and unveiling themselves.</a>&#8221; I can only assume he meant this both literally and figuratively, as not all the women wear headscarves, but some who do do indeed take them off when in the <em>Frauenraum</em> or during class.</p>
<p>I fell into the role of literacy teacher by way of the <em>Frauenraum</em>, where I started volunteering in January. The class was already up and running but they wanted to offer it on more days and were having trouble finding willing teachers. Other <em>Frauenraum</em> volunteers, I was told, had flatly refused to teach out of principle, scoffing at the idea that a separate class be created when there was a perfectly good one already on offer. This is Germany, after all, a country where men and women are presumably equal and interact on all levels of society. If the husbands had a problem with that, tough. Isn&#8217;t it in the best interest of these women that we integrate them into our way of life as quickly as possible?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4460 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-05-12 11.42.50" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-05-12-11.42.50-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>These days, it is difficult to have a discussion in Germany about refugees that doesn&#8217;t include a question about gender. <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/02/08/not-our-women-from-cologne-to-berlin/">Post-Cologne</a>, it is near impossible. Despite the fact that the attacks on New Year&#8217;s Eve were carried out by a more diverse group than originally portrayed in the media, that night&#8217;s unfortunate events have marked a turning point in attitudes towards refugees.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.focus.de/politik/deutschland/zdf-umfrage-offenbart-so-haben-die-silvester-uebergriffe-beeinflusst-was-deutsche-ueber-fluechtlinge-denken_id_5213962.html">One poll</a> showed that, between December 2015 and January 2016 alone, the number of Germans who felt the country couldn&#8217;t handle the influx of refugees rose from 46% to 60%. Thirty-three percent stated that Cologne had &#8220;fundamentally changed&#8221; their opinions about refugees. And the ring-wing <span class="st"><em>Alternative für Deutschland</em></span> (AfD) party, which initially emerged in opposition to the euro, has placed anti-refugee sentiment at the core of their increasingly popular platform. Their leader has controversially <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/alternative-for-germany-shows-its-true-right-wing-colors-a-1076259.html">called for the use of firearms against incoming refugees</a>.</p>
<p>This is the same country that was at the forefront of Europe&#8217;s refugee response only nine months ago. The same country that led the continent&#8217;s discourse on establishing a common European solution. The same country that initiated what became globally lauded as <em>Wilkommenskultur</em> (welcome culture).</p>
<p>So, what&#8217;s changed?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4401 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-650x650.jpg" alt="2016-02-10 11.59.46" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-300x300.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-10-11.59.46-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>When the “refugee crisis” hit Germany last summer, hundreds of residents felt compelled to slather butter on rolls and pass them out to refugees arriving at train stations. This was by all accounts heart-warming and admirable, but it was also the easy part. The conversation we are having now is a more complicated one, one that even the seemingly simple question of whether to offer a female-only literacy class echoes:</p>
<p>What happens next and how might our society change as a result?</p>
<p>One could blame Cologne, but the foundation for this confrontation was laid long before. A staggering <a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article147280667/Fuer-die-meisten-gehoert-der-Islam-nicht-zu-Deutschland.html">60% of the country</a> is of the opinion that Islam does not belong in Germany. (It is also worth noting that Germans consistently overestimate the number of Muslims living in the country. The real figure, while one of the highest in the EU, <a href="http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2015/11/17/5-facts-about-the-muslim-population-in-europe/">is still only 5.8%</a>.)</p>
<p>There is an underlying preconception in Germany, as in many Western countries, that Islam is synonymous with misogyny and a lack of female rights. That “<a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article149756193/Wie-Sumtes-Wutbuerger-lernten-Fluechtlinge-zu-lieben.html">according to their religion, women are nothing</a>” or even more extreme, that &#8220;<a href="http://www.vice.com/de/read/fluechtlinge-vergewaltigen-deutsche-kinder-wie-rassisten-versuchen-stimmung-gegen-alle-nicht-deutschen-zu-machen-775">these young men will come and rape our daughters</a>&#8220;. This preconception likely stems from a variety of factors: images we see in the media, politicians portraying Muslims as backward or extremist, or current conflicts within the Middle East. An argument heard less often is made by <a href="http://ideas.time.com/2013/11/01/do-muslim-women-need-saving/">Columbia University Professor Lila Abu-Lughod</a>, who explores the conflation of religion and socioeconomic status. Gender inequality within Muslim majority societies stems mainly from economic inequality, and migrants in Germany have traditionally been low-skilled. Therefore what we may label as clashes due to religion may have stronger roots in poverty and lack of opportunity.</p>
<p>Earlier this year in Berlin, <a href="http://www.rbb-online.de/politik/beitrag/2016/04/berlin-kopftuch-streit-vor-arbeitsgericht-keine-guetliche-einigung.html">a young teacher went to court</a> because she was denied a teaching post due to her headscarf (the case was thrown out on grounds of the state&#8217;s Neutrality Act). More recently in Switzerland, a <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-36382596">regional authority ruled</a> that two teenage brothers must shake the hands of their female teachers despite it being against their religious beliefs to touch women they are not related to. Traditionally receiving societies such as Germany are perpetually learning how to manage integration in the face of growing diversity. Unfortunately, we seem insistent on concentrating on how &#8220;their values&#8221; may threaten &#8220;ours&#8221;, rather than on what type of society we want to live in together.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4406 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-02-17 12.07.15" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-02-17-12.07.15-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>To be fair, my own engagement at the Rathaus has not come without challenges. On my first day teaching, I swallowed a lot of frustration as another volunteer and I watched the women turn to their husbands for approval before following us to class. <em>Nur Frauen</em> (&#8220;only women&#8221;), we tried to communicate to the more skeptical looking of the men with a smile, while I stifled the urge to roll my eyes.</p>
<p>We&#8217;ve also heard a host of disturbing stories by way of the interpreters. Rape, abuse, threats of divorce. Some stories are from Afghanistan while others allegedly took place here in Berlin. At times, I am ashamed to find myself relieved that I can&#8217;t talk to the women directly about what I&#8217;ve heard, for fear it might affect the way I interact with them. For now, our exchanges are limited to topics like telling time and types of fruit &#8211; they&#8217;re big fans of banana and pineapple &#8211; as well as the apparently always shocking and never boring topic of me being a 30 year old woman without a husband or children (some of my students have 6, 7, even 9 children).</p>
<p>But until we&#8217;re able to have those more in-depth conversations, I remain convinced that offering a class under imperfect circumstances is better than offering no women&#8217;s class at all. For what, I&#8217;ve asked myself, will give these women more independence than the ability to navigate the city on their own? And what will give them a better chance of being able to navigate the city on their own than the ability to read and write?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4405 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-650x488.jpg" alt="2016-04-20 10.14.53" width="650" height="488" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-650x488.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/2016-04-20-10.14.53-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p>Nothing exhibited this more clearly to me than a few weeks ago, when we held an arts project week for our women. The week consisted of two trips to separate parks so they could learn about various plant types and practice drawing them. The excitement of the women was palpable. They got to have a Middle Eastern picnic, a real treat after months of bland cafeteria fare. They got to pick flowers in the woods to take back to the home. There was laughing, there was dancing, and there were so many selfies.</p>
<p>We later found out through interpreters that, for several of the women, it was their first time in a park without a husband or male relative.</p>
<p>At the end of the week, a local artist took the womens&#8217; drawings and stenciled them onto power boxes near the Rathaus. On the Friday, we took a stroll around the neighborhood together to see them for the first time. The Farsi-speaking volunteer asked the women to point out their drawings and explain why they chose to draw them specifically. &#8220;Who drew this?&#8221; she asked when we got to the second box, pointing to a beautiful palm tree. &#8220;Me,&#8221; answered one of our students, &#8220;I drew it because it reminds me of home. And if you cut off the head, the whole plant dies.&#8221;</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The Frauenraum at Rathaus Wilmersdorf is looking for volunteers. To get involved, sign up at https://volunteer-planner.org/.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>For another take on the headscarf, I recommend watching <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/video/2015/jun/24/hijab-not-oppression-feminist-statement-video">this Guardian video</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>All photos my own.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/05/31/the-frauenraum/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: &#8220;I&#8217;m not Turkish, but my husband is&#8221;</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[love]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tunisia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1251</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In a capital city marked by transformation and transience, where people are perpetually coming and going, it can feel like a true rarity to meet someone actually from that city. “H” was my first Berlin friend from Berlin. We met through a language website, after she sent me a request to practice French in exchange for German. H was working on her degree to become a French teacher. I was still new to the city and could count my local friends on one hand...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_3811" style="width: 733px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://jurigottschau.com/"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3811" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3811 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz.jpg" alt="grillplatz" width="723" height="482" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz.jpg 723w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/grillplatz-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 723px) 100vw, 723px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3811" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p style="text-align: left;">In a capital city marked by transformation and transience, where people are perpetually coming and going, it can feel like a true rarity to meet someone actually <em>from</em> that city.</p>
<p>&#8220;H&#8221; was my first Berlin friend from Berlin. We met through a language website, after she sent me a request to practice French in exchange for German. H was working on her degree to become a French teacher. I was still new to the city and could count my local friends on one hand. The first time we hung out was in February 2012 at a cafe under the <em>Savignyplatz S-Bahn</em> arches. H ended up helping me with my research on teacher quality in Germany, and I gave her tips for her upcoming study abroad program in France. Soon enough our linguistic meet-ups evolved into a friendship that waved off grammar practice in favor of relaxed Sunday afternoon coffee dates.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Our relationship also became a kind of exchange of culinary cultures. I started joining her annually to break the fast during Ramadan. As the resident atheist I wouldn&#8217;t fast before these meals. Yet I&#8217;d still be the one gnawing away at my fingers until sundown, while H and her sisters waited patiently for their first sips of rose flavored water and soup drizzled with fresh lemon juice. In return, H  joined my international crew of friends for her first Thanksgiving dinner, initiated into the world of cranberry sauce, candied sweet potatoes, and general American gluttony. Her contribution &#8211; mounds of Turkish <em>Lahmacun</em> (spiced lamb pizza) &#8211; was eagerly divvied up like party favors at the end of the night.</p>
<div id="attachment_3611" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3611" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3611 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340-650x650.jpg" alt="IMG_3340" width="650" height="650" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/IMG_3340-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3611" class="wp-caption-text">Ramadan dinner with H</p></div>
<p style="text-align: left;">It didn&#8217;t take long for us to discover our mutual fascination with questions of citizenship and identity. We attended several events together on the topic and often spent our cafe time discussing our hybrid families and understanding of <em>Deutschsein</em> or &#8220;Germanness&#8221;. See, while H is a true <em>Berlinerin</em> &#8211; she was born and grew up here &#8211; her parents are from Tunisia. We shared the feeling of having more than one home; while I straddled the Atlantic, H had a foot on either side of the Mediterranean. But unlike me, H had grown up with the challenge of having to persistently defend her Germanness, to the wider community and to her own parents.</p>
<p>In countries like Germany that are still embracing their multicultural identities &#8211; Germany first recognized itself as a country of immigration in 2005 &#8211; too many still have a binary understanding of native vs. foreigner that acknowledges bloodlines over birthplace and physical appearance over personal identity. There remains a habit of probing those who look &#8220;different&#8221; about their roots, otherwise known as the dreaded &#8220;But where are you <em>really</em> from?&#8221; <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/11/lens-with-wings-roots-and-sweaty-hands/">question</a>. Those on the receiving end of this question are often referred to as the &#8220;perpetual foreigner&#8221;, ethnic minorities who will always be seen as the “other” because of how they look.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">In H&#8217;s case, it didn&#8217;t take long to notice that the vast majority of those she came across assumed she was Turkish, including other Turkish-Germans. &#8220;Oh right, the Turkish one,&#8221; a girl on her basketball team responded, when I introduced myself as H&#8217;s friend. H once told me she gets asked if she&#8217;s Turkish more than her best friend, an actual Turkish-German who happens to be blond and fair-skinned.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3697 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-650x487.jpg" alt="2014-01-19 17.26.48" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/2014-01-19-17.26.48.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>The confusion isn&#8217;t all too surprising, considering H&#8217;s darker features, for one, and the demographics of the city, for two. Turkish-Germans are the city&#8217;s largest ethnic minority and the largest community of Turks outside of Turkey. Estimates of the number of Turks in Berlin range from 200,000-500,000 (a combination of those with Turkish passports, partial Turkish ancestry, and ethnic minorities from Turkey). A far cry from the approximately <a href="http://www.berlin.de/lb/intmig/statistik/demografie/einwohner_staatsangehoerigkeit.html">1,500 Tunisian nationals</a> in Berlin.</p>
<p>The story of H&#8217;s parents also mirrors that of many Turkish-Germans. They immigrated to the city separately as part of a guest-worker program in the 1970s and met on the job at corporate giant, Siemens. Originally, they planned to return to Tunisia together. The couple worked 2-3 jobs, sending remittances to family in Tunisia to save up to build a house there. They sent their 3 eldest daughters back for 9 years to live with relatives and go to school. But when Germany tightened family reunification laws in the 80&#8217;s, excluding those older than 16 without German citizenship, they brought the 3 girls back to Berlin to keep the family together, by then consisting of 5 daughters.</p>
<p>H is daughter number 4 and has only visited Tunisia on vacation. She admits that a distinction exists between the older and younger sisters, due to this geographic divide in upbringing, especially apparent in attitudes toward the headscarf and family planning. Her oldest sister &#8220;lives by the Qu&#8217;ran&#8221; and hopes to move back to Tunisia permanently one day. H, on the other hand, identifies as a &#8220;<em>Berlinerin</em> with Tunisian roots&#8221;; she has no intention of leaving Germany anytime soon.</p>
<div id="attachment_3791" style="width: 657px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3791" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3791 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg" alt="htunisia" width="647" height="484" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia.jpg 647w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia-300x224.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/htunisia-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 647px) 100vw, 647px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3791" class="wp-caption-text">H on vacation in Tunisia</p></div>
<p>When it comes to questions and comments about her being Turkish, I&#8217;ve only ever seen H respond with patience and grace. It&#8217;s the difficulties with her own parents, and especially mother, that affect her most. If you ask her about her upbringing, H will tell you that her parents were &#8220;pretty modern for immigrant standards&#8221;, letting her play sports and stay out with friends until 10pm. Sleepovers and clubs weren&#8217;t allowed, but H found ways around her parents&#8217; rules, such as working at social events like the <em>Volksfest </em>and later heading west to Dortmund for university.</p>
<p>Boyfriends, on the other hand, were out of the question. Particularly those outside of the Tunisian-German community. H dated a little in secret, but didn&#8217;t get serious with anyone until she met &#8220;A&#8221; at 19. At 28, A was almost a decade older and managing a series of internet cafes. The flirtation started small with jokes at the shop, building up slowly to weekend jogs together. Finally, A asked H out on a date.</p>
<p>H managed to keep the relationship hidden from her parents for 6 years. &#8220;I was sure they&#8217;d disapprove because he&#8217;s Turkish,&#8221; she explains. Even though both Tunisians and Turks in Germany are predominantly Muslim, H says it&#8217;s not uncommon for the older immigrant generations to be prejudiced against one another. &#8220;The Tunisians here think that all Turkish boys are in gangs, are loud and have no respect, and don&#8217;t achieve anything,&#8221; H claims; &#8220;Tunisians in Tunisia think more positively about Turks than Tunisians in Germany do.&#8221;</p>
<p>When she told her parents about the relationship in 2013, her mother threatened that H was &#8220;ruining her life&#8221; and that if she continued, they would disown her. &#8220;I haven&#8217;t even told them yet that A is Shiite,&#8221; H joked (her family is Sunni).</p>
<div id="attachment_3792" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3792" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3792 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-650x202.jpg" alt="A&amp;H" width="650" height="202" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-650x202.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH-300x93.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/AH.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3792" class="wp-caption-text">A &amp; H</p></div>
<p>According to H, the problem is her mother&#8217;s stubbornness more than anything else. But listening to the stories one can&#8217;t help but notice an underlying theme of fear, logical or not. A fear of losing one&#8217;s child. A fear of not relating to one&#8217;s grandchildren. A fear of the dilution of one&#8217;s cultural lineage over generations. &#8220;Many in the Tunisian-German community are scared that their kids will marry Turks and end up in Turkey,&#8221; H agrees, &#8220;my mother is also afraid her grandchildren will never learn Arabic.&#8221; H and her sisters speak strictly Tunisian Arabic with their parents. When just amongst each other, a mix of Arabic and German.</p>
<p>Language is just one question of many that H and A will face as parents. They have already decided that A will primarily speak Turkish and H mostly German, which she is more comfortable with than Arabic. They have even talked about where they will <em>really</em> end up one day. H tells me that the Tunisian consulate pays for the bodies of Tunisian nationals in Germany to be sent back for burials. A, who came to Berlin at 18 as a student, gave up his Turkish passport to become German.  As an entrepreneur he&#8217;s eager to launch projects in Turkey and maybe even retire there one day, but is limited without citizenship.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">After months of not seeing each other, H and I finally find time last November for one of our Sunday coffee dates. H arrives to the Italian cafe in an uncharacteristically bulky sweater that makes me raise my eyebrows. Shortly after ordering our lattes and chocolate cake, she spills the beans: she and A have gotten married, and she&#8217;s newly pregnant. The religious ceremony was held at their apartment with an Imam presiding and a handful of their closest friends and siblings present. H&#8217;s parents chose not to return early from their vacation in Tunisia to attend. As for their upcoming grandchild, wherever he or she decides to be &#8220;<em>really</em> from&#8221;, they are still in the dark.</p>
<p><em> &#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong> </em></p>
<p><em>&#8220;A&#8221; requested that this article remain anonymous, in order to not further weaken his cause, should H&#8217;s parents somehow come across it.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/01/15/interview-im-not-turkish-husband/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: The Taxi Driver</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2014 14:00:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kurdistan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2314</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Orhan was 5 when his father moved to Berlin in 1972. It was only one year before West Germany would halt guest worker recruitment from non-European countries to fill labor shortages after World War II. His mother followed 7 years later with his youngest sister and they lived in Rudow in southeastern Neukölln - where they still live over 30 years later. "They got jobs as cleaners in an office," Orhan recounts, "but they were fired!" he adds, snorting in laughter.  I look up from my notepad, surprised...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Had I hopped into Orhan&#8217;s taxi en route to the airport, I likely would&#8217;ve assumed he was Turkish and left it at that. He might have asked me where I was flying to and I might have commented on the weather. He would&#8217;ve pulled my suitcase out of the trunk and wished me a good flight, and I would&#8217;ve thanked him. But instead, thankfully, I met Orhan in a very different context &#8211; our half-marathon training group. What follows here is his story about growing up in Kurdistan and Turkey as the child of guest workers and moving to Berlin 20 years ago. The story I would&#8217;ve likely missed. </em></p>
<div id="attachment_2377" style="width: 588px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/2014-03-30-09-50-36-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2377" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2377" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/2014-03-30-09-50-36-1.jpg?w=640" alt="Orhan and Sophia pre 2014 Berlin half marathon" width="578" height="578" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/2014-03-30-09-50-36-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/2014-03-30-09-50-36-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 578px) 100vw, 578px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2377" class="wp-caption-text">Orhan and I pre-race 2014</p></div>
<p>I meet Orhan at Fehrbelliner Platz&#8217;s Park <span class="st">Café</span>. We choose a table outside amongst the masses soaking up the unusually warm March sun. It&#8217;s that strange break between afternoon and evening,  the mood equally fitting for a coffee or beer. The space is buzzing but in a state of exhalation, as the day starts to settle and everyone&#8217;s shoulders wilt a few centimeters. This is where Orhan spends every Thursday between 4:45 and 6pm, while his daughter takes a kickboxing class around the corner.</p>
<p>My first order of business is a selfish one: though I&#8217;ve asked Orhan multiple times to tell me where he grew up, I still can&#8217;t remember the name, let alone comprehend its location geographically. Orhan draws me a little diagram: he grew up in <em>Hotan</em>, a tiny village near a town called <em>Varto</em>, part of a district called <span class="st"><em>Mûş</em></span> that lies in Anatolia, in the predominantly Kurdish southeastern part of Turkey.</p>
<div id="2330" style="width: 582px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://geopoliticsrst.blogspot.de/2012/10/turkei.html"><img aria-describedby="caption-2330" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2330 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/mapkurdistan.jpg" alt="Kurdistan on a map " width="572" height="447" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/mapkurdistan.jpg 572w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/mapkurdistan-300x234.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 572px) 100vw, 572px" /></a><p id="caption-2330" class="wp-caption-text">Varto is slightly northeast of Diyarbakir, the unofficial capital of Turkish Kurdistan</p></div>
<p>Orhan was 5 when his father moved to Berlin in 1972. It was only one year before West Germany would halt guest worker recruitment from non-European countries to fill labor shortages after World War II. His mother followed 7 years later with his youngest sister and they lived in Rudow in southeastern Neukölln &#8211; where they still live over 30 years later. <em>They got jobs as cleaners in an office</em>, Orhan recounts, <em>but they were fired!</em> he adds, snorting in laughter.  I look up from my notepad, surprised. &#8220;Why is that funny?&#8221; <em>Well, they worked with friends &#8211; they&#8217;d moved to Berlin together &#8211; and one of the guys was really funny. So they were always fooling around and making noise..</em>.<em> and one day they got fired! That guy was a real comedian.<br />
</em></p>
<p>Orhan only heard that story years later. He had stayed behind in Kurdistan, in the village with his grandmother. <em>My father didn&#8217;t plan on staying that long, like most guest workers</em>, Orhan explains,<em> but my mom eventually went, too, and my Oma became my main mom. She ended up raising me. </em>After school, Orhan did an apprenticeship in wood-making<em>. It was a 6km walk to work from Oma&#8217;s every day, alone, sometimes in 1m of snow. I was always scared the wolves would get me! </em></p>
<div id="attachment_2368" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/gallery_0610222020109423828131.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2368" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-2368" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/gallery_0610222020109423828131.jpg?w=640" alt="Portrait of a Kurdish woman (Source: Renkliisler)" width="640" height="648" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2368" class="wp-caption-text">Portrait of a Kurdish woman in Varto (Source: Renkliisler)</p></div>
<p>In the 1980s, Orhan&#8217;s parents used money earned in Germany to buy land and build a house in Izmir, on Turkey&#8217;s western coast. Orhan switched from wood-making to electrician work, and got a factory job making stoves. His remaining siblings (of which there are 5 total) started to join his parents in Berlin, applying for visas and leaving one by one. Orhan applied too, but his request was denied. German family reunification policy* has a 16 year old age limit for third country (non EU) nationals to join their parents in Germany. After age 15, other factors apply for a residence permit, such as German language proficiency and the &#8220;ability to integrate&#8221;. Orhan was already in his 20s. So he stayed in Izmir, looking after the house and spending summers in the village with his grandmother and uncle. Then came 1993, when <em>Hotan </em>and many other Kurdish villages were destroyed in a war between Turkish government forces and Kurdish rebels. The war, called &#8220;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/24/world/kurds-are-finally-heard-turkey-burned-our-villages.html">one of the most violent secrets of the 1990&#8217;s</a>&#8220;, killed more than 30,000 and displaced thousands more.</p>
<p>Orhan&#8217;s chance to go to Germany came shortly thereafter. <em>My boss asked me to go to Germany to fix a faulty order we had exported there&#8230; they needed someone who spoke a little German. </em>It was Orhan&#8217;s first trip to Germany, and by the time he returned, he had decided to try moving there again. <em>Since I had gotten a visa for the work trip and come back, I had earned the Embassy&#8217;s trust</em>, Orhan chuckles, <em>it was much easier to apply for a visa the next time.</em> On December 10, 1994, Orhan left Turkey with a 3 month visa. Upon arrival in Germany he applied for asylum. He was 27.</p>
<p>He was sent to an asylum home outside Berlin in <span class="st">Eisenhüttenstadt, Brandenburg</span>. <em>We were fed three times a day and the workers were pretty nice to us, but the conditions weren&#8217;t great&#8230; 7 or 8 of us sleeping together in one room. </em>For a year, Orhan spent one night every two weeks there to comply with policy.<em> They knew my family was in Berlin&#8230; I spent the rest of the time with them. </em>Orhan&#8217;s asylum request was eventually granted, on the grounds that his hometown in Kurdistan had been destroyed. <em><br />
</em></p>
<div id="2341" style="width: 618px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article123743604/Asylbewerberheim-in-Eisenhuettenstadt.html"><img aria-describedby="caption-2341" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2341 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/asylbewerberheim-in-eisenhuettenstadt.jpg" alt="asylum home in Eisenhuettenstadt" width="608" height="405" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/asylbewerberheim-in-eisenhuettenstadt.jpg 620w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/asylbewerberheim-in-eisenhuettenstadt-300x199.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px" /></a><p id="caption-2341" class="wp-caption-text">Asylum seekers arrive to Eisenhüttenstadt (Source: Die Welt)</p></div>
<p>This was in the mid-1990s, a decade before Germany would officially recognize itself as a country of immigration and develop a <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">national integration plan that included integration courses for newcomers</a>. Orhan signed up for a language course on his own, hoping to learn enough German to study economics at university. He quit after 3 months. <em>It wasn&#8217;t fun and always after work</em><em>, when I was so tired </em>(he did construction at the time)<em>. </em><em>The grammar was really hard. It&#8217;s still hard.<br />
</em></p>
<p>A cousin&#8217;s <span class="st">fiancé</span> suggested he try being a taxi driver. <em>I failed my taxi license test 3 times because I couldn&#8217;t pronounce the street names correctly!</em> <em>Being a taxi driver is a bit boring but it&#8217;s a clean job. Not like construction. And I like the freedom.</em></p>
<p>Orhan&#8217;s been a taxi driver ever since, working 10 hour days 5-6 days a week. He has two children, a son from his first marriage to a Turkish-German woman and a daughter with his current wife, whom he met at a gym over 10 years ago &#8211; a gym they still attend together. <em>I live a good life here. I travel a lot and I have a flexible job. </em>Orhan tries to go to Kurdistan at least once or twice a year, and has taken his kids 4 times. His next visit is this May. <em><br />
</em></p>
<p><em>My kids have 59% <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">Migrationshintergrund</a>, </em>Orhan says laughing,<em> when I&#8217;m angry with my son I scold him in Turkish, but usually we speak German. He can understand Kurdish, too.</em> <em>I tried speaking Kurdish with my daughter for a year but then gave up,</em> he adds, a hint of regret in his voice.</p>
<p>&#8220;Do you think German integration policy has gotten better since you first arrived here 20 years ago? With services like the integration courses?&#8221; <em>German immigration policy isn&#8217;t very fair</em>, Orhan replies scowling, <em>If I marry someone from Turkey and want to bring them here, they have to prove they speak German before arriving! But people from <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/20/roma-in-berlin-bureaucracy-in-lichtenberg/">Bulgaria and Romania</a>** can just come here and get social benefits even if they don&#8217;t speak the language</em>.</p>
<p><em>I don&#8217;t have German citizenship and I don&#8217;t want it,</em> Orhan declares, <em>why would I need it? </em><em>My wife and I want to buy a house in Izmir and spend maybe one third of the year there. Four months in Berlin, 4 in Izmir, 4 in Kurdistan. There&#8217;s nothing special there, where I&#8217;m from in Kurdistan&#8230; only mountains, animals </em>(the wolves!)<em>, and rocks, but, </em>Orhan makes a fist and holds it close to his stomach, <em>it still feels like home.</em></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Varto">According to Wikipedia</a>, Berlin holds Europe&#8217;s largest population from Varto, Kurdistan. Germany has Europe&#8217;s largest population of Kurds, <a href="http://www.aljazeera.com/video/europe/2013/05/201358161349732897.html">approximately 800,000</a>, many of whom came as guest workers in the 1960s. For more information on the history of this immigrant community (in German), click <a href="http://www.trend.infopartisan.net/trd0299/t090299.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>*For more information on Germany&#8217;s family reunification policy, click <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/dgs/home-affairs/what-we-do/networks/european_migration_network/reports/docs/emn-studies/family-reunification/2._de_emn_ncp_small-scale_study_iv_family_reunification_final_en_version_en.pdf">here</a> and <a href="http://www.expatica.com/de/essentials_moving_to/essentials/German-permits-for-family-reunification_18892.html%20">here</a>.</p>
<p>**Despite being part of the EU since 2007, Bulgarians and Romanians have only had access to Germany&#8217;s social welfare system since 2014, when Germany lifted work policy restrictions. This was after the EU deemed Germany in violation of economic rules of engagement.</p>
<p><em>All photos linked to source. A big thank you to Orhan for his participation!<br />
</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Berlin: the Istanbul Connection</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/29/beyond-berlin-the-istanbul-connection/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2013 18:14:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gastarbeiter-guestworker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Istanbul]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1643</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Istanbul gives Berlin its baseline. In kind, Berlin is richly integrated into the complexity of Istanbul. For no relationship is ever purely one-sided. And so a Berlin : Istanbul connection, which moves beyond <i>Gastarbeiter</i> music and Fatih Akin films, is what one can find after six days immersed in the shapes and silhouettes of this city of 13 million...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Istanbul gives Berlin its baseline. In kind, Berlin is richly integrated into the complexity of Istanbul. For no relationship is ever purely one-sided. And so a Berlin : Istanbul connection, which moves beyond <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/oct/25/music-germany-migrant-workers-compilation"><em>Gastarbeiter </em>music</a> and <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0015359/">Fatih Akin films</a>, is what one can find after six days immersed in the shapes and silhouettes of this city of 13 million.</p>
<div id="attachment_1654" style="width: 630px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/photogram-20131024120809.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1654" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1654" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/photogram-20131024120809.jpg" alt="Photogram-20131024120809" width="620" height="620" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/photogram-20131024120809.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/photogram-20131024120809-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1654" class="wp-caption-text">Europe meets Asia</p></div>
<p>The <a href="http://www.dw.de/turkish-guest-workers-transformed-german-society/a-15489210">guest-worker program between Turkey and Germany</a> is often cited as the beginning of a long-standing socio-cultural and economic relationship, though such ties <a href="http://www.slowtravelberlin.com/a-short-history-of-turkish-berlin/">got their start long before</a> the post-war boom period of the 1960s. The &#8216;Turkish factor&#8217;, regardless of how it came to be, makes Berlin, and Germany for that matter, the place we know. Without it, students would miss their late night meaty snack in the likes of Döner, the skyline would miss many of its stunning minarets, and the census would be sorely missing the strength of difference (just to name a few).</p>
<p>But being Turkish, German-Turkish, or Turkish-German in Berlin are states of being <a title="Over and Over" href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">without a formula</a>. In other words, there is <a href="http://www.slowtravelberlin.com/a-short-history-of-turkish-berlin/">more to the Turkish factor than just culinary contributions</a> and street-side renditions of &#8220;<em>walla</em>&#8221; taking place on German soil. There is, in fact, also a &#8216;German factor&#8217; abroad.</p>
<p>Traveling to Istanbul opens up the possibility for a more two-sided conversation, where the German traveler can encounter home and the foreign at the same time, in a place familiar but distant in its urban position. And that is just what we (me and my German companion, Juri) did just a few weeks ago.</p>
<p><strong>Day 1 in Istanbul: Stammtisch</strong></p>
<p>Upon our arrival into Istanbul&#8217;s (proudly named) Ataturk airport, we were led like lost sheep into the belly of a beast, i.e. Turkey&#8217;s passport control. All around us the air buzzed in German, repeating the ritual of my everyday commute on the metro, this time with the confusion and frustration of a forced queue in a city far away from German-land. A mustached man holding a sign for <em>Studenten der Humboldt Universität</em> (students of Berlin&#8217;s Humboldt University) stood on the other side of the human barrier, shifting his weight methodically. Entering behind us would certainly be this year&#8217;s study trip from <a href="http://www.sowi.hu-berlin.de/studiengaenge/masowi/getma">Humboldt University&#8217;s Turkish German Master&#8217;s program</a> in the social sciences, which sends Berliners to Ankara and Istanbul every year.</p>
<p>As we wandered into one bookshop after another on our first evening, it seemed that not only visiting German students would be speaking the language of <em>Sauerbraten</em> and Goethe<i>.</i> Residents of Istanbul are learning <em>Almanca </em>(German), maybe now more than ever.</p>
<div style="width: 506px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_almanca.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class=" " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_almanca.jpg" alt="Istanbul_Almanca" width="496" height="496" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">advertisements for German language learning in a bookshop</p></div>
<p><strong>Day 2 in Istanbul: Book Swap</strong></p>
<p>Juri and I stumbled upon a German bookstore on an afternoon of gray and drizzle, just off the pedestrian-friendly thoroughfare of <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2013/06/14/world/europe/taksim-scenes.html?_r=0">Taksim</a>. Within seconds of walking through quaint double doors, we could hear &#8211; once again &#8211; the language of my daily commute. A young German woman chatted enthusiastically with her father, a yellow Reclam paperback of some German classic in her hand. Her father peered over his narrow reading glasses, raising his eyes just to hit the inventory at the back of the store &#8211; stacks of imported magazines and newspapers, including the kitschy tabloids older women with orange hair read at the bus stops in Berlin.</p>
<p>I wandered to the western edge of the dimly lit shop, discovering 20 ft. high shelves of children&#8217;s books in German. Perhaps kids in Istanbul will also grow up reading <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pippi_Longstocking"><em>Pippi Langstrumpf.</em></a></p>
<div id="attachment_1644" style="width: 506px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_books.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1644" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-1644" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_books.jpg" alt="Istanbul_books" width="496" height="496" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_books.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_books-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 496px) 100vw, 496px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1644" class="wp-caption-text">German children&#8217;s literature</p></div>
<p><strong>Day 3 in Istanbul: Sharing the Lunch Box</strong></p>
<p>The Germans take their bread seriously, carefully kneading in all kinds of goodies the average American baker might omit out of concern for dental integrity. The so-called Turkish bread one can purchase in Berlin, from <em>Dönerbrot</em> to <em>Milchbrot</em>, has no fit-for-a-squirrel seeds to offer. Enter <em>Vollkornbrot &#8211; </em>your triple whole grain bread &#8211; to be found in your average Istanbul super market. For all the yoga-bending heath nuts in Berlin: this bread is manufactured in Turkey, though ingredients on the package are also translated into German.</p>
<p>And the bread fun doesn&#8217;t stop here. Even the Döner in Istanbul is served in a bun much robuster than Berlin&#8217;s &#8216;Turkish&#8217; prototype.</p>
<div id="attachment_1648" style="width: 506px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_bread.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1648" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-1648" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_bread.jpg" alt="Istanbul_bread" width="496" height="496" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_bread.jpg 620w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_bread-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 496px) 100vw, 496px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1648" class="wp-caption-text">just your everyday super market</p></div>
<p><strong>Day 4 in Istanbul: The Döner Stories</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">The picture of this Döner? No, it wasn&#8217;t taken in Berlin. This dripping lance of assorted protein can be found on the lively streets of Istanbul, where Döner kiosks are visited with as much enthusiasm as in Berlin (so it appeared). There are slight differences in the composition of the sandwich, or shall we say differences in Döner before it became <em>Döner Kebap</em> in Berlin. As the rumor goes, <em>Döner Kebap</em> was invented by a <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/foodanddrink/4295701/The-man-who-invented-the-doner-kebab-has-died.html">Turkish-German named Mahmut</a>, who happened to serve the traditional vertical meat in a triangular cut of flat bread, instead of in more pita-like Istanbul fashion. The reason, as stated in this same rumor: more bread, so that drunken Berliners might stumble home with saucy meats intact.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Thirty some years later in Istanbul, meat on a spit can now be received with french fries and fried veggies in that bread package. Berliner style.</p>
<div style="width: 568px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_dc3b6ner.jpg"><img loading="lazy" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_dc3b6ner.jpg" alt="Istanbul_Döner" width="558" height="558" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">is it lamb? chicken? beef? everything? it&#8217;s Döner.</p></div>
<p><strong>Day 5 in Istanbul: Gimme Some Cake with that Coffee</strong></p>
<p>The German concept of <em>Kaffee und Kuchen</em> (coffee and cake), which inspires the strip of torte-laden cafes in my neighborhood, has made its way to Istanbul in a rich way. Istanbul has its fair share of home-grown sweets, the most delicious ones in fact, involving large amounts of crude honey and nut-laced syrups. Yet, cake with layers of unsweetened cream and a buttery crust, a small apple tart without cinnamon, or a cream-puff styled torte reminds me of my Sunday afternoons devouring Berlin&#8217;s <em>Kuchen</em> culture with friends. And this in the city of the best Baklava I have ever put in my mouth.</p>
<p>In Istanbul&#8217;s trendy harbor-side district, <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/travel/2013/mar/22/istanbul-karakoy-top-10-cafes-shops-galleries">Karaköy</a>, we doused ourselves in familiar sugars at a cafe called <a href="http://www.karabatak.com/">Karabatak</a>. A locale where locals in tweed jackets and horn-rimmed glasses slowly sip syrup-sweetened black coffee from delicate (read tiny) French presses. The influence of the Viennese coffee genius and founder Julius Meinl saturates the deco. Dressed up like a Freudian coffee salon, tiles lining the walls, jazzy serenades rolling into &#8216;intellectual&#8217; conversations, one could also be in Berlin&#8217;s Prenzlauer Berg. The extensive magazine selection: <em>Der Spiegel</em>, <em>Marie Claire Deutschland</em>, <em>Vogue Deutschland</em>, dispersed among the newest copy of T<em>he New Yorker</em> and Turkish design magazines. A cosmopolitan coffee date full of Berlin swag and Turkish youngsters.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_cafe.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/istanbul_cafe.jpg?w=640" alt="Istanbul_cafe" width="512" height="682" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Day 6 in Istanbul:</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Repeat cosmopolitan coffee date with Berlin swag and Turkish youngsters. For hours and with many forks.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Day 7 in Istanbul: What I Know</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">We boarded our plane in the dark and found ourselves again in German-land, surrounded by the lucid colors of night and the strangely familiar. The smells that had once been part of a Berlin immigrant cityscape were, after the return, now an experience tied to a place, constitutive of a tangible and pungent cross-continental connection. Two worlds connect. In fact, they were never separated.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">We had only heard one side of the conversation.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">&#8211; <em>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em><a href="http://www.dw.de/turkish-guest-workers-transformed-german-society/a-15489210">Approximately 3 million residents or citizens of Germany have Turkish background</a>, meaning either they or their parents were born in Turkey, according to the German system of demographic classification. The Turkish population in Germany intensified with the guest-worker agreement between Turkey and Germany, which allowed for the reunification of families four years following the initial agreement, thereby turning the &#8216;guest-worker&#8217; into an immigrant with, in many cases, children. Today, <a href="http://www.dw.de/turkeys-economic-boom-lures-german-workers/a-16873373">more and more Germans (with or without background) are considering a move to Turkey</a>, learning about Turkey, or learning Turkish, reflecting the true nature of a two-sided relationship. </em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">All photos were taken by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Multiculturalism, Diversity, and the Big City</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2013 18:48:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kreuzberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1358</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[With my back to them at the street-side café I felt like a judge on "<a href="http://www.nbc.com/the-voice/">The Voice</a>", straining my neck for any hint of where they were from or what they looked like, resisting the urge to swirl around and start dancing on my chair. Truth be told my ears had perked up as soon as the trio plopped down at the table behind me, switching between topics like gentrification in Kreuzberg and the cultural difference between <em>Kaffee</em> and "coffee" as quickly as they were switching between German and English...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/photo-1-2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/photo-1-2.jpg" alt="photo-1 (2)" width="640" height="640" /></a></p>
<p>With my back to them at the street-side café I felt like a judge on &#8220;<a href="http://www.nbc.com/the-voice/">The Voice</a>&#8220;, straining my neck for any hint of where they were from or what they looked like, resisting the urge to swirl around and start dancing on my chair. Truth be told my ears had perked up as soon as the trio plopped down at the table behind me, switching between topics like gentrification in Kreuzberg and the cultural difference between <em>Kaffee</em> and &#8220;coffee&#8221; as quickly as they were switching between German and English.</p>
<p>Voice #1: &#8220;I speak differently when I speak to you, or to Brits, or to other Americans. I’m speaking much slower right now and I explain things differently.&#8221; <em> Aha! A fellow American. Is she a teacher? Is this a language class? </em><em>&#8220;</em>Wait, were you just speaking in English or German?&#8221; <em>Hmm, maybe not a teacher. Did she also grow up with both languages? Is that a slight accent I detect? </em></p>
<p>Voice #2: &#8220;My name, Uyen&#8230; well for us the middle name is actually the main name, the name before that is just to make the name more beautiful. And my last name is unique, a combination of my mother&#8217;s and father&#8217;s names. Even my sisters don&#8217;t have it because the province where I was born doesn&#8217;t have the same rules like they do here.&#8221; &#8216;<em>Uyen&#8217;&#8230; is that Vietnamese? Germany has <a href="http://www.germany.info/Vertretung/usa/en/05__Legal/02__Directory__Services/04__Family__Matters/__Name.html">laws</a> about children&#8217;s names.. maybe she was born in Vietnam and then her family moved to Germany and her sisters were born here?</em></p>
<p>Voice #3: &#8220;In another language it&#8217;s always different, the, the&#8230; how do you say <em>Betonung auf Englisch</em>?&#8221; <em>The others are struggling to find the translation, should I interject&#8230;? No that&#8217;d be rude, though maybe they&#8217;d appreciate the&#8230;</em></p>
<p>SLAM! Down went my button and I whirled around.</p>
<p>&#8220;Emphasis!&#8221; I yelped, nearly toppling over on the cobblestones. &#8220;Sorry&#8230; for, uh, listening in on your conversation,&#8221; I continued a bit sheepishly, trying to redeem myself, &#8220;It was just really interesting!&#8221;</p>
<p>Lucky for me they were not only open to the vocabulary assistance but also for a chat with the lady who&#8217;d been shamelessly eavesdropping on them (and typing up parts of their conversation, they&#8217;d later learn).  Ten minutes later it was clear that while my sleuthing wasn&#8217;t entirely off the mark, it wasn&#8217;t the whole picture either. Voice #1 belonged to Lea: originally born in Serbia but living in the US for most of her life, currently pursuing a Master&#8217;s degree in Social Work in Boston, but had spent a few years of her upbringing in Germany. Her German, just like mine, was fluent and <em>almost</em> accent free but peppered by the occasional grammar mistake or forgotten vocabulary word. Voice #2 was Uyen: Vietnamese-German (or <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">German-Vietnamese</a>) as I suspected. Born in Vietnam, grew up in Berlin, also currently studying. And Voice #3 was Nicole&#8217;s: A German also working toward her degree in Social Work. The three were in a class together but it wasn&#8217;t a language one. Instead they were enrolled in an international summer course called &#8220;Diversity in the Big City&#8221;. A course focused on diversity in urban environments for those working in social professions and partly financed by the Federal Foreign Office in cooperation with the DAAD, Germany&#8217;s Academic Exchange Service. The course examines diversity through four lenses: social participation, social structure and urban development, migration and integration, and education.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-22-16-28-54.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-22-16-28-54.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-08-22 16.28.54" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>This is one of those moments I wish Chancellor Angela Merkel had been around to see. Not that I think about Merkel all that often or necessarily consider her a fun café partner, but it would&#8217;ve been satisfying to show the politician who proclaimed that &#8220;<a href="http://www.thenewamerican.com/world-news/europe/item/8685-sarkozy-joins-cameron-merkel-condemns-multiculturalism">multiculturalism has utterly failed</a>&#8221; this positive example of multiculturalism in the everyday.</p>
<p>And there we go again with one of our favorite words, &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221;. If we were so inclined, we could spend this whole damn blog analyzing that term. We wouldn&#8217;t mind so much actually &#8211; Kelly can&#8217;t even use the term &#8220;culture&#8221; without first defining it and I could happily talk your ears off about the relationship between cultural capital and educational achievement. Thankfully we&#8217;re savvy enough to realize it wouldn&#8217;t make things very fun for all of you. <em>Or would it?</em> No, of course it wouldn&#8217;t. Moving on. But write us if it might.</p>
<p>To be fair, it&#8217;s pretty near impossible to create a definitive understanding of &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221;.  The word&#8217;s become increasingly loaded as countries face burgeoning levels of immigration and struggle to incorporate diverse populations within their borders. In turn it&#8217;s dissected by academics, used strategically to shape policy, and tossed around in the everyday. It&#8217;s elusive and as some like to call it, a &#8220;moving target&#8221;. Kelly hit the nail on the head in one of <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/10/whose-multikulti-is-it-the-elusive-definition-of-multiculturalism/">her posts</a> and then bolded that nail so you&#8217;d pay attention: &#8220;The various meanings of <em>Multikulti</em> are just as ‘multi’ as the differences the word aims to describe&#8221;<strong>.</strong></p>
<p>I think we can start by agreeing that there is a stark difference between <em>saying</em> you&#8217;re something and actually <em>doing</em> something. Sociology Professor and Harvard PhD Irene Bloemraad has packaged this difference into a neat little theory called &#8220;symbolic&#8221; vs. &#8220;material&#8221; multiculturalism. In other words, talking the talk vs. walking the walk.</p>
<p>The United States, for example, is all about <em>symbolic multiculturalism</em>. Whichever food related metaphor you prefer &#8211; &#8220;melting pot&#8221;, &#8220;salad bowl&#8221;, or &#8220;ethnic stew&#8221; (yup, people say that) &#8211; the country&#8217;s national identity is forever tied to immigration and diversity. Yet as Bloemraad rightly points out, the US&#8217;s support of multiculturalism is more social than political: the country <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2NpHwYrIXWY">embraces multiculturalism</a> and individual expression but is not big on providing institutionalized resources toward integration and the political participation of immigrants.</p>
<p><em>Material multiculturalism</em> on the other hand is the government stepping in and addressing immigrant integration in an institutionalized way. Merkel&#8217;s certainly right that Germany is far from being a beacon of multiculturalism, but let&#8217;s not ignore the positive &#8220;material&#8221; work the country has recently embarked on: <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">integration courses</a>, new citizenship laws, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/18/rave-education-per-square-kilometer/">educational initiatives</a>, etc. Lea, Uyen, and Nicole&#8217;s &#8220;Diversity in the Big City&#8221; course is another example of how a small effort can promote multiculturalism both symbolically and materially: creating a space for international students to study diversity is a symbolic acknowledgement that those working in social spheres should gain this perspective. Funding these courses through the government is a material backing of this acknowledgement.</p>
<p>Much work still needs to be done, and I&#8217;m the first to acknowledge that four highly educated women chatting diversity over cappuccinos is a far cry from the challenges many other groups face in regards to integration. But whatever &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221; is, may, or should be, it hasn&#8217;t failed. It&#8217;s a symbolic and material work in progress. <em>Our</em> work in progress.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The adorable café pictured above is called</em> <a href="http://www.schoenescafe.de/">schönes café</a> <em>and is located in Kreuzberg&#8217;s Graefekiez. For more information on the &#8220;Diversity in the Big City&#8221; course and others run by DAAD, click <a href="https://www.daad.de/deutschland/studienangebote/sommerkurse/en/?ipp=50&amp;seite=1&amp;sk_akademie=0&amp;skchapter=0&amp;skduration=0&amp;skenter=&amp;skid=841&amp;sksubject=12&amp;skterm=&amp;sktown=&amp;stipendiate=0">here</a>. </em></p>
<p>Non-professional photos by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rave: Education Per Square (Kilo)Meter</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/18/rave-education-per-square-kilometer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2013 08:26:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moabit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=787</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[After all this talk about <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/">Nazis</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/">N-Words</a>, and <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/29/prejudice-with-condiments-understanding-schwabenhass/">negative stereotypes</a>, I think it's time we had some good news around here, don't you? <p style="text-align:left;">Enter <em>Ein Quadratkilometer Bildung</em>, or "Square Kilometer Education".</p>
<p style="text-align:left;"><em>Quadratkilometer Bildung</em> (QKB) is an educational development and learning platform that addresses education on a regional basis, with a focus on disadvantaged populations. They call it "closing gaps". I call it common sense...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/galerie1_1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-788" style="margin: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/galerie1_1.jpg" alt="Galerie1_1" width="642" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/galerie1_1.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/galerie1_1-300x199.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/galerie1_1-650x432.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 642px) 100vw, 642px" /></a></p>
<p>After all this talk about <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/">Nazis</a>, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/">N-Words</a>, and <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/29/prejudice-with-condiments-understanding-schwabenhass/">negative stereotypes</a>, I think it&#8217;s time we had some good news around here, don&#8217;t you?</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Enter <em>Ein Quadratkilometer Bildung</em>, or &#8220;Square Kilometer Education&#8221;.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.eu/"><em>Quadratkilometer Bildung</em></a> (QKB) is an educational development and learning platform that addresses education on a regional basis, with a focus on disadvantaged populations. QKB programs bridge schools with other regional institutions relevant to the lives of youth: we&#8217;re talking everything from youth service and day care centers to local authorities and city government. Programs also focus on <a href="http://oecdeducationtoday.blogspot.de/2013/05/evolving-attitudes-towards-early.html">early childhood education</a> and getting parents and community members involved early on. Education is thus attacked from multiple angles and a wider lens, becoming more collaborative, holistic, and effective. They call it &#8220;closing gaps&#8221;. I call it common sense.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/galerie5_1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/galerie5_1.jpg?w=300" alt="Galerie5_1" width="652" height="434" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Like most countries, Germany&#8217;s education system has its strengths and its weaknesses. The strongly adhered to tracking system employed by most German states means that students graduate with recognized qualifications and are better prepared for jobs, but are also separated early (usually in 4th grade) and only interact with students of their &#8220;level&#8221;. The recent focus on <a href="http://www.unesco.de/5588.html?L=1">inclusive education</a> has increased interest in <em>Gesamt</em>&#8211; or <em>Gemeinschaftsschulen</em> (comprehensive schools for all students), yet Germany&#8217;s federal system gives states control over their respective education systems. Read: it&#8217;s up to the individual states and may never happen. As long as tracking persists, and socioeconomic status remains <a href="http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00148-006-0102-y#page-1">the major determinant</a> for which track a child is funneled into, students with <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">migration backgrounds</a> will remain at a disadvantage.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Not surprisingly, QKB is run in two areas of Berlin plagued by low socioeconomic status and high numbers of residents with migration backgrounds: <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/">Neukölln</a> and Moabit. The Neukölln QKB program focuses on experiential learning workshops, early math skills, and talent development. In Moabit, programs emphasize <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/01/happy-weekend-a-roma-reimage/">Roma</a> school mentors and learning therapy for students with disabilities. Both programs pinpoint the need for early childhood language acquisition and increased parental involvement.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/tools11-e1374079477814.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/tools11-e1374079477814.jpg?w=300" alt="Tools1" width="637" height="471" /></a><strong>Unsere Traum Schule/Our Dream School (my favorite response: &#8220;a small petting zoo with small animals because the big ones&#8230;&#8221;)</strong></p>
<p>A few weeks ago, Kelly and I attended QKB&#8217;s second annual Film Night where the organization shared mini-clips of their programs and opened the floor for discussion. Together with the rest of the audience, we giggled through scenes of preschoolers scrunching their faces while trying to balance a scale, cringed at kids fitting themselves into drawers and shoving one another under cupboards, and came close to tears at emotional testimonials from mentors and parents.</p>
<p>The German term for education<em>, Bildung</em>, is more complex and comprehensive than its English counterpart. <em>Sich bilden</em> means &#8220;to form&#8221; or &#8220;to give rise to&#8221;. We&#8217;ve already agreed it takes a village to raise a child. How long before we realize that means the whole village?</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By</em><strong><em> Sophia Burton</em> </strong></p>
<p><em>In September 2013, QKB is opening a <a href="http://campusbildungimquadrat.eu/temporaeregalerie/">temporary gallery</a> at Berlin&#8217;s infamous </em><a href="http://tonymacaroni.wordpress.com/2012/08/24/campus-rutli-cr%C2%B2/">Campus Rütli – CR²</a> <em>school. The exhibit will serve as a communications platform connecting educational institutions with artists and the community. More information about the success of QKB programs by region (in German) can be found <a href="http://www.google.de/imgres?um=1&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sa=N&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;hl=de&amp;biw=1564&amp;bih=872&amp;tbm=isch&amp;tbnid=uqxsaX3evs8U1M:&amp;imgrefurl=http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.org/impressum/&amp;docid=4p0JNgWBJqHJiM&amp;imgurl=http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.org/wp-content/themes/km2/background/hintergrund3.jpg&amp;w=1024&amp;h=768&amp;ei=MormUafvG6nx4QSE9oHoBQ&amp;zoom=1&amp;iact=hc&amp;vpx=497&amp;vpy=219&amp;dur=1489&amp;hovh=194&amp;hovw=259&amp;tx=148&amp;ty=93&amp;page=1&amp;tbnh=141&amp;tbnw=188&amp;start=0&amp;ndsp=40&amp;ved=1t:429,r:3,s:0,i:91">here</a>. Information on QKB in English can be found <a href="http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.eu/">here</a> (click &#8220;km2 Education in English&#8221;).<br />
</em></p>
<p>First and second photo <a href="http://www.google.de/imgres?um=1&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sa=N&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;hl=de&amp;biw=1521&amp;bih=899&amp;tbm=isch&amp;tbnid=T1N-winrd21uFM:&amp;imgrefurl=http://www.land-der-ideen.de/presse/meldungen/ein-quadratkilometer-bildung&amp;docid=uokQqHVMjOJSjM&amp;imgurl=http://www.land-der-ideen.de/sites/default/files/styles/galleryformatter_slide/public/gallery/Galerie1_1.jpg&amp;w=800&amp;h=532&amp;ei=OM7mUcvDNIq1tAaR44CACw&amp;zoom=1&amp;iact=rc&amp;dur=360&amp;page=1&amp;tbnh=137&amp;tbnw=185&amp;start=0&amp;ndsp=39&amp;ved=1t:429,r:25,s:0,i:163&amp;tx=171&amp;ty=51">source</a>; Third photo <a href="http://www.google.de/imgres?um=1&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sa=N&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;hl=de&amp;biw=1521&amp;bih=899&amp;tbm=isch&amp;tbnid=bmcFUeai-R91iM:&amp;imgrefurl=http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.org/tools/&amp;docid=zkAFP8FKT9dE4M&amp;imgurl=http://www.ein-quadratkilometer-bildung.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/06/Tools1.jpg&amp;w=1500&amp;h=1125&amp;ei=VNHmUYjEFNDEtAaY1oDgDg&amp;zoom=1&amp;iact=rc&amp;dur=285&amp;page=1&amp;tbnh=158&amp;tbnw=209&amp;start=0&amp;ndsp=39&amp;ved=1t:429,r:31,s:0,i:181&amp;tx=116&amp;ty=109">source</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Whose Multikulti is it? The elusive definition of Multiculturalism</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/10/whose-multikulti-is-it-the-elusive-definition-of-multiculturalism/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2013 21:24:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=985</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The various meanings of the German word <em>Multikulti </em>are just as 'multi' as the differences the word aims to describe. Take the <em>Multikulti </em>breakfast, for example. Apparently, a "<em>Multikulti</em> breakfast" is eating Vegemite with maple syrup. Or is it? ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: justify;">If you put the German word <em>Multikulti* (</em>translated as &#8216;multicultural&#8217;, though it means much more) into Google Images, the many different representations, interpretations, and applications of the word appear in the humorous montage only the inter-webs can produce. Children with varying skin tones and hair textures playing together, ethnically diverse adults holding hands on a lawn, differently colored chess pieces dotting a globe, or &#8211; my favorite &#8211; a cartoon depiction of <em>Multikulti</em> individuals against a backdrop of the percentages of <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/"><em>Menschen mit</em> <em>Migrationshintergrund,</em></a> individuals with migration background, in large cities in Germany. A rosy-cheeked Muslim, a brown boy with a German flag, and&#8230;a strange child with a large gold necklace? <strong>The various meanings of <em>Multikulti </em>are just as &#8216;multi&#8217; as the differences the word aims to describe.</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://www.duesseldorf-blog.de/"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://www.duesseldorf-blog.de/wp-content/uploads/2009/01/integration.jpg" alt="" width="397" height="320" /></a></p>
<p><strong>the Public</strong></p>
<p>On the streets of Berlin, in the local paper, in the city&#8217;s stuffy Metro cars the picture isn&#8217;t any clearer. A sign reading &#8220;Multikulti party catering&#8221;  swings from a Senegalese food cart at the Bergmannstraßenfest. Heaps of thickly-sliced fried plantains with Cocktail sauce. &#8220;Multikulti in Schöneberg&#8221; headlines a newspaper article on real estate development. Dark-haired children frolicking on a sidewalk with no blonde-haired children in sight. &#8220;Multikulti shop&#8221; describes a place where one can find &#8216;party hats&#8217; and exotic party favors, as told from an elderly woman on the U-7. &#8220;Multikulti has absolutely failed&#8221; smeared across the room in the Chancellorin&#8217;s <a href="http://www.sueddeutsche.de/politik/integration-seehofer-sieben-punkte-plan-gegen-zuwanderung-1.1012736">speech</a>. Words planted within an integration discourse just learning to deal with real, long-lasting immigration, rather than the comings and goings of guest-workers.</p>
<p>In the airwaves of Berlin the word <em>Multikulti</em> is used as one might use &#8220;diversity&#8221;, even as one might simply say &#8220;different&#8221; or &#8220;differences&#8221;. <strong>It is sometimes used without comment or value-judgment. It is sometimes used to draw  lines in the sand between <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">integration</a> &#8211; read assimilation &#8211; and segregation &#8211; read parallel societies &#8211; as if any process were ever so clear and immediate.</strong> But when is such a word political and when does it <em>just</em> mean &#8216;different&#8217;?</p>
<p>Take the <em>Multikulti </em>breakfast, for example. A &#8220;<em>Multikulti</em> breakfast&#8221; is eating Vegemite with maple syrup, apparently. Simply put: something a little different from somewhere a little further than Cologne, Munich, or even Rostock, could be <em>Multikulti.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.morgengold.de/live/"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://www.morgengold.de/live/digitalAssets/125/125059_illu_multikulti_l.gif" alt="" width="536" height="225" /></a></p>
<p><strong>the Personal</strong></p>
<p>I spoke to a friend with whom I study sociocultural anthropology here in Berlin about what the word <em>Multikulti</em> means to him. He is young, German, gay, well-educated, well-traveled, and &#8216;anthropologically curious&#8217; (i.e. we love to deconstruct words like &#8216;culture&#8217;, making this whole piece quite a challenge in and of itself). He lives in the African Viertel in Wedding (my old stomping grounds) and spends quite a bit of time in <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/27/rave-neukollns-intercultural-day-to-day/">Neukölln</a> &#8211; the district branded with <em>Multikulti </em>as both claim-to-fame and <a href="http://www.stern.de/tv/sterntv/heinz-buschkowsky-multikulti-ist-gescheitert-1906880.html">scandal</a>.</p>
<p><em>Close your eyes and think of </em>Multikulti. <em>Now open them. What do you see</em>? I was hoping that such an exercise would work a little bit like Google Images, assembling a lovely decoupage of different ideas and popular motifs with the speed of a mouse-click. <em>I just think of Multivitaminsaft</em><em>, </em>multivitamin juice<em>.</em> <em>It just sounds like putting together a bunch of different pieces</em>, then branding the whole jar with a catch-all phrase for society&#8217;s use. <em>Do you see </em>Multikulti<em> in Wedding? </em>I ask. Wedding has a high and growing number of non-German residents, in terms of both citizenship and place of birth. <em>No, because it just exists. So, I wouldn&#8217;t call it Multikulti per say. <strong>It isn&#8217;t hyped up yet, like it is in Neukölln.</strong> <strong>Since everyone is moving to Neukölln, it&#8217;s become </strong></em><strong>Multikulti<em>. </em><em>I also just think of <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/18/happy-weekend-karneval-der-kulturen-carnival-of-cultures/">Karneval der Kulturen</a>. </em></strong><em>Packaged things&#8230;</em>Packaged diversity, rather than the real stuff, which doesn&#8217;t need external PR.</p>
<p><em>Multikulti</em>: the catch-all black-box term for dealing with difference. Its meaning depends on whose mouth delivers it, which  spaces enclose it (or don&#8217;t), and in which situation such a word is flung into the public or personal realm. And that is just the tip of the Vegemite-syrup-breakfast sandwich.</p>
<p>Understanding <em>Multikulti </em>is situational, buried in context and everyday life. <strong>It is a filler word, one to be picked up and laid down in places where our language fails at getting at complexities of urban encounters and differences, at challenging and playful <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/welcome-to-collidoscope/">collisions</a>.</strong> Before any more political discussions continue as to whether Berlin as a city will &#8220;fail&#8221; because of its <em>Multikulti</em> character, perhaps we should confirm just exactly what this <em>Multikulti is</em> to us, to voters, to residents, to admirers, to little children appearing in articles for or against a concept they may have never even heard of. This is a concept, <em>Multikulti</em> and multiculturalism, which, as our societies embrace difference as more the norm than the exception, might become irrelevant.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.eltern.de/kleinkind/erziehung/multikulti.html"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://s1.eltern.de/thumbnails/0001/00000000001/02/01/400pxx300px/0201a2c51441606763fa18b32f8ddd0auniqueidkindergarten_multikulti.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="300" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>*</em>Multikulti<em> is a term in the German language to be found not only in Germany, but in Austria and Switzerland, as well. This piece does not attempt to glorify the practice of &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221; politically or socially, nor does it seek to provide an operational definition for all uses of the term. Multiculturalism, including the more socially-flexible and popular term of </em>Multikulti<em> particularly in Berlin, will never mean one thing to all people. Multiculturalism is, however, often a matter of policy, making it concrete and important for the lives of many &#8211; which begs the question as to the efficacy of shaping society on the basis or in opposition to an elusively undefinable phenomenon. As the above picture illustrates, only through communication between these various poles of whatever </em>Multikulti<em> may be, can policies which are good for everyone be implemented and public discourses celebrating difference passed on.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>For a comprehensive review of the policy side of Multiculturalism in both the Americas and the European Union, see the Migration Policy Institute&#8217;s informative <a href="http://www.duesseldorf-blog.de/">report.</a></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Photo sources: images linked to web source</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Become a German (in just under 650 hours)</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2013 08:48:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=823</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[You must clean up after your dog. You must ride your bike in the right direction of the bike lane, </em>recites a Russian student. <strong>The audience chuckles.</strong> <em>First work, then... </em>chants the teacher. <strong>The audience groans.</strong> <em>Do you know any examples of German humor?</em> asks the teacher. <em>Uhhh, </em>fumbles the Japanese student. 10 seconds go by. <em>I'm still thinking, </em>he mutters and scratches his head. <strong>The audience roars...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/12_jorge_prados_beratungstermin_04.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/12_jorge_prados_beratungstermin_04.jpg" alt=" BERATUNGSTERMIN (BEI DER INDUSTRIE-UND HANDELSKAMMER)" width="640" height="360" /></a>No, not you, unless you&#8217;re interested. If so, then it&#8217;s time to sharpen your pencils, place them neatly in one of Germany&#8217;s ubiquitous pencil cases, and get ready to go back to school.</p>
<p>Let&#8217;s rewind a bit: <strong>For a long time, Germany refused to acknowledge itself as a &#8220;land of immigration&#8221;.</strong> The bulk of recent immigration came from post-World War II guest worker programs which were initially meant to be temporary, but many migrants stuck around. Their children and children&#8217;s children &#8211; the second and third generations &#8211; were born in Germany but continued to face challenges in regards to integration. They struggled socioeconomically and educationally, lacked German language proficiency, and often lived in parallel societies. In addition, Germany&#8217;s population was aging and fertility rates were declining.</p>
<p>So at the turn of the 21st century, Germany also made a sharp turn where immigration policy was concerned. Integrating &#8220;non-ethnic&#8221; immigrants and their children (and recruiting highly-skilled immigrants) became a priority. A <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">birthplace citizenship provision</a> was introduced, a national integration plan created, and a &#8220;Federal Commissioner for Migration, Refugees, and Integration&#8221; established. Language became the focal point of integration efforts:<strong> the majority of third country nationals (those from outside of the EU ) are now required to take over 600 hours of state-funded integration courses.</strong></p>
<p>Which brings us back to &#8220;Become a German&#8221; or <em>Werden Sie Deutscher</em>, a new documentary that follows an integration course in Berlin over the course of 10 months. We watch as the class &#8211; whose &#8220;stars&#8221; come from countries like Uruguay, Bangladesh, Bulgaria, and Turkey &#8211; wades its way through simulated spats with neighbors and gay marriage debates in the classroom to real-life job search trials and mundane subway rides.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/start1.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-833 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/start1.jpg" alt="start1" width="682" height="381" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/start1-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/start1-310x174.jpg 310w" sizes="(max-width: 682px) 100vw, 682px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Cultural Orientation &#8211; Rules and Behaviors. &#8220;Time is money&#8221;&#8230;&#8221;First work, then play&#8221;.</strong></p>
<p>As with any documentary, scenes are cut and pasted together to elicit the most laughs and cringe-worthy moments. Since this is Germany, at least half of the movie zooms in on bureaucracy and rules. <em>You must never</em> <em>throw out an important piece of paper</em>. <em>You must clean up after your dog. You must ride your bike in the right direction of the bike lane, </em>recites a Russian student. <strong>The audience chuckles.</strong> <em>First work, then&#8230; </em>chants the teacher. <strong>The audience groans.</strong> <em>Do you know any examples of German humor?</em> asks the teacher. <em>Uhhh, </em>fumbles the Japanese student. 10 seconds go by. <em>I&#8217;m still thinking, </em>he mutters and scratches his head. <strong>The audience roars.</strong> <em>Please wait outside,</em> instructs a bureaucrat to a family standing outside Berlin&#8217;s <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/24/lens-becoming-foreign-at-the-auslanderbehorde/">foreign resident center</a> in the middle of winter. <strong>The audience gasps. </strong></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/image-475099-galleryv9-svlk.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-835 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/image-475099-galleryv9-svlk.jpg" alt="Film / Werden sie Deutscher" width="640" height="359" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/image-475099-galleryv9-svlk.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/image-475099-galleryv9-svlk-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/image-475099-galleryv9-svlk-650x364.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/image-475099-galleryv9-svlk-310x174.jpg 310w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>The bureaucracy focus is exaggerated, considering that only 45 of the 645 required course hours are delegated to &#8220;orientation&#8221;. Yet, despite how <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/22/lens-becoming-berlinerin-at-the-burgeramt/">ridiculous </a>or boring German bureaucracy may seem, it&#8217;s a necessary system to understand and be able to navigate when living here. Just like regular school, these courses are not all about grades and memorization. They&#8217;re about life skills.</p>
<p>Though far from perfect, these courses are also a commendable effort in giving the newly arrived a fighting chance. The United States proudly waves its &#8220;multiculturalism loving melting pot of immigration&#8221; banner far and wide, but where is its federal office of immigrant integration and state-funded language courses? The adult immigrants I volunteered with in the US came to English class every day after work of entirely their own volition and out of their own pockets.</p>
<p>This film poses a host of larger questions about integration governance: What responsibility do countries have in welcoming newcomers and preparing them for their new society? What should (or shouldn&#8217;t) integration courses be teaching besides language? What does it really mean to be &#8220;integrated&#8221;? It also ignores some important questions: How do courses handle students with varying levels of education and literacy in their native tongues?  <strong>How are regular schools and the media addressing migration to promote intercultural understanding on the side of &#8220;natives&#8221;?</strong> How must German society continue to evolve to truly meet their new-found claim as a &#8220;land of immigration&#8221;?</p>
<p>Integration is, after all, a two-way street. Let&#8217;s just hope we&#8217;re all riding in the right direction.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By</em><strong><em> Sophia Burton</em></strong></p>
<p>&#8220;Werden Sie Deutscher&#8221; is currently <a href="http://www.werdensiedeutscher.de/kinotermine/">playing</a> in select cities around Germany.</p>
<p>Photo sources:<a href="http://www.spiegel.de/kultur/kino/kinodokus-werden-sie-deutscher-und-beerland-starten-a-886037.html"> Spiegel </a>and <a href="http://www.werdensiedeutscher.de/">Werden Sie Deutscher</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The N-Word</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2013 12:20:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nazi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=658</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When I posted the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/">Who's/Whose Normal?</a> article a few weeks ago, I expected the "N-word" of interest to be<em> Neger</em>, a term that falls somewhere between "negro" and "nigger" on the translation and offensiveness spectrum. Instead, the strongest reactions came in response to another N-Word: Nazi...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;">When I posted the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/">Who&#8217;s/Whose Normal?</a> article a few weeks ago, I expected the &#8220;N-word&#8221; of interest to be<em> Neger</em>, a term that falls somewhere between &#8220;negro&#8221; and &#8220;nigger&#8221; on the translation and offensiveness spectrum. Instead, the strongest reactions came in response to another N-Word: Nazi.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/thenword.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-756" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/thenword.png" alt="thenword" width="546" height="366" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">For those who haven&#8217;t read the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/14/rant-whoswhose-normal/">original post</a>, the controversy stemmed from a comparison I made between a Berlin storefront poster campaign and Nazi propaganda (on an aesthetic &#8211; not political &#8211; basis). On second thought, I shouldn&#8217;t put that last bit in parentheses, because it&#8217;s the essence of my point. Despite Berlin being <strong>Germany&#8217;s most ethnically and culturally diverse city</strong>, these particular <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/2013-04-11-09-35-05.jpg">storefront posters</a> feature <em>only</em> heterosexual Caucasian families. On an aesthetic basis (skin tone, facial features, body build), they don&#8217;t differ much from the fair blond couples on Nazi posters. A couple brunettes are included here or there, but I don&#8217;t consider that diversity. The bad man himself was a brunette, no? That&#8217;s probably not going to make me any friends either.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">While I am in no way comparing the people from this store to Nazis (I repeat: in no way!), I was disappointed by these posters and the message they send. On multiple posters and within an <a href="http://www.leiser.de/frontend/startseite.htm">entire website</a>, I find it disconcerting to see only one type of ethnicity, sexuality, and idea of beauty. And both creative process scenarios &#8211; whether <em>Leiser</em> consciously made this decision or didn&#8217;t realize that this is what they were doing &#8211; are also disconcerting.</p>
<p>Although many agreed with me that the images were problematic, my Nazi comparison was not as well-received. In the spirit of promoting discourse and &#8220;seeing things from every lens&#8221;, I thought it critical to share a selection of these reactions. Disclaimer: All German comments have been loosely translated by yours truly.</p>
<p><strong>German Commenter 1:</strong> In the U.S., you use the term &#8220;Nazi&#8221; as a joke, e.g. &#8220;You&#8217;re a cleaning Nazi&#8221;, just like we say the term <em>Negerküss</em> [Nigger-kiss]. Neither group considers the history and context of the other. In Germany, we only call really evil and abominable people Nazis, people who seem to be OK with what the Nazis did. It is the worst insult you can give someone. That&#8217;s why it&#8217;s such a hard pill for me to swallow when &#8220;normal&#8221; people (even if they are racist or discriminatory) are compared with Nazis, just like it is hard for Americans when they hear us use the term <em>Neger</em>.</p>
<p><strong>German Commenter 2:</strong> Sophia, you have to be really careful with the use of the term &#8220;Nazi&#8221;. Your comparison [of the storefront posters] to Nazi propaganda goes too far. Germans have a total complex when it comes to our history and you can&#8217;t just make that sort of comparison. As an American, you can&#8217;t understand how hard it is growing up with this history&#8230; You&#8217;re not exactly going to make friends with this sort of comparison.</p>
<p><strong>German/American Commenter in response to above:</strong> Is being critical un-German? Isn&#8217;t that how the Germans got into the Nazi/Holocaust mess to begin with?</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>American Commenter in response to above:</strong> Oh my god! Do these people seriously believe that anti-black racism is the same as calling someone &#8220;a cleaning Nazi&#8221;?? And that you can&#8217;t possibly understand that because you didn&#8217;t grow up there? WTF! I&#8217;m not jumping in because I don&#8217;t want to hijack a thread and you&#8217;re being much more diplomatic than I would be, but dude! What the hell!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-767 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes.jpg" alt="yikes" width="592" height="437" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes-300x221.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/yikes-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 592px) 100vw, 592px" /></a><strong>Me after reading the comments</strong></p>
<p>What these comments have made clear is that context is paramount in the interpretation of language. Perhaps more importantly, however, it has made clear that one shouldn&#8217;t limit themselves to only their immediate context. We can&#8217;t always dissect every word to see if it may offend someone, but we should be more mindful of the political, cultural, and historical contexts of other groups when using potentially hurtful language.</p>
<p>I&#8217;ve often heard that Americans are more PC (politically-correct) than Europeans. Yet, this discussion has shown me that that is not necessarily the case. All nations have sore spots in their histories &#8211; some more recent than others, some that should be sorer than they seem to be &#8211; where we need to tread lightly. We also handle these sensitive topics differently. There&#8217;s still no slavery memorial in Washington, DC, but the German capital is laden with memorials and museums acknowledging their &#8220;black mark on history&#8221;. Americans are known for being the kings (&amp; queens!) of PC language, but the Germans actually came up with a dictionary of Nazi terms to promote awareness of their use.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/350_b22810-2_u1d.gif"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/350_b22810-2_u1d.gif" alt="350_B22810-2_U1D" width="350" height="469" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>&#8220;A &#8216;Coming To Terms With The Past&#8217; Dictionary: The use of Nazi language in public speech&#8221; (</strong><a href="http://www.google.de/imgres?um=1&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sa=N&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;hl=de&amp;biw=1540&amp;bih=844&amp;tbm=isch&amp;tbnid=Ynymf1mQ2JxEDM:&amp;imgrefurl=http://www.wbg-wissenverbindet.de/WBGShop/php/Proxy.php%3Fpurl%3D/wbg/products/show,29637.html&amp;docid=VJO4nm_T0fhTJM&amp;itg=1&amp;imgurl=http://www.wbg-wissenverbindet.de/WBGShop/resources/cover/350_B22810-2_U1D.gif&amp;w=350&amp;h=469&amp;ei=WDWvUYqbB4bTtAapy4C4BA&amp;zoom=1&amp;iact=rc&amp;dur=292&amp;page=1&amp;tbnh=133&amp;tbnw=99&amp;start=0&amp;ndsp=60&amp;ved=1t:429,r:5,s:0,i:99&amp;tx=83&amp;ty=83">Source</a><strong>)</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Yes, the Germans have a word for &#8220;coming to terms with the past&#8221;: <em>Vergangenheitsbewältigung.</em> <em>Vergangenheit</em> simply means &#8220;the past&#8221;, but <em>bewältigen </em>can translate to several verbs, including &#8220;to overcome&#8221;<em>. </em><strong>What does it mean &#8211; as nations and people -to overcome difficult periods in our history?</strong> Does it mean erecting public memorials and monuments? Does it mean holding companies responsible for the images that they portray and promote? Does it mean never using the &#8220;N-word&#8221; or, alternately, being able to use it as a joke? I&#8217;m all ears and mindful speech.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/06/the-n-word/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
