<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Kreuzberg &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/kreuzberg/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Interview: Three Dimensions of Integration</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/07/interview-three-dimensions-of-integration/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/07/interview-three-dimensions-of-integration/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2014 07:14:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ex-pat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kreuzberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theater]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2212</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It's easy (and admittedly amusing) to reduce expats to stereotypes, as if we all neatly fall into one or the other category based on which country we hail from, what we do for a living, or where we party and eat brunch. Reality is always more nuanced and multi-dimensional. Dare we even say, interesting?...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Immigrant integration and identity can be very personal subjects and not everyone wishes for their views and experiences to be made public. Though all the stories in this interview are true, names and some cities have been changed to protect the artist&#8217;s identity, per his request.</em></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_0609.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_0609.jpg?w=640" alt="Admiralbruecke in Kreuzberg" width="604" height="604" /></a></p>
<p>It&#8217;s easy (<a href="http://www.uberlin.co.uk/stereotypes-different-expats-youll-meet-berlin/">and admittedly amusing</a>) to reduce expats to stereotypes, as if we all neatly fall into one or the other category based on which country we hail from, what we do for a living, or where we party and eat brunch. Reality is always more nuanced and multi-dimensional. Dare we even say, interesting?</p>
<p>Take Alex, American-born artist and documentary filmmaker living in Berlin. On first sight, the dual American-Polish citizen may appear to fit into a few niches: creative type with a studio in <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/20/lens-an-ode-to-the-maybachufer/">trendy Kreuzberg</a>, one of a rapidly growing number of young <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/07/rant-or-rave-jew-in-a-box/">Jews in Berlin</a>, jetsetter popping between speaking engagements in Europe and gigs in Los Angeles and Seattle. But Alex&#8217;s life in Berlin was more happy accident than predestined by career or background. The idea came from a professor who happened to hear him &#8220;complaining in the hallway about wanting to leave [his homestate] Illinois” and suggested a semester program in Offenbach near Frankfurt, Germany.</p>
<p>In 2003, Alex left the U.S. for Germany, and in the past decade, has spent time in Frankfurt, Stuttgart, and Karlsruhe. For the past six years he has been Berlin-based.</p>
<p><a href="http://friedrichshainblog.de/santa-maria-gutes-mexikanisches-restaurant-in-berlin-kreuzberg/"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2225" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/santa-maria-mexikaner-kreuzberg.jpg" alt="santa maria in kreuzberg" width="600" height="450" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/santa-maria-mexikaner-kreuzberg.jpg 600w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/santa-maria-mexikaner-kreuzberg-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/santa-maria-mexikaner-kreuzberg-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></a></p>
<p>I meet Alex in his studio on Adalbertstraße, where he shows me some clips of his documentary films and tells me start-ups are starting to take-over former artist space in the building. &#8220;Do you feel integrated?&#8221; I ask later over habanero-spiked food and aguas frescas at Oranienstraße&#8217;s Santa Maria Restaurant. &#8220;You&#8217;re really making me think here,&#8221; Alex ponders, slicing into his pumpkin burrito, &#8220;it&#8217;s a top-heavy question though, isn&#8217;t it? Depends on what you mean by &#8216;integrated&#8217;.&#8221;</p>
<p>Alex isn&#8217;t a fan of dichotomies, the idea that every question always has a right or wrong answer. He prefers to see the world in three dimensions, which he describes as &#8220;the pause in-between inhaling and exhaling&#8221;. Fittingly, by the end of our conversation, he&#8217;s given us three dimensions through which to consider integration.</p>
<p><strong>The Dance Performance</strong></p>
<p>Alex recently attended a dance performance by Wang Ramirez, a pair that works between Berlin, Paris, and London and are &#8220;<a href="http://wangramirez.com/">as diverse as the cultures that clashed and harmonized when its founders met</a>.&#8221;</p>
<p>“She is ethnically Korean but grew up in Germany, and he grew up in France but has Spanish roots,” Alex explains. &#8220;At one part during the evening&#8217;s program, a woman comes on stage and asks them one of those typical questions about language and identity. How their backgrounds influence their performance and such. Wang and Ramirez respond in a mix of languages and movements, getting progressively more incoherent, to show how essentially absurd and futile that question can be.&#8221;</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://vimeo.com/79000095"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter  wp-image-2223" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/wangramirez.jpg" alt="wangramirez" width="601" height="335" /></a><br />
<strong>The Jewish Guilt</strong></p>
<p>While attending a conference in Weimar to hear a professor friend of his speak, Alex was approached by a young German student looking for participants in a Jewish identity project.&#8221;He had just found out that he had some Jewish ancestry,&#8221; Alex recounts. &#8220;He wanted to do a photography project on young Jews in Germany to acknowledge this, and asked us if we would participate. Later, when my friend and I were alone and could discuss openly, we realized this project, like so many others, was focused on the past. My friend said, &#8216;why doesn&#8217;t he focus on Germany&#8217;s future instead, as a multicultural country? Perhaps learning Turkish would be a more meaningful contribution.’&#8221;</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>The Subway Encounter</strong></p>
<p>One late night on the U-Bahn, Alex found himself among a group of young Turkish-Germans. &#8220;People can&#8217;t usually tell where I&#8217;m from right off the bat. These guys in the U-Bahn asked me. My grandfather was a Sephardic Jew from Beirut, so I just told them I had a Lebanese grandfather and left out the rest. Once they thought I was Arab they started on how they love everyone and all religions&#8230; <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/">Muslims</a>, Christians, Jews, etc. Later I wondered how the conversation would have been different if I had said I was Jewish.&#8221;</p>
<p><a href="http://www.aviatorsandacamera.com/travel/nye-art-technology-in-berlin-part-2/"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter  wp-image-2224" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/ubahn.jpg" alt="berlin u-bahn" width="533" height="397" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/ubahn.jpg 259w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/ubahn-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 533px) 100vw, 533px" /></a></p>
<p>&#8212;&#8211;</p>
<p>&#8220;Berlin is a great place to come and figure out who you are and what you want to do. It&#8217;s just not the best place to make that happen, funding and opportunity wise,&#8221; Alex explains. &#8220;I always say Berlin is a city full of possibility, but not necessarily potential.&#8221; Alex, like many expats, is not sure what the future holds, other than it being a transnational one. No matter how much opportunity exists on the West Coast, it seems he will always be tied to Germany and, more specifically, Berlin. &#8220;Berlin is a city that breaks my heart,&#8221; he reminisces, &#8220;it broke my heart even before I lived here. Just the thought that a place like this even exists.”</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>First image by Sophia Burton, all others linked to sources.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/07/interview-three-dimensions-of-integration/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Multiculturalism, Diversity, and the Big City</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2013 18:48:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kreuzberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1358</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[With my back to them at the street-side café I felt like a judge on "<a href="http://www.nbc.com/the-voice/">The Voice</a>", straining my neck for any hint of where they were from or what they looked like, resisting the urge to swirl around and start dancing on my chair. Truth be told my ears had perked up as soon as the trio plopped down at the table behind me, switching between topics like gentrification in Kreuzberg and the cultural difference between <em>Kaffee</em> and "coffee" as quickly as they were switching between German and English...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/photo-1-2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/photo-1-2.jpg" alt="photo-1 (2)" width="640" height="640" /></a></p>
<p>With my back to them at the street-side café I felt like a judge on &#8220;<a href="http://www.nbc.com/the-voice/">The Voice</a>&#8220;, straining my neck for any hint of where they were from or what they looked like, resisting the urge to swirl around and start dancing on my chair. Truth be told my ears had perked up as soon as the trio plopped down at the table behind me, switching between topics like gentrification in Kreuzberg and the cultural difference between <em>Kaffee</em> and &#8220;coffee&#8221; as quickly as they were switching between German and English.</p>
<p>Voice #1: &#8220;I speak differently when I speak to you, or to Brits, or to other Americans. I’m speaking much slower right now and I explain things differently.&#8221; <em> Aha! A fellow American. Is she a teacher? Is this a language class? </em><em>&#8220;</em>Wait, were you just speaking in English or German?&#8221; <em>Hmm, maybe not a teacher. Did she also grow up with both languages? Is that a slight accent I detect? </em></p>
<p>Voice #2: &#8220;My name, Uyen&#8230; well for us the middle name is actually the main name, the name before that is just to make the name more beautiful. And my last name is unique, a combination of my mother&#8217;s and father&#8217;s names. Even my sisters don&#8217;t have it because the province where I was born doesn&#8217;t have the same rules like they do here.&#8221; &#8216;<em>Uyen&#8217;&#8230; is that Vietnamese? Germany has <a href="http://www.germany.info/Vertretung/usa/en/05__Legal/02__Directory__Services/04__Family__Matters/__Name.html">laws</a> about children&#8217;s names.. maybe she was born in Vietnam and then her family moved to Germany and her sisters were born here?</em></p>
<p>Voice #3: &#8220;In another language it&#8217;s always different, the, the&#8230; how do you say <em>Betonung auf Englisch</em>?&#8221; <em>The others are struggling to find the translation, should I interject&#8230;? No that&#8217;d be rude, though maybe they&#8217;d appreciate the&#8230;</em></p>
<p>SLAM! Down went my button and I whirled around.</p>
<p>&#8220;Emphasis!&#8221; I yelped, nearly toppling over on the cobblestones. &#8220;Sorry&#8230; for, uh, listening in on your conversation,&#8221; I continued a bit sheepishly, trying to redeem myself, &#8220;It was just really interesting!&#8221;</p>
<p>Lucky for me they were not only open to the vocabulary assistance but also for a chat with the lady who&#8217;d been shamelessly eavesdropping on them (and typing up parts of their conversation, they&#8217;d later learn).  Ten minutes later it was clear that while my sleuthing wasn&#8217;t entirely off the mark, it wasn&#8217;t the whole picture either. Voice #1 belonged to Lea: originally born in Serbia but living in the US for most of her life, currently pursuing a Master&#8217;s degree in Social Work in Boston, but had spent a few years of her upbringing in Germany. Her German, just like mine, was fluent and <em>almost</em> accent free but peppered by the occasional grammar mistake or forgotten vocabulary word. Voice #2 was Uyen: Vietnamese-German (or <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">German-Vietnamese</a>) as I suspected. Born in Vietnam, grew up in Berlin, also currently studying. And Voice #3 was Nicole&#8217;s: A German also working toward her degree in Social Work. The three were in a class together but it wasn&#8217;t a language one. Instead they were enrolled in an international summer course called &#8220;Diversity in the Big City&#8221;. A course focused on diversity in urban environments for those working in social professions and partly financed by the Federal Foreign Office in cooperation with the DAAD, Germany&#8217;s Academic Exchange Service. The course examines diversity through four lenses: social participation, social structure and urban development, migration and integration, and education.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-22-16-28-54.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-08-22-16-28-54.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-08-22 16.28.54" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>This is one of those moments I wish Chancellor Angela Merkel had been around to see. Not that I think about Merkel all that often or necessarily consider her a fun café partner, but it would&#8217;ve been satisfying to show the politician who proclaimed that &#8220;<a href="http://www.thenewamerican.com/world-news/europe/item/8685-sarkozy-joins-cameron-merkel-condemns-multiculturalism">multiculturalism has utterly failed</a>&#8221; this positive example of multiculturalism in the everyday.</p>
<p>And there we go again with one of our favorite words, &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221;. If we were so inclined, we could spend this whole damn blog analyzing that term. We wouldn&#8217;t mind so much actually &#8211; Kelly can&#8217;t even use the term &#8220;culture&#8221; without first defining it and I could happily talk your ears off about the relationship between cultural capital and educational achievement. Thankfully we&#8217;re savvy enough to realize it wouldn&#8217;t make things very fun for all of you. <em>Or would it?</em> No, of course it wouldn&#8217;t. Moving on. But write us if it might.</p>
<p>To be fair, it&#8217;s pretty near impossible to create a definitive understanding of &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221;.  The word&#8217;s become increasingly loaded as countries face burgeoning levels of immigration and struggle to incorporate diverse populations within their borders. In turn it&#8217;s dissected by academics, used strategically to shape policy, and tossed around in the everyday. It&#8217;s elusive and as some like to call it, a &#8220;moving target&#8221;. Kelly hit the nail on the head in one of <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/10/whose-multikulti-is-it-the-elusive-definition-of-multiculturalism/">her posts</a> and then bolded that nail so you&#8217;d pay attention: &#8220;The various meanings of <em>Multikulti</em> are just as ‘multi’ as the differences the word aims to describe&#8221;<strong>.</strong></p>
<p>I think we can start by agreeing that there is a stark difference between <em>saying</em> you&#8217;re something and actually <em>doing</em> something. Sociology Professor and Harvard PhD Irene Bloemraad has packaged this difference into a neat little theory called &#8220;symbolic&#8221; vs. &#8220;material&#8221; multiculturalism. In other words, talking the talk vs. walking the walk.</p>
<p>The United States, for example, is all about <em>symbolic multiculturalism</em>. Whichever food related metaphor you prefer &#8211; &#8220;melting pot&#8221;, &#8220;salad bowl&#8221;, or &#8220;ethnic stew&#8221; (yup, people say that) &#8211; the country&#8217;s national identity is forever tied to immigration and diversity. Yet as Bloemraad rightly points out, the US&#8217;s support of multiculturalism is more social than political: the country <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2NpHwYrIXWY">embraces multiculturalism</a> and individual expression but is not big on providing institutionalized resources toward integration and the political participation of immigrants.</p>
<p><em>Material multiculturalism</em> on the other hand is the government stepping in and addressing immigrant integration in an institutionalized way. Merkel&#8217;s certainly right that Germany is far from being a beacon of multiculturalism, but let&#8217;s not ignore the positive &#8220;material&#8221; work the country has recently embarked on: <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">integration courses</a>, new citizenship laws, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/18/rave-education-per-square-kilometer/">educational initiatives</a>, etc. Lea, Uyen, and Nicole&#8217;s &#8220;Diversity in the Big City&#8221; course is another example of how a small effort can promote multiculturalism both symbolically and materially: creating a space for international students to study diversity is a symbolic acknowledgement that those working in social spheres should gain this perspective. Funding these courses through the government is a material backing of this acknowledgement.</p>
<p>Much work still needs to be done, and I&#8217;m the first to acknowledge that four highly educated women chatting diversity over cappuccinos is a far cry from the challenges many other groups face in regards to integration. But whatever &#8220;multiculturalism&#8221; is, may, or should be, it hasn&#8217;t failed. It&#8217;s a symbolic and material work in progress. <em>Our</em> work in progress.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The adorable café pictured above is called</em> <a href="http://www.schoenescafe.de/">schönes café</a> <em>and is located in Kreuzberg&#8217;s Graefekiez. For more information on the &#8220;Diversity in the Big City&#8221; course and others run by DAAD, click <a href="https://www.daad.de/deutschland/studienangebote/sommerkurse/en/?ipp=50&amp;seite=1&amp;sk_akademie=0&amp;skchapter=0&amp;skduration=0&amp;skenter=&amp;skid=841&amp;sksubject=12&amp;skterm=&amp;sktown=&amp;stipendiate=0">here</a>. </em></p>
<p>Non-professional photos by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Ramadan with Neighbors: It&#8217;s About Showing Up</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2013 14:17:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kreuzberg]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1203</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For those non-Muslims among us, Ramadan is an almost hidden spectacle with mysterious allure: the hot tea, the music, and the platters of food only come out when the sun has turned in for the day or before it has even appeared. We hear the clatter of dishes from our neighbors’ windows late into the night or watch children unpack colorful sweets on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eid_ul-Fitr"><i>Eid al-Fitr</i></a>, all without necessarily being able to place these traditions in our own line of experience. In honor of the last night of Ramadan, here is a reflection on an event Sophia and I attended last Friday as part of Berlin's festival <a href="http://www.piranhakultur.de/event/events_2013/naechte_des_ramadan"><i>die </i></a><i><a href="http://www.piranhakultur.de/event/events_2013/naechte_des_ramadan">Nächte des Ramadan</a>, </i>the Nights of Ramadan...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Many of the world&#8217;s cities teem with fasting bodies during the c. 30 days of the Muslim holiday of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramadan_(calendar_month)">Ramadan</a>. About <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/berlin/berlinerstatistik/1670484.html">300,000 Muslims</a> live in Berlin: that makes for a lot of hungry individuals during the holy month. Of course, not every Muslim fasts, not every faster is Muslim, and not all Muslims celebrate Ramadan the same (or even at all). But for those non-Muslims among us, Ramadan is an almost hidden spectacle with mysterious allure: the hot tea, the music, and the platters of food that only come out when the sun has turned in for the day or before it has even appeared. We hear the clatter of dishes from our neighbors’ windows late into the night or watch children unpack colorful sweets on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eid_ul-Fitr"><i>Eid al-Fitr</i></a>, all without necessarily being able to place these traditions in our own line of experience. So, what is it actually like to break the fast at the end of the day among friends and family? Among neighbors?</p>
<p>Today is the last day of Ramadan, so it is high time for some reflection on an event Sophia and I attended last Friday as part of Berlin&#8217;s festival <a href="http://www.piranhakultur.de/event/events_2013/naechte_des_ramadan"><i>die </i></a><i><a href="http://www.piranhakultur.de/event/events_2013/naechte_des_ramadan">Nächte des Ramadan</a>, </i>the Nights of Ramadan. Organized by the <a href="http://kreuzbergmuseum.de/index.php?id=1">Kreuzberg Museum</a>, the whole community was invited to an <a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/berlin/muslime-in-berlin-reim-den-ramadan,10809148,23930332.html"><i>Iftar </i></a>celebration, the nightly breaking of the fast, in the museum&#8217;s garden right near <i>Kottbusser Tor</i>. Of course the breaking of bread in the privacy of one’s home is different from the organization of an intentional <em><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/10/whose-multikulti-is-it-the-elusive-definition-of-multiculturalism/">Multikulti</a></em> program. This event was not just about eating and drinking in public after another day doing without: it was about bringing fasting bodies together with the curious non-Muslims or non-fasters among us.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/photo.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1208" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/photo.jpg?w=640" alt="photo" width="640" height="640" /></a></p>
<p><i>The gates to the Kreuzberg Museum open to long tables and benches decked with white cloth and table settings. Plates of bloated dates run down the center, stuffed with walnuts, dark chocolate, and coconut.  </i>&#8220;They just put everything in them our bodies might want”,<i> says the small-framed woman across from me with a laugh &#8211; an instructor of </i><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">Integrationskurse</a><i>* in Berlin, she tells me. Having fasted and even worked all day, she doesn&#8217;t seem one bit tired, rather concentrated and composed. I am boiling in the midst of what I consider extreme humidity; not a bead of sweat is to be seen on her face which sits surrounded by heavy, sage-green cloth. </i>“You just get used to it, to not eating”,<i> she responds, when I ask if it is difficult, my flashbacks of Lent-related chocolate withdrawal ever-present. </i>“And I can lay down once and a while at work to rest”,<i> she adds. She has been fasting for years, even before she was a practicing Muslim. </i>“I used to fast with my brother, though my parents never participated”.<i> She is originally from Azerbaijan, six years in Germany and still not sure if it’s home. “</i>They are German”,<i> she says pointing to her three friends, “</i>I just live here”<i>. A laugh erupts into the sticky night. She rests her palm on her cheek. </i></p>
<p><i>I find the buffet prepared by (the speaker’s words not mine) </i>die Arabische Frauen<i> (Arab women) and try to take a picture of the overwhelming spread. Ladies in bright colors scurry to assemble more heaps of greasy drumsticks, mounds of semolina and rice with toasted almonds, deep-fried spinach and clumps of rose-colored meat in a breaded dress. </i></p>
<p><i>A small man brings the microphone to his lips  &#8211; not on the stage, but beneath it &#8211; and the prayer begins. It is exactly 9:02pm, and the sun has sunken beneath the city lights. No one dares to nibble on the dates, which is the signal that the fast has been broken. It is silent except for the melodic call to prayer. The teacher from Azerbaijan mouths the words without making a sound, her cheekbones concealed now by the edges of her headscarf</i>. <i>Her head turns downward to fall into her hands forming an invisible Koran in her lap, her palms and their scriptures seeming to capture all sound.</i></p>
<p><i>The three friends of our new teacher-friend return to the table with piles of food, offering us as much as we like, since we will not be getting in line until after those who have fasted. When we protest, the teacher remarks in between slow and measured bites off the chicken bone in her hand,</i> “Your stomach shrinks throughout the day, so your eyes are much bigger than your capacity”. <i>She smiles and points to the mound of food in the middle of our table. Köfte is rolled onto our plates as we politely probe with questions. The three friends are just beginning their 20s, studying at university, active in the </i>organization <a href="http://www.muslimische-jugend.de/">Muslimische Jugend in Deutschland e.V</a><i>. Their involvement in this organization brought them and the teacher together, who seems to smile adoringly but wisely at her younger companions as they speak. None of the three wear </i>hijab; <i>one is engaged to her high school sweetheart and studying to earn her PhD in forensic science. </i></p>
<p style="text-align: center;" align="center"> <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/photo-2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter  wp-image-1207" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/photo-2.jpg?w=640" alt="photo (2)" width="448" height="448" /></a></p>
<p><i>The director of the Kreuzberg Museum addresses the public – families finished eating though chattering loudly as ever, interested passers-by with backpacks watching the stage, the Kreuzberg Fire Dept. laughing with friends and looking dapper in suits. A small German man in a somber white button-down and black pant, he thanks the neighbors for their patience in tolerating the noise and those neighbors who came to take part, then introduces the musical performance of the night. The Iraqi-German musician <a href="http://www.saif-karomi.com/music.htm">Saif Karomi</a> enters the stage with a beautiful Oud gripped in his right hand. His music, with the accompaniment of a slender wooden flute and a steady Djembe, seeps out into the night. Most of the windows from Kotti’s high-rise apartments are glowing, many left open to let the sounds and the light stream in. </i></p>
<p style="text-align: center;" align="center"><a href="http://www.piranhakultur.de/gallery/ramadan_2013/saif_karomi_02_08"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1231" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/music.jpg" alt="Music" width="400" height="333" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/music.jpg 400w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/music-300x249.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a></p>
<p><i>Trays of dessert circulate the courtyard: pistachio cream with rose water in a honey-soaked pancake </i>(Qatayef);<i> walnuts bathed in honey, chopped, and folded delicately into sweet bread; pistachio and nougat doused in dark chocolate and coconut. Hot tea is served in elegant glasses fit to the palm. Clapping begins in rhythmic compliment to the weeping lull of the Oud. At 11pm the lanterns are extinguished. We head out the gates of the Kreuzberg museum, passing a line of young people smoking on the steps near the sheet of Kebap shops and neon-lit bars. We move on and outward into the other neighborhoods we know well, my body in anything but a state of want.</i></p>
<p align="center"> <a href="http://www.recettes-cuisine-afrique.info/IMG/jpg/Qatayef.jpg"><img loading="lazy" src="http://www.recettes-cuisine-afrique.info/IMG/jpg/Qatayef.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="300" /></a></p>
<p>At this event, I kept asking myself what the words &#8220;integration&#8221; and &#8220;diversity&#8221; really mean to the politicians who speak them. To me, it is not about &#8220;to each his or her own&#8221; or just about learning the majority language, rather it is about taking part in a two-way process. It is about getting to know one another and forging new spaces of neighborhood between these ways of knowing. It is often just about showing up to our neighbor’s barbecue, about inviting the friendly guy from the <i>Späti</i> to a party, about delivering mail to the lady upstairs (even if she never looks friendly) and staying in a slightly damp hallway to chit-chat (and not because you want to). I have learned from these experiences that it really is just about going to places, interacting with others, and maybe asking questions. Taking an interest in the life and interests of one’s neighbor is an integral part of what it means to live in a metropolis. Any other way forward and things might just fall apart.</p>
<p>Ramadan is one way of holding everything together, keeping us honest in whether or not we really value difference – just like I really value pistachio cream and the Oud, maybe just as much as I value mayo on my fries or the American Diner. Such meet-your-neighbor events also give us reason to congregate and converse about all the things we do not know but might just assume about one another. Not everyone at this event wore <em>hijab</em> or prayed with beads, not everyone fasted, not everyone was Muslim or even the same type of Muslim, for that matter.</p>
<p>It should be of interest to all of us that nearly 7% of Berlin&#8217;s population may be abstaining from food and water in 90 degree heat and 50% humidity, still going to work, driving cars, pushing strollers, running errands, participating in daily life during the holiest days in the Muslim religion. This phenomenon is happening all over the world, times ten, in many different shapes and flavors.</p>
<p>The Kreuzberg Museum holds this event every year. We hope events like it will show up in places less expected than Kreuzberg, maybe even more situated in the everyday. We just have to show up and be a part of it.</p>
<p><i>&#8211; By <b>Kelly Miller</b></i></p>
<p>*<i>Integrationskurse</i> are federally mandated integration courses for immigrants and refugees within their first three years of residence in Germany. However, these courses have only been in existence since 2005, allowing many earlier waves of immigrants the chance to participate in a combination of language-learning and cultural orientation after the three year period has passed.</p>
<p>Photos by Sophia Burton or otherwise sourced with link to image.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
