<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>History &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/category/history/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Why Feminism and Hijab Go Together</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2016/12/04/feminism-hijab-go-together/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2016 09:30:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[feminism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hijab]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4704</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As Muslim refugees who choose to wear hijab become a lasting part of the societies of those European states that have taken them in, their right to be different must be defended. Most importantly, we must defend the right of women to choose. It is this choice that makes women free. This is why feminism and hijab go together.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Donald Trump will soon take over the most (seemingly) powerful office in the United States. In just one month,&nbsp;<em>Vogue</em> will launch&nbsp;its <a href="http://en.vogue.fr/fashion/fashion-news/articles/conde-nast-international-launches-vogue-arabia/43938">first ever Arabia edition</a>. These two events are related &#8211; by hijab.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Only hours after Trump was proclaimed victor by electoral vote, a certain fear took hold in minority populations in the United States. Fear of deportation, of political oppression, of social persecution. This fear has proven itself well-founded. The Southern Poverty Law Center recently reported </span><a href="http://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/hate-on-the-rise-after-trumps-election">a dramatic increase in hate crimes and xenophobic harassment</a>, since Trump’s victory.</p>
<div id="attachment_4711" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4711" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4711 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341-650x433.jpg" alt="reise_usa-2015-bearbeitet-341" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_USA-2015-Bearbeitet-341.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4711" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Given the President-elect’s verbal attacks on Islam and Muslims in (or coming to) America, this fear of emboldened hostility in the general populace is felt <a href="http://people.com/bodies/muslim-women-scared-wear-hijab-trump-win/">ever so acutely</a> by America’s diverse Muslim community. Muslim women, in particular, have expressed a new hesitation to wear hijab in public &#8211; the traditional headscarf &#8211; following the election. As </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">New York Magazine</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> reports, many young Muslima <a href="http://nymag.com/thecut/2016/11/after-trumps-win-muslim-women-are-afraid-to-wear-the-hijab.html">took this fear to twitter</a>. One young woman tweeted her devout mother’s words of caution, &#8220;Please don’t wear your hijab today,&#8221; only to be attacked by right-wing trolls, twitter’s escalating problem in this age of free speech and anti-democratic vitriol. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Whether or not a Trump presidency and its fallout will actually lead to physical harm of Muslim women is not something we can know, right now. But we can juxtapose this fear&nbsp;with hijab as an object of both identity and ridicule&nbsp;&#8211; an object that conservative movements and some European governments have taken outright offense to.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Editor-in-chief of Vogue<em> Arabia</em> is a Saudi princess, a self-professed queen of elegant women in any silhouette. She, </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Deena Aljuhani Abdulaziz, </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">is also a champion of the down-to-earth cat-walk. And she does not (perhaps no surprise here) actually live in the Kingdom</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Although D. Aljuhani Abdulaziz&nbsp;does not herself wear hijab, she supports women who do. According to her interview with </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The New York Times</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, the consumer preferences of Muslim women are <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/11/03/fashion/islamic-fashion-vogue-arabia.html">at the core of this <em>Vogue</em></a>. The magazine’s mission for women in the Muslim world, she explained, is to highlight dress in its femininity, its creativity, and its usage by everyday women across the Arab world, hijab or no hijab. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is not only Arab women living in Doha or Beirut who ascribe to the beauty norms of hijab-wearing models and hijab-based marketing, thus <em>Vogue Arabia</em>’s readership will surely not stay confined to the Arab world. It is published online in both English and Arabic and maintains an international aesthetic (both in branding and in the women who gloss its pages). The princess and Conde Nast seem cognizant of the status of women in hijab: they represent an established style and lifestyle, on a global scale. </span></p>
<div id="attachment_4712" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4712" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4712 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2-650x433.jpg" alt="reise_london-2014-bearbeitet-2" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Reise_London-2014-Bearbeitet-2.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4712" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This recognition is not limited to Big Money in the Arab world. Women in hijab have begun to take their place among trendsetting brands in countries in which they are decidedly the minority. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Even in Trump’s America, CoverGirl recently <a href="http://firsttoknow.com/meet-the-new-face-of-covergirl-hijab-wearing-beauty-blogger-nura-afia/?utm_source=contentad_backfill&amp;utm_campaign=meet-the-new-face-of-cov-211246&amp;pp=1&amp;utm_medium=180533">added a Muslima in hijab</a> to its blogosphere and promotional sites, a hijab-friendly designer <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-37381770">stole the show at this year’s New York Fashion Week</a>, a U.S. beauty pageant contestant&nbsp;did <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/goatsandsoda/2016/11/29/503729951/the-beauty-pageant-contestant-wore-a-burkini">the whole thing in burkini and hijab</a>, and (if you haven’t heard) Marvel released <a href="http://marvel.wikia.com/wiki/Kamala_Khan_(Earth-616)">its first Muslima superhero</a>. Yes, even superheroes can wear scarves, and <a href="https://mic.com/articles/125199/badass-muslim-superheroes-comics-tv">it doesn&#8217;t stop at Marvel</a>.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><em>Vogue</em> and these other agents of popular culture bring the hijab into a different type of mainstream &#8211; of fashion and femininity. In asserting that &#8220;Yes, this too is a woman,&#8221; a woman’s choice of what to wear is expanded. Bikinis were first <a href="http://content.time.com/time/photogallery/0,29307,1908353_1905442,00.html">popularized and freed from social taboo</a> by aggressive marketing campaigns and photo-shoots. So, why not hijab? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Perhaps the most important point, however, is not whether or not hijab can be normalized; it is whether or not such mainstreaming actually leads to more freedom. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the case of Muslima in increasingly hostile environments, such as the United States or any European state as of late, this freedom is being put to the test. Hijab or body-covering of any sort is increasingly becoming a marker of difference. With the rise of the populist Right, our societies are becoming more and more opposed to such difference. And the power of the masses has, historically, had something to say about women’s dress, women’s bodies, and, ultimately, women’s rights. For better or for worse.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Women’s heads have been the subject of political struggle for centuries. In this century, the forcible removal of hijab has corresponded with two trends, in particular: with Western influence in majority-Muslim countries or, as this summer’s burkini controversy demonstrated, with Western societies asserting nationalistic values and (patriarchal) identity. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;Freedom from&#8221; or &#8220;freedom to&#8221; are phrases associated with women’s behaviors, from dress to sexual activity to reproductive health, from France to Saudi Arabia. And we are often told to take a side: &#8220;Do you want women to be free from patriarchal oppression?&#8221; or &#8220;Do you want women to be free to wear whatever they choose?&#8221; </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But how does one think about the fight to wear hijab and the fight to be freed from hijab in one, unified thought? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Iran is a near perfect testament to such a thought. The country&#8217;s transition from Reza Shah Pahlavi to Ayatollah Khomeini provides an example of an apparent (and near perfect) paradox in practice.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the late 1920s in a still monarchical Iran, the Shah instituted what he called &#8220;a gradual process of hijab removal&#8221; from public institutions. The Shah’s friend and mentor, Turkey’s Mustafa Kemal Attatürk, espoused the view that head-covering reflected not only non-Western dress but non-Western thought. &#8220;Backwards women&#8221; stood for an undesirable social system, which extended into the confines of the home. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hijab was thus a stand-in or a symbol for the greater societal transformation each autocratic leader desired for the value system of his society. If Turkey and Iran were to join the rational, &#8220;enlightened&#8221; throngs of European history, in body and in mind, women had to remove their scarves.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Iran, in the period between these so-called modernization reforms and the Revolution, looked much like any other European country, with tanned youth in swimsuits smoking cigarettes on the beach, and Beatles records flying off the shelves. But in the late 1970s, frustration with the corrupt dictatorship of the Shah and the monarchy as a system of undemocratic government brought thousands of Iranian men and women out onto the streets. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the early days of 1979, secular and religious women alike protested for the right to ascribe to the value system of their choice. Whether Western or not, it was up to women to decide, not the Shah. </span></p>
<div id="attachment_4714" style="width: 510px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4714" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4714 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Iranian_Revolution_1979_marching_young_people.jpeg" alt="iranian_revolution_1979_marching_young_people" width="500" height="339" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Iranian_Revolution_1979_marching_young_people.jpeg 500w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Iranian_Revolution_1979_marching_young_people-300x203.jpeg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4714" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Wikimedia Commons</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As the revolution took a strident Islamic turn, women who did not wear hijab began to see the institution of the new state as a threat to their freedom of choice. Indeed, the &#8220;Islamic&#8221; in &#8220;Islamic Republic&#8221; now meant hijab, for all women. Iranian women were thus divided along ideological lines, and the new Islamic state was thus effective in reducing the voice and power of its most educated and mobile constituency: women.</span></p>
<p><iframe title="March 8, 1979 Iranian Women March Against Hijab and Islamic Laws" width="650" height="488" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/pxGYLk92edY?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With religious rule by Ayatollah Khomeini came moral rule in the homes and upon the bodies of women. Laws protecting women against the men of their family were eliminated. But as long as women were covered, they were able to obtain political office, attend university, and build a career. The hijab acted as a pass into the greater halls of society. It continues to act as the safeguard of a theocratic order, which exercises control while permitting necessary freedoms.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Iranian case is not so different from the European burkini fiasco last summer. The burkini &#8211; a full-body covering made of swimwear material, with an attached head covering like a swim cap &#8211; was banned in many French towns and cities for its subversion of secularist values. Women were to uphold the state’s belief in its own ideological abstention from religious practice in public life. Even while swimming. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The ban has since been <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-37198479">overturned at a federal level</a>, though some French municipalities claim that they will continue to enforce it. The mayor in the town where the ban made headlines, with police officers requiring a woman to remove her <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/08/28/world/europe/france-burkini-bikini-ban.html?_r=0">burkini on the beach</a>, called the ban an attempt to require &#8220;<a href="http://edition.cnn.com/2016/08/30/europe/french-mayor-cogolin-burkini-ban/">them to adopt our way of life.&#8221;</a> The &#8220;them&#8221; in this sentiment could be none other than Muslims, Europe&#8217;s favorite Other.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Liberal democracies, which respect the rights of minorities, demand pluralism &#8211; in lifestyle, in religious practice, in appearance, in ideology. Why does this pluralism extend only partially to women?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In France, the beach was briefly a battlefield. Muslim women were caught at the cross hairs of a power play between establishment norms and the liberty of choice that defines many arguments of cultural expression in other countries. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But the battlefield is an ideological one, surpassing the boundaries of nation and norms. It all comes down to the right to choose.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This is something women have been fighting for for centuries, from the ability to choose political leadership to the ability to choose a marital partner. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We can debate the merits behind the practice of the headscarf, its history in the Islamic world or even in the life of the prophet Muhammad, but what we should not debate is the ability of a woman to choose a practice, if it does no harm to her. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">France, in particular, makes the argument that the mere act of covering the body does harm to &#8220;the dignity and liberty&#8221; of said body. The issue of hijab is thus framed as one of protection, i.e. paternalism. A closer look at France’s relationship to identity politics and its systematic attempts to eliminate differences for the sake of the secular, homogeneous French state suggests that the protection enacted here is a fairly one-way street: There is &#8220;freedom from&#8221; but rarely &#8220;freedom to.&#8221;<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In Germany, a similar ban on head coverings for women exists. This ban is <a href="http://www.dw.com/en/can-muslim-women-wear-a-headscarf-at-work-in-germany/a-17953746">often a private and religious matter</a>, with church-based organizations or certain institutions able to decide when and if they will tolerate hijab. The attempts by school districts to ban headscarves in their teaching staff have been only partially successful, as German courts usually have the last word, overturning discriminatory practices, unless a specific legal conflict can be identified.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">German politicians have <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/08/19/germanys-potential-burqa-ban-has-a-problem-where-are-the-burqas/?utm_term=.947e281fb60a">also proposed a burqa ban</a>. The only problem is: hardly any women in Germany wear a burqa. Here, a moral stance is taken in preventing supposed harm before this harm could be said to occur. Ideology much? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Of course, the burqa is far from the burkini or the hijab. But it is no coincidence that the burqa ban discussion resurfaced and gained political momentum around the time of the burkini fiasco in France. Some European leaders may oppose France&#8217;s handling of the burkini on its beaches, but many have verbally and practically expressed their approval of policing Muslim women&#8217;s dress.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If one were to apply this&nbsp;logic of&nbsp;infringement of personal liberty to other arenas affecting the female body, one would end up with a long list of potential offenders, from beauty salons to botox offices to lingerie stores, where certain body parts are literally strapped down and constrained for the sake of smooth curvature. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;But these things make us feel good, make us feel pretty,&#8221; a French woman would likely respond. &#8220;And this is my right!&#8221;</span></p>
<div id="attachment_4715" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4715" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-4715 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420-650x433.jpg" alt="berlin-bearbeitet-2014-420" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/Berlin-Bearbeitet-2014-420.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-4715" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Type &#8220;hijab&#8221; into Pinterest and a fashion show will appear &#8211; women who use hijab as a way to present themselves in their way to the world. Stroll down the Turkish market at Berlin&#8217;s Maybachufer and you will encounter smiling groups of Muslima holding silk scarves up to their faces, matching patterns with dresses and jackets in mind, practicing new and different folds, depending on the material.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are wedding hijabs, hijabs for supermarket trips, and hijabs for dates, just as there are shoes for weddings, for nights out, or for lazy Saturdays.<br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hijab, like shoes, can make women feel good, because they make women feel pretty in a way that is also comfortable. It is both a lifestyle with religious and cultural roots and an identity mixed up with the many different conceptions humans have of beauty. Beauty: with all its socio-cultural baggage, the construct of forces beyond our individual minds and mirrors, forces that will always be a little bit oppressive but also a little bit fun, because they are familiar and somehow the product of our daily life within them. And this is their, our right.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As Trump ascends his throne to rule over the many who do not approve of or give license to his authoritarianism or assimilationist view of cultural differences, the hijab becomes one of those things that needs protection.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As Muslim refugees who choose to wear hijab become a lasting part of the societies of those European states that have taken them in, their right to be different must be defended. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Most importantly, we must defend the right of women to choose.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is this choice that makes women free. This is why feminism and hijab go together.</span></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>For more on the history of women in Iran, from hairstyles to political movements, see these sources: U.S. Institute of Peace&#8217;s <a href="http://iranprimer.usip.org/resource/womens-movement">Iran Primer: the Women&#8217;s Movement;</a> these pieces from a </em>New York Times<em>&nbsp;series &#8220;<a href="http://nytlive.nytimes.com/womenintheworld/2015/06/02/6-pervasive-misconceptions-about-iranian-women/">6 Pervasive Misconceptions about Iranian Women</a>&#8221; and &#8220;<a href="http://nytlive.nytimes.com/womenintheworld/2015/09/15/the-day-100000-iranian-women-protested-the-head-scarf/">The Day 100,000 Women Protested the Headscarf</a>&#8220;; this acclaimed book on the complexity of the Revolution: </em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Islamic-Utopian-Political-Biography-2000-06-03/dp/B019NRY9QG/ref=sr_1_3?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1480842551&amp;sr=1-3&amp;keywords=an+islamic+utopian+ali+shari%27ati">An Islamic Utopian: A Political Biography of Ali Shari&#8217;ati;</a><em> and the memoir, </em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/1400064708/?tag=thneyo0f-20">Iran Awakening</a><em>, by the Nobel-prize-winning activist Shirin Ebadi.<br />
</em></p>
<p><em>And if you&#8217;re curious about women in hijab on the internet and in the fashion world, here are some people to watch: <a href="https://www.hautehijab.com/blogs/hijab-fashion">Haute Hijab</a> (U.S. fashion blogger with an entry titled &#8220;Embracing Our Identity in a Post 2016 Election World&#8221;), <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC_KQKeg7kNrlvrIXPnpwgEA">Dina Tokio</a> (U.K. vlogger and fashion designer), <a href="http://ww38.hipsterhijabis.com/about.html">Hipster Hijabis</a> (just what it sounds like), <a href="http://hanatajima.com/">Hana Tajima</a> (up-and-coming U.K. fashion designer), and <a href="http://hijablicious.com/">Hijablicious</a> (a site for &#8220;hijab with soul&#8221;).</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Moralpolitik and the Ressentiments of Change</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 15:35:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=4120</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[According to headlines, the German government has pledged haven – albeit temporary in many cases – to up to 800,000 refugees or migrants applying for asylum in the country. The U.S., despite initial wavering, has signaled that it will work to raise its refugee quota yearly, with the goal of a 100,000 cap by 2017. Yet within and around this historical moment of humanitarian crisis and measured political response are the inflammatory words of Donald Trump. He recently roared to a crowd in Iowa that, if elected, he “will deport all of the 11 million illegal migrants in this country.”]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As German and U.S. refugee policies inevitably collide in light of current events, this writer finds herself in the United States. The other writer of this blog will soon be in Germany, taking stock of the so-called “refugee crisis” on the ground. On my side of the Atlantic, a crisis is not yet to be felt… at least not so acutely. This has as much to do with media semantics as it does with history.</p>
<p>According to headlines, the German government has pledged haven – albeit temporary in many cases – <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/aug/20/germany-raises-estimate-refugee-arrivals-800000">to up to 800,000 refugees or migrants applying for asylum in the country</a>. The U.S., despite initial wavering, <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/news/nation/2015/09/20/increase-admission-refugees-kerry-says/fnCweeIlCS8g47VF7VAkBP/story.html">has signaled that it will work to raise its refugee quota</a> yearly, with the goal of a 100,000 cap by 2017. The Pope, as leader of the spiritual state of Catholicism, <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">has planned to make migrants and refugees one of the few central issues of his travels around the Western Hemisphere this week</a>.</p>
<p>All at once, it seems that moral duty, a college ethics course, and politics have fused into one mandate to assist.</p>
<p>Yet within and around this historical moment of humanitarian crisis and measured political response are the inflammatory words of Donald Trump. He recently roared to a crowd in Iowa that, if elected, he “<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">will deport all of the 11 million illegal migrants in this country.</a>” When asked by Univision’s anchor Jorge Ramos how he would accomplish such a feat, he coolly responded, “I’m a great manager.”</p>
<div id="attachment_4127" style="width: 630px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4127" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-4127" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg" alt="Donald Trump immigration" width="620" height="372" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP.jpg 620w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Trump-Charlie-Neibergall-AP-300x180.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4127" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Charlie Neibergall/AP via <em><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/aug/27/donald-trump-deport-11-million-migrants-is-that-even-possible">The Guardian</a></em></p></div>
<p>One can easily get caught up in the absurdity that is the American campaign season, enjoying its theatrics as a harmless part of the celebrity process. But Trump’s words should hold weight, and they should be cause for alarm.</p>
<p>Trump’s message is not as obtuse, as unnecessarily harsh as it might seem; it reflects not only present sentiment but historical precedent… for both the United States and Germany. With the current refugee and migrant crisis, old tensions are slowly and loudly being unearthed. And the mobility of many of the world&#8217;s displaced, traumatized, and poor is not likely to change any time soon.</p>
<p>National Public Radio’s <em>Fresh Air</em> <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/10/439114563/americas-forgotten-history-of-mexican-american-repatriation">recently interviewed</a> one of the scholars behind the book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Decade-Betrayal-Mexican-Repatriation-1930s/dp/0826339735">Decade of Betrayal: Mexican Repatriation in the 1930s</a>”. The volume documents a massive and relentless deportation program at a time when xenophobia and economic distress were rampant. Historians Raymond Rodriguez and Francisco Balderrama document what is nothing short of a terrifying episode in American history – frightening for what right-wing reactionaries in a new age of migration might be capable of.</p>
<p>As Rodriguez shared with <em>Fresh Air</em>’s host, Terry Gross, the 1930s treated Mexican Americans with great malice and abuse. For reason only of their heritage, they were targeted by government programs and private citizens alike. This abuse culminated in the federal government&#8217;s campaign to strip millions of Americans of their citizenship. Not all those rounded up in deportation raids were naturalized citizens, though <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">estimates suggest than ½ of those expelled were</a>. Most were visa-holders of some sort, their only crime having been born a member of a demonized ethnic group.</p>
<p>Governmental programs to round up and expel society’s undesirables often begin in cities, according to history (see the American strategy of Japanese internment or Nazi Germany&#8217;s institution of the urban ghetto). And so Los Angeles was the primary target of the government’s Mexican American deportation program. Largely as a response to the despair the Great Depression had unleashed across the country, officials systematically sent entire families from the L.A. area back to Mexico, with no infrastructure in place to receive them. <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">From 1929 to 1944, 1/3 of L.A.’s Mexican American population was deported</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4128" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4128" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4128" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-650x487.jpg" alt="Los Angeles Mexican Americans 1932" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932-80x60.jpg 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Los-Angeles-Public-Library-Herald-Examiner-Collection-1932.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4128" class="wp-caption-text">Source: Los Angeles Public Library/Herald Examiner Collection via <em><a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2015/09/08/437579834/mass-deportation-may-sound-unlikely-but-its-happened-before">National Public Radio</a></em></p></div>
<p><em>Ressentiments</em> – projection of resentment or fear onto often vulnerable groups in society – were widespread both in the U.S. and in Germany throughout the Great Depression. Xenophobia in the face of severe economic collapse paved the way for Germany’s organized extermination machinery. The U.S.’s internment of Japanese and German citizens, its continued subordination of Black Americans, and its systematic deportation of Mexican Americans demonstrate that this country was in no way spared such a nasty past.</p>
<p>Slowly but surely, such <em>ressentiments</em> have now begun to return. This time, Germany may be more in the right, even despite a few documented attacks on refugee facilities, while America edges closer toward the precipice of wrong.</p>
<p>…</p>
<p>On my side of the ocean, I have arrived into a complicated sector of the nexus of natural diversity and these increasing <em>ressentiments. </em>Vancouver, Washington, where both my parents now live, <a href="http://www.thenation.com/article/browning-america/">is becoming increasingly &#8220;Brown&#8221;</a>. Separated only by a short bridge across the Columbia River, Southwest Washington has become Portland&#8217;s semi-urban/semi-rural extension. Because the northern bank of the river offers families more space for cheaper, better funded schools for fewer private tax dollars, and income tax exemption, immigrants who may have otherwise moved to the Portland, Oregon metro area are now planting themselves on the side of its less expensive neighbor. Portland, as a result, <a href="http://www.oregonlive.com/news/index.ssf/2009/01/in_a_changing_world_portland_r.html">has become increasingly White</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_4129" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4129" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-4129" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-650x366.jpg" alt="Interstate bridge over the Columbia River, connecting Portland, Oregon and Vancouver, Washington" width="650" height="366" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-650x366.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-300x169.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_002.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-4129" class="wp-caption-text">Interstate bridge over the Columbia River, connecting Portland, Oregon and Vancouver, Washington</p></div>
<p>According to most recent U.S. census data, Vancouver is now 11% Hispanic, inching closer to the national average. We can expect this number to be much higher in reality, as immigrants will often opt out of participation in the census. There are other ethnic groups represented in Vancouver’s demographic development: For example, 18% of families speak a language other than English at home, and the traditional taco truck has recently seen competition in North African, Japanese, and Thai flavors.</p>
<p>None of this would seem all that significant, if I were not writing about a traditionally conservative county, with once sprawling farm land and a historical military base; a county that has now been converted into a rare blend of suburban developments, strip malls, urbane boutiques, and miles and miles of regional road. The nickname of &#8220;Van-tucky&#8221;* &#8211; something I have only heard used on the other side of the water, mind you &#8211; might tell you all you need to know.</p>
<p>The rate of poverty in Vancouver is also higher than the national average. Vancouver&#8217;s mayor recently <a href="http://www.cityofvancouver.us/ced/page/affordable-housing-task-force">launched a task force</a> to investigate the cause of growing homelessness, rising rents, and increased demand for housing in the city’s most accessible and commercially viable areas. Serving as Portland’s &#8220;bedroom community&#8221; brings with it numerous tax and transportation disadvantages, as well, such as costly inter-city transit for a significant commuter population and bridges nationally notorious for being structurally unsound.</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p>In a brand-new cocktail bar in downtown Vancouver, which serves only locally-distilled (read artisanal) spirits, I sip my smoky-cucumber-tequila mixture and listen in on the interaction between the unlikely combination of guests who have just joined me on the patio. Three White bikers &#8211; two older women with smokers&#8217; cough and one machismo with a mustache &#8211; scoff at the price of their beer. Across from them at a nearby table, two women in their mid-20s, both with long black hair, one who speaks English with an accent.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-4130" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-650x366.jpg" alt="cocktail Vancouver, Washington" width="650" height="366" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-650x366.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-300x169.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/WP_20150907_003.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Older veterans and cowboy-like characters are scattered across Vancouver’s downtown like curated remains of what was once here. They drink Rainier out of cans &#8211; Washington State’s Pabst Blue Ribbon with more local charm &#8211; and chain smoke in the park. They inhabit the dive bars with names like &#8220;Lounge&#8221; and antique neon advertisements. It seems that establishments like this new artisanal cocktail bar threaten to upset a tender balance between familiarity, comfort, and growth.</p>
<p>“$4! Bullshit”, one of the women hollers. The two younger ladies nudge their shoulders closer together, in order to continue a conversation disrupted by the boom of our three new patio companions.</p>
<p>The machismo turns toward the young women’s table, putting his hand on one of their legs. “Where you from, honey?&#8221;, he begins his monologue, &#8220;I’m a native, been here for more than 20 years, Detroit before that. You know how much this place has changed?”</p>
<p>Neither responds; however, the one whose leg is playing host to the man’s hand begins to shift uncomfortably.</p>
<p>&#8220;Where you from honey? You aren&#8217;t from around here, I can tell you that!&#8221;, one of the older women yells between sips from her can. “When did Rainier get this damn expensive? It’s bullshit, $4! I’ll tell you something…”</p>
<p>One of the young, dark-haired women flashes machismo a smile. &#8220;I&#8217;m from Panama!&#8221;, she says, and extends her hand for a shake. He takes it and squeezes it, returning both their hands to the table.</p>
<p>“I’m American, from here&#8221;, the other woman says, her leg now turned as far away from his body as the chair allows.</p>
<p>&#8220;But where are your parents from then?&#8221;, machismo asks with a chuckle. &#8220;That&#8217;s what I&#8217;m asking, ain&#8217;t it?&#8221;</p>
<p>She concedes, but stands to use the restroom (or simply disappear into the building) as she does: &#8220;Well, I&#8217;m Filipino.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p><em>Ressentiments</em> toward the Other can begin and fester in spaces of socioeconomic change. With President Obama’s pledge to take in 100,000 refugees, the question becomes “How will this country prepare its citizens to engage respectfully and kindly with members of a majority Muslim country?” The first step in this process is realizing that we have a lot of work to do, and we need politicians who will help us get there.</p>
<p>Germany has seen a fair share of reporting on the readiness of its population to open its arms to newcomers. It is easy to draw parallels to the past, particularly to Germany’s track record in <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/20/441732811/in-germany-migrants-find-footing-but-also-some-resistance">failing to integrate its guest-worker population and in promoting ethnic-based citizenship until it was almost too late</a>. However, it is Germany the rest of the world now looks to in awe &#8211; for choosing a kind of <em>moralpolitik</em> over patterns of the past.</p>
<p>Being so far away from a society I sometimes feel I know more about than my own (society of origin), I can’t help but beam with pride in watching small towns across Germany distribute clean clothes, socks, new toys, children’s books, and warm meals to the thousands of human beings in need who have crossed their borders. Nevertheless, Germany has since issued temporary border controls. Order still wins out over populist charity.</p>
<p>But aiming for a collective solution to the continuous stream of migrants and refugees into Europe, German leaders have worked to reach agreement upon a refugee quota for EU member states. Just this Tuesday this quota became a provisional reality.</p>
<p>Time will tell if all members comply, and if a sense of moral duty is really as strong as images of kind citizens touting bags of donations suggest. Yet I do have the sense that with each step toward welcoming the Other, <em>ressentiments</em> have fewer chances of surviving. When demonstrations of kindness are just so strong, so publicly undeniable, that Trump-esque hate can find no oxygen for its fire.</p>
<p>That is what I hope for America.</p>
<p>At the moment, the U.S. remains crippled and complicated by its multi-layered fears of all the regions of the world it has wronged. As UN Ambassador <a href="http://www.npr.org/2015/09/23/442761552/10-000-syrian-refugees-just-the-floor-of-u-s-effort-says-ambassador-power">Samantha Power made clear in an NPR interview recently</a>, the country is not ready to simply do the right thing; it has to be a calculated response, taking security into account.</p>
<p>Overcoming fear is America&#8217;s consistent and stubborn challenge. I just hope the mistakes of the 1930s can mean something.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*Van-tucky is a reference to the southern state of Kentucky, the unofficial home of fried-chicken and horse races.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2015/09/28/moralpolitik-and-the-ressentiments-of-change/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Circumcision at the Jewish Museum Berlin</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/12/05/review-circumcision-jewish-museum-berlin/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2014 13:14:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Judaism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3532</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Circumcision has a history of being used to make distinctions between 'us' and 'them', particularly in Germany. In the United States the debate on foreskin or no-foreskin looks much different, citing hygiene rather than religious freedom. This begs the question if arguments against a religious practice, such as the one raised in the German context, can ever be purely about legal arguments - for the rights of children, as German courts have decreed - when strong divisions between those of Christian heritage and those of Muslim and/or Jewish heritage remain. This question was the inspiration for the newest exhibition at the Jewish Museum Berlin, a timely one, at that...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Circumcision has a long history of enabling Othering processes, i.e. society defining itself on the basis of what it is not. According the Duke anthropologist <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/william-m-obarr/celebrating-circumcision_1_b_1902275.html">William O’Barr</a>, the absence of circumcision in Michelangelo’s famous <em>David</em> exemplifies this bit: Despite David’s well-known Jewish roots, let alone his place as a key protagonist in the Jewish scriptural tradition, his foreskin remains seemingly intact; this David seems more Florentine, more like the dominant Europeans at the time, than Jewish.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/books/2011/jul/29/david-mary-hoffman-review"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-3537" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/David-Michelangelo-007.jpg" alt="David Michelangelo" width="487" height="293" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/David-Michelangelo-007.jpg 459w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/David-Michelangelo-007-300x180.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 487px) 100vw, 487px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Michelangelo likely had little experience with circumcision, given that this practice was historically reserved for the Jewish minority. The lack of foreskin thus served as a point from which the fringe of majority culture could be measured. Most Europeans at the time were simply <em>not </em>circumcised.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">In Germany, circumcision is still a practice attributed to members of the Jewish and Islamic traditions. Given Germany&#8217;s immigration history, the practice also serves largely to distinguish more recent immigrants from your German with either Catholic or Protestant roots. In kind, the debate as to the legality and humanity of the removal of a child&#8217;s foreskin has taken on an us vs. them quality. The discussion has also tended to position &#8216;reason and modernity&#8217; against &#8216;antiquated tradition&#8217;, as this<a href="http://www.taz.de/!98008/"> interview</a> with a German Green Party member indicates (a party, which gave strong support to legislation banning the practice among infants and young children). Just two years ago, a Cologne court ruled against the circumcision of youngsters. The decision was presented as an act in favor of the human rights of children &#8211; this logic continues to dominate.</p>
<p>In the United States, approx. 79% of men are circumcised, <a href="http://www.cdc.gov/hiv/pdf/prevention_research_malecircumcision.pdf">according to the Center for Disease Control</a>. Many of these men do not belong to religious traditions that prescribe the practice; I doubt many parents would cite compliance with God&#8217;s covenant as the reason for their son’s procedure. Since its introduction during WWII as a matter of (presumed) <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2788411/">hygiene</a>, it never had time to become a pronounced public marker of difference.</p>
<div id="attachment_3565" style="width: 541px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://www.guggenheim.org/new-york/collections/collection-online/artwork/3478"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3565" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3565 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/circumcision-january1.jpg" alt="circumcision-january pollock" width="531" height="450" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/circumcision-january1.jpg 531w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/circumcision-january1-300x254.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 531px) 100vw, 531px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-3565" class="wp-caption-text">Jackson Pollock 1946, &#8220;Circumcision&#8221;</p></div>
<p>But even in the United States, the practice has more recently come under a critical knife, though more medical than cultural, as a recent <em>Atlantic </em><a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2014/12/foreskin-keep-or-cut/383362/">article</a> on the subject illustrates. The more contemporary critique in the United States seems to be little more than an attempt to re-evaluate the merits of bodily modification, without going so far as to refer to this practice as &#8216;mutilation&#8217; on the part of fundamentalist religions.</p>
<p>Given this background, the importance of context is undeniable in evaluating the discourse on circumcision from one place to another. In other words, the &#8216;who&#8217;s who&#8217; in <em>beschnitten</em> vs. <em>unbeschnitten</em> may say much more about the state of society (and its latent tensions) than medical-ethical arguments against the practice immediately reveal. This begs the question if arguments against a religious practice, such as this one, can ever be purely about the rights of children, as German courts have decreed and German politicians argued. This question and the delicate history from which it emerges were the inspiration for the newest exhibition at the <a href="http://www.jmberlin.de/main/EN/homepage-EN.php">Jewish Museum Berlin</a> – an institution known for <a href="http://www.jmberlin.de/main/EN/03b-Academy/04-Academy-Programs/00-academy-programs.php">programming</a> on inclusion/diversity topics that extends beyond the docket of Jewish history and culture.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Haut-Ab.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-3569 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Haut-Ab.jpg" alt="Haut Ab" width="330" height="374" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Haut-Ab.jpg 330w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Haut-Ab-264x300.jpg 264w" sizes="(max-width: 330px) 100vw, 330px" /></a></p>
<p>The exhibit, &#8220;<a href="http://www.jmberlin.de/main/DE/01-Ausstellungen/02-Sonderaustellungen/2014/brit-mila.php">Haut ab!</a>&#8221; or &#8220;<a href="http://www.jmberlin.de/main/EN/01-Exhibitions/02-Special-Exhibitions/2014/brit-milah.php">Snip it!</a>&#8220;, opened a little more than one month ago. Days before the exhibit’s scheduled reveal, I had the opportunity to take part in a preview for bloggers and tweeters. Our tour guide was the exhibition’s co-curator, an expert in Judaica. In addition to the objects&#8217; historical significance, her comments revealed a recognition of the tightly-stretched contemporary fabric upon which the exhibit rests. The careful placement of artifacts, soundbites, and images transmits a similar message of a need to explain and take stock of a (perhaps unnecessarily) tension-filled topic, in light and because of history.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3539 size-large aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004-650x365.jpg" alt="WP_20141022_004" width="650" height="365" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004-650x365.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_004.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>Entering through the exhibit&#8217;s initial darkened spaces &#8211; final preparations being made, lighting not quite right &#8211; a historical narrative of a religion&#8217;s genesis and later adaptations in diaspora forms a quilt of impressions. The next rooms give way to the ritual&#8217;s place in Islam and the stark move from Christianity&#8217;s embrace of old Jewish tradition &#8211; as being sacredly tied to the life and times of Jesus &#8211; to artists&#8217; depictions of Othered violence, even savagery, against children. Juxtaposed with a historical development are artifacts from the Islamic ceremony in which a young boy is inducted into a long Muslim lineage. For all Berliners, the following image is a familiar one: costumes for a &#8216;little prince&#8217;, complete with scepter and golden cap. But how many recognize this as part of a fundamental <em>rite de passage, </em>the commanded removal of foreskin? Images of the sons of German guest workers in the 1970s, little princes in-waiting, place the practice further back in German heritage than the media tends to convey. As Germany&#8217;s immigration history indicates, circumcision is nothing new. But this photograph of an eager little boy could have been taken last week, swimming in a hat much too big among a happy mass of friends and family.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-3558 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016-650x365.jpg" alt="WP_20141022_016" width="650" height="365" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016-650x365.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016-310x174.jpg 310w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_016.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a></p>
<p>The final room of the exhibit greets visitors with an interactive arrangement of outside discourses on circumcision, clips taken primarily from American television. Images and audio insert diverse perspectives into what our guide calls &#8216;the polemical German frame&#8217;. Familiar cartoons and sitcoms cast blue light onto the carpeted floor. Scenes from South Park, Judge Judy. As we exit, a final work, the oeuvre of commentary, salutes its visitors: three figures, bodies identical, if not for the flags draped over three sets of genitalia.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-3557 aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021-365x650.jpg" alt="WP_20141022_021" width="350" height="623" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021-365x650.jpg 365w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021-168x300.jpg 168w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/WP_20141022_021.jpg 366w" sizes="(max-width: 350px) 100vw, 350px" /></a></p>
<p>One could make the case that circumcision in Germany is more a stand-in for society&#8217;s difficult grappling with religious difference and demographic change. Perhaps more background is needed to do so, however. So to be more specific, as a <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/politik/deutschland/studie-belegt-grosse-vorbehalte-gegenueber-muslimen-a-1006332.html">recent study</a> by the <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/en/welcome/">Berlin Institute for Empirical Migration and Integration Research</a> indicates, a majority of Germans polled continue to see Islam as un-German &#8211; this despite the approx. 5+ million Muslims who have made Germany their home. To complicate things, Germany is one of the most secular countries in Europe, with most of its residents of so-called Christian heritage bearing little association to either church or faith in their daily lives. There is also a history of a certain institutional religiosity despite public secularism: for example, the prominence of the CDU Party (Christian Democratic Union) and the obligatory church-tax to Protestant or Catholic churches, even synagogues, while blatantly excluding Muslim houses of prayer.</p>
<p>As this new exhibit at the Jewish Museum Berlin demonstrates, circumcision in Germany is complicated, deeply embedded in <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/28/world-cup-fever-how-malleable-is-german-identity/">the question of German identity</a> and the norms that demarcate such a thing. I wonder, though, if the constant discussion serves only to create scandal out of culture. For where is Othered difference, when there is no longer spectacle?</p>
<p>&#8220;Snip it&#8221;/&#8221;Haut ab&#8221; at the Jewish Museum Berlin runs until March 1. It&#8217;s worth a visit.</p>
<p>&#8211; <em>By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>All images are linked to original source or were otherwise taken by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>World Cup Fever: How malleable is German identity?</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/28/world-cup-fever-how-malleable-is-german-identity/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2014 09:43:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[World Cup]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2873</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Germany's World Cup victory has unleashed a new wave of patriotism, as well as a new identity crisis. This patriotism might only be as good as the boundaries it is ready and able to redefine. An act of flowing colors and neighbor-to-neighbor high-fives may have started a new understanding of who is allowed into the club, but policies and institutions need to take it one step further. Otherwise, patriotism is just as good as nationalism, which rules by way of exceptionalism. In the type of inclusive global society many of us would love to build, there is no room for exceptionalism...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In 2006 Germany hosted the World Cup; it also organized a social-marketing campaign for the sole purpose of revamping and re-solidifying patriotism. These things, i.e. national pride, rarely happen organically, particularly for countries with strong regional identities and histories of division. The goal of the campaign: the encouragement of colors-wearing, flag-toting, &#8216;Schland&#8217;-cheering citizens of the federal republic. One image made its way through German newspapers and magazines during this novel World Cup fever, representing what was now allowed, what could again be said without glancing over one&#8217;s shoulder &#8211; a 15-year old girl, <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/spiegel/print/index-2014-29.html">Monique Bienge</a>, waving a scarf on which the German national anthem is printed, as pictured below.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.spiegel.de/spiegel/print/d-47282143.html"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2874 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/die-deutschland-party.jpg" alt="Germany World Cup" width="454" height="599" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/die-deutschland-party.jpg 454w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/die-deutschland-party-227x300.jpg 227w" sizes="(max-width: 454px) 100vw, 454px" /></a></p>
<p>The text on Monique&#8217;s scarf reads:</p>
<p><em>Unity and justice and freedom</em><br />
<em> for the German fatherland!</em><br />
<em> To that let us aspire</em><br />
<em> In a spirit of fraternity,</em><br />
<em> With heart and soul.</em></p>
<p>So-called football nationalism is not limited to one time of the year (or to every four years, for that matter), however. Its colors bleed into the surrounding shapes of civic life, exerting influence and changing norms with each successive step toward normalcy. The iconic image pictured above articulates Germany&#8217;s re-entrance through the gates of national pride &#8211; a process that began <em>en force </em>in 2006 and culminates today with the German national team&#8217;s WC victory.</p>
<p>But back when the gates were still swinging closed, often in classrooms or at the dinner table of <a href="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/68er-Bewegung">68er</a> grandparents, German politicians didn&#8217;t dare proclaim the type of national pride other countries are famous for. The American political landscape I know<em> requires</em> a language of exceptionalism*, as even <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UK7JEYqIfw4">President Obama&#8217;s recent speech at the UN General Assembly</a> demonstrates. In stark contrast, a <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/politik/deutschland/muegelner-buergermeister-ich-bin-stolz-deutscher-zu-sein-a-502950.html">mayor in Saxony in 2007</a> said he was &#8216;proud to be German&#8217;, and public rebukes followed (in part due to accusations of radical-right leanings); the jury was still in session.</p>
<p><strong>This year things were a bit different.</strong></p>
<p>After the German national team took home the trophy, standing before Berlin&#8217;s Brandenburg Gate with faces toward the historic German <em>Siegessäule</em> or &#8216;pillar of victory&#8217;,<em> </em>German flags did not disappear, did not crawl back into the hole from whence they had come. Little old ladies with bags of flowers and desserts kept their colored armbands tightly on the wrist; pubescent school kids kept wearing jerseys to school, in many cases looking a little underwashed and a little over-hormoned.</p>
<p>And it all seemed so normal, at least for some of us. And yet, as <a href="http://www.zeit.de/kultur/2014-07/schweinsteiger-blutkrieger-dfb-medienkritik">an article in <em>die Zeit</em></a> (a German weekly) pointed out, this was again anything but an organic process: &#8220;The German Football Association managed to become a synonym for Germany&#8221;, explained in part by what the author called &#8217;embedded journalism&#8217; of a different type, AKA German media sources working closely to manufacture a patriotic relationship to the German soccer team &#8211; something the association (DFB) does not vehemently deny.</p>
<p>But even if many citizens and residents of Germany were convinced of the linkage between national pride and a football win, latent critique still found its way into the conversation, particularly in response to the team&#8217;s <a href="http://youtu.be/bg6ZFv63URE">controversial parody</a> of the defeated Argentinians.</p>
<p><em>Die taz</em> (a German daily) <a href="http://taz.de/Pro-und-Contra-Gauchogate/!142556/">debated the potential controversy</a>; even a <a href="http://taz.de/Nachlese-zur-Fussball-WM/!142947/">guest post </a>from someone associated with the team asked, <em>if we are allowed to celebrate, how loud, how long, and who is included?</em> <em>Der Spiegel</em> (a tad more conservative national magazine) went after a similar though more general question &#8211; <em>who are we Germans again</em>? With a fully-veiled woman, a <em>Pfand</em>-schlepping chap, a working mother, all cloaked in German colors, the magazine responded: &#8216;We Germans&#8217;<em>, </em>as<em> </em>the cover photo and its video are called, are all a little different.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.spiegel.de/images/image-723794-magazincover300-dmug.gif" rel="http://www.spiegel.de/spiegel/print/index-2014-29.html"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://www.spiegel.de/images/image-723794-magazincover300-dmug.gif" alt="Der Spiegel World Cup" width="300" height="396" /></a></p>
<p>In other countries, patriotic displays would likely not be paired with an existential crisis. But this is Germany. As the above extract from the German national anthem mentions, a fatherland is at stake here &#8211; one that, at the time of the anthem&#8217;s composition, did not exist.</p>
<p>German-speaking public officials and intellectuals debated the question of identity and belonging during the years leading up to the creation of the federal conglomeration of German states (out of the former Holy Roman Empire and environs). And in 1871, (mostly) peasants were absorbed into a territorial construction more or less controlled by Prussia (a state no longer in existence), all based on inklings of a so-called <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pan-Germanism">Pan-Germanism</a>. In other words, <em>whose </em>&#8216;fatherland&#8217; we are really talking about depends not only on who you ask, but also on when this question is and has been posed in the past.</p>
<p><strong>But what might this mean for the public exercise of patriotism?</strong></p>
<p>The historically-rooted &#8216;German question&#8217; &#8211; i.e. who are the Germans? &#8211; has yet to be completely solved. This is the point. How could it be? Countries, their populations, their mandates, their political philosophies of law and justice, even their borders, are constantly changing.</p>
<p><strong>As <em>Der Spiegel&#8217;s</em> &#8220;We Germans&#8221; cover demonstrates, the WC victory might be an opportunity to collectively re-work this changing German identity, while it is still hot and malleable.</strong></p>
<p>For the outsider, all this hullabaloo in the face of three differently colored stripes might seem exaggerated, even just written off as a sign of unresolved historical traumata. But from a philosophical perspective, it is indeed productive to acknowledge all that patriotism implies, i.e. what and whom it excludes. Such a topic is ever-relevant to the productive identity project that might emerge from this World Cup victory&#8230; with the potential to re-create boundaries of belonging for the better.</p>
<p>The cacophony of voices relating to Germanness and all that it encompasses has often been frustrating for German politicians, particularly in relation to defining citizenship laws. But rallies in the streets and public displays of &#8216;belonging to the German club&#8217; have somehow put these oft-exclusionary discussions on hold for a minute, giving journalists the chance to <a href="http://taz.de/WM-und-Integration-in-Berlin/!142407/">write about on-the-ground cohesion </a>or harmony in a country that often fosters a language of <a href="http://www.spiegel.tv/#/filme/duisburg-marxloh/">ghettoization</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_2888" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/wm-berlin.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2888" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-2888" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wm-berlin.jpg?w=640" alt="Photo by Juri Gottschau" width="640" height="401" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2888" class="wp-caption-text">Photo by <a href="http://www.jurigottschau.com/">Juri Gottschau</a></p></div>
<p>That said, after the streets have cleared and the flags have been taken down, <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/meinung/deutschland-ist-weltmeister-wm-traum-wm-trauma/10207938.html"><em>where does this leave the many immigrants or non-traditional members of German society</em>?</a> asked a columnist with immigration background, recently. For patriotism, like nationalism, thrives on exclusion. That is to say, a group is only a group if it has the capacity to actively determine who belongs and who does not. In essence, this is the definition of the modern state. Part of the state&#8217;s mandate is the ability to exercise force (as opposed to violence, according to Hannah Arendt), in order to maintain these boundaries, something rarely questioned in public discourse or by political constituencies.</p>
<p>These boundaries are not a given, however: they result from and are constantly reproduced in political processes,  enshrined not only in law but in everyday institutions, ideologies, and practices of the outsiders vs. the insiders. This means that they can be changed.</p>
<p><strong>In the end, this new German patriotism is only as good as the boundaries it is ready and able to redefine. An act of flowing colors and neighbor-to-neighbor high-fives may have started a new understanding of who is allowed into the club, but policies and institutions need to take it one step further. Otherwise, patriotism is just as good as nationalism &#8211; a political project and instrument of the state with the purpose of coercing national conscription, labor-market participation, and civic legitimacy by way of <em>exceptionalism</em>.</strong></p>
<p>In the type of inclusive global society many of us would love to build, there is no room for exceptionalism.</p>
<p>All big words and ideas aside, patriotism might have the chance to be democratic and inclusive or it might become dangerously exclusive. As I have witnessed in my home country of the United States, this often depends on who sets the governmental agenda but also who shapes discussions as to what types of restrictions are legitimate, particularly in regards to labor-market and immigration policies.</p>
<p>But it doesn&#8217;t have to be so top-down or even so economically-driven. We can decide who belongs to our club, and maybe, in an ideal world, politicians will respond. In my opinion, this should be the German World Cup take-away.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*The phenomenon of national exceptionalism as a political value and even as a &#8216;moral quest&#8217; is demonstrated best by the American political right and the movement to shame political leaders or public opposition who <em>do not</em> believe in the superior story, governmental system, and social values of the United States. Newt Gingrich&#8217;s propaganda-documentary <a href="http://youtu.be/oQsCW1hbOGw">A City Upon a Hill</a> is case-in-point; Ron Paul&#8217;s (of the far-right American Libertarian Party) <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0BOrM6j1-2s">defense of his own views of &#8216;moderate exceptionalism&#8217;</a> to conservative critiques is another.</p>
<p><em>For more on my (and our) philosophy regarding borders and belonging, read the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/about/a-manifesto/">Collidoscope Manifesto</a> on cities, difference, and building community.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Berlin needs you (but why?)</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/04/review-berlin-needs-you-but-why/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/04/review-berlin-needs-you-but-why/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2014 08:20:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2702</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Why is immigration important? The debate takes many angles. There's the demographic argument, that developed countries with low birth rates and aging populations need bodies to maintain the replacement rate. There's the globalization take, that the movement of people in all forms is increasingly inevitable and contributes to global competitiveness and 21st century skills. The moral or even religious spin, emphasizing human dignity, charity, an obligation for prosperous nations to help those more needy. But few arguments are as pervasive as the economic one...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_2738" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdad.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2738" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2738 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad.jpg?w=640" alt="" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad-300x199.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdad-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2738" class="wp-caption-text">©Barbara Dietl</p></div>
<p>Why is immigration important? The debate takes many angles. There&#8217;s the <a href="http://www.thelocal.de/20131126/germany-needs-more-immigration">demographic argument</a>, that developed countries with low birth rates and aging populations need bodies to maintain the replacement rate. There&#8217;s the globalization take, that the movement of people in all forms is increasingly inevitable and contributes to global competitiveness and 21st century skills. The moral or even religious spin, emphasizing human dignity, charity, and an obligation for prosperous nations to help those more needy. Yet few arguments are as pervasive as the economic one: that immigrants fill labor shortages, tend to be more innovative, start businesses and create jobs, pay taxes, and contribute to the social welfare net (yes, often more than they &#8220;take away&#8221;).</p>
<p>It is this economic argument that is often relied upon as a point of mutual agreement that immigrants are needed. Maybe not <a href="http://www.dw.de/opinion-foreigners-welcome-sort-of/a-17651819">“wanted”</a>, but at least needed.</p>
<p>This argument extends beyond newcomers to the 2nd and 3rd generations. In countries like Germany where the history of immigration has been primarily low skilled, children of migrants still face numerous linguistic, cultural, and socioeconomic challenges. These are exacerbated by a stratified education system that is associated with lower educational attainment, limited access to higher education, and fewer chances for economic mobility. Germany fares particularly poorly in this arena: it has the <a href="http://www.oecd.org/general/oecdeducationsystemsleavemanyimmigrantchildrenflounderingreportshows.htm">OECD&#8217;s largest performance disparity</a> between native and immigrant students and is one of the only countries where 2nd generation students perform worse on international assessments than the 1st generation.</p>
<p>Enter <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> (Berlin needs you!), a program that works to improve the educational and economic outcomes of students with migrant backgrounds. Launched by the state of Berlin as part of its overall integration plan in 2006, it aims to increase the number of these students entering the public sector by 25% by bridging schools with the professional world. It is coordinated by BQN, <em>das Berufliche Qualifizierungsnetzwerk für Migrantinnen und Migranten in Berlin</em> (the Vocational Qualification Network for Immigrants in Berlin) and is funded by the state of Berlin.</p>
<p><iframe title="Berlin braucht dich! - Diverse Wege in die Arbeitswelt" width="650" height="366" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fwBxQu93g3o?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>The program works in cycles: a day-long introduction to a business or organization for 7th graders, a week-long internship for 8th graders, 3-week internships for 9th graders, and training and application days for 10th graders. Participating schools help their students find training spots with an online matching tool. Spots are currently offered in Berlin&#8217;s public sector, public companies, and the metal and electrical industries, though BQN is working toward expanding the program to include small businesses. The program has also evolved from a focus on the vocational training system (<em>Duales System</em> &#8211; working and learning in a company) to more dual study opportunities <em>(Duales Studium</em> &#8211; studying and working simultaneously).</p>
<p>Mitri Sirin, a German TV reporter of Turkish-Syrian background, moderates the 5th <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> consortium meeting in June. He highlights the culture of low expectations and need for more varied training opportunities for migrant students during a panel on diversity politics.<em> The idea that any kid in the 7th grade would know what they wanted to be when they grow up is a fairy tale,</em> he scoffs. <em>Of course I was funneled into a vocational internship with other kids like me. I was still able to make something or other of myself</em>, he adds to chuckles from the audience,<em> but not all are so lucky.</em></p>
<div id="attachment_2790" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdconsortium.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2790" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2790 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium.jpg?w=640" alt="Berlin braucht dich! Consortium Meeting June 2014" width="640" height="480" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdconsortium-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2790" class="wp-caption-text"><em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> Consortium Meeting June 2014 ©BQN Berlin</p></div>
<p>When the panel concludes, a group of giggling students race out from behind the stage to plaster black paper on the windows and switch off the lights. It&#8217;s a bit eerie to be cloaked in darkness with pop music blaring before 11am, but soon enough the black-light theater performance has the audience tapping their feet and grinning widely. While entirely up for interpretation, the images of a ball being passed around between two sets of hands and a student struggling in a white sheet before becoming a colorful butterfly suggests a story-line of transnationalism and diversity.</p>
<p><em>The theater program is</em> <em>a kind of &#8220;empowerment action&#8221;</em>, explains Robert Westermann, PR Manager of Berlin braucht dich! <em>The group comes from one of the 32 schools we cooperate with&#8230; students from this school also take part in our internships. </em></p>
<p>Later that morning, we make sure to join the small workshop where the same students share their experiences. <em>I&#8217;ve been in Germany for 2 years and can&#8217;t speak German that well,</em> <em>but black-light theater is like another language that I can speak to everyone, without having to actually say anything, </em>shares one Iranian girl.  <em>In theater you have to learn to control yourself, but you can also be free</em>, says another. <em>Theater has taught me how to be loud</em>, exclaims a third.</p>
<div id="attachment_2737" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2737" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2737 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht.jpg?w=640" alt="Schule am Schloss students post-performance. Source: Berlin braucht dich!" width="640" height="480" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdschwarzlicht-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2737" class="wp-caption-text"><em>Schule am Schloss</em> students take a bow post-performance ©BQN Berlin</p></div>
<p><em>In my view, the most innovative aspect of </em>Berlin braucht dich!<em> is that schools and companies are working together on a constant and sustainable level</em>, describes Robert.<em> This stable network makes it possible to operationalize key ideas around &#8220;intercultural openness&#8221;, by changing structures, processes, and mentalities. </em></p>
<p><em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> has experienced marked success in its 8 years of operation. Since 2006, the ratio of trainees in the public sector with a migration background has been steadily on the rise and by 2009 had doubled to 16.9%. By 2013, every 5th trainee (20.5%) in the public sector and public companies had a migration background.</p>
<p>Yet it is the emphasis on mutually understood and implemented &#8220;intercultural openness&#8221; that implies <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em> is about more than Euro signs. In addition to securing a more intercultural workforce through sheer numbers, BQN offers free <a href="http://www.berlin-braucht-dich.de/aktivitaeten/diversity-trainings/">diversity trainings</a> for partner schools and businesses. Migration is acknowledged not only as a reality, but as a key factor that contributes both &#8220;to our quality of life now and the sustainability of our future.&#8221; While the demand for such trainings has been low on the school side, BQN has implemented many with employees from their partner companies.</p>
<div id="attachment_2800" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/bbdstudents.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2800" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2800 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents.jpg?w=640" alt="bbdstudents" width="640" height="480" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents.jpg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents-300x225.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents-650x487.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bbdstudents-80x60.jpg 80w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2800" class="wp-caption-text">Moderator and TV reporter Mitri Sirin (middle) with theater group students ©BQN Berlin</p></div>
<p>The path to a truly intercultural workforce is still laden with hurdles. Recent studies on Germany show that <a href="http://www.migazin.de/2014/06/02/vorurteil-widerlegt-junge-migranten-nicht-haeufiger-kriminell-als-deutsche-jugendliche/">prejudice</a> and <a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/karriere/studie--mit-tuerkischem-namen-sinken-chancen-auf-ausbildungsmarkt,10808620,26663588.html">hiring discrimination</a> against students with migrant backgrounds is alive and well. Access to higher education and many employment opportunities is entirely off the table, as a disproportionate number &#8211; <a href="http://www.boeckler.de/35923_41774.htm">about half</a> &#8211; of these students are funneled into the lowest vocational school track. As one of the business representatives at the meeting explained to the theater group, <em>If any of you came into an interview at our offices, you would do great. But to get to the interview stage, you would still have to pass the entrance test first, which focuses on German, math, and logic. </em></p>
<p>Challenges such as these require integrated policy approaches. Approaches that distinguish the actors involved and hold them accountable for their roles in changing the structures, norms, and mentalities that fuel these challenges. Approaches that extend beyond just the economic argument and are brave enough to acknowledge everyone&#8217;s role in fostering an intercultural and inclusive society that values the potential of each individual. In short, Berlin doesn&#8217;t just need you. It needs all of us.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>Thank you to Robert Westermann, PR Manager of <em>Berlin braucht dich!, </em>for inviting us to the consortium meeting and providing information for this article.</p>
<p>For more information on <em>Berlin braucht dich!</em>, check out their German website <a href="http://www.berlin-braucht-dich.de/">here</a>. Info in English can be found <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/ewsi/en/practice/details.cfm?ID_ITEMS=13081">here. </a></p>
<p>For another article from us on Berlin based programs for students with migrant backgrounds, click <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/07/18/rave-education-per-square-kilometer/%20">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/04/review-berlin-needs-you-but-why/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: the Klezmer Gentiles</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2014 09:55:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Holocaust]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jewish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[memory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Poland]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2468</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[International artists in Berlin occupy a semi-privileged position, able to ask critical questions of society without being publicly rebuked. An example of such an artist is Soliman Lawrence. Soli has been photographing the memorialization of Jewish culture in Poland for years, following the tracks of a new form of engagement with the past, as enacted by a more recent generation of Poles. In contrast to Poland, Germany now has its fair share of Jews. What might this mean for memory and its rituals?...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>An interview is never one-sided &#8211; in fact, it is a constructive conversation. I am as much a part of this piece as the artist who answered my questions. Without the contributions of the other, individual statements would hold little significance. So thanks, Soli, for letting me share our conversation. </em></p>
<p>International artists in Berlin are one category of newcomers who, although shaping the cultural politics and economic fabric of Berlin perhaps more than other groups of foreign residents (those without German citizenship), are often left out of the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/11/integration-in-berlin-research-for-a-desolate-landscape/">critical integration debate</a>. Whether or not they learn German or German constitutional law seems to matter little to the politicians and journalists fueling the heavily institutionalized, assimilating discourse. I have yet to meet an artist who has been pressured by the authorities to &#8216;integrate&#8217; him or herself, as is the case with members of different social and economic groups.</p>
<p>This semi-privileged position has its benefits: Berlin&#8217;s creatives are often able to ask critical questions of society without being publicly rebuked, far enough from local history to recognize nuance and apply cultural critique in a non-threatening fashion.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2684 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>An example of such an artist is an old friend <a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/">Soliman Lawrence</a>. Soli has been photographing the memorialization of Jewish culture in Poland for years, following the tracks of a new form of engagement with the past, as enacted by a more recent generation of Poles. His collection of work is titled &#8220;<a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/unquietplacesphoto.html">For those whose faith has been broken</a>&#8220;. They do so, as Soliman&#8217;s stories and their pictures explain, through ritual, one example of which is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Klezmer">Klezmer</a> music. The fascinating part of this story: there are few Jews to speak of in Poland.</p>
<p>Beyond a revived Klezmer tradition, Soliman photographs reconstructed synagogues, Jewish-themed festivals, hand-made figurines, the maintenance of Jewish cemeteries &#8211; all weaving a tale of things past, now re-born as an ode to matzo ball soup or rabbinical characters.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2681 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland" width="640" height="423" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11-300x198.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11-650x429.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>Soliman is not Jewish, though his choice of topic likely gets many thinking that personal biography must inform the interest. I met with Soliman at a little cafe in Neukölln to talk art, history, and memory. Parallels between German memorialization of Jewish culture in Berlin and that which is happening in Poland were not at the tip of his tongue; these parallels were on the tip of mine, however.</p>
<p>Soliman is American by passport, has been a Berlin resident for more than 8 years, making the nationality question a bit tricky. He studied philosophy in the United States, stems originally from the Northern part of Florida, and has a contemplative way about him &#8211; he seems to move slowly, take things in and digest them before forming an opinion.</p>
<p>His artistic career began with a camera, has now evolved into a sort of philosophical exploration of what it means to remember. <em>Memory is at the center of my work</em>, he tells me, <em>how people remember after something has passed, how they remember together</em>. He is interested in the idea of <em><a href="http://www.postmemory.net/">post-memory</a>, the ways in which memory stays alive without the original witnesses</em>. Photography serves a crucial purpose, documentation allowing for connection.</p>
<p>Soliman first started making trips to Poland in 2006, visiting the growing Klezmer festivals in places like Krakaw. <em>Here is the biggest and best festival in Poland</em>, he tells me. I imagine VW buses jammed full with young, alternative Poles, spending warm nights outdoors, not for the beat of electronic sounds but for renditions of clarinet and fiddle. Actually, <em>it is quite mixed</em>, he tells me: young/old, hip/not.</p>
<p><em>When I first showed up in Krakaw, I was taking pictures of everything. I assumed a lot of the stuff I was photographing had something to do with Antisemitism &#8211; graffiti on the walls somehow looked antisemitic to me, these little tiles in the main square with five-pointed stars</em>, <em>for example</em>, he says with a laugh. <em>Then I realized that these stars were actually six-pointed, so </em>not <em>necessarily</em> <em>antisemitic</em>. <em>Very often, one finds what one searches for</em>, I add. This is even more true for a photographer, able to capture and catalog what may be happenstance occurrence, curating images into some sort of narrative about a people or place.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2682 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>That doesn&#8217;t mean that Antisemitism isn&#8217;t present in Polish society, however: <em>it&#8217;s complicated</em>, he says. An interview with Soliman on Jewish memorial culture in Poland appeared in 2012 in <em>die</em> <i>Zeit Online </i>with the headline: &#8220;<em>Wie Nicht-Juden die jüdische Kultur Polens wiederbeleben/</em> &#8220;<a href="http://www.zeit.de/video/2012-12/2032360755001/holocaust-wie-nicht-juden-die-juedische-kultur-polens-wiederbeleben">How Non-Jews Are Resurrecting Poland&#8217;s Jewish Culture</a>&#8220;. I recall watching the interview then, having heard of the beginnings of his Polish adventures back in 2010, when Soli and I first met, and being struck by the oddity of it all, the sense of a manufactured experience to take the place of an entire culture now lost. And yet, it was impossible not to find parallels with the city we both share, I felt: the way in which memory of Jewish culture in Berlin is fractured between recreations of the diaspora experience, a come-back Jewish culture in Germany, and a newer wave of young Israelis.</p>
<p>Soli has given quite a number of interviews in Germany since his project first began to receive attention. A <a href="http://juedische-woche-dresden.de/veranstaltung-2013/items/108.html">recent exhibition of his work in Dresden</a> put him into more contact with the German media. <em>So, did any of these journalists ask about your thoughts on Jewish memorialization in Germany, in Berlin, or on any similarities between Poland and Germany?</em>, I ask. At first, he doesn&#8217;t understand my question, seems a bit perplexed. Then, <em>No</em>,<em> in fact, no one even got close to formulating that question. Interesting that you bring that up. </em></p>
<p>Jewish culture in Berlin is diffuse, hard to put a finger on, as &#8211; with Jews everywhere &#8211; there is no one way to be Jewish and certainly no one way to be Jewish in Berlin. A memorial culture is also difficult to construct, when Jews are in fact present. To boot, there is no <em>one</em> way to memorialize the Holocaust and the thriving Jewish culture in Germany that preceded it. At least no one way that would satisfy the diverse groups who were affected by the genocide. In Poland, very little has happened at an institutional, top-down level. And so revivals of classic Ashkenazi traditions like Klezmer have been a means of memorializing a lost sector of Polish life, many years after its musicians were made to disappear.</p>
<p><em>At my first Klezmer festival, I didn&#8217;t really know what to do with myself. People were dancing, it was celebratory, there was this feeling of community</em>, he says. He was a bit stand-offish, not understanding why active participation was required. <em>This is the ritual</em>, he explains, <em>it is through such a collective ritual that some form of memory is reconstructed and created for the next generation.</em> <em>Many of these young people probably have no real connection to contemporary Jewish people</em>, he adds,<em> but this type of memory doesn&#8217;t require personal connection, rather an attachment to space and a desire to make a place &#8211; a memorial &#8211; out of it.</em></p>
<p>In Berlin, there is a strong attention to memorial sites or objects &#8211; the <a href="http://www.stolpersteine-berlin.de/en/stolpersteine"><em>Stolpersteine</em></a>, <a href="http://www.holocaust-mahnmal.de/en"><em>Memorial to the Murdered Jews of Europe</em></a>, <a href="http://www.slowtravelberlin.com/touching-berlins-ghosts/"><em>Bayerisches Viertel</em></a>, to name a few. These are spaces that are visited and even organized by many but are perhaps not as interactive or collective as a Klezmer ritual. One might simply pass by its insignia, whereas Klezmer is somehow a more active process, Soli explains.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2685 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9-300x199.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9-650x432.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p><em>But are these Klezmer festivals in Poland really about remembering and mourning the Holocaust? </em>I ask. <em>Yes, it is about that but not only about that.</em> <em>It is about thinking about the Jews that were once here, by people who were too young to have had the chance</em>.</p>
<p>There is a tendency<em> </em>in memorializing activities to focus on objects and their stories; materiality is desired, physical connection reconstructed. The Holocaust documentation and education center where I used to work curated a collection called &#8220;<a href="http://www.wsherc.org/museum/everyday-objects">Everyday Objects</a>&#8220;, the National Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM) releases <a href="http://www.ushmm.org/information/exhibitions/curators-corner">weekly stories online from its archival vault of objects</a>, and even the recent <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/sportingscene/2014/04/memory-objects-commemorating-the-boston-marathon-bombings.html?utm_source=dlvr.it&amp;utm_medium=twitter">Boston Marathon bombings are being actively commemorated through the collection of ordinary things</a>.</p>
<p><em>When talking with journalists, they just don&#8217;t really understand why Klezmer music is so popular in Poland, </em>Soli comments, as if to emphasize the stark differences between the German memory process and that of the Poland he knows:<em> Memory is expressed differently across space.</em> <em>My work is about these different memory ways, memory forms. </em></p>
<p>Surprising to many, Berlin is home to a fair number of Jews, and not just returned German Jews or those that fled from the former Soviet Union, but Israeli Jews, secular Israelis, secular Diaspora Jews from Argentina etc. &#8211; colliding in one city, not necessarily finding community among one another, because why should they? To make the argument, however, that perhaps things aren&#8217;t as different as they seem, I add that one does see a sort of stereotypical Jewish culture in Berlin, from the <a href="http://www.exberliner.com/locations/luigi-zuckermann-deli/">classic deli</a><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> </span>serving pastrami sandwiches to the local bagel shop. Both places in mind are not run by anyone of Jewish heritage, catering to a historic Jewish culture, perhaps even to New York Jewry rather than Berlin. This is not to say that there are no Jewish delis or bagel shops in Berlin that are owned by Jews. <em>But might the more theatrical recreations be a form of memorial culture, similar to Klezmer festivals?</em> I ask. <em>Maybe</em>, he says, <em>but I know a  few Israelis, and they don&#8217;t necessarily eat bagels. They go to this one shop on </em>Sonnenallee<em> where they can get hummus served warm, like back home in Israel</em>.</p>
<p>The varied layers of Jewish culture, identity, and memory in the Berlin landscape prevent one from making any static comparison to the situation in Poland, it seems &#8211; a place with very few Jews to speak of and a history wrought with a non-institutionalized form of memory, at least until recently. The Israeli and general Jewish presence in Berlin further complicates a comparison between the memory culture of Poland and that of Berlin in a very real sense. To be the authors of a tradition that re-appropriates Jewish tradition means being responsible for potential misappropriation. In Poland, I doubt there are too many active members of the Jewish community who would heavily criticize the rebirth of Klezmer in this form. <em>There aren&#8217;t</em>, Soli says.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2683 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>If he feels strange about researching this issue as an American artist without Jewish descent &#8211; <em>No</em>. The Holocaust is a large part of how Americans understand Germany, I add, in order validate his work from a place of personal opinion. The past was certainly a key factor in my own interest in contemporary German politics and society, as my <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/">article on Sachsenhausen</a> demonstrates.</p>
<p>The question is, if such a connection between a bleak past and curious future can be made, productively, and with much room for nuance and reflection. Soliman Lawrence&#8217;s work allows for just that. Like other artists, he is able to describe memory ways as they are occurring, not overtly criticizing but allowing others to draw their own conclusions or parallels.</p>
<p>We all remember differently. The most important thing is simply to remember.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>Jewish identity in Berlin, Jews in Germany, Israelis in Berlin: there is no shortage of debate, public presence, or diversity. Here a recent <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/culture/2014/05/so-long-israel-hello-berlin.html">article from <em>The New Yorker</em></a> on this topic and a few articles from us, written from the most varied of positions:</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/">Why Remembering the Holocaust is Good for Immigrants</a> &#8211; integration policy and a visit to Sachsenhausen concentration camp</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/07/rant-or-rave-jew-in-a-box/">Rant or Rave? Jew in a Box</a> &#8211; a controversial exhibit at the Berlin Jewish Museum</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">Interview: TV, the Treasury Minister, and Third Culture Kids</a> &#8211; Israeli in Berlin</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/07/interview-three-dimensions-of-integration/">Interview: Three Dimensions of Integration</a> &#8211; Jewish-American artist in Berlin</p>
<p>Last but not least, a few links for finding that Jewish deli or that Israeli hummus: <a href="http://www.berlinfo.com/Lifetime/Shopping/food/jewish/, http://forward.com/articles/165718/berlins-jewish-comeback/?p=al">Berlins Jewish Comeback</a>, <a href="//www.hagalil.com/deutschland/berlin/gemeinde/kosher.htm">Hagalil</a>, <a href="http://www.jewish-berlin.com/kosher.php">Jewish-Berlin</a>, <a href="http://www.berlinjewish.com/tips-for-your-berlin-vacation">Jewish in Berlin</a>, <a href="http://www.exberliner.com/food/land-of-the-lox-can-you-get-deli-food-in-berlin/">ExBerliner deli food list</a>.</p>
<p><em>All images were graciously provided by Soliman Lawrence as part of the series &#8220;<a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/unquietplacesphoto.html">For those whose faith has been broken</a>&#8220;. To see some of Soliman&#8217;s newer projects, check out his homepage. </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: Seeing Berlin Through The Homeless</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2014 12:22:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bureaucracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GDR-DDR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitte]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Schöneberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[volunteering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2398</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[They wait for the subway doors to close before they address the car with a rehearsed speech. "Excuse the interruption, I am one of Berlin's annoying homeless people"... it usually begins, as they peddle newspapers and scan the crowd for an outstretched hand holding change or food. The majority of us keep our hands tucked away or firmly gripping our phones. Some of us fall into convenient bouts of exhaustion, promptly leaning back and closing our eyes. In this moment, we are restricted to a shared space...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_2604" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2604" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2604 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-650x433.jpg" alt="hermannplatz" width="650" height="433" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-650x433.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/hermannplatz-e1413112424150.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2604" class="wp-caption-text">Photo by Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p>In Berlin they are especially visible on the <em>Bahn</em>. They wait for the subway doors to close before they address the car with a rehearsed speech. <em>Excuse the interruption, I am one of Berlin&#8217;s annoying homeless people&#8230;</em> it usually begins, as they peddle newspapers and scan<em> </em>the crowd for an outstretched hand holding change or food. The majority of us keep our hands tucked away or firmly gripping our phones. Some of us fall into convenient bouts of exhaustion, promptly leaning back and closing our eyes. In this moment, we are restricted to a moving car, a shared space. We can&#8217;t dodge a corner or cross the street, but we still find ways to make them invisible. We don&#8217;t look up because we feel uncomfortable. We become frustrated at them for making us feel this way. We may even become angry &#8211; at them, at society, at ourselves.</p>
<p>How the simple presence of one person can incite so much emotion, judgement, and shame.</p>
<p>How it must feel, to be simultaneously so visible and invisible.</p>
<div id="attachment_2605" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2605" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2605 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-650x459.jpg" alt="eye" width="650" height="459" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-650x459.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697-300x212.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/eye-e1413112413697.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2605" class="wp-caption-text">Photo by Juri Gottschau</p></div>
<p><em>It&#8217;s one of the worst things for homeless people, being treated as invisible. Answer them when they speak to you, make eye contact, acknowledge them!</em> our guide Carsten Voss urges us by the end of our walk. We are wrapping up a tour called &#8220;Obdachslose zeigen ihr Berlin&#8221; (The homeless present their Berlin), run by non-profit organization <em>Querstadtein. </em>The group offers tours in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Mitte that show the reality of homelessness in the city.</p>
<p>Our guide speaks from personal experience. Decked out in designer glasses and a well-fitting sweater, it&#8217;s challenging to picture this man as the subject of the powerful story he delivers in front of stately <span class="st">Viktoria-Luise-Platz</span>. Carsten worked 80+ hours a week as a manager of an international tradeshow before burning-out and falling into depression. First came the loss of his job, then his apartment. He refused help from loved ones, other than taking refuge in a friend&#8217;s shed for a few months. It would be a year before he clawed his way back out. He cites one defining moment: <em>I happened to glance into someone&#8217;s window from the street. The woman was cooking and the man was watching </em>Tagesschau<em> on TV&#8230; I realized that if I didn&#8217;t make a change then, I would never have that again.</em></p>
<p>That year Carsten counted among Berlin&#8217;s estimated 4,000 <em>Obdachslose</em> (literally translates to &#8220;without shelter&#8221;). Not to be confused with <em>Wohnungslose</em> (&#8220;house-less&#8221;), which refers to those without homes but still in the system, <em>Obdachslose</em> are no longer in the system and may or may not have a place to sleep. Berlin has Germany&#8217;s highest concentration of <em>Obdachslose, </em>both from within and outside of the country.</p>
<p><em>There are three main categories of </em>Obdachslose <em>in Berlin</em>, Carsten explains early on in the tour. <em>Former refugees from East Germany, those groups of young people who usually have dogs with them, and immigrants.<br />
</em></p>
<p><a href="http://ec.europa.eu/social/main.jsp?catId=1061&amp;langId=en">Migrant homelessness throughout the EU</a> has risen in recent years, exacerbated by the economic crisis. This may come as no great surprise, though it&#8217;s a blow to hear that many in Berlin<em> end up staying because they find the conditions of being homeless here better than their lives back home. </em>Carsten describes this group in three geographic waves: the first from Poland, second from the Baltics, and third from Bulgaria and Romania<em>. Of course they came here planning to find jobs, start families, create a life. Some make it, but many don&#8217;t. </em></p>
<div id="attachment_2586" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-23-14-33-35.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2586" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2586 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-23-14-33-35.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-23 14.33.35" width="640" height="480" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2586" class="wp-caption-text">Cold Weather Assistance for Berlin&#8217;s Homeless by District, Winter 2013/14</p></div>
<p>Berlin has a long tradition of homelessness. It&#8217;s a poor city &#8211; Germany&#8217;s poorest &#8211; but also equipped with robust social services. Berlin has a history of attracting those who are &#8220;different&#8221;, including many immigrants, due to its diversity and tolerant atmosphere. During the days of the Berlin Wall, it was also a haven for males escaping military conscription (which ended altogether in 2011). Carsten moved to Berlin for this reason, and says he and many others like him entered fields like social work and education. This, he claims, has contributed to the city&#8217;s liberal nature and strong social net.</p>
<p>Berlin&#8217;s homeless tend to cluster in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Charlottenburg, two districts in West Berlin now more associated with high rents and artisanal cafes than alternative lifestyles. Carsten guides us to Nollendorfplatz, Berlin&#8217;s LGBT hub and site of the annual pride parade, Christopher Street Day. We stand across from the colorful <em>Regenbogen-Stele, </em>a r<span class="userContent">ainbow column erected in 2000 to celebrate the area&#8217;s high concentration of homosexual residents and open-minded atmosp<span class="text_exposed_show">here. The statue itself carries two symbols: the rainbow flag for gay pride and the <em>Rosa Winkel</em>, a pink badge first used by Nazis to distinguish homosexuals in concentration camps, and what later became an international symbol for gay rights.<br />
</span></span></p>
<div id="attachment_2507" style="width: 538px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/2014-03-23-14-21-00-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2507" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2507" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/2014-03-23-14-21-00-1.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-23 14.21.00-1" width="528" height="528" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2507" class="wp-caption-text">Nollendorf Platz&#8217;s &#8220;Regenbogen-Stele&#8221; or rainbow column celebrating gay rights</p></div>
<p>As we inspect the square, Carsten points out what our untrained eyes fail to see: a 24-hour grocery store well-equipped with bottle deposit machines, a van selling the street newspaper, a well-lit intersection. <em>Homeless people are part of this neighborhood, they have a community here</em>, he says.</p>
<p>But another faction of the city&#8217;s homeless blend in so well that we don&#8217;t see them at all. <em>Most people have an image in mind of the bag lady (or guy), unkempt and dirty, pushing around a cart filled to the brim with random items, muttering crazy things to themselves.</em>.<em>. most homeless people don&#8217;t look or act like that. </em> Carsten estimates that 60% fall into this category, homeless people who look &#8220;normal&#8221; so they can use spaces and services within the city without being noticed. They schedule their day in such a way that they always have a place to be, something to eat, even a bed to sleep in. They know when the citizens&#8217; office opens and when they can grab a shower, when they can rest in the library or supermarket, who is offering a free lunch or haircut in the city. <em>It&#8217;s an exhausting life, they have to be very organized, and they are constantly in public</em>, Carsten emphasizes: <em>the only time they have to themselves is in the shower.</em></p>
<div id="attachment_2621" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-24-08-25-20.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2621" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2621 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/2014-03-24-08-25-20.jpg?w=640" alt="2014-03-24 08.25.20" width="640" height="480" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2621" class="wp-caption-text">Assistance notice for homeless youth in Charlottenburg</p></div>
<p>Carsten&#8217;s happy ending is a welcome take-away from an otherwise harrowing topic, but he warns against the assumption that all homeless people are unhappy or need to be saved. While many do suffer from mental illness and drug and alcohol abuse, others have deliberately chosen this lifestyle. <em>Some people want to live this way, and we have to respect that. We have to recognize them as part of society.</em></p>
<p><span class="userContent"><span class="text_exposed_show">It&#8217;s easy to dodge corners and cross streets, to switch subway cars to avoid someone&#8217;s stench or words, to grip our phones and look down. </span></span></p>
<p>It&#8217;s not as easy to look up.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>The Querstadtein homeless tours (in German) take place in <span class="st">Schöneberg</span> and Mitte, usually on Sundays and for approximately 2 hours. Tickets cost <span class="st">€</span>9,40, and <span class="st">€</span>5,40 for students, seniors, and individuals on welfare. More information can be found at <em>http://querstadtein.org/de/stadtfuehrungen/.<br />
</em></p>
<p>For more on the Querstadtein tours in English, click <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/zeitgeist/berlin-tour-gives-a-glimpse-of-berlin-as-seen-by-homeless-people-a-913758.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>For more on the increasing restrictions on public space for homeless people across Europe, <a href="http://www.surveillance-and-society.org/articles5%283%29/homelessness.pdf">click here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/10/review-seeing-berlin-through-the-homeless/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: The Taxi Driver</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2014 14:00:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asylum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kurdistan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[refugees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2314</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Orhan was 5 when his father moved to Berlin in 1972. It was only one year before West Germany would halt guest worker recruitment from non-European countries to fill labor shortages after World War II. His mother followed 7 years later with his youngest sister and they lived in Rudow in southeastern Neukölln - where they still live over 30 years later. "They got jobs as cleaners in an office," Orhan recounts, "but they were fired!" he adds, snorting in laughter.  I look up from my notepad, surprised...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Had I hopped into Orhan&#8217;s taxi en route to the airport, I likely would&#8217;ve assumed he was Turkish and left it at that. He might have asked me where I was flying to and I might have commented on the weather. He would&#8217;ve pulled my suitcase out of the trunk and wished me a good flight, and I would&#8217;ve thanked him. But instead, thankfully, I met Orhan in a very different context &#8211; our half-marathon training group. What follows here is his story about growing up in Kurdistan and Turkey as the child of guest workers and moving to Berlin 20 years ago. The story I would&#8217;ve likely missed. </em></p>
<div id="attachment_2377" style="width: 588px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/2014-03-30-09-50-36-1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2377" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2377" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/2014-03-30-09-50-36-1.jpg?w=640" alt="Orhan and Sophia pre 2014 Berlin half marathon" width="578" height="578" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/2014-03-30-09-50-36-1.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/2014-03-30-09-50-36-1-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 578px) 100vw, 578px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2377" class="wp-caption-text">Orhan and I pre-race 2014</p></div>
<p>I meet Orhan at Fehrbelliner Platz&#8217;s Park <span class="st">Café</span>. We choose a table outside amongst the masses soaking up the unusually warm March sun. It&#8217;s that strange break between afternoon and evening,  the mood equally fitting for a coffee or beer. The space is buzzing but in a state of exhalation, as the day starts to settle and everyone&#8217;s shoulders wilt a few centimeters. This is where Orhan spends every Thursday between 4:45 and 6pm, while his daughter takes a kickboxing class around the corner.</p>
<p>My first order of business is a selfish one: though I&#8217;ve asked Orhan multiple times to tell me where he grew up, I still can&#8217;t remember the name, let alone comprehend its location geographically. Orhan draws me a little diagram: he grew up in <em>Hotan</em>, a tiny village near a town called <em>Varto</em>, part of a district called <span class="st"><em>Mûş</em></span> that lies in Anatolia, in the predominantly Kurdish southeastern part of Turkey.</p>
<div id="2330" style="width: 582px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://geopoliticsrst.blogspot.de/2012/10/turkei.html"><img aria-describedby="caption-2330" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2330 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/mapkurdistan.jpg" alt="Kurdistan on a map " width="572" height="447" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/mapkurdistan.jpg 572w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/mapkurdistan-300x234.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 572px) 100vw, 572px" /></a><p id="caption-2330" class="wp-caption-text">Varto is slightly northeast of Diyarbakir, the unofficial capital of Turkish Kurdistan</p></div>
<p>Orhan was 5 when his father moved to Berlin in 1972. It was only one year before West Germany would halt guest worker recruitment from non-European countries to fill labor shortages after World War II. His mother followed 7 years later with his youngest sister and they lived in Rudow in southeastern Neukölln &#8211; where they still live over 30 years later. <em>They got jobs as cleaners in an office</em>, Orhan recounts, <em>but they were fired!</em> he adds, snorting in laughter.  I look up from my notepad, surprised. &#8220;Why is that funny?&#8221; <em>Well, they worked with friends &#8211; they&#8217;d moved to Berlin together &#8211; and one of the guys was really funny. So they were always fooling around and making noise..</em>.<em> and one day they got fired! That guy was a real comedian.<br />
</em></p>
<p>Orhan only heard that story years later. He had stayed behind in Kurdistan, in the village with his grandmother. <em>My father didn&#8217;t plan on staying that long, like most guest workers</em>, Orhan explains,<em> but my mom eventually went, too, and my Oma became my main mom. She ended up raising me. </em>After school, Orhan did an apprenticeship in wood-making<em>. It was a 6km walk to work from Oma&#8217;s every day, alone, sometimes in 1m of snow. I was always scared the wolves would get me! </em></p>
<div id="attachment_2368" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/gallery_0610222020109423828131.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2368" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-2368" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/gallery_0610222020109423828131.jpg?w=640" alt="Portrait of a Kurdish woman (Source: Renkliisler)" width="640" height="648" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2368" class="wp-caption-text">Portrait of a Kurdish woman in Varto (Source: Renkliisler)</p></div>
<p>In the 1980s, Orhan&#8217;s parents used money earned in Germany to buy land and build a house in Izmir, on Turkey&#8217;s western coast. Orhan switched from wood-making to electrician work, and got a factory job making stoves. His remaining siblings (of which there are 5 total) started to join his parents in Berlin, applying for visas and leaving one by one. Orhan applied too, but his request was denied. German family reunification policy* has a 16 year old age limit for third country (non EU) nationals to join their parents in Germany. After age 15, other factors apply for a residence permit, such as German language proficiency and the &#8220;ability to integrate&#8221;. Orhan was already in his 20s. So he stayed in Izmir, looking after the house and spending summers in the village with his grandmother and uncle. Then came 1993, when <em>Hotan </em>and many other Kurdish villages were destroyed in a war between Turkish government forces and Kurdish rebels. The war, called &#8220;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/24/world/kurds-are-finally-heard-turkey-burned-our-villages.html">one of the most violent secrets of the 1990&#8217;s</a>&#8220;, killed more than 30,000 and displaced thousands more.</p>
<p>Orhan&#8217;s chance to go to Germany came shortly thereafter. <em>My boss asked me to go to Germany to fix a faulty order we had exported there&#8230; they needed someone who spoke a little German. </em>It was Orhan&#8217;s first trip to Germany, and by the time he returned, he had decided to try moving there again. <em>Since I had gotten a visa for the work trip and come back, I had earned the Embassy&#8217;s trust</em>, Orhan chuckles, <em>it was much easier to apply for a visa the next time.</em> On December 10, 1994, Orhan left Turkey with a 3 month visa. Upon arrival in Germany he applied for asylum. He was 27.</p>
<p>He was sent to an asylum home outside Berlin in <span class="st">Eisenhüttenstadt, Brandenburg</span>. <em>We were fed three times a day and the workers were pretty nice to us, but the conditions weren&#8217;t great&#8230; 7 or 8 of us sleeping together in one room. </em>For a year, Orhan spent one night every two weeks there to comply with policy.<em> They knew my family was in Berlin&#8230; I spent the rest of the time with them. </em>Orhan&#8217;s asylum request was eventually granted, on the grounds that his hometown in Kurdistan had been destroyed. <em><br />
</em></p>
<div id="2341" style="width: 618px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://www.welt.de/politik/deutschland/article123743604/Asylbewerberheim-in-Eisenhuettenstadt.html"><img aria-describedby="caption-2341" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2341 " src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/asylbewerberheim-in-eisenhuettenstadt.jpg" alt="asylum home in Eisenhuettenstadt" width="608" height="405" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/asylbewerberheim-in-eisenhuettenstadt.jpg 620w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/asylbewerberheim-in-eisenhuettenstadt-300x199.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px" /></a><p id="caption-2341" class="wp-caption-text">Asylum seekers arrive to Eisenhüttenstadt (Source: Die Welt)</p></div>
<p>This was in the mid-1990s, a decade before Germany would officially recognize itself as a country of immigration and develop a <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">national integration plan that included integration courses for newcomers</a>. Orhan signed up for a language course on his own, hoping to learn enough German to study economics at university. He quit after 3 months. <em>It wasn&#8217;t fun and always after work</em><em>, when I was so tired </em>(he did construction at the time)<em>. </em><em>The grammar was really hard. It&#8217;s still hard.<br />
</em></p>
<p>A cousin&#8217;s <span class="st">fiancé</span> suggested he try being a taxi driver. <em>I failed my taxi license test 3 times because I couldn&#8217;t pronounce the street names correctly!</em> <em>Being a taxi driver is a bit boring but it&#8217;s a clean job. Not like construction. And I like the freedom.</em></p>
<p>Orhan&#8217;s been a taxi driver ever since, working 10 hour days 5-6 days a week. He has two children, a son from his first marriage to a Turkish-German woman and a daughter with his current wife, whom he met at a gym over 10 years ago &#8211; a gym they still attend together. <em>I live a good life here. I travel a lot and I have a flexible job. </em>Orhan tries to go to Kurdistan at least once or twice a year, and has taken his kids 4 times. His next visit is this May. <em><br />
</em></p>
<p><em>My kids have 59% <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">Migrationshintergrund</a>, </em>Orhan says laughing,<em> when I&#8217;m angry with my son I scold him in Turkish, but usually we speak German. He can understand Kurdish, too.</em> <em>I tried speaking Kurdish with my daughter for a year but then gave up,</em> he adds, a hint of regret in his voice.</p>
<p>&#8220;Do you think German integration policy has gotten better since you first arrived here 20 years ago? With services like the integration courses?&#8221; <em>German immigration policy isn&#8217;t very fair</em>, Orhan replies scowling, <em>If I marry someone from Turkey and want to bring them here, they have to prove they speak German before arriving! But people from <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/11/20/roma-in-berlin-bureaucracy-in-lichtenberg/">Bulgaria and Romania</a>** can just come here and get social benefits even if they don&#8217;t speak the language</em>.</p>
<p><em>I don&#8217;t have German citizenship and I don&#8217;t want it,</em> Orhan declares, <em>why would I need it? </em><em>My wife and I want to buy a house in Izmir and spend maybe one third of the year there. Four months in Berlin, 4 in Izmir, 4 in Kurdistan. There&#8217;s nothing special there, where I&#8217;m from in Kurdistan&#8230; only mountains, animals </em>(the wolves!)<em>, and rocks, but, </em>Orhan makes a fist and holds it close to his stomach, <em>it still feels like home.</em></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Varto">According to Wikipedia</a>, Berlin holds Europe&#8217;s largest population from Varto, Kurdistan. Germany has Europe&#8217;s largest population of Kurds, <a href="http://www.aljazeera.com/video/europe/2013/05/201358161349732897.html">approximately 800,000</a>, many of whom came as guest workers in the 1960s. For more information on the history of this immigrant community (in German), click <a href="http://www.trend.infopartisan.net/trd0299/t090299.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>*For more information on Germany&#8217;s family reunification policy, click <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/dgs/home-affairs/what-we-do/networks/european_migration_network/reports/docs/emn-studies/family-reunification/2._de_emn_ncp_small-scale_study_iv_family_reunification_final_en_version_en.pdf">here</a> and <a href="http://www.expatica.com/de/essentials_moving_to/essentials/German-permits-for-family-reunification_18892.html%20">here</a>.</p>
<p>**Despite being part of the EU since 2007, Bulgarians and Romanians have only had access to Germany&#8217;s social welfare system since 2014, when Germany lifted work policy restrictions. This was after the EU deemed Germany in violation of economic rules of engagement.</p>
<p><em>All photos linked to source. A big thank you to Orhan for his participation!<br />
</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/30/interview-the-taxi-driver/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; and the White Audience</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2014 14:00:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Afrodeutsch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nazi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[segregation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theater]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2248</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One attends a play about an Afro-German living in the years of Nazism and Jim Crow not because of the dramaturgy. One buys the ticket because of the topic's near absence in the German discourse. This is not a review of the play, but rather a continuation of the discussion with the cast that followed. As one of the cast-members remarked, it all comes down to audience: "Black folks probably wouldn't go to the theater to see this play in the U.S., let alone have enough money for the ticket. And here, we have a white audience. So, who are we really talking to here? Who is seeing this play?"...
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>As a student of my own history and place in this world, nothing is more difficult for me than to write about issues of privilege, white-ness, black-ness, and justice in one sitting, because there is so much that can go wrong, so many terms that can be mis-used or mis-assigned, and so many truths that cannot be conveyed in one text. I have done my best. And with all my socio-anthropological know-how, I may still miss the point or offend, for which I am sorry: so is the nature of the subject.</em></p>
<p>One attends a play about an <em>Afrodeutscher* &#8211; </em>Afro-German &#8211; living in the years of Nazism and Jim Crow not because of the dramaturgy. One buys the ticket because of the topic, i.e. its novelty and near absence in the German discourse. &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221;, &#8220;Made Black&#8221;, at the <a href="http://www.etberlin.de/">English Theatre Berlin</a> explores the rich text of race in 1930s Berlin through the experience of Klaus, an unknowing Afro-German &#8211; a word that still spikes the air with rarity, German-ness still seen by many as a monopoly of the white-skinned.</p>
<p>But Klaus&#8217;s character and his experience of targeted exclusion are not that far from the present, as a conversation with the cast will demonstrate.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_4.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_4.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht" width="640" height="1016" /></a></p>
<p>The play&#8217;s dense telling of a complicated history of race, citizenship, and post-colonialism through dialogue is impressive. Equally worthy of praise is the playwright&#8217;s collaboration with a well-versed historian.  The Afro-German actor, with a biography startlingly similar to the protagonist he portrays, is also seemingly extraordinary. The most important element, however, relates to its audience and what this means for theater as a medium of cultural critique.</p>
<p>This is not a review of the play, per se, on which the curtains closed this past Sunday. Rather, this is a review of the discussion with the cast, playwright, and director that came after, the sentiments of which will remain prominent and powerful in my mind, long after audience members have discarded their ticket stubs.</p>
<p><strong>The Conversation</strong></p>
<p>Thursday night, we, a primarily white audience, wait patiently for the cast to take their places at the foot of the stage. The protagonist of the play, the actor to play the American jazz musician, the actor to play the German politician, the playwright (Alexander Thomas), and the director file into folding chairs. <strong>&#8220;Black folks probably wouldn&#8217;t go to the theater to see this play in the U.S., let alone have enough money for the ticket. And here, we have a white audience. So, who are we really talking to here? Who is seeing this play?&#8221;</strong>, says the actor who plays the Black American musician &#8211; the play&#8217;s connective thread to Jim Crow.<strong> </strong>The scene seems to agree.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_3.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2259" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_3.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht theater cast" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>Daniel Brunet, the mustached upstate New Yorker who produces the <a href="http://www.etberlin.de/producing-series/the-lab/">LAB series</a> for the English Theatre and directed this play, chimes in about the lack of representation of certain &#8220;communities&#8221; in cultural institutions. The problem of equitable, fair representation is something sure to resound for both American and German audiences, though certainly in different ways.</p>
<p>This problem is an old one. But it rattles and recalls Berlin&#8217;s more recent debates on multiculturalism, intercultural politics, and the integration &#8211; or just plain tolerance &#8211; of difference. &#8220;The topic of being German <em>and </em>of<em> </em>being a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Person_of_color">person of color</a> (p.o.c.) continues, often with little progress&#8221;, a p.o.c. from the audience remarks, a hint of a German accent in the throat. This topic is contemporary, indeed.</p>
<p><strong>Can theater change these parameters? Can theater ask for more diversity from institutions that have no incentive to include them?</strong></p>
<p>The playwright, a Black American married to a white German woman, wrote &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; as a way to process &#8220;the complexity of these issues&#8221;. And yet, as he makes perfectly clear, representing his own stereotypes of Germans and &#8220;the lack of place in [his] mind for an Other of color in Germany&#8221; is central to the play. &#8220;Otherwise, I would have been acting dishonestly&#8221;, he says, looking into the glare, behind which fragments of the audience, of us, must appear.</p>
<p>The protagonist of the play, himself an Afro-German, speaks, his English flooded with German vowels, his mannerisms oddly similar to his character, who re-asserts his German identity proudly throughout the play in deference to the Othering looks of those around him. This Other, created by the Black American writer, is somehow a reflection of himself, he states, admitting how through rehearsals he struggled to read his lines, even bursting into tears; how the first time he read the play, he felt personally implicated and stripped bare. <strong>&#8220;I am German, my father left when I was three years old, I grew up with my mother, was born in Hamburg, that is all I have ever known”</strong>, he says. The biographies are nearly identical, minus 80 years and a certain regime.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2311.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2255" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2311.jpg?w=640" alt="Schwarz gemacht stage" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>The anger he enacts in the play now takes hold of his voice: the desperation and frustration. <strong>“Once I read the script I knew it had to be done, we had to make this play. Though, during intermission, when I was sprawled on the stage in a pile of paper [the stage is composed mainly of bundles and bundles of blank paper], I sometimes thought ‘what am I doing here, who am I talking to&#8217;”</strong>.</p>
<p>Despite these questions of audience and representation, the play successfully sends a message, one of critique. It weaves the complicated history of American segregation and its sub-human treatment of Blacks with the messianic framing of America&#8217;s involvement in WWII. Through the diverse arrangement of its characters, the play scrutinizes American moral authority in the fight against Nazi ideology and fascism, drawing dramatic attention to Jim Crow and the commonalities between racist ideologies.</p>
<p><strong>The parallels between American oppression and Nazi tyranny become painfully clear, eliciting the following question from the audience: &#8220;Would you show this play in America? And under what conditions?&#8221;</strong></p>
<p>&#8220;We would just need a theater to show it&#8221;, the playwright says with a smile, confidently speaking for the work alone. &#8220;The play was actually meant for an American audience&#8221;, he adds, hence the translation of German passages and numerous references to American &#8216;race sciences&#8217;, details often omitted from textbooks. &#8220;This is a history of not only segregation but of a science [eugenics and race-based Social Darwinism] that many Americans do not know about&#8221;.</p>
<p>Such a truth of ignorance is reflected in the young woman in the play, who claims that the protagonist, Klaus, is not like &#8220;the other Negroes back home!&#8221;, though she has &#8220;never met one&#8221;.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2258" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/schwarz-gemacht_2.jpg?w=640" alt="colonialism Jim Crow" width="640" height="411" /></a></p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Theater approaches many controversial political topics in the United States, because it can. A very particular demographic is going to the theater; and that is where such issues can be discussed&#8221;</strong>, Brunet adds.</p>
<p>The playwright explains that he is willing to relinquish artistic license and allow others to define the scope and boundaries of the play&#8217;s possible interpretations. Some scenes are based on his own childhood, others on historical research and collaboration with the author of <em><a href="https://www.press.umich.edu/174272/other_germans">Other Germans</a>, </em>Tina M. Campt<em>, </em>about being a person of African heritage in Germany.</p>
<p>&#8220;But what is the point of the play?&#8221;, the jazz musician asks, perhaps to the audience, perhaps to no one present in this room. It is not about carving out identity from the crowd, asserting the value of the image in the attic mirror, but rather &#8220;about convincing society – the powerful – that exclusion is harmful and degrading to human beings. Now, and back then!&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;The point is, speaking truth to power&#8221;</strong>, he says, referencing, most notably, <a href="http://www.cornelwest.com/">Dr. Cornel West</a>, a giant in the continued civil rights movement for people of color, for the exploited lower classes.</p>
<p>Theater is not a dialogue with the masses, nor a dialogue with society in general, however. &#8220;Like cultural media and cultural politics, it is a dialogue with the powerful and their ideas&#8221;, says Brunet. The rest is some trickle down effect or, as the p.o.c. from the audience adds, &#8220;a change in consciousness&#8221;.</p>
<p>The camera man, a towering Black man with an equally large voice, speaks to the political or &#8220;transformative nature of the play&#8221;: <strong>“Most people ask themselves the question, are things really that different now? That is what this play does, it asks that question again of the powerful&#8221;.</strong></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5em;">With these words, I instantly feel implicated by my privilege, the things afforded to me on the basis of the position and body I was born into. The room shrinks. I shift in my seat.</span></p>
<p><span style="line-height: 1.5em;">We are the audience. We are the ones who should see this play. We shape the discourse, often to the detriment of those who do not fit the desired mold. Theater might be a chance to reflect on <a href="http://www.taz.de/!116745/">critical whiteness</a>, even on its limitations.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2296.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2250" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/img_2296.jpg?w=640" alt="English Theatre Berlin" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>One of the members of the cast remarks, perhaps to break a long 15 seconds of silence, <strong>&#8220;Can we imagine a black actor playing Romeo? A white actor playing Othello? Is it bad that we can&#8217;t?&#8221;</strong> For the sake of this question, &#8220;Schwarz gemacht&#8221; should be produced in another season, maybe in another city, as a voice in a room with too few listeners.</p>
<p>I sincerely hope that it might be staged in the United States, a country, where diversity often means tolerating the one that is different but disrespecting him or her just the same. As <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/ta-nehisi-coates/">Ta-Nehisi-Coates</a> wrote in <em>The Atlantic</em> this Tuesday, <strong>&#8220;We are in America, where our absence of virtue is presumed, and we must eat disrespect in sight of our sons.<em> </em>And who can be mad in America? Racism is just the wind, here. Racism is but the rain.&#8221; </strong></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*After the Nazi dust had cleared the German capital and West German society had taken root, the Black American poet and activist Audrey Lorde began to popularize the term <em>Afrodeutsche(r) </em>or Afro-German,<em> </em>during <a href="http://www.audrelorde-theberlinyears.com/">her years in the city</a>, effectively building a movement that at least gave a name to an almost invisible population.</p>
<p><em>For more information on Afro-German history in English, click <a href="http://german.about.com/od/culture/a/blackhistger.htm">here</a>. For more information on Afro-German organizations in Berlin and in all of Germany: <a href="http://isdonline.de/">Initiative schwarze Menschen in Deutschland</a>, <a href="http://www.afro-deutsche.de/">Afrodeutsche e.V</a>, <a href="http://www.adefra.com/">Schwarze deutsche Frauen und schwarze Frauen in Deutschland</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>For an interesting twist, check out our <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/09/weekend-review-germanys-brown-babies-how-americas-good-guy-image-might-get-a-run-for-its-money/">article on Black Germans</a> (the change of language here was intentional) growing up in the United States to adoptive parents, often in the segregated South. </em></p>
<p>Photo source: Kelly Miller and <a href="http://jurigottschau.com/">Juri Gottschau</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/19/review-schwarz-gemacht-and-the-white-audience/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lens: An Ode to the Maybachufer</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/20/lens-an-ode-to-the-maybachufer/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/20/lens-an-ode-to-the-maybachufer/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2014 11:53:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Culinary Cultures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Our Lens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gentrification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multiculturalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1853</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[From Berlin's "problem district" to more expensive than spießig Charlottenburg: Kreuzberg's made quite the transformation over the decades, but migration continues to shape its identity and reputation as a district. The bulk of Kreuzberg's diversity stems from the '50s and '60s, when guest workers were recruited by West Germany to fill labor shortages after World War II*. Kreuzberg's dilapidated housing became home to guest workers, primarily from Turkey...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From Berlin&#8217;s &#8220;problem district&#8221; to <a href="http://www.bz-berlin.de/aktuell/berlin/kreuzberg-teurer-als-charlottenburg-article1398469.html">more expensive</a> than <em>spießig</em> Charlottenburg: Kreuzberg&#8217;s made quite the transformation over the decades, but migration continues to shape its identity and reputation as a district.</p>
<p>The bulk of Kreuzberg&#8217;s diversity stems from the &#8217;50s and &#8217;60s, when guest workers were recruited by West Germany to fill labor shortages after World War II*. Kreuzberg&#8217;s dilapidated housing became home to guest workers, primarily from Turkey. The district soon came to be known as &#8220;Little Istanbul&#8221;. In 2014 you would still be hard pressed to find a block without a <em>Döner</em> <em>Kebab </em>stand or five, but the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/07/ramadan-with-neighbors-its-about-showing-up/">district&#8217;s diversity</a> extends far past Anatolia.</p>
<p>Along with districts like Neukölln and Wedding, Kreuzberg is renowned for its <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/11/happy-weekend-its-not-about-integration-or-isnt-it/">immigrant integration</a> challenges that include low educational attainment and poor German language skills, high unemployment rates, crime and drug abuse, and gentrification. At the same time, the area has become increasingly attractive to <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/09/06/multiculturalism-diversity-and-the-big-city/">students</a>, hip expats, and young families. The result is a veritable array of nationalities, cuisines, houses of worship, and attires, as vivid as the graffiti gracing the walls of its gray housing and slender canals.</p>
<p>There are many popular spots in Kreuzberg, but the Maybachufer canal is perhaps one that most poignantly displays the cultural fusion that makes Kreuzberg a very special place to call home.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/swans.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/swans.jpg" alt="swans" width="594" height="594" /></a></p>
<p><strong>An Ode to the Maybachufer</strong></p>
<p>If I go away, I&#8217;ll remember the swans. And the walls of graffiti they floated along.</p>
<p>Rows of satellite dishes, speckled across gray concrete. Lingerers outside Kaiser&#8217;s, empty bottles at their feet.</p>
<p>Men huddled over pear-shaped glasses of Çay. Girls in tiny shorts and tights, snags in their thighs.</p>
<p>A market with only two rows, but infinite choice. Vendors calling &#8220;lecka! lecka!&#8221;, hints of somewhere else in their voice.</p>
<p>Hair smothered by scarves or impossibly fake dye. Individuals by words: &#8220;expat&#8221;, &#8220;immigrant&#8221;. You or I.</p>
<p>Where &#8220;German&#8221; ends and &#8220;other&#8221; begins, we futilely try to decide.</p>
<p>But the swans. They just keep floating by.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The Maybachufer Turkish Market (U1-Kottbusser Tor or U8-Schoenleinstrasse) runs on Tuesdays and Fridays from approximately 12pm-6pm. Go for the cheap produce and spinach-cheese <em>Gözleme. </em><br />
</em></p>
<p>* West Germany recruited 14 million guest workers between 1955 and 1973 during the post World War II &#8220;economic miracle&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>For more on Turks in Germany and guest worker programs:</strong></p>
<p>http://www.azcentral.com/news/articles/global-immigration-germany.html?nclick_check=1</p>
<p><strong>For more on Kreuzberg:  </strong></p>
<p>http://www.fhxb-museum.de/</p>
<p>http://travel.michelin.com/web/destination/Germany-Berlin/news-Kreuzberg_forever-Reichenberger_Str_177</p>
<p>http://www.humanityinaction.org/knowledgebase/32-in-kreuzberg-there-are-no-foreigners-scrutinizing-berlin-s-diversity</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/02/20/lens-an-ode-to-the-maybachufer/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
