<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Jewish &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/jewish/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Interview: the Klezmer Gentiles</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2014 09:55:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creative activism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Holocaust]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jewish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[memory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Poland]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2468</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[International artists in Berlin occupy a semi-privileged position, able to ask critical questions of society without being publicly rebuked. An example of such an artist is Soliman Lawrence. Soli has been photographing the memorialization of Jewish culture in Poland for years, following the tracks of a new form of engagement with the past, as enacted by a more recent generation of Poles. In contrast to Poland, Germany now has its fair share of Jews. What might this mean for memory and its rituals?...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>An interview is never one-sided &#8211; in fact, it is a constructive conversation. I am as much a part of this piece as the artist who answered my questions. Without the contributions of the other, individual statements would hold little significance. So thanks, Soli, for letting me share our conversation. </em></p>
<p>International artists in Berlin are one category of newcomers who, although shaping the cultural politics and economic fabric of Berlin perhaps more than other groups of foreign residents (those without German citizenship), are often left out of the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/11/integration-in-berlin-research-for-a-desolate-landscape/">critical integration debate</a>. Whether or not they learn German or German constitutional law seems to matter little to the politicians and journalists fueling the heavily institutionalized, assimilating discourse. I have yet to meet an artist who has been pressured by the authorities to &#8216;integrate&#8217; him or herself, as is the case with members of different social and economic groups.</p>
<p>This semi-privileged position has its benefits: Berlin&#8217;s creatives are often able to ask critical questions of society without being publicly rebuked, far enough from local history to recognize nuance and apply cultural critique in a non-threatening fashion.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2684 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-8-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>An example of such an artist is an old friend <a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/">Soliman Lawrence</a>. Soli has been photographing the memorialization of Jewish culture in Poland for years, following the tracks of a new form of engagement with the past, as enacted by a more recent generation of Poles. His collection of work is titled &#8220;<a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/unquietplacesphoto.html">For those whose faith has been broken</a>&#8220;. They do so, as Soliman&#8217;s stories and their pictures explain, through ritual, one example of which is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Klezmer">Klezmer</a> music. The fascinating part of this story: there are few Jews to speak of in Poland.</p>
<p>Beyond a revived Klezmer tradition, Soliman photographs reconstructed synagogues, Jewish-themed festivals, hand-made figurines, the maintenance of Jewish cemeteries &#8211; all weaving a tale of things past, now re-born as an ode to matzo ball soup or rabbinical characters.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2681 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland" width="640" height="423" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11-300x198.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/photo-11-650x429.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>Soliman is not Jewish, though his choice of topic likely gets many thinking that personal biography must inform the interest. I met with Soliman at a little cafe in Neukölln to talk art, history, and memory. Parallels between German memorialization of Jewish culture in Berlin and that which is happening in Poland were not at the tip of his tongue; these parallels were on the tip of mine, however.</p>
<p>Soliman is American by passport, has been a Berlin resident for more than 8 years, making the nationality question a bit tricky. He studied philosophy in the United States, stems originally from the Northern part of Florida, and has a contemplative way about him &#8211; he seems to move slowly, take things in and digest them before forming an opinion.</p>
<p>His artistic career began with a camera, has now evolved into a sort of philosophical exploration of what it means to remember. <em>Memory is at the center of my work</em>, he tells me, <em>how people remember after something has passed, how they remember together</em>. He is interested in the idea of <em><a href="http://www.postmemory.net/">post-memory</a>, the ways in which memory stays alive without the original witnesses</em>. Photography serves a crucial purpose, documentation allowing for connection.</p>
<p>Soliman first started making trips to Poland in 2006, visiting the growing Klezmer festivals in places like Krakaw. <em>Here is the biggest and best festival in Poland</em>, he tells me. I imagine VW buses jammed full with young, alternative Poles, spending warm nights outdoors, not for the beat of electronic sounds but for renditions of clarinet and fiddle. Actually, <em>it is quite mixed</em>, he tells me: young/old, hip/not.</p>
<p><em>When I first showed up in Krakaw, I was taking pictures of everything. I assumed a lot of the stuff I was photographing had something to do with Antisemitism &#8211; graffiti on the walls somehow looked antisemitic to me, these little tiles in the main square with five-pointed stars</em>, <em>for example</em>, he says with a laugh. <em>Then I realized that these stars were actually six-pointed, so </em>not <em>necessarily</em> <em>antisemitic</em>. <em>Very often, one finds what one searches for</em>, I add. This is even more true for a photographer, able to capture and catalog what may be happenstance occurrence, curating images into some sort of narrative about a people or place.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2682 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-6-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>That doesn&#8217;t mean that Antisemitism isn&#8217;t present in Polish society, however: <em>it&#8217;s complicated</em>, he says. An interview with Soliman on Jewish memorial culture in Poland appeared in 2012 in <em>die</em> <i>Zeit Online </i>with the headline: &#8220;<em>Wie Nicht-Juden die jüdische Kultur Polens wiederbeleben/</em> &#8220;<a href="http://www.zeit.de/video/2012-12/2032360755001/holocaust-wie-nicht-juden-die-juedische-kultur-polens-wiederbeleben">How Non-Jews Are Resurrecting Poland&#8217;s Jewish Culture</a>&#8220;. I recall watching the interview then, having heard of the beginnings of his Polish adventures back in 2010, when Soli and I first met, and being struck by the oddity of it all, the sense of a manufactured experience to take the place of an entire culture now lost. And yet, it was impossible not to find parallels with the city we both share, I felt: the way in which memory of Jewish culture in Berlin is fractured between recreations of the diaspora experience, a come-back Jewish culture in Germany, and a newer wave of young Israelis.</p>
<p>Soli has given quite a number of interviews in Germany since his project first began to receive attention. A <a href="http://juedische-woche-dresden.de/veranstaltung-2013/items/108.html">recent exhibition of his work in Dresden</a> put him into more contact with the German media. <em>So, did any of these journalists ask about your thoughts on Jewish memorialization in Germany, in Berlin, or on any similarities between Poland and Germany?</em>, I ask. At first, he doesn&#8217;t understand my question, seems a bit perplexed. Then, <em>No</em>,<em> in fact, no one even got close to formulating that question. Interesting that you bring that up. </em></p>
<p>Jewish culture in Berlin is diffuse, hard to put a finger on, as &#8211; with Jews everywhere &#8211; there is no one way to be Jewish and certainly no one way to be Jewish in Berlin. A memorial culture is also difficult to construct, when Jews are in fact present. To boot, there is no <em>one</em> way to memorialize the Holocaust and the thriving Jewish culture in Germany that preceded it. At least no one way that would satisfy the diverse groups who were affected by the genocide. In Poland, very little has happened at an institutional, top-down level. And so revivals of classic Ashkenazi traditions like Klezmer have been a means of memorializing a lost sector of Polish life, many years after its musicians were made to disappear.</p>
<p><em>At my first Klezmer festival, I didn&#8217;t really know what to do with myself. People were dancing, it was celebratory, there was this feeling of community</em>, he says. He was a bit stand-offish, not understanding why active participation was required. <em>This is the ritual</em>, he explains, <em>it is through such a collective ritual that some form of memory is reconstructed and created for the next generation.</em> <em>Many of these young people probably have no real connection to contemporary Jewish people</em>, he adds,<em> but this type of memory doesn&#8217;t require personal connection, rather an attachment to space and a desire to make a place &#8211; a memorial &#8211; out of it.</em></p>
<p>In Berlin, there is a strong attention to memorial sites or objects &#8211; the <a href="http://www.stolpersteine-berlin.de/en/stolpersteine"><em>Stolpersteine</em></a>, <a href="http://www.holocaust-mahnmal.de/en"><em>Memorial to the Murdered Jews of Europe</em></a>, <a href="http://www.slowtravelberlin.com/touching-berlins-ghosts/"><em>Bayerisches Viertel</em></a>, to name a few. These are spaces that are visited and even organized by many but are perhaps not as interactive or collective as a Klezmer ritual. One might simply pass by its insignia, whereas Klezmer is somehow a more active process, Soli explains.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2685 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9-300x199.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-9-650x432.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p><em>But are these Klezmer festivals in Poland really about remembering and mourning the Holocaust? </em>I ask. <em>Yes, it is about that but not only about that.</em> <em>It is about thinking about the Jews that were once here, by people who were too young to have had the chance</em>.</p>
<p>There is a tendency<em> </em>in memorializing activities to focus on objects and their stories; materiality is desired, physical connection reconstructed. The Holocaust documentation and education center where I used to work curated a collection called &#8220;<a href="http://www.wsherc.org/museum/everyday-objects">Everyday Objects</a>&#8220;, the National Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM) releases <a href="http://www.ushmm.org/information/exhibitions/curators-corner">weekly stories online from its archival vault of objects</a>, and even the recent <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/sportingscene/2014/04/memory-objects-commemorating-the-boston-marathon-bombings.html?utm_source=dlvr.it&amp;utm_medium=twitter">Boston Marathon bombings are being actively commemorated through the collection of ordinary things</a>.</p>
<p><em>When talking with journalists, they just don&#8217;t really understand why Klezmer music is so popular in Poland, </em>Soli comments, as if to emphasize the stark differences between the German memory process and that of the Poland he knows:<em> Memory is expressed differently across space.</em> <em>My work is about these different memory ways, memory forms. </em></p>
<p>Surprising to many, Berlin is home to a fair number of Jews, and not just returned German Jews or those that fled from the former Soviet Union, but Israeli Jews, secular Israelis, secular Diaspora Jews from Argentina etc. &#8211; colliding in one city, not necessarily finding community among one another, because why should they? To make the argument, however, that perhaps things aren&#8217;t as different as they seem, I add that one does see a sort of stereotypical Jewish culture in Berlin, from the <a href="http://www.exberliner.com/locations/luigi-zuckermann-deli/">classic deli</a><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> </span>serving pastrami sandwiches to the local bagel shop. Both places in mind are not run by anyone of Jewish heritage, catering to a historic Jewish culture, perhaps even to New York Jewry rather than Berlin. This is not to say that there are no Jewish delis or bagel shops in Berlin that are owned by Jews. <em>But might the more theatrical recreations be a form of memorial culture, similar to Klezmer festivals?</em> I ask. <em>Maybe</em>, he says, <em>but I know a  few Israelis, and they don&#8217;t necessarily eat bagels. They go to this one shop on </em>Sonnenallee<em> where they can get hummus served warm, like back home in Israel</em>.</p>
<p>The varied layers of Jewish culture, identity, and memory in the Berlin landscape prevent one from making any static comparison to the situation in Poland, it seems &#8211; a place with very few Jews to speak of and a history wrought with a non-institutionalized form of memory, at least until recently. The Israeli and general Jewish presence in Berlin further complicates a comparison between the memory culture of Poland and that of Berlin in a very real sense. To be the authors of a tradition that re-appropriates Jewish tradition means being responsible for potential misappropriation. In Poland, I doubt there are too many active members of the Jewish community who would heavily criticize the rebirth of Klezmer in this form. <em>There aren&#8217;t</em>, Soli says.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2683 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg?w=640" alt="Jews Poland Klezmer" width="640" height="426" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7.jpg 700w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7-300x200.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/soli_photo-7-650x433.jpg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>If he feels strange about researching this issue as an American artist without Jewish descent &#8211; <em>No</em>. The Holocaust is a large part of how Americans understand Germany, I add, in order validate his work from a place of personal opinion. The past was certainly a key factor in my own interest in contemporary German politics and society, as my <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/">article on Sachsenhausen</a> demonstrates.</p>
<p>The question is, if such a connection between a bleak past and curious future can be made, productively, and with much room for nuance and reflection. Soliman Lawrence&#8217;s work allows for just that. Like other artists, he is able to describe memory ways as they are occurring, not overtly criticizing but allowing others to draw their own conclusions or parallels.</p>
<p>We all remember differently. The most important thing is simply to remember.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>Jewish identity in Berlin, Jews in Germany, Israelis in Berlin: there is no shortage of debate, public presence, or diversity. Here a recent <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/culture/2014/05/so-long-israel-hello-berlin.html">article from <em>The New Yorker</em></a> on this topic and a few articles from us, written from the most varied of positions:</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/">Why Remembering the Holocaust is Good for Immigrants</a> &#8211; integration policy and a visit to Sachsenhausen concentration camp</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/07/rant-or-rave-jew-in-a-box/">Rant or Rave? Jew in a Box</a> &#8211; a controversial exhibit at the Berlin Jewish Museum</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/">Interview: TV, the Treasury Minister, and Third Culture Kids</a> &#8211; Israeli in Berlin</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/03/07/interview-three-dimensions-of-integration/">Interview: Three Dimensions of Integration</a> &#8211; Jewish-American artist in Berlin</p>
<p>Last but not least, a few links for finding that Jewish deli or that Israeli hummus: <a href="http://www.berlinfo.com/Lifetime/Shopping/food/jewish/, http://forward.com/articles/165718/berlins-jewish-comeback/?p=al">Berlins Jewish Comeback</a>, <a href="//www.hagalil.com/deutschland/berlin/gemeinde/kosher.htm">Hagalil</a>, <a href="http://www.jewish-berlin.com/kosher.php">Jewish-Berlin</a>, <a href="http://www.berlinjewish.com/tips-for-your-berlin-vacation">Jewish in Berlin</a>, <a href="http://www.exberliner.com/food/land-of-the-lox-can-you-get-deli-food-in-berlin/">ExBerliner deli food list</a>.</p>
<p><em>All images were graciously provided by Soliman Lawrence as part of the series &#8220;<a href="http://www.solimanlawrence.com/unquietplacesphoto.html">For those whose faith has been broken</a>&#8220;. To see some of Soliman&#8217;s newer projects, check out his homepage. </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/05/30/interview-the-klezmer-gentiles/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview: TV, the Treasury Minister, and Third Culture Kids</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2013 13:08:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ex-pat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jewish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Third Culture Kids]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transnationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1543</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It's not everyday you're on TV, let alone get alluded to as a traitor by a host of public figures, including the Minister of the Treasury, all for being an expat. But both of these things happened to my friend and colleague Moran Yaheli when she was recently profiled in a report about Israelis living abroad...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/img_2302.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/img_2302.jpg?w=640" alt="IMG_2302" width="640" height="425" /></a>It&#8217;s not everyday you&#8217;re on TV, let alone get alluded to as a traitor by a host of public figures, including the Minister of the Treasury, all for being an expat. But both of these things happened to my friend and colleague Moran Yaheli when she was recently profiled in a TV report about Israelis living abroad.</p>
<p><em>We were on 4 episodes, there were 5 in total, and I&#8217;ve been on the morning talk show and the radio, </em>Moran recounts&#8230; <em>and I was told that a satire show used our part from the morning show. This Sunday I&#8217;m going to be on another morning show panel. I&#8217;m a Z-list celebrity!</em></p>
<p>But we&#8217;ll get back to that.</p>
<p>Moran moved to Berlin from Tel Aviv in 2011 after meeting her now fiancé, Bastiaan (Bas). Their story alone is a lesson in 21st century romances: they met on the online Couchsurfing platform, and Moran spent a few nights on Bas&#8217; couch in Amsterdam while traveling around Europe. After surviving a few months of long-distance Skype calls and the occasional visit, the two decided to make a home for themselves in Europe. They both found jobs in Berlin and now live together in the <em>Schöneberg</em> district. Last year they welcomed their first baby, a beautiful boy named Tommy.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/israel-part-ii-081-kl-auto.jpeg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1627" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/israel-part-ii-081-kl-auto.jpeg?w=640" alt="Israel part II 081 kl auto" width="640" height="425" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/israel-part-ii-081-kl-auto.jpeg 768w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/israel-part-ii-081-kl-auto-300x199.jpeg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/israel-part-ii-081-kl-auto-650x431.jpeg 650w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p>Tommy is primed to grow up as what has been coined the Third Culture Kid (TCK): &#8220;a person who has spent a significant part of his or her developmental years outside their parents’ culture&#8221; (David Pollock). With an Israeli mother, Dutch father, childhood (or at least babyhood) in Germany, and frequent trips to both mother- and fatherlands, Tommy will grow up navigating at least three cultural codes, languages, and geographies. It may seem like an unusual life, but it&#8217;s more and more a norm in our increasingly globalized and interconnected world. Even Buzzfeed published an <a href="http://www.buzzfeed.com/regajha/31-signs-youre-a-third-culture-kid">article</a> on &#8220;signs you&#8217;re a TCK&#8221; that included swearing in multiple languages, time zone expertise, and a transient understanding of &#8220;home&#8221;.</p>
<p><em>Tommy is a child of combined cultures, </em>Moran reflects<em>&#8230; he has both an Israeli and Dutch passport&#8230; but even though he was born in Berlin he can&#8217;t be a German citizen (without giving up the Israeli one). It&#8217;s the same for me, I feel I have more than one &#8220;home&#8221;, and I guess he will have that, too.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/285679521_640.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1580" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/285679521_640.jpg" alt="285679521_640" width="640" height="360" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/285679521_640.jpg 640w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/285679521_640-300x168.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/285679521_640-310x174.jpg 310w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://vimeo.com/41264088">Source</a></p>
<p>With only 8 months behind him so far in this world, Tommy has already taken two lengthy trips to Tel Aviv and one to the Netherlands. He is a dual citizen and hears an average 2-4 languages per day: Hebrew from his mom, Dutch from his dad, German from his environment, and English, the language in which his parents communicate.</p>
<p><em>We want to do the OPOL method, &#8216;One Parent One Language&#8217;, have you heard of it? </em>Moran asks me.<em> That way he gets just Hebrew from me, just Dutch from Bas. Tommy&#8217;s baby noises are kind of both Hebrew and Dutch, he does a lot of the &#8220;Chhh&#8221; noise&#8230; </em>she giggles.<em> When the neighbor babysits he only speaks German with him. I want him to go to a bilingual Hebrew-German Kita </em>(child care center).</p>
<p>Tommy is not just (im)migrant, not just citizen, but somewhere in between. He was born and lives in Berlin but isn&#8217;t a German citizen. If he moves to either Israel or the Netherlands, he will be moving there as a citizen but won&#8217;t necessarily have grown up there. His diverse lineage, cross-cultural upbringing, and even his darker features may mean he carries the mark of <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/"><em>Migrationshintergrund</em></a> most of his life, whether in Germany, Israel, the Netherlands, or somewhere else. Tommy will &#8220;build relationships to all these cultures but perhaps never have full ownership of any&#8221;. TCKs often feel a stronger sense of belonging and connection to others who have a similar background rather than a particular one. When Tommy grows up, he may fall in love and marry another TCK, someone who grew up in Rome with Singaporean and British parents, or perhaps someone from Sydney with French and Brazilian parents. Studies say his chances of doing so are <a href="http://www.denizenmag.com/2011/09/infographic-the-modern-third-culture-kid/">1 in 4</a>. His future inclination to raise his children as TCKs? <a href="http://www.denizenmag.com/2011/09/infographic-the-modern-third-culture-kid/">Even higher</a>. His sense of home will be an abstract one, one that he feels more in relation to people, memories, and experiences than citizenship, borders, and geography.</p>
<p><em>I can&#8217;t vote in Israel because Israeli doesn&#8217;t allow absentee ballots&#8230; even my cousin </em>(in Israel)<em> doesn&#8217;t think I should be able to vote in their elections because I don&#8217;t live there, </em>Moran rolls her eyes.<em> But even though I don&#8217;t live in Israel, I still feel it&#8217;s my home&#8230; my friends and family are there. As for Tommy, he will have 3 homes for now and as he grows maybe just two- Israel which he will visit a lot, and Holland where he will likely live at some point. If we&#8217;re in Holland or Germany, I&#8217;m going to be seen as a foreigner. I don&#8217;t want Tommy to be made fun of or be ashamed of me. So it&#8217;s important for me that Tommy meets and grows up in an international environment, with kids who also have diverse backgrounds. With other kids like him.<br />
</em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/2013-10-08-16-38-33.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/2013-10-08-16-38-33.jpg?w=640" alt="2013-10-08 16.38.33" width="512" height="682" /></a></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Confusions and complications aside, studies on Third Culture Kids show that they reap a whole host of benefits from their intercultural upbringings and lifestyles: TCKs live in four countries during their lives on average, 85% speak two or more languages (47% speak three or more), and 90% earn a Bachelor&#8217;s Degree with 40% going on to further study. Statistically they&#8217;re a well-educated, well-rounded, and well-suited group for the demands of the 21st century, both professionally and personally. They just may have difficulty articulating to you <a href="http://vimeo.com/41264088">where home is</a>.</p>
<p><em>I don&#8217;t know where Tommy will end up, </em>considers Moran.<em> Right now the current situation in Israel is complicated and I can&#8217;t see us going back. Economically, politically, demographically, religiously, etc. But I am not giving up hope&#8230; Israel is a beautiful place, the best place, it&#8217;s just unfortunately in crisis. If things get better I would be on the first plane home. And, if the situation improves, I would love for Tommy to choose Israel, too.  </em></p>
<p>As to the economic situation&#8230;</p>
<p><em>The rising number of Orthodox Jews is scary and it is so expensive to live in Tel Aviv. I paid the same rent for a shoebox in Tel Aviv as I do now with Bas in our big, new flat in Berlin. Groceries are over twice as expensive in Israel than Germany!</em></p>
<p>126% more expensive in fact, which brings us back to the TV report. Grocery and rent costs were one topic Moran and a series of other Israeli expats were asked about when interviewed about living abroad. The economic situation in Israel is pretty dire and gave rise to the ongoing social justice protests that began in 2011, the largest in the country&#8217;s history with over 1 million people gathering in Tel Aviv&#8217;s Rabin Square. While mostly focused on the cost of living differences, Moran also got token questions about what it feels like to be a Jew in Germany. On the show, the journalist shuttles her over to the Holocaust Memorial to the Jews in <em>Mitte</em>. He&#8217;s curious how she feels when she sees it.</p>
<p><em>The Jewish Memorial doesn&#8217;t speak to me,</em> Moran explained first to the journalist and later to me. <em>It&#8217;s more the everyday. Like seeing trains covered in snow&#8230; we don&#8217;t have snow covered trains in Israel and it reminds me of images we saw in school of the deportation of the Jews. Or hearing the voice on the train say &#8216;</em>Ausstieg&#8217;<em> which always makes me think of &#8216;Auschwitz&#8217;. Seeing old people on the street and wondering what role they played in World War II.</em></p>
<p>And the Minister of the Treasury? When asked to respond to the TV report, he was in Budapest, giving a speech on antisemitism.</p>
<p><em>A word to all those who have &#8220;had it&#8221; and left for Europe&#8230; </em>Moran translates his response for me&#8230;<em> I&#8217;m here to deliver a speech in the Budapest Parliament about antisemitism, to remind them of how they tried to kill my father here only because Jewish people didn&#8217;t have their own land, how they did kill my grandfather in a camp, how they starved my uncles, how my grandmother was rescued at the last second from a &#8220;death march&#8221;. So excuse me if I&#8217;m a bit impatient with people who are willing to throw away the only homeland the Jewish people have ever had, just because Berlin is &#8220;more convenient&#8221;.</em></p>
<p>Other politicians and one of the country&#8217;s most famous lawyers went so far as to call the Israeli expats in Berlin &#8220;traitors&#8221; and &#8220;slime that crawls in the sewer of Jewish society&#8221;, respectively. On the whole, however, Moran reports positive responses and understanding from those back in Israel, something she claims is a shift from the Zionist past.</p>
<p><em>It&#8217;s the older generation that has a problem with people leaving Israel&#8230; the ones who escaped antisemitism, built the country and died in wars to protect it, </em>Moran explains. <em>They see our leaving as abandoning the ship, the cause, the ideal&#8230; for money. My parents were born in Israel but my grandparents were from Europe, so I have two passports, too, </em><em>Israeli and Romanian. </em><em>I want Tommy to grow up with both tradition and choice&#8230; for his religion and for where he makes his home. </em></p>
<p>And choices he will have&#8230;</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p><em>For those with Hebrew skills or simply interested in watching and pretending to understand (like me), you can check out the video that includes Moran, Bas, and Tommy <a href="http://news.nana10.co.il/Article/?ArticleID=1007634">here</a>. Also, I recommend this great little video about TCKs made by a Georgetown University student <em><a href="http://vimeo.com/41264088">here</a></em>. There&#8217;s also a Facebook group dedicated to TCKs around the world, check it out <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Third-Culture-Kids-TCKs/274710935889196">here</a>! </em></p>
<p><em>For the German perspective on the German-Israeli friendship and the question of expats, click <a href="http://www.sueddeutsche.de/politik/israel-berlin-wir-fahren-nach-berlin-1.1793580">here</a> (for German speakers). </em></p>
<p>All images not with a linked source are my own or Moran&#8217;s.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/10/18/interview-tv-the-treasury-minister-and-third-culture-kids/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rave: Why Remembering the Holocaust is Good for Immigrants</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2013 08:43:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GDR-DDR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Holocaust]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jewish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[museums]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nazi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WWII]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=1353</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In 2005, Germany officially became an immigration country with the establishment of its federal office for migration. The question - who are the Germans anyway? - has become increasingly important in deciding what to impart to these newcomers set to stay. Expats are good at constructing Germanness for the Germans themselves, often leaving out the Holocaust in such a description of 'German identity', however. Today's Germany - an immigration country - is a republic built on tragic events like the Holocaust, just as France is a country built on colonialism. Everything has a context, and it is this context that immigrants to Germany should learn to understand for the sake of a more complete country - a civic society which respects differences and celebrates them...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p dir="ltr">In 2005, Germany officially became an immigration country with the establishment of its federal office for migration (<a href="http://www.bamf.de/EN/Startseite/startseite-node.html">BAMF</a>). A wave of new laws and institutions were to follow, set to absorb those meant to stay &#8211; not just <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gastarbeiter">guest-workers</a>, not temporary migrants, not <a href="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vertragsarbeiter">comrades</a> (so-called <em>Vertragsarbeiter</em> from communist countries), but immigrants. In turn, <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">German identity </a>has been shoved into the limelight. This country and its residents have witnessed plenty of change and adjustment, but redefining self and country after the fall of the Berlin Wall (even during the student <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protests_of_1968">protests of 1968</a>) had little to do with defining oneself in opposition to a foreign but stationary Other. Although individuals and families with non-German origins have been coming for centuries, confronting what will be an official change in what it means to be German is rather new, rather fresh.</p>
<div style="width: 600px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b038669g"><img loading="lazy" class=" " title="Justin Rowlatt and his wife Bee set out to live like a typical German family" src="http://images.dailyexpress.co.uk/img/dynamic/20/590x/make-me-a-german-420020.jpg" alt="Justin-Rowlatt-and-his-wife-Bee-set-out-to-live-like-a-typical-German-family" width="590" height="350" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Who are the Germans anyway? A BBC series answers this question by-doing</p></div>
<p dir="ltr">The question &#8211; who are the Germans anyway? &#8211; becomes increasingly important when deciding what to impart to newcomers. Which traditions deserve saving? What is important? The answers to these questions are not as simple as good bread or Hefeweizen. Expats with an outsider perspective are not shy in constructing simple &#8216;Germanness&#8217; for the Germans themselves. The BBC reality TV series &#8220;<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/tv-and-radio/2013/aug/07/make-me-german-tv-review">Make Me a German</a>&#8221; plays with stereotypes and assumptions about what is <em>typisch deutsch</em> (typically German); the viral blog post <a href="http://www.uberlin.co.uk/what-i-know-about-germans/"><em>What I know about Germans </em></a>is just one example of trendy list-making of all things &#8216;German&#8217; by temporary residents; Berlin-based comedy writer <a href="http://adam-fletcher.co.uk/">Adam Fletcher</a> has created an entire <a href="http://store.hipstery.com/">brand</a> just based on the funny categorization of ‘Germanness’. On a tote bag in Fletcher’s line of nifty and hilarious merchandise: an engineer’s instruments, a watch, whole wheat, nude culture, asparagus. But where is the concentration camp in these lists, this series, or this fashion line? Where is the Holocaust?</p>
<div id="attachment_1362" style="width: 522px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218225820494823.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1362" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-1362" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218225820494823.png?w=640" alt="Aviary Photo_130218225820494823" width="512" height="682" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1362" class="wp-caption-text">Entrance to Sachsenhausen concentration camp, Oranienburg, DE</p></div>
<p dir="ltr">This past weekend, I embarked on a day-long tour of the former <a href="http://www.stiftung-bg.de/gums/en/index.htm">Sachsenhausen concentration camp</a> with a good friend here in Berlin &#8211; a friend, who just happens to be Jewish and originally from Ukraine.  We were a small group for an English speaking tour, minuscule in comparison to the masses of Italian and Spanish tour groups all heading to the same location. Two Taiwanese students, an American-Spanish couple on vacation from their residence in Saudi Arabia, a Brazilian student traveling Europe for the first time, a Bulgarian engineer, and Max and I (both Americans). We met our guide Alex, exchanged small talk, in part to find out why we all were willing to commit seven hours on a Sunday to hearing about tragedy, visiting the haunted, vast expanses of Sachsenhausen &#8211; a concentration camp just right on the edge of Berlin, reachable with the S-Bahn (public transit).</p>
<p dir="ltr">In contemporary political discussions about integration of immigrants into ‘German society’, no one claims that integration requires learning the lessons of the Holocaust. And yet, federal integration programs combined with international perception of Germanness say just that. The public concept of historical memorialization and its application, called <em>Vergangenheitsbewältigung, </em>is just as important to living in German society as <em>v</em><em>ollkorn Brötchen </em>or <em>Oktoberfest. </em></p>
<p dir="ltr">On our tour&#8217;s long walk from <a href="http://www.oranienburg.de/texte/seite.php?id=91511">Oranienburg</a> station to the gates of the camp, passing average-looking &#8216;German&#8217; homes with gardens neatly segregated from the street by high fences, I spoke with Natalia (the student from São Paulo) about Germany, the Germans, and the Holocaust. She brought up an interesting point: “How do the Germans feel about it &#8211; that people go to Venice to see the canals and to Berlin to see the Holocaust? I can imagine they don’t like it”. A man jogged past us in bright running-gear, his dog trotting behind him, just passing the entrance to the camp. This is part of being German &#8211; accepting that this is how you are seen in the world, that this history is an indivisible part of any sense of being German, it seemed.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218225935786183.png"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-1363" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218225935786183.png?w=640" alt="Aviary Photo_130218225935786183" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p dir="ltr">For new residents of Berlin, the past still matters and maybe even more than integration programs can provide for. My Ukrainian-American-Jewish friend Max (gotta love them hyphens) and his family left Kiev when he was five, in part due to Antisemitism. His great-great-grandparents were killed in the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Babi_Yar">Babi Yar massacre</a> of 1941. The precarious relationship of the German government to its new status as an immigration country, let alone the way it classifies its non-German residents, is very much familiar to Max. &#8220;So, how does that make you feel as a Jew in Germany?&#8221;, I asked a bit sheepishly, recognizing the change of context from friendly chatter we usually entertain to rrrrrreal real fast. Many Jewish immigrants to Germany have likely heard this question before. “Antisemitism is more the exception than the rule. I don’t feel confronted by it in daily life&#8230;but I know it’s there”, he concluded. He is supportive of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-Fascist_Action">Antifa</a> movements, aware that being Jewish in Germany is complicated but totally do-able, requiring a little finesse. Berlin, of course, has all kinds of finesse.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Our tour entered Sachsenhausen through the renovated watchtower and its metal gates, a construction bearing the architectural legacy of the post-war custodians of the camp and many others &#8211; the (East) German Democratic Republic. A stream of other visitors followed our trail, audio devices pressed to their ears. I felt strange, almost supportive of an odd form of tourism, securing Natalia&#8217;s comment about the connection of Holocaust tourism to German identity in reality.</p>
<p dir="ltr" style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-3419" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_1302182256975699431.png" alt="aviary-photo_130218225697569943" width="606" height="606" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_1302182256975699431.png 606w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_1302182256975699431-300x300.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 606px) 100vw, 606px" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">A cacophony of languages could be heard as we moved from one monument within the camp to another &#8211; Swedish, Japanese, British English, French &#8211; all reading the same saddening information on plaques or biographical exhibition panels, all bearing witness to tragedy and an integral part (if not the deciding event) of this country&#8217;s history and present.</p>
<p dir="ltr">We moved to the far edge of the camp, heading toward the restored Barrack 38: the Jewish barrack turned memorial documentation center. As we entered the small structure, the smell of charred wood was unmistakable, paint peeling from the siding of the latrine and sleeping porch. Arson. In 1992, German identity was thrust under international limelight after reunification and the growing pains that followed, further exacerbated by the rise of Neonazism in the former East. Arson was a key expression of this tension. This same year of the attack on Barrack 38, Neonazis set fire to a refugee housing facility not too far from Berlin, terrorizing residents in the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Riot_of_Rostock-Lichtenhagen">riot of Rostock-Lichtenhagen</a>. The political activities of parties and movements, such as the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Democratic_Party_of_Germany">NPD</a> (German Nationalist Party with strong Neonazi ties), as well as the recent <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/topic/national_socialist_underground/">Neonazi terror-cell</a> and its string of xenophobic murders across Germany, point to a  contemporary relevance of the Nazi past to Germany’s future as a country of immigration. The Holocaust and its constitutive role in Germany identity has been part of the country&#8217;s historical development ever since. What to teach immigrants &#8211; remember the Holocaust.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3420" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226423822983-650x487.png" alt="aviary-photo_130218226423822983" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226423822983-650x487.png 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226423822983-300x225.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226423822983-80x60.png 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226423822983.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">We left the camp in a drizzle of rain, boarding the S-Bahn back to Berlin. As our guide Alex (speaking a high variety of the King&#8217;s English) began to share an illustrative vignette about the end of the war and deterioration of Nazi moral power in Germany, passengers in the train appeared perturbed. A woman with fiery hair shook her head in disgust; she furled insults in German in our guide&#8217;s direction (understood only by me at the time). Another stern-faced German woman entered shortly after, raising her voice to replace that of the recently exited red-haired woman. Her lips quivering, she looked to be my mother’s age, the veins in her neck traumatically flinching, exposed. “Why don’t you just stop talking. It is rude what you are doing. It is not right what you are doing. We don’t need to be lectured to! You must stop&#8221;, she said abruptly in English.</p>
<p dir="ltr">German trains and buses are anything but loud, each keeping to his or herself in a very strong show of privacy. This may be a stereotype, but it illuminates the particular conflict that ensued quite well.</p>
<p dir="ltr">With eyes closed in shock, our guide explained that we were on an educational tour of the concentration camp, that he had been doing this for years and had never had such a negative reaction. He kept calm and showed no sign of anger or distress. The female companion of the pulsing-veined woman responded loudly with perhaps the only words she knew: &#8220;shut uppp!&#8221;, popping the &#8216;p&#8217; just at the end.</p>
<p dir="ltr">My friend Max intervened &#8211; asked our guide to have a seat, standing to allow him to do so. With hands shaking and eyes kept closed, Alex continued his narrative: the time after the war, the protests of 1968, de-Nazification in educational and political institutions, current movements of young people, general skepticism toward patriotism in Germany ever since &#8211; all forming parts of a whole history that has never really come to a close.</p>
<p dir="ltr">As we exited the train, the pulsing-veined woman ran to Alex, extending her hand to graze his: &#8220;I agree with everything you said!&#8221;, she said, &#8220;but you were just speaking so loud for a public place! It is a train, not a classroom. Your voice was really just too loud for all of us, so for next time, just speak quieter.&#8221; She paused, Alex thanked her. And then with one last quiver of the lip: &#8220;I was one of those Germans you talked about, one of those students with guilt for something I wasn&#8217;t even old enough to have participated in. So thank you for what you said&#8230;&#8221;</p>
<p dir="ltr">&#8220;I don’t want anyone thinking ‘oh these horrible Germans’. I don’t want you all leaving thinking that,&#8221; the woman added as we had nearly let the train doors shut behind us, her eyes directed at all of us in a show of penetrating honesty. Education about the past does more than just memorialize or prevent reoccurrence: it avoids essentialization of historical events and preserves the complexity of it all.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-3421" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226704073063-650x487.png" alt="aviary-photo_130218226704073063" width="650" height="487" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226704073063-650x487.png 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226704073063-300x225.png 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226704073063-80x60.png 80w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/aviary-photo_130218226704073063.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></p>
<p dir="ltr">With the new immigration status of 2005 and the integration programs that followed, came the creation of an <a href="http://www.bamf.de/EN/Willkommen/DeutschLernen/Integrationskurse/InhaltAblauf/inhaltablauf-node.html">&#8216;integration curriculum&#8217;</a>, including cultural orientation that included this very facet of Germanness: the Holocaust. Immigrants participating in the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/06/18/review-become-a-german/">integration courses </a>visit historical institutions designed to communicate the significance of the Nazi period for Germany as both a modern state and as a group of transnational or transethnic individuals.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Official curriculum including Holocaust field-trips doesn&#8217;t answer all questions, however. Politicians are still scratching their heads at the &#8216;German question&#8217; &#8211; each party choosing which elements it wants to claim for the imagined &#8216;nation&#8217;, some famously campaigning for a <em>Leitkultur (</em>one central guiding culture for Germany by Germans). Such a sentiment has been heavily criticized by most politicians outside of the leading conservative party (CDU), including the head of the Jewish Council of Germany, Paul Spiegel. In a speech to Parliament, Spiegel said <em><a href="http://www.berliner-zeitung.de/archiv/leitkultur---die-scharfe-kritik-von-paul-spiegel-am--verbalen-zuendeln-der-politiker--hat-die-union-aufgeschreckt--der-bundesrat-stimmte-dem-antrag-auf-ein-verbot-der-rechtsextremen-npd-zu--merz-versuchte-zu-intervenieren,10810590,9851008.html">&#8220;Ist es etwa deutsche Leitkultur, Fremde zu jagen, Synagogen anzuzünden, Obdachlose zu töten?&#8221;</a>, &#8220;is it &#8216;German culture&#8217; to hunt down foreigners, to light synagogues on fire, to kill the homeless</em>?&#8221; The Holocaust is not far from these debates about Germanness, thus it is no wonder that it is included at least in educational programs to include newcomers in German society.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Today&#8217;s Germany &#8211; an immigration country &#8211; is a republic built on tragic events like the Holocaust, just as France is a country built on colonialism. This is not to say that countries and their residents are reducible to history. Rather it is to say that institutions and individuals are still intimately connected to what came before. It is about understanding how one can relate to such a history in its contemporary place, shaping either collective guilt or political activism (in the likes of Antifa) just the same. Everything has a context, and it is this context that immigrants to Germany should learn to understand for the sake of a more complete country &#8211; a civic society which respects differences and celebrates them. For Germany is not just for those who were once classified as &#8216;ethnically German&#8217;, it is for anyone that chooses to reside in Germany. Becoming German* is understanding history and what it might mean for the present, regardless of ethnicity.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><em>-By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>*Not sure, if you are German? Take this funny quiz from none other than Adam Fletcher <a href="http://www.thegermanquiz.com/">here</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>Our free tour to Sachsenhausen concentration camp was provided by <a href="http://www.viveberlintours.de/en/tours/sachsenhausen">Vive Berlin Tours</a></em>, <em>meeting Tuesdays, Fridays, and Sundays at 10am at Balzac Coffee on Potsdamer Platz year-round. Our guide, <a href="http://www.viveberlintours.de/en/guides">Alex</a>, comes highly recommended, as does this cooperative-style tour company which prides itself on expertise and narrative, as well as fairness for its employees. </em></p>
<p>Photo source: first image linked to source, otherwise taken by Kelly Miller</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/08/25/rave-why-remembering-the-holocaust-is-good-for-immigrants/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rant or Rave? Jew in a Box</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/07/rant-or-rave-jew-in-a-box/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/07/rant-or-rave-jew-in-a-box/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2013 08:51:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Informed Tourism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jewish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[museums]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.wordpress.com/?p=178</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p style="text-align:left;">What did you first think of when you read the post title? Saturday Night Live? World War II? Either way, I'm pleased to have gotten your attention. Let's talk about Jew in a Box...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/jewishmuseum.png"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-189" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/jewishmuseum.png" alt="jewishmuseum" width="599" height="397" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/jewishmuseum.png 599w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/jewishmuseum-300x198.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 599px) 100vw, 599px" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">What did you first think of when you read the post title? Saturday Night Live? World War II? Either way, I&#8217;m pleased to have gotten your attention. Let&#8217;s talk about Jew in a Box.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Jew in a Box is a nickname for what the Jewish Museum in Berlin is calling <em>Die ganze Wahrheit</em>, or The Whole Truth: a special exhibit that teaches Germans about real-life Jews, to put it bluntly. For two hours a day, a Jewish volunteer sits in a box and answers questions from museum-goers about all things Jewish. Any topic is free game, from God to Netanyahu to pork to circumcision.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">A half-Jew myself, I really want to like this exhibit. And I do in many ways. I believe that direct exposure to &#8220;others&#8221; can help break down barriers and generate understanding between groups. <strong>It often just takes meeting one person to humanize an entire group and start to break down harmful stereotypes.</strong> And a forum for being open and where there are no stupid questions, well let&#8217;s just say I often wish life were like that.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">I also appreciate the focus on the<em> current</em> experience of Jews in Germany. Germany does a whole lot to acknowledge the past, but the fact remains that <strong>most Germans today don&#8217;t have regular contact with Jews and know little about their religion and culture.</strong> Or maybe they do, and just don&#8217;t know it. Many would likely be surprised to learn that Berlin has a thriving &#8211; and growing &#8211; population of young Israelis and Jews. <a href="http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/features/2013/02/201322711114892470.html">Experts put estimates at up to 30,000</a>, maybe even higher since many Israelis have European passports and <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">aren&#8217;t considered immigrants</a>. Of course that doesn&#8217;t come close to the half a million Jews who lived in pre-war Germany, but it&#8217;s still considerable.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Negative reactions to the exhibit span from calling it &#8220;distasteful&#8221; to &#8220;degradation of the Jew.&#8221; I wouldn&#8217;t go as far to say the latter, but can understand a bit of the former. I see how the &#8220;box&#8221; analogy would make one uneasy. There&#8217;s also a fine line between being open and disrespectful, and with no filters and provocative signs surrounding the exhibit with statements like &#8220;The Jews are guilty of everything,&#8221; there&#8217;s potential for things to get offensive. But probably the biggest problem with this exhibit is that it&#8217;s somewhat reductionist. The Jews are more than a religious group- they are a diaspora, and a diverse one at that. An Orthodox Jew living in Brooklyn and a Jew from Ethiopia living as a Christian to escape persecution have less in common than I do with Oprah.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Can any one Jew really give &#8220;the whole truth&#8221;? This half-Jew isn&#8217;t sure.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>The Whole Truth runs from March 22- September 1, 2013. The Jewish Museum is located at Lindenstraße 9-14  10969 Berlin.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Photo Source: <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/04/05/world/europe/berlin-exhibition-on-judaism-hits-a-nerve.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=0">New York Times</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/07/rant-or-rave-jew-in-a-box/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
