<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>football &#8211; Collidoscope Berlin</title>
	<atom:link href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/tag/football/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local</link>
	<description>See Berlin through a lens of migration and difference</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:15:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Interview: Ali for (and from) Germany</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/09/02/interview-ali-for-and-from-germany/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sophia Burton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2014 08:27:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Local Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guestworkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neukölln]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=3183</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the wake of Germany's World Cup victory, much has been said about a renewed sense of German patriotism and its implications. While some have feared a connection to Germany's dark past, others have welcomed the discourse as a chance to shape a new sense of belonging within the country's evolving demographics. We've already written something about it here. But what a discussion on national identity means on the personal level is another story. Or rather many stories. Here's one...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the wake of Germany&#8217;s World Cup victory, much has been said about a renewed sense of German patriotism and its implications. While some have feared a connection to Germany&#8217;s dark past, others have welcomed the discourse as a chance to shape a new sense of belonging within the country&#8217;s evolving demographics. We&#8217;ve already written something about it <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/28/world-cup-fever-how-malleable-is-german-identity/">here</a>. But what a discussion on national identity means on the personal level is another story. Or rather many stories. Here&#8217;s one.</p>
<div id="attachment_3184" style="width: 439px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3184" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3184 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/ali.jpg" alt="Ali für Deutschland " width="429" height="429" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/ali.jpg 429w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/ali-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 429px) 100vw, 429px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3184" class="wp-caption-text">Ali at the Germany-France game at Train Cocktailbar</p></div>
<p>It took Ali <span class="gD">Riza Gürbüz over 30 years to feel welcome in Germany. Originally from East Anatolia, Ali moved to Berlin at age 12 with his brother and sister. His mother had arrived 8 years prior in 1973 as part of the last wave of guest worker recruitment. She was living in <span class="st">Neukölln and working for a cleaning company</span>. His father stayed behind in Turkey.</span></p>
<p><span class="gD"><em>The beginning wasn&#8217;t easy</em>, Ali recounts. Understanding German society, learning the language, feeling at home&#8230; this all took time. But eventually he gained his footing, finished his schooling, completed an <em>Ausbildung</em> (apprenticeship), and in 1986, began a career in industrial mechanics. Today, he&#8217;s married, has a 12 year old daughter and an active social life, and makes music in his free time. He still lives in N<span class="st">eukölln. </span><br />
</span></p>
<p><span class="gD"><strong>But despite spending the majority of his life in Germany, having German citizenship, and making a home here, he&#8217;s often felt like an outsider.</strong> </span></p>
<p><em>I still don&#8217;t really have any German friends</em>, Ali tells me on the last night of Ramadan in July, after breaking the fast together. We&#8217;re sitting outside on Kreuzberg&#8217;s iconic <span class="st"><em>Oranienstraße</em></span> with his friends, also both named Ali, both German-Turks* born in Berlin. Ali and Ali nod their heads in agreement. A rollerblading demonstration passes by in front of us. <em>I don&#8217;t understand it,</em> Ali says. <em>We all have the same sources of stress &#8211; work, money, family &#8211; so why don&#8217;t we make more of an effort to be nice to one another? </em></p>
<div id="attachment_3358" style="width: 660px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3358" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3358 size-large" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis-650x473.jpg" alt="Breaking the fast on Oranienstraße" width="650" height="473" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis-650x473.jpg 650w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis-300x218.jpg 300w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/xbergalis.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3358" class="wp-caption-text">Breaking the fast on Oranienstraße</p></div>
<p><span class="gD">Ali can cite the definitive moment in which he felt that he had finally &#8220;arrived&#8221; in Germany. <em>I was in the Bundeswehrkrankenhaus [German Armed Forces hospital] last December for a week due to a skin issue. I received such kind and affectionate treatment from the nurses and doctors. The same treatment as everyone else. I shared a room with a guy named Wolfgang, and we talked for two days straight, about everything. The atmosphere made me feel really welcome and inspired.</em></span></p>
<p>So inspired, that he started writing a song on his phone while still on his hospital bed. Two days after he was released, he finished &#8220;Ali <span class="st">für</span> Deutschland&#8221; (literally &#8220;Ali for Germany&#8221;), a World Cup song in <span class="gD">support of the </span>German national team. After recording it, Ali ran around to different departments and bureaus in the city, asking for support. Eventually he got a production company to film it for free. The song is available for purchase online (99 cents on iTunes) and half of the proceeds go to a homeless shelter in his neighborhood.<em> I really believed in the song and project, </em>Ali explains, <em>I wanted to show that someone who has my name and looks like me supports the German team. That people from all over the world with different backgrounds live here and consider it their home. </em><em><br />
</em></p>
<p><strong>Ali <span class="st">für</span> Deutschland Music Video: </strong></p>
<p><iframe width="650" height="366" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Mzqz6hCF7uI?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>Singing alongside Ali in the music video is his daughter. <em>I see that she&#8217;s growing up differently than I did, that she&#8217;s happier. I hope this song contributes to that. </em>For Ali, it all comes back to the media. <em>When Mesut Özil [German-Turkish football player] makes a good play, German-Turkish kids get patted on the back. If he does poorly, people shake their heads at us. The migration background is always emphasized. </em></p>
<p>Ali&#8217;s point is backed by research. <a href="http://www.stern.de/panorama/stern-umfrage-knappe-mehrheit-lehnt-islam-als-teil-deutschlands-ab-2128967.html">A recent Stern poll</a> shows that over half of Germans believe that Islam does not belong in German society. <a href="http://mediendienst-integration.de/artikel/der-islam-gehoert-zu-deutschland-spielhaus.html">Experts</a> argue that Islam is often conflated with Turks, the headscarf, and migration due to images perpetuated in the media. Another common image: German-Turkish or Arab youth as more violent or prone to criminal acts than their &#8220;native&#8221; counterparts, a stereotype repeatedly rebuked by <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/schulspiegel/wissen/kriminalitaet-von-migranten-laut-gutachten-nicht-hoeher-a-983536.html">studies</a>. <em>There are so many positive examples of what German-Turks have done and do for this country</em>, Ali says,<em> but news and social media continuously choose to show negative images. I want the media to show more positive images. </em><em><br />
</em></p>
<p>Ali is a positive person by nature. His face lights up when he shares stories of making connections to people at work or through his music. But he also has plenty of examples of feeling unwelcome or misunderstood on account of his background. He makes a conscious effort to speak Turkish with his daughter only at home and German out in public, in order to avoid judgment. More than once he&#8217;s been told &#8220;Du bist mein Lieblingst<span class="st">ürke</span><em>&#8221; </em>(&#8220;You&#8217;re my favorite Turk&#8221;), by a coworker or a club bouncer, for not stirring up trouble. <em>What am I supposed to do with that?</em> Ali asks, his eyes filling with emotion. Recently, a colleague joked to Ali that the reason his work contract was not renewed was because of his new hairstyle. <em>You look like a Turk now</em>, he told Ali.</p>
<p>After 6 years at the company, successfully training incoming employees, Ali had expected to keep his job. <em>After the video, they told me my music was making me slower at work, which wasn&#8217;t true,</em> Ali says, shaking his head<em>. <strong>I always felt like they were waiting for me to explode, to show my &#8220;Turkish temper&#8221;. In the end I think they just couldn&#8217;t deal with my humanness.</strong></em></p>
<div id="attachment_3359" style="width: 579px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3359" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-3359" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/alitsm.jpg" alt="Performing at a Football Academy Gala, August 2014" width="569" height="335" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/alitsm.jpg 569w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/alitsm-300x176.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 569px) 100vw, 569px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3359" class="wp-caption-text">Performing at a Football Academy Gala, August 2014</p></div>
<p>Ali is disappointed but not disheartened. He is taking this unexpected turn as a chance to reconsider career paths. <em>I have so much experience, and I want to use that to do something good</em>, he says. He&#8217;s now thinking seriously about becoming a social worker for kids with migration backgrounds. <em>I know </em><em>what they&#8217;re going through.</em> <em>I can go into their homes and talk to their parents, help them see what options they have and make sure they don&#8217;t give up. </em>More than likely, he&#8217;ll do it with music. <em>I learned early on that music allows you to reach a lot of people. Music is its own language, one that you don&#8217;t need to understand, just feel.</em></p>
<p>Ali is certainly &#8220;for&#8221; Germany, but does he consider himself from Germany? <em>Whew,</em> Ali lets out a deep breath, <em>I&#8217;m not sure. I have parts of German culture and parts of Turkish culture. But I think, most of all, I&#8217;m a Berliner.</em></p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Sophia Burton</strong></em></p>
<p>*The term German-Turk is a hyphenation often used for people born and/or raised in Germany with 2nd or 3rd generation Turkish backgrounds. For more on language, migration, and identity, see our article <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/04/23/over-and-over/">here</a>.</p>
<p>For German interviews with Ali, click <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/video/ali-fuer-deutschland-deutsch-tuerke-nimmt-wm-song-auf-video-1500438.html">here</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kGYNujx3RvQ">here</a>.</p>
<p><em>All of Ali&#8217;s quotes have been translated/paraphrased by Sophia Burton.<br />
</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>World Cup Fever: How malleable is German identity?</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/07/28/world-cup-fever-how-malleable-is-german-identity/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2014 09:43:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inclusion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[World Cup]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2873</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Germany's World Cup victory has unleashed a new wave of patriotism, as well as a new identity crisis. This patriotism might only be as good as the boundaries it is ready and able to redefine. An act of flowing colors and neighbor-to-neighbor high-fives may have started a new understanding of who is allowed into the club, but policies and institutions need to take it one step further. Otherwise, patriotism is just as good as nationalism, which rules by way of exceptionalism. In the type of inclusive global society many of us would love to build, there is no room for exceptionalism...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In 2006 Germany hosted the World Cup; it also organized a social-marketing campaign for the sole purpose of revamping and re-solidifying patriotism. These things, i.e. national pride, rarely happen organically, particularly for countries with strong regional identities and histories of division. The goal of the campaign: the encouragement of colors-wearing, flag-toting, &#8216;Schland&#8217;-cheering citizens of the federal republic. One image made its way through German newspapers and magazines during this novel World Cup fever, representing what was now allowed, what could again be said without glancing over one&#8217;s shoulder &#8211; a 15-year old girl, <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/spiegel/print/index-2014-29.html">Monique Bienge</a>, waving a scarf on which the German national anthem is printed, as pictured below.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.spiegel.de/spiegel/print/d-47282143.html"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2874 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/die-deutschland-party.jpg" alt="Germany World Cup" width="454" height="599" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/die-deutschland-party.jpg 454w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/die-deutschland-party-227x300.jpg 227w" sizes="(max-width: 454px) 100vw, 454px" /></a></p>
<p>The text on Monique&#8217;s scarf reads:</p>
<p><em>Unity and justice and freedom</em><br />
<em> for the German fatherland!</em><br />
<em> To that let us aspire</em><br />
<em> In a spirit of fraternity,</em><br />
<em> With heart and soul.</em></p>
<p>So-called football nationalism is not limited to one time of the year (or to every four years, for that matter), however. Its colors bleed into the surrounding shapes of civic life, exerting influence and changing norms with each successive step toward normalcy. The iconic image pictured above articulates Germany&#8217;s re-entrance through the gates of national pride &#8211; a process that began <em>en force </em>in 2006 and culminates today with the German national team&#8217;s WC victory.</p>
<p>But back when the gates were still swinging closed, often in classrooms or at the dinner table of <a href="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/68er-Bewegung">68er</a> grandparents, German politicians didn&#8217;t dare proclaim the type of national pride other countries are famous for. The American political landscape I know<em> requires</em> a language of exceptionalism*, as even <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UK7JEYqIfw4">President Obama&#8217;s recent speech at the UN General Assembly</a> demonstrates. In stark contrast, a <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/politik/deutschland/muegelner-buergermeister-ich-bin-stolz-deutscher-zu-sein-a-502950.html">mayor in Saxony in 2007</a> said he was &#8216;proud to be German&#8217;, and public rebukes followed (in part due to accusations of radical-right leanings); the jury was still in session.</p>
<p><strong>This year things were a bit different.</strong></p>
<p>After the German national team took home the trophy, standing before Berlin&#8217;s Brandenburg Gate with faces toward the historic German <em>Siegessäule</em> or &#8216;pillar of victory&#8217;,<em> </em>German flags did not disappear, did not crawl back into the hole from whence they had come. Little old ladies with bags of flowers and desserts kept their colored armbands tightly on the wrist; pubescent school kids kept wearing jerseys to school, in many cases looking a little underwashed and a little over-hormoned.</p>
<p>And it all seemed so normal, at least for some of us. And yet, as <a href="http://www.zeit.de/kultur/2014-07/schweinsteiger-blutkrieger-dfb-medienkritik">an article in <em>die Zeit</em></a> (a German weekly) pointed out, this was again anything but an organic process: &#8220;The German Football Association managed to become a synonym for Germany&#8221;, explained in part by what the author called &#8217;embedded journalism&#8217; of a different type, AKA German media sources working closely to manufacture a patriotic relationship to the German soccer team &#8211; something the association (DFB) does not vehemently deny.</p>
<p>But even if many citizens and residents of Germany were convinced of the linkage between national pride and a football win, latent critique still found its way into the conversation, particularly in response to the team&#8217;s <a href="http://youtu.be/bg6ZFv63URE">controversial parody</a> of the defeated Argentinians.</p>
<p><em>Die taz</em> (a German daily) <a href="http://taz.de/Pro-und-Contra-Gauchogate/!142556/">debated the potential controversy</a>; even a <a href="http://taz.de/Nachlese-zur-Fussball-WM/!142947/">guest post </a>from someone associated with the team asked, <em>if we are allowed to celebrate, how loud, how long, and who is included?</em> <em>Der Spiegel</em> (a tad more conservative national magazine) went after a similar though more general question &#8211; <em>who are we Germans again</em>? With a fully-veiled woman, a <em>Pfand</em>-schlepping chap, a working mother, all cloaked in German colors, the magazine responded: &#8216;We Germans&#8217;<em>, </em>as<em> </em>the cover photo and its video are called, are all a little different.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.spiegel.de/images/image-723794-magazincover300-dmug.gif" rel="http://www.spiegel.de/spiegel/print/index-2014-29.html"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="http://www.spiegel.de/images/image-723794-magazincover300-dmug.gif" alt="Der Spiegel World Cup" width="300" height="396" /></a></p>
<p>In other countries, patriotic displays would likely not be paired with an existential crisis. But this is Germany. As the above extract from the German national anthem mentions, a fatherland is at stake here &#8211; one that, at the time of the anthem&#8217;s composition, did not exist.</p>
<p>German-speaking public officials and intellectuals debated the question of identity and belonging during the years leading up to the creation of the federal conglomeration of German states (out of the former Holy Roman Empire and environs). And in 1871, (mostly) peasants were absorbed into a territorial construction more or less controlled by Prussia (a state no longer in existence), all based on inklings of a so-called <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pan-Germanism">Pan-Germanism</a>. In other words, <em>whose </em>&#8216;fatherland&#8217; we are really talking about depends not only on who you ask, but also on when this question is and has been posed in the past.</p>
<p><strong>But what might this mean for the public exercise of patriotism?</strong></p>
<p>The historically-rooted &#8216;German question&#8217; &#8211; i.e. who are the Germans? &#8211; has yet to be completely solved. This is the point. How could it be? Countries, their populations, their mandates, their political philosophies of law and justice, even their borders, are constantly changing.</p>
<p><strong>As <em>Der Spiegel&#8217;s</em> &#8220;We Germans&#8221; cover demonstrates, the WC victory might be an opportunity to collectively re-work this changing German identity, while it is still hot and malleable.</strong></p>
<p>For the outsider, all this hullabaloo in the face of three differently colored stripes might seem exaggerated, even just written off as a sign of unresolved historical traumata. But from a philosophical perspective, it is indeed productive to acknowledge all that patriotism implies, i.e. what and whom it excludes. Such a topic is ever-relevant to the productive identity project that might emerge from this World Cup victory&#8230; with the potential to re-create boundaries of belonging for the better.</p>
<p>The cacophony of voices relating to Germanness and all that it encompasses has often been frustrating for German politicians, particularly in relation to defining citizenship laws. But rallies in the streets and public displays of &#8216;belonging to the German club&#8217; have somehow put these oft-exclusionary discussions on hold for a minute, giving journalists the chance to <a href="http://taz.de/WM-und-Integration-in-Berlin/!142407/">write about on-the-ground cohesion </a>or harmony in a country that often fosters a language of <a href="http://www.spiegel.tv/#/filme/duisburg-marxloh/">ghettoization</a>.</p>
<div id="attachment_2888" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://collidoscopeberlin.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/wm-berlin.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2888" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-2888" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wm-berlin.jpg?w=640" alt="Photo by Juri Gottschau" width="640" height="401" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2888" class="wp-caption-text">Photo by <a href="http://www.jurigottschau.com/">Juri Gottschau</a></p></div>
<p>That said, after the streets have cleared and the flags have been taken down, <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/meinung/deutschland-ist-weltmeister-wm-traum-wm-trauma/10207938.html"><em>where does this leave the many immigrants or non-traditional members of German society</em>?</a> asked a columnist with immigration background, recently. For patriotism, like nationalism, thrives on exclusion. That is to say, a group is only a group if it has the capacity to actively determine who belongs and who does not. In essence, this is the definition of the modern state. Part of the state&#8217;s mandate is the ability to exercise force (as opposed to violence, according to Hannah Arendt), in order to maintain these boundaries, something rarely questioned in public discourse or by political constituencies.</p>
<p>These boundaries are not a given, however: they result from and are constantly reproduced in political processes,  enshrined not only in law but in everyday institutions, ideologies, and practices of the outsiders vs. the insiders. This means that they can be changed.</p>
<p><strong>In the end, this new German patriotism is only as good as the boundaries it is ready and able to redefine. An act of flowing colors and neighbor-to-neighbor high-fives may have started a new understanding of who is allowed into the club, but policies and institutions need to take it one step further. Otherwise, patriotism is just as good as nationalism &#8211; a political project and instrument of the state with the purpose of coercing national conscription, labor-market participation, and civic legitimacy by way of <em>exceptionalism</em>.</strong></p>
<p>In the type of inclusive global society many of us would love to build, there is no room for exceptionalism.</p>
<p>All big words and ideas aside, patriotism might have the chance to be democratic and inclusive or it might become dangerously exclusive. As I have witnessed in my home country of the United States, this often depends on who sets the governmental agenda but also who shapes discussions as to what types of restrictions are legitimate, particularly in regards to labor-market and immigration policies.</p>
<p>But it doesn&#8217;t have to be so top-down or even so economically-driven. We can decide who belongs to our club, and maybe, in an ideal world, politicians will respond. In my opinion, this should be the German World Cup take-away.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p>*The phenomenon of national exceptionalism as a political value and even as a &#8216;moral quest&#8217; is demonstrated best by the American political right and the movement to shame political leaders or public opposition who <em>do not</em> believe in the superior story, governmental system, and social values of the United States. Newt Gingrich&#8217;s propaganda-documentary <a href="http://youtu.be/oQsCW1hbOGw">A City Upon a Hill</a> is case-in-point; Ron Paul&#8217;s (of the far-right American Libertarian Party) <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0BOrM6j1-2s">defense of his own views of &#8216;moderate exceptionalism&#8217;</a> to conservative critiques is another.</p>
<p><em>For more on my (and our) philosophy regarding borders and belonging, read the <a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/about/a-manifesto/">Collidoscope Manifesto</a> on cities, difference, and building community.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Integration in Berlin: Research for a Desolate Landscape</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/11/integration-in-berlin-research-for-a-desolate-landscape/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/11/integration-in-berlin-research-for-a-desolate-landscape/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2014 09:01:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Identity & Belonging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy & Practice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[integration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=2390</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On April 2, the new <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/">Berlin Institute for Empirical Research on Integration and Migration</a> (BIM) was launched. Certainly not the first institute of its kind in Germany, Berlin's Humboldt University, the Hertie Foundation, the Federal Employment Agency, and the German Football Association held a press conference to frame this initiative as new and needed. The reason: the field  - what is really known about the integration or inclusion of diversity - is more desert than rain-forest in this country of immigration...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On April 2, the new <a href="http://www.bim.hu-berlin.de/">Berlin Institute for Empirical Research on Integration and Migration</a> (BIM) was launched. Certainly not the first institute of its kind in Germany, Berlin&#8217;s Humboldt University, the Hertie Foundation, the Federal Employment Agency, and the German Football Association held a <a href="http://www.hu-berlin.de/service/veranstaltungen/veranstaltungen_neu/?stat=show&amp;vk_id=2715">press conference</a> to frame this initiative as new and needed. The reason: the field  &#8211; what is really known about the integration or inclusion of diversity &#8211; is more desert than rain-forest in this country of immigration.</p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-7.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2419" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-7.jpg?w=550" alt="BIM 7" width="550" height="668" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-7.jpg 535w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-7-247x300.jpg 247w" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></a></p>
<p>Improving the civic and social infrastructure of a city often begins with data. Aside from &#8220;Big Data&#8221; being the buzzword of 2014, plain ol&#8217; data is worth discussing. For <a href="http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2014/04/14/huge-new-york-development-project-becomes-a-data-science-lab/?_php=true&amp;_type=blogs&amp;_r=0">data can instruct city planners, lawmakers, social workers etc. to better approach problems of urban spaces</a> and their economies, in ways which benefit residents, including the marginalized. It might just be common sense, but empirical research (the critical boots-on-the-ground kind) is an act of taking stock of what is and what isn&#8217;t, which can prove quite useful in societies undergoing (or just learning to deal with) change.</p>
<p>Data, in this sense, is information gathered to solve a problem or answer a question. According to all panelists at the press conference, whether researchers or community and/or political stakeholders, this data is desperately required to answer the question of integration. Or is integration instead a problem to be solved?</p>
<p>As one of the not-so-timid anthropologists on the stage stated during the round of questions, <em>What we are really taking about, when we talk about integration, is how to learn to deal with and approach difference in society. </em></p>
<p><strong>The data imperative</strong></p>
<p>In light of Germany&#8217;s changing demography and political landscape, regarding immigration policy, the categories and models used to understand and support local populations have become outdated, as the <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/german-coalition-talks-move-closer-to-new-dual-citizenship-law-a-933523.html">dual-citizenship debate</a> in German Parliament over the last few months has indicated. More than just the classic census is required to capture the complexity of today&#8217;s metropolis. In Germany&#8217;s capital, where policy-makers brush shoulders with constituents and neighbors alike, real data could not be more in demand and yet, ironically, easier to find. This data goes beyond numbers.</p>
<p>Given this deficit of information and the few reasons for it, the Federal Ministry for Migration and Refugees (BAMF) <a href="http://www.bundesregierung.de/Content/DE/Pressemitteilungen/BPA/2014/04/2014-04-02-integration-kuratoriumsvorsitz.html">has been actively involved in BMI&#8217;s founding</a> and is set to be involved in its future;  BAMF&#8217;s new federal integration commissioner, Aydan Özo<span style="color: #435050;">ğ</span>uz<span style="color: #435050;">,</span> is a key member of the BIM board. Her vocal presence at the press conference made one thing clear: <em>We don&#8217;t even have the numbers, quite honestly, to determine these differences</em> [between &#8216;foreigners&#8217;, &#8216;foreign-born&#8217;, citizens with migration background etc.]. <em>This makes my job quite difficult</em>, she articulated loudly to the audience of mostly journalists. <em>We just do not have the data.</em></p>
<div style="width: 659px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img loading="lazy" src="http://www.bundesregierung.de/Content/DE/Artikel/IB/Bilder-IB/2014-04-02-eroeffnung-bim2.jpg?__blob=bpaTopmeldung&amp;v=1" alt="Eröffnungsveranstaltung des Berliner Instituts für empirische Integrations- und Migrationsforschung" width="649" height="406" /><p class="wp-caption-text">Photo source: BIM HU, Dirk Enters</p></div>
<p>Wolfgang Niersbach, President of the German Football Association (DFB) &#8211; one of three sponsors of the institute and the DFB&#8217;s first sponsorship of this kind &#8211; reiterated this data-driven impetus for more research at length. In 2006, the DFB employed its very own integration commissioner to better navigate the challenging combination of passionate football fans, visible diversity, and racism. A sweeping anti-racism campaign has been the culmination of these efforts, <em>though much is still to be learned</em>, Niersbach said. <em>Our hope for this institute is to get some more solid ground under our feet, to learn more about what works and what doesn&#8217;t work. </em>It is a learning process, and it begins with better information.</p>
<p>A key research focus of the new institute is the relationship between sports and integration, e.g., the participation of youth with migration backgrounds in local football clubs. But the playing field is different in football; <em>integration happens everyday, as 40% of the players have non-German backgrounds,</em> Niersbach mentioned emphatically, looking down the table at colleagues to see their reactions. To boot, social or ethnic differences are experienced on a more intensive and yet common-place level (at least organizationally) in football, compared to German society at large.</p>
<p>Niersbach explained: <em>Two talented football players grow up in Nuremberg playing together, they both go professional, they both have Turkish backgrounds. One day, one of them calls us up and says that he has decided to play for the Turkish national team, the other for the German national team. We are completely fine with that! We let them do what they want to do! But it was not always like that. </em>Times have changed, and so should terms and categories (the dual-citizenship debate, once again case-in-point).</p>
<p><strong>A clarification of terms</strong></p>
<p>The institute&#8217;s projects, team of researchers, sponsors, as well as its leadership, are truly diverse. Inter-disciplinary and embracing of different methodologies and languages of information, the institute seeks to embody what it studies, something Dr. Sebastian Braun, Director of BIM, emphasized throughout his introduction. A football advocate seated next to a well-known political scientist and culture critic;  anthropologists gawking at the government employee over-using the word &#8216;foreigner&#8217;; clinical psychiatrists tolerating the tactics of the employment agency, in dealing with issues of health and job competency. Diversity has to begin somewhere.</p>
<p>But where it will certainly prove to get messy is in this sticky, touchy realm of language.</p>
<p>Frank J. Weiser of the Federal Employment Agency spoke from the perspective of the market-driven state, the key aim of which is full employment and a balanced checkbook: <em>We want to improve our work with </em>Ausländer (foreigners)&#8230;<em>many of these foreigners have access to entitlement programs and experience higher unemployment than their German counterparts. I just work with the numbers, </em>he said smiling, seeming pleased with his honesty. <em>Social cohesion, approaching difference &#8211; but what about jobs?!</em>, he might have said.</p>
<p>The fissure between practice, policy, and the ideals of academia is still there and not likely to go away.</p>
<div id="attachment_3410" style="width: 646px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-3410" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-3410 size-full" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-3.jpg" alt="Director of German Football Association, Rep. Director of Federal Employment Agency; Photo source: DFB" width="636" height="310" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-3.jpg 636w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-3-300x146.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 636px) 100vw, 636px" /><p id="caption-attachment-3410" class="wp-caption-text">Director of German Football Association, Rep. Director of Federal Employment Agency; Photo source: DFB</p></div>
<p><em>The foreigners on our football teams used to be the exotics. In 1963, when DFB was founded, we only had three players with any sort of migration background. Today, 40% of our players have some relationship to immigration, </em>Niersbach commented.</p>
<p>Hands shot up in a hurry from the rows of journalists filling the hall.</p>
<p>A free-lance reporter and coach for a local football league called the use of the word <em>&#8220;Ausländer&#8221;</em> (foreigner)<em> </em>by both men into question. How strange it was to hear a term describing kids born or raised in Germany, kids that play football in Germany as foreign: <em>There are kids that play on our teams that are different, yes, but they play together&#8230; these kids don&#8217;t need to be integrated just because they happen to have a different skin tone.</em></p>
<p>The most vocal of the anthropologists, Prof. Dr. Wolfgang Kaschuba, director of Humboldt University&#8217;s European-Anthropology Department, agreed with this critique, bringing the other oddly-applied term <em>Menschen mit Migrationshintergrund</em> (people with migration background) into the discussion. It is not just about the word &#8220;foreigner&#8221;, which connotes otherness, apart-ness; rather, the problem lies with the terms themselves, how they shift from one individual or community to the next without time for distinction &#8211; <em>that is the humorous aspect in all of it</em> and the aspect worth exploration, i.e. empirical research. <em>I don&#8217;t used the word Ausländer at all, but I do use </em>Menschen mit Migrationshintergrund<em>, though I shorten it to MMH, and I say it M-M-H just to emphasize the irony of these terms in the German debate.</em></p>
<p>To close this round of questions, the Director of Humboldt University added, <em>When we are talking about integration, we are focusing on those people who have decided to stay in Germany, to live here, to work here. </em>But what does it mean to &#8220;decide&#8221;? To stay? To live? No one at the front of the room mentioned citizenship laws, legal frameworks regarding work and residency permission, or those political ideologies that might bar any empirical work on terminology from having real impact in Parliament. Surely, data for this will be gathered, but the question is, who will listen.</p>
<p><strong>Taking stock</strong></p>
<p>In response to a question from the <em>Tagesspiegel, as to how this institute plans to transfer its knowledge to policy-makers</em>, Naika Forouton, the Representative Director of the institute, responded, <em>One of the purposes of the institute is to move away from a one-sided discourse that we have all experienced&#8230;[However], We do not see that as our job, delivering some report to policy-makers. Pure political performance is not our role.</em></p>
<p><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-4.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-2411" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/bim-4.jpg?w=640" alt="BIM 4" width="640" height="480" /></a></p>
<p>In 2013 Naika Forouton wrote a highly-informative report in conjunction with the <a href="http://www.migrationpolicy.org/">Migration Policy Institute</a> (MPI), based in Washington D.C., on <a href="http://www.migrationpolicy.org/research/identity-and-muslim-integration-germany">Muslim identity and citizenship in Germany</a>. In 2012, she contributed to a volume of policy analyses for MPI. Policy analysis and the effects thereof constitute a large part of her professional activities, in fact. Perhaps the difference lies in the medium.</p>
<p>In closing, federal integration commissioner, Aydan Özo<span style="color: #435050;">ğ</span>uz, described the field to be investigated by the new BIM as deserted, barren. And to that, <em>Immigrants have been here a long time, but now they are simply increasing. The current discourse is dominated by fear; it is a fear-laden process. It is important, with this in mind, to represent how things really are.</em></p>
<p>But can we amend this desolate landscape through empirical research alone and the data it yields?</p>
<p>The anthropologist, Dr. Wolfgang Kaschuba, seemed to say &#8220;no&#8221;: <em>We need a new form of group understanding, group consensus, even relationships, even in the postmodern age, even in the era of individualism. We need to come together.</em></p>
<p>If all this coming together will produce the data this city and its neighborhoods need, somehow making it to the highest echelons of power, the BIM is a needed initiative, indeed. If not, the ivory-tower-dilemma may leave the German Football Association and others in waiting.</p>
<p><em>&#8211; By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em>For more information on the fascinating convergence of football, integration, and political engagement, see projects from the following institutions: <a href="http://www.bosch-stiftung.de/content/language1/html/28056.asp">Robert-Bosch-Stiftung</a> project page, <a href="http://heimatkunde.boell.de/dossier-fussball-integration">Heinrich-Böll-Stiftung</a> project page (here <a href="http://www.nfv-www.de/downloads/s_992/dossier_fussball_integration.pdf">PDF</a> report), <a href="http://www.integration-gelingt-spielend.de/index.php/integration/fussball-integration.html">Bundesliga Stiftung</a> project page (here <a href="http://www.bundesliga.de/media/native/dokument/ebs_broschuere.pdf">PDF </a>report), <a href="http://www.dfb.de/?id=508798">DFB &#8211; German Football Association</a> project page. </em> <em>For more press (German language) on the new institute, here a selection of sources: <a href="http://www.migazin.de/2014/04/07/anpfiff-fuer-die-migrationsforschung/">Migazin</a>, <a href="http://www.tagesspiegel.de/wissen/neues-institut-fuer-migrationsforschung-in-berlin-spielfeld-fuer-die-zuwanderung/9708232.html">Tagesspiegel</a>, <a href="http://www.dfb.de/news/de/d-nachhaltigkeit/dfb-foerdert-neues-institut-fuer-integrationsforschung-in-berlin/56752.html">DFB</a>.</em></p>
<p>All photos unless sourced otherwise were taken by yours truly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2014/04/11/integration-in-berlin-research-for-a-desolate-landscape/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Happy Weekend: &#8220;It&#8217;s not about integration&#8221;, or isn&#8217;t it?</title>
		<link>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/11/happy-weekend-its-not-about-integration-or-isnt-it/</link>
					<comments>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/11/happy-weekend-its-not-about-integration-or-isnt-it/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kelly Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2013 10:42:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Spaces & Places]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Arts & Creativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multikulti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theater]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turkey]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://collidoscopeberlin.local/?p=498</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Tonight at <a href="http://www.ballhausnaunynstrasse.de/index.php?id=21&#38;evt=810">Ballhaus Naunynstraße</a>, İmran Ayata und Neco Çelik will present the opening of their newest play, "<em>Liga der Verdammten</em>" (League of the Damned), tackling the dynamic configuration of players and fans in Kreuzberg's very own "<em>Multi-Kulti</em>" football league, <em><a href="http://www.tuerkiyemspor.info/">Türkisempor</a>. </em>Originally formed by Berlin's  marginalized 'guest workers' just 35 years ago, its reputation proceeds it, as do the stereotypes...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Because it is spring, the streets are a bit more bedazzled with color. Be it the bright scoops of Waldmeister ice cream or the gorgeously green chestnut trees that seem to have suddenly appeared, the city is a-blooming. Balls, bikes, and shorts are emerging in kind, which leads quite nicely to this Saturday&#8217;s tip. Surprise, it has nothing to do with good eats but with the stage and, well, the connection between immigration and football (or soccer for the Americans among us).</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/esra_rotthoffballhausnaunynstrasse.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-501 alignnone" style="margin: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/esra_rotthoffballhausnaunynstrasse.jpg" alt="Esra_RotthoffBallhausNaunynstrasse" width="460" height="231" srcset="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/esra_rotthoffballhausnaunynstrasse.jpg 460w, http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/esra_rotthoffballhausnaunynstrasse-300x150.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 460px) 100vw, 460px" /></a></p>
<p>Tonight at <a href="http://www.ballhausnaunynstrasse.de/index.php?id=21&amp;evt=810">Ballhaus Naunynstraße</a>, İmran Ayata und Neco Çelik will present the opening of their newest play, &#8220;<em>Liga der Verdammten</em>&#8221; (League of the Damned), tackling the dynamic configuration of players and fans in Kreuzberg&#8217;s very own &#8220;<em>Multi-Kulti</em>&#8221; football league, <em><a href="http://www.tuerkiyemspor.info/">Türkisempor</a>. </em>Originally formed by Berlin&#8217;s  marginalized &#8216;guest workers&#8217; just 35 years ago, its reputation proceeds it, as do the stereotypes. But &#8220;[it] is not about integration&#8221;, Neco Çelik told <em>die Taz,</em> a daily newspaper,<em> </em>on Thursday. This is the beauty of the play: it is a story about a lifestyle, a community, a sport-culture of roughness and realness in response to societal pressure without intending to play into the trap of &#8216;ethnic&#8217; theater. One could even say that this piece is about the game of making a life after immigration&#8230;or one could say that it is, in fact, JUST about football.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignright" style="margin: 10px;" src="http://collidoscopeberlin.local/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/d567a-566px-257e1.png" alt="" width="204" height="204" />The play premieres tonight, but it runs until 24.05. Each showing begins at 8pm, leaving a few hours between the end of the work day and the stage to kick around a ball, maybe get some green grass on the knees. In springtime, there might be nothing better.</p>
<p>Happy playing or spectating, and of course, happy weekend!</p>
<p><em>-By <strong>Kelly Miller</strong></em></p>
<p><em><em><a href="http://www.tuerkiyemspor.info/">Türkisempor</a></em> might be forced to close its doors, cancelling its season and youth programs due to lack of funds. &#8220;Berlin without Türkisempor is like </em>Wurst<em>without curry&#8221; says it&#8217;s campaign; this might be one statement not worth testing for validity. For more information on how to get involved in saving one of Kreuzberg&#8217;s and Berlin&#8217;s great intercultural institutions, visit the campaign <a href="http://www.tuerkiyemspor.info/magazin/artikel.php?artikel=1679&amp;type=2&amp;menuid=128&amp;topmenu=45">site</a> to donate or find out more about the league, its programs in the community, and its plans for the future. </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>http://collidoscopeberlin.local/2013/05/11/happy-weekend-its-not-about-integration-or-isnt-it/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
